So let's get started.
So interactive fiction is a kind of game.
So before we get into that, we need to talk about what is a game.
So I am not really a game developer, and probably many definitions of what a game is, but I
have tried to define it here.
So a game is like you have a state, and then from that state you have choices, which leads
to other states.
And that is a game, because it requires interaction.
Then the next step is to define what is a good game.
So that's a more difficult question, so we need to involve some more mathematics.
So if we start by saying that the uppercase C is the set of all possible choices in a
given game.
And then we define if to be a function from this set of choices to the real numbers that
calculates what we define as choice funness, such that the higher the number, the more
fun the choice is.
Then a good game is a game where f of C1 is equal to f of C2 for all C1 and all C2 in
the set of choices.
So as an example of this, we have this from before, but in this case, all if evaluates
to 1.
Such that all choices give us a set of choices.
So we have a set of choices that give the same amount of fun.
So for example, as an example of a game that does not have this property, you could think
of a normal 3D game where, for example, you might have to try to enter into a nice quest
that gives you lots of funness, or you could also choose to just walk around in a circle
that gives you less funness.
So that makes that a bad game.
And of course, this definition immediately disqualifies almost all existing games.
But I think it's like a useful thing to aim for.
So the next thing is just to give you an overview of the games I play, to put this talk in context.
So these are the 10 most recent played games on my Steam profile page.
So I've just kind of different genres, but I can see multiple genres, multiple games
that kind of are in the genre of text heavy and simulation heavy.
And then there are some other ones.
So I'm going to show you some of them.
These are the ones that are kind of more just action.
But for example, this one to the left, Cinemaware Anthology, that's games from the 90s where
they kind of tried to make a movie and it kind of failed.
It's called Cinemaware or Bookware.
It's kind of from that full motion video period in time.
Kind of didn't work out.
Interesting ideas.
And then right here down to the right, we have Heaven's Vault, which is a super nice game.
It's extremely text heavy.
Essentially a text game, but with some graphics added on to make it more editable for people.
And the core gameplay loop in this game is to decode a human language, which I think
is like a great gameplay loop.
So that's kind of an overview to put things in context.
So in this presentation, I would like to, so the background is I would like to create
a piece of interactive fiction that is a game consisting only of text.
I've never done so before.
I have kind of done it before.
I have kind of done a little bit, but not like a full-fledged game.
I haven't really done much game development in general.
That could be a pro.
It could also be a con.
And I know of several approaches to get started, but I have never been able to decide which
one to kind of go for.
So I'm doing this presentation in order to force me to make a choice, which is funny
because interactive games are also all about choices.
So today I will cover single player games, multiplayer games.
And then I will try to think of applications of the underlying technology in non-interactive
fiction because maybe we can kind of spread out and use it in a general fashion.
So about interactive fiction.
It's kind of a very broad category, kind of at the top, at the most obvious level is text
adventure games.
Then we have choose your own adventure books.
Some of you know these.
We have visual novels.
We have movie novels.
We have books.
We have multi-user dungeons that's multiplayer, but also mostly text-based.
And then we also have mainstream games that have, for example, dialogue trees and essentially
everything that is kind of text-centric in those, maybe some mini-games, maybe some other
stuff.
So it's kind of broad.
I would like to maybe focus it a bit more today just in order to be able to finish this
talk at all.
So there are some prominent examples of interactive fiction.
We have Sork from the 70s.
Kind of re-released in the 80s as well.
We have the Hitchhiker's Guide to the Galaxy, which was released as a text adventure game
by Infocom in 1984.
Super hard.
I have never completed it.
It's a good idea, but in practice it completely fails as a game, I think.
Then we have Lambda Moo, which is one of these multiplayer games.
And then I guess around 20 years ago, the commercial aspect of these games, 20, 30 years
ago even, kind of declined.
And since then, it has mostly been a hobbyist endeavor to create these text adventures,
which is funny because that's also how it started.
So it's kind of only around the 80s, but this was a proper commercial way of doing game
development.
And then kind of starting again a bit now, but not in its pure form.
Kind of used as a side part to more mainstream kind of gameplays.
In order to be able to focus in on something.
You can say there are two broad categories of interactive fiction.
There's the one to my left here, which is where you actually enter commands on your
keyboard.
For example, you enter drink beer and then the parser says not understood.
Then you enter go on stage and then it says now you are standing on a stage.
Then you can view your inventory and then it says you are currently carrying an older
laptop.
And then you can connect the laptop to the display cable.
That can also be expressed.
In a different format, to my right, where instead of manually typing these choices,
you are presented with a list of valid choices and then you click on that.
The good thing about this is that there are no invalid inputs.
So for example, to my left I have this drink beer, which was not understood because the
game developer didn't implement that feature.
Whereas onto the right, that just doesn't exist because it's not implemented.
So the right version, where you pick from a list of choices.
It's kind of more limited, but it's also more precise, so you won't get into having
to fight the parser.
And for this talk, I will mostly focus on the format to the right, where you pick from
a list, because I think that's much, much nicer.
The old left version was kind of hip for most of interactive fiction's lifetime, but I think
the right version is becoming more and more popular.
So to start with, let's focus on single-player games.
So let's start with single-player games.
So I haven't, as I said, really been much active in this field of game development,
but I was actually active once when I was a child.
I used to do much of this interactive fiction.
So I guess about 18 years ago, I was quite prolific.
So to give you an example of what interactive fiction is, I will show you something I did
back then.
It's a horror story centered around kind of my greatest fear back then.
Which was having to take a shower.
So let's try to find it here.
Yes.
So we can try to run it.
It doesn't work because it's a Microsoft Word file.
So we have to open it instead, I guess.
So this is kind of, you have some pages, right?
And then the format is that, oh, sorry, the format is that you have this step one and
then some choices.
Which leads to other steps.
But instead of doing this manually, what you can do is close this one, and then I entered
it into a tool I made, a vital bag.
Let's try this.
It's in Danish, but I will translate it if you go along.
We're not going to do the entire game because even though it's short, I have lots of other
things I want to talk about.
So okay, the starting page, right?
When you start the game, we mentioned this, it says like, okay, you're going through your
yearly shower.
Of course you don't want to, and you're really fighting this.
You close your eyes and think about what to do.
And then choice one is to try to escape, but my adults are probably too strong.
And choice two is try to be clever.
So two fingers for two, one finger for one.
Okay, I see, let's try to be clever.
Then we click on this.
Okay.
What does it say?
It says cleverness is fine.
You are waiting till you are smart.
Okay.
You are waiting till you are in the bathroom.
Then you hurry out and lock the door with the secret key, which hasn't been introduced
yet.
So that's kind of an interesting gameplay thing.
Your dad yells at you and your mom says you are a lab thing went wrong.
What are you going to do now?
So this is actually kind of relatable because I haven't showered for a couple of days here
at Bornhack.
So it's kind of, kind of, I get kind of get in the zone by playing this, right?
So let's take one more choice and then we can continue.
So, uh, choice one is go outside in the air and play, choice two is go up and play PlayStation.
One or two?
I kind of see PlayStation trumping.
Let's try a trick test.
You are sitting peacefully up in your room and playing GTA Vice City, but suddenly you
can hear your dad's feet on the way of the chairs, the stairs.
What are you going to do now?
Okay.
Let's stop this for now because I think if we just continue, just picking some, oh, oh,
uh, you jump out, but you forgot that you are on this, uh, really high up in an apartment.
So you die at the end.
Okay.
So that was a quick game, right?
That's good because then we can continue along.
So the point of this was that this is a static graph of, uh, of choices.
So even if you reset it, it's not going to be widely different, which tries some other
choices.
They are all statically defined.
Uh.
It's not a very interesting game if you try to replay it, or even if you just start to
think about how it's, how it's created because there's no simulation underneath, it's kind
of boring.
Uh, so there is this trend, um, in, in games in general that you would like to do a remaster.
I have noticed this and I am sure most other people have noticed this as well.
So many remasters, so many special editions, uh, the graphics are improved.
Uh.
But it's the same game underneath.
So what I wanted to do today was to make a remaster of my old game, but not just to recreate
it, but to, instead of having this static graph of choices, make it into a full blown
simulation, or at least start doing that.
So, uh, what I mean by that is that let's go into my editor and then, uh, let's create
a new file.
Okay.
Um, so there is this, uh, programming language called, uh, Prolog, which is really, really
cool.
Woo.
Uh, and it's quite old.
And the interesting part is when you say simulation, it's not really clear what you're going for.
You're going for like old school eighties, uh, symbolic, uh, simulation of, of kind of
objects.
Are you gonna go full machine learning?
And I am not going to go full machine learning because I don't really understand it.
So I'm going back to the eighties.
Okay.
Uh, uh, implement a world of facts that kind of, uh, uh, correspond to the ideas in the
original static graph of choices game.
So let's start by defining the facts of this world.
So we can say we have some parents, right?
Oh, you can make some predicates.
It's okay.
If you don't know Prolog, most people don't.
It can be hard to learn, but once you learn it, the great thing is, uh, that's not really
much to it.
Uh, what you see is pretty much what's there.
There's no extra hidden features.
Uh, it's kind of just what it is.
That's great.
So we have two parents, right?
And what else?
Uh, it can also be useful probably to define what a person is.
So a person is a person.
If that person is a parent and the person is also a person, if that person is you, that's
what a person is.
And now we can evaluate this so we can say what persons exists.
So a person can be that or mom or you.
So that's all the set of possible persons in this game.
That's fine.
The next thing is to try to define what possible actions do we have.
So for this one, we will make a predicate called possible.
So this for a given state.
How can we progress?
From that state to another state.
That's what we want to define.
So what do I have?
Uh, yes.
So the point of this game is to avoid taking a shower.
So let's say that it's possible for a person to take a shower.
Uh, if this is, if, if, uh, that person is in the bathroom.
And the bathroom is locked, is locked because if the bathroom is not locked, uh, you will
automatically escape from this.
That's kind of the rules of this world.
And okay.
So a side note here, um, I think one of the things, uh, in many modern games is that you
start playing it and then at some point you don't know what to do, and then you have to
exit the game and go to some kind of weekend.
I think that's pretty tricky.
And then there are so many details on that.
And I hate that.
I want everything to be in the game and that's what we're doing right now.
We're defining everything from scratch all of the game world.
So that's I think, perfect.
Um, so we can kind of continue this.
Uh, so now we have said that it's possible to shower.
Um, but apart from that, we also have to define these new predicates that we kind of just
assumed were present.
So we can say.
say, a bathroom is locked if someone, if you have some person, and that person has performed
the action of locking the bathroom. This might seem kind of obvious, but we have to define
every single thing ourselves, so there will be some obvious things because humans don't
think kind of in discrete steps all the time, but our simulation will have to do that. And
you can continue with that, so we can also say that to be able to lock something, like
to be able to do this thing that we claim we want to do, if it's possible, it's only
possible for a person to lock the bathroom, or to lock any kind of location, let's try
to generalize it.
If
you have, let's say, that person has some key, and let's say that key locks the location.
Oh, I've made, this is too much, yes. Yes, all right. And you can kind of continue along
with this, but I also want to cover other things today.
So I cheated from home and made one like this, where it's similar but has more kind
of content. So let's try to evaluate some of this, so imagine that we have these lines
of the world defining what kind of simulation we're in, and then our first step is to..
I've worse things to my computers. You can continue like this for 60 seconds, okay?
One minute, then we collapse.
One minute.
That's it.
Go ahead, and let's start moving.
0, I was coffee.
There we go.
No, where's b går end we end.
There's a lot of colleagues.
It adds them up.
Yes.
Yes, there are a lot of cases where you see that.
first step is to, let's say, check where we are. So we can query the world and say,
where am I right now? In you where? And then it says completely, it doesn't know that,
and that's because we haven't really defined the concept of locations. We have kind of
set like, okay, there's this bathroom location, but we haven't actually defined any location
existing outside of the bathroom. So the beginning game state is just, you exist, but you're
not actually anywhere at all, but you can go to the bathroom. So that's kind of something
you could add on, make a better simulation by actually having the concept of locations.
We don't need that for now, we are kind of ignorant. So, and more interesting query is
probably...
to say, like, what do the NPCs do? So we can say, given the starting state, what will
the dad do?
Uh, oh, did I do something wrong?
No, that should work.
Unknown procedure...
So Prolog is quite fun, but it's also quite fun to debug it, right? So let's see...
Uh...
What if I just do...
This?
Okay.
So we can see that...
What it says that we are querying what possible acts does the dad have, and the dad has the
action, it can carry himself to the bathroom, it can carry the mom to the bathroom, it can
carry my... me to the bathroom.
Okay.
So it's likely that the NPC will take the final action, let's say that.
Oh, he can also grab himself.
That sounds weird.
Okay.
That's the four possible actions.
So let's say that it's...
This action, he wants to carry you to the bathroom, so let's try to...
Uh...
Introduce that as a fact in our program.
So now that's kind of established.
So let's try to...
Uh...
possible because we introduced this action up here of being carried to the
bathroom so if you try to comment that out and again ask like what are my
choices from the beginning state of the game it will just say oh there are no
possible choices so it's important that we have this choice so if you want to do
the same thing as we try to do in the playthrough just before in the old
version of the game what we're going to do now is grab the bathroom key so I
guess let's do that so we enter this you grab the bathroom key now that is done
and then I think we may have to remove some facts now
no
Let's see if it says so.
Yes, we used to have this fact that the bathroom key was
reachable, but now that we have grabbed it,
we need to remove this.
This is a limitation of Prolog.
You can retract some things, but it's also a bit limited,
and we are kind of abusing it.
So what you would want to do is make
a nicer Prolog-based system that extends this
with some nicer features.
So now there's, did we fully retract this bathroom key?
Yeah, that's fine.
All right.
So let's go on and then say, what possible actions
do we have now that we have taken the bathroom key?
So OK, now that we have the bathroom key,
we have this new action possible.
Which is to lock the bathroom.
What else can we do?
We can still grab ourselves.
We can escape from bathroom.
So we could escape from bathroom,
but it makes more sense to lock it first and then escape.
So let's try that.
Still manually entering it into the program as a new fact.
So we make the actions of locking the bathroom,
and then we make the action of escaping from bathroom.
OK.
And now let's see.
So we did a lot of actions, kind of unfair to the NPCs.
So let's see what is the possible action for our dad.
He can shower.
He can carry himself to the bathroom.
He can carry the mom to the bathroom.
No, he shouldn't be able to do that.
OK, so clearly there are some logic errors here.
But it's quite fun to debug these things.
Because you're not traversing a static graph of choices.
You're traversing this simulation, which has state,
that goes to another state.
And then sometimes you get kind of emergent behavior.
You don't really expect that, oh, yes, this action makes sense.
Because it's entirely enforced by our system
that this action is possible.
And if you don't want that action to be possible,
it's because we didn't manage to implement
the simulation correctly.
So it's kind of a combination.
Of being able to do more things that you didn't kind of think
were possible, but the system tells you,
yes, this is indeed possible.
So let's move on.
This was 60 lines of prologue, kind of buggy,
kind of showing what you could do.
To do this better, you would want
to have a more full simulation, where what you do
is for each character you have, you give them a goal.
And then they will try to achieve this goal.
By taking the action that gives most utility to that.
That's also a very old idea, not really new in any regard.
But it's easy to implement in these prologue-like languages.
And that's kind of the way to go.
A couple of years back, eight years or so,
there was this system called Versu, which unfortunately
isn't available, because it was, there's a whole story about it.
But they made a nice paper, which kind of put together, you know,
a lot of things.
And they put together these ideas of these emergent simulation-based
game plays.
So you have this concept of contexts.
So in this, to my right here, we have the context pastry,
which contains one interaction possibility.
Then we have other contexts, which also contain
interaction possibilities.
And then these contexts can be added or removed
based on what you do.
And the game play is mostly centered
around very small human actions, like blinking to someone
or making an off-site remark.
And then all the characters are fully simulated.
And there are two levels to the simulation.
One is kind of a background state of the world
that they designed and reused across different games, which
contains so many concepts of locations and emotions
and so on.
And then the top layer is then the game itself, which then,
basically, is a game.
It builds onto this bottom layer and enables these characters
to really do lots of things, because they also
have to react to each other.
So you can have like a new reaction chain where
you do something, and then a character reacts,
and then another character reacts, and so on.
And the great thing is you can actually
play as any of the characters, because the system is
built on a strong foundation.
And it's kind of the same as I just did, but more time
and more development.
The budget and so on.
For tree of choices, this old-school approach,
there are some quite modern tools that extend it a little bit
and also give a nice user experience.
Trine is quite popular.
There's this ink language.
And there's also something called the yarn spinner,
which seems nice.
Then let's move on to multiplayer games.
This is not something I play a lot.
And when I do, I often find it quite hectic.
So if at all possible, I would prefer something a bit
like turn-based multiplayer games.
The basic idea in regards to interactive fiction
is to utilize the fact that humans
are story-generating devices.
So let's say you have two humans.
Then one human is saying something,
and the other is responding to that.
So for example.
This.
This is my first attempt, where I'm just
trying to keep it as simple as possible.
We have a yellow guy and purple guy.
And yellow guy is the game master.
And he writes, you see a lamp that
is transmitted over the internet to this other person who
receives that and then has to act on it.
Then that person says, get lamp, which
is received by the game master, who then
says that the lamp explodes, which is then
received by the player.
This is kind of the simplest possible text-based multiplayer
experience.
The problem is that it's just chatting.
There's no system in place.
You can just chat, and there's nothing
enforced by a nice, complicated system, which we like.
It's also a problem that is super lopsided.
You have one person who is controlling the game
and one person who is only responding to it.
We would like something that is more balanced.
And we would like something that is more balanced.
And also, the game master has, it's not only lopsided,
it's also the game master has too much power.
So it's not fun, and it's not balanced.
So what we want to do is think about how can we kind of
zone in on a smaller area in these multiplayer text games
that we can actually explore.
And I thought about this, and I couldn't come up with anything.
So there's this idea of trying to limit the surface area
in order to get something done.
So I was just kind of waiting around for something
to happen to me.
And then one day, my friend Simon sent me an email
saying that these .Quest domain names are super cheap.
You should buy one.
And then I was like, oh yes, I'm going to buy one
and use it for my project.
And then I thought, OK, .Quest, what is .Quest?
What can I do?
And then I bought this domain.
And it's just, I have this nice Emacs web browser.
So you can just go to, I bought this domain.
Can I load it?
Do I have internet?
If I don't have internet, you can go to Hest.Quest.
This is funny because it's a pun.
No, it's not a pun, actually.
It rhymes.
And Hest in Danish means.
Horse.
So apparently it doesn't load, but that doesn't matter.
So I bought this horse website.
And then I had to learn about horses
in order to make games about horses.
So the great thing is, I thought, OK, interactive fiction
is such a big thing.
And if you want to make a simulation of the world,
that's such a big, big task.
So I thought, now that I have this horse website,
I can just make a very, very small simulation that only
involves horses.
Because I'm sure that they are less complicated than humans.
But I didn't know anything about horses.
So I went to the library in order to find out what's a horse.
There is this nice library next to where I live.
And I have kind of biked across it for 10 years,
but never actually been inside.
So I went inside and kind of looked for,
I found this giraffe book that's not a horse.
Then there's a zebra book.
It's kind of close to a horse, but not really.
And then I found some really nice books.
Books and games.
I kind of got distracted a bit.
Oh, and then I found, oh, this is a nice plaque.
So this one says, where is the book?
So I kind of zoomed in a bit.
And then you have some useful topics, starting with H.
And then I thought, oh, HEST, that's horse.
That's for me.
Now I can learn about what's a horse.
So a horse is 63.61, apparently, on this decimal system.
So I went to this.
And I thought, oh, that's one.
But there were no books.
Really, there were absolutely no books on horses.
So I was kind of devastated.
I don't know what to do.
Then I looked to the comics section.
And I found this nice comic.
I read this as a child.
And then I thought, well, I will borrow this.
So it's called SOS from in Danish.
So I bought it.
I borrowed it.
There's this nice self-service system on Danish libraries.
It just works.
So that comic I borrowed, I'm not
going to say this original title.
But it's by Greg and Franklin.
And it's actually the first release
of that series in Denmark.
But it's not the first chronologically speaking
from the origin country.
It's about fascism.
And the most important thing about it
is that it has a twist at the end.
And that kind of made me realize, OK, when I'm making a game,
I need a twist as well.
The day after, I went out to see some actual horses.
They are kind of in the background,
because I'm actually a little afraid of horses.
So I didn't want to go too close to them.
They're kind of strange animals.
So I observed them from a distance.
And what I realized is a horse eats, I guess, sleeps, walks,
runs, bites.
So the great thing is that without learning about horses,
we actually managed to restrict ourselves even further.
So that makes it possible to make a very contained game.
So I'm going to go through an example now.
So my game is called Hungry Horse.
This is a mug up.
The goal is that you are a horse, you are hungry,
and you want to eat something.
So in this game, it's similar to the example
I showed earlier with yellow guy and purple guy.
But now, we are using Prolog to enforce that nothing
happens that cannot happen.
So once you write down a fact, that fact is in the system,
and you have to abide by it.
So first, we say that you are a horse, and you are hungry.
That's the game.
OK.
And that's what the game master says.
And then the person who plays this game reads that,
and then suggests some new facts.
So the yellow facts are always final,
but the facts on this purple side are suggestions.
So the player says that, OK, in order to eat something,
that something has to be reachable.
And in order for that to be reachable,
in order for me to not be hungry anymore,
in order for me to, instead of be hungry, to be full,
I have to eat something.
This ad here is kind of an ad hoc extension of Prolog.
It doesn't exist.
It's to enforce that, normally, in Prolog,
if you have both the fact that you are hungry and you are full,
they can coexist.
We would like them to be exclusive,
such that when you enable this fact that you are full,
you will automatically remove the fact that you are full.
You can kind of implement that with some exclusive logic,
but that doesn't exist in Prolog.
So we are suggesting, the player is suggesting these facts,
that, yeah, you just have to eat something,
and then you're full.
And then what's happened is that the game master says,
fact not accepted, but here's a fact
that I think is close to what you suggested,
but something that I will accept.
So the game master says that, yes, you'll
become full if you eat something,
but that thing you eat have to contain enough food.
So we have this new enough food predicate,
which is defined as that something can just
be enough food, but it can also be enough food
if it's similar to another thing which is also enough food.
So that's kind of some more levels to this.
So that is now a fact.
You can work with it.
You can become full if you eat something that has enough food
for you.
And then the game master continues, saying,
you are standing in a barn.
Next to you is a pile of hay.
So the obvious step for the player
is then to kind of state that, I think that this pile of hay
is enough food for me.
But then the game master can say, fact not accepted.
And then the player has to think of another thing.
OK, the player just looks around, like, what else do I see
than this pile of hay?
And the game master says, then, OK, I'm going to eat this.
OK, I'm going to eat this.
OK, you are standing in a barn.
There's a small window behind you.
You are surrounded by a short fence outside of which
exists the barn building.
So I'm not sure about the barn terminology.
It's probably not called like a barn and a barn building,
but let's accept that for now.
So in addition, the game master provides some new facts
that, OK, we have this new concept of a location,
and you are apparently in the barn.
And we say that there's a connection between the barn
and the window.
Oh.
And the outside.
And there's also a connection between the barn and the fence
that has been mentioned and the general barn building, barn
area.
And then the game master also defines the concept
of locations and how to be able to cross between locations,
which we can kind of ignore.
But the game master has to do this
because the underlying system doesn't
have a built-in concept of different locations,
like in our first single-player example.
Then the player tries to be clever.
So the player has to define what is height.
You can say that something can be low or something can be tall.
So the player defines that low is lower than high
and says that horses always jump high, and the fence is low.
That's kind of the claim that the player then tries to make,
and the game master has to approve.
OK.
And then the player tries to define the act
of crossing something by saying that you can cross something
if you can jump over it, and you are jumping higher
than the object itself is.
And the game master says, OK, that is fair.
That sounds like how the world kind of works.
And then the game master continues saying,
you are in the barn building now.
Around you are many barn cubicles.
Again, not sure about the terminology, but many barn
cubicles.
Containing a variety of animals.
And again, some new facts like, OK, this new location
is connected to these other locations,
and there's this tall barrier, which is high.
So you cannot jump over it, because you
have to jump higher than high, which is not defined currently.
Then the player just kind of, this
is something that horses do, apparently.
They just kind of neigh.
And then the game master says, many horses
reply with a neigh of their own.
The collective sound vibrations destroy the soul,
the lamb that has been lighting up the barn.
So now there's a new fact to our world that the light is off.
Then the player has to use this fact and says that, OK, we
say that the concept of jumping only
exists because we can see how high something is.
So the player tries to convince the game master that I
can jump to any height.
If I cannot see what I'm jumping across,
which is a super silly idea, but we define this world.
So if the game master accepts that fact,
then we kind of accept it.
And then the player also says that, since this is a fact now,
I hope, I want to cross this tall barrier,
because now I am blind.
And then I will eat lots of food.
And the game master says, OK.
And then now at this point, we can use prologue or something,
similar to verify that this goal that we had from the beginning,
that we are no longer hungry, but now full,
has been verified based on the facts that we have introduced
during this gameplay.
So our actions are completely enforced
by the underlying system.
I think that's great.
It's not perfect, so you can think about some improvements.
I haven't implemented this.
That's a possible improvement to do that.
And also, just to have a list of all currently
active facts, like Babeson kind of to the right in the menu,
such that you don't forget how the world currently works.
That will fail if there are too many facts, but in most games,
it should be mostly like some not too many.
You want to have more than two players.
Two players is technically multiplayer,
but you should be able to handle any number of players.
Maybe make a library of reusable facts.
There are many concepts that I think should be common,
like locations.
And walking between them.
You should have some dice rolls.
That's a part of any game.
Some randomness.
And it could also be nice to encode the flavor text
inside the facts that have been introduced.
That requires more work, and it's probably not
super straightforward.
But it would make sure that whatever the game master
writes also has to be enforced.
Right?
by the facts that the game master provides.
I think to
cannot get rid of this lopsidedness,
you could also make it such that
the player and the game master
play two games at the same
time, such that they exist
in the same world and are affected by the
same facts, so
we reach some kind of balance. That would also
be more difficult if you have more than
two players, but you should be able to engineer
something.
Okay, so the next and final topic
is applications of
these simulation things that I have talked about
in non-interactive fiction.
So I'm thinking about books,
films,
theater, you name it.
Anything that doesn't require
interactive
action from a user.
So let's see.
I want to talk
about
yes, the other day
I was walking
this nice dog.
I couldn't decide which picture
to show here, so that's a couple of
Oh, yeah.
So I was walking this dog, and
I meet someone on the street
who just starts talking to me.
This happens,
and he mentions
that
he also knew a dog like this,
and the owners of that dog
moved to New York.
New Zealand,
because they were producing hearing aids,
and hearing aids are quite big in New Zealand,
he told me.
And that was like, okay, fair enough.
Then he went on to tell me
that
he just got a girlfriend
who is a model, and knows
another model. And I thought,
okay, interesting, but
what does this have to do with anything,
and why are you talking to me?
So at this point, he had kind of provided
me with different backstories,
and I was very eager to get to
the punchline, the conclusion
of this story.
And he just kept talking,
and I was just like,
what is the conclusion?
It was also awkward,
because I couldn't really participate in this conversation,
because I didn't know
New Zealand models really well.
And then he
says that I want to take my girlfriend
to New Zealand. And I thought,
well, technically, these
facts are connected,
but there's no immediate narrative
link from
the above facts to the
final conclusion. It was so confusing
for me, and I just went home,
and I was just confused for the rest of the day,
because
let's try to make a diagram.
So the facts are that he has a
girlfriend who is a model,
and has a friend who is also a model.
New Zealand
has at least one Siberian husky dog,
which is
okay,
there's some error in the diagram.
But New Zealand has many hearing aids.
That's what we know, right?
So the goal
that he presented was,
he wanted to take his girlfriend to New Zealand
for some reason. And this
is the narrative jump that
he presented that I did not understand.
And I thought,
maybe if you try to
generalize this, so why would you like
to take a person to a location?
That's because maybe
person is from location, so it could be
that his girlfriend was from New Zealand,
but then why did he talk about dogs?
Because I kind of imagined that, OK, you
need to use all these background facts
and tie them nicely together at the end.
So the other option is that New Zealand has
some kind of nice attribute.
For example, it has a dog, or it has hearing aids,
and you like hearing aids or dogs.
So that's kind of what I thought,
but none of it really made sense.
So I thought that was a nice way to think about things,
but it was also kind of a complicated story.
So I'm trying to present instead a simpler story now
to make it less complicated in order
to talk about what we actually are going to talk about.
So my simpler story is we have a human who discovered fire.
The human learned that the fire improves the food.
Then the human accidentally burned himself to a crisp.
And the final step, which is the twist,
is that the human was eaten by a hungry horse.
So we have this four-step story.
And as before, we can try to put it in a diagram.
So we have at the top kind of the conclusion.
The human was eaten by a hungry horse.
And then there are several links to earlier facts from that.
So he was eaten because he is food.
And he was eaten by the horse because the human is good food.
Because the fire improves the food, which is in this case
the human.
And this is known because the human discovered fire.
And it's known specifically because we are kind
of the all-knowing reader.
So in the story, only the human technically knows this.
But also, if you read the story, you also know that.
So on the left side, we have that the human burned themselves
to a crisp.
And it's possible because the human discovered fire.
So this is kind of a high-level diagram of the story
containing the four points.
But we have to make it more precise in order
to kind of think about any underlying generalized things.
So let's try to remove some of the weird English things
about articles and past and present.
Just make the sentence simpler.
I have a nice diagram here where we've kind of, you know,
kind of say that a horse eats the human.
And the horse specifically eats because it's hungry.
And it specifically eats the human
because the human is good food.
And the food is good because the fire improves the food, which
is known because the human discovered the fire.
And we can extend this diagram work in even more fine grains
by having some more arrows around and saying
that the human is dead because the human used the fire
to burn the human to death.
And we can also say that discovering fire is kind of
similar to learning about something.
So let's try to use fewer kind of verbs.
So we just say that discover and learn is the same word.
But this diagram is still kind of not super useful on its own.
So we should go back to our prologue
and try to make it nice and text-based as we like it.
So we should have simple textual encodings of the background
facts.
of our story so I made something oh the website loaded that's nice so let's go
to this one so I wrote some prolog and let's try to make some queries so I
won't go into detail with this specific file but what we have here is again
this possible thing which tells us what action is possible during according to
what state we are currently in and some other background things that we need to
know so the first step to replicate so we want to replicate the story that we
provided so the first step that is to state that we have a human which is
alive oh sorry so we have to actually do it in here
and the next thing is the first sentence of the story was that we make
this subject verb object where we say human learn file that's our simplified
English version oh again I am entering it in the wrong place so now that is a
fact and then what we want to do the next fact is
this subject verb order of human learns and then the human this is the point
where the human learns that the fire improves the food so to encode that in
our product system we say that human learn that we make a new subject verb
object that fire improve food but instead of just entering this we have to
make sure that it's
possible according to our system. So we query the system, say possible, and says that's
true. Okay, so that's nice. So we can enter that again because it's okay. Then the next
thing that happened in the story was that the human burned themselves to a crisp and
there are so many details and flavors to that specific sentence, but we are simplifying
it and saying that subject, verb, object, human, burn, human. So we want to say, is
this possible? And it's it. But what if, so what if we hadn't introduced this fact before
that the human learned that fire improves the food? No, specifically this first one,
that the human learns the concept of fire. Let's try to comment that out.
What is the comment? Status. So now we have commented out the first part of the story
where the human learns the concept of fire. And then we try again to check if the third
option, the third thing is doable, that the human burns themselves and it's false. So
we have enforced through our system of facts in Prolog that we cannot make any continuity
errors. So let's go back to this and then let's enter this new.
Fact to our system. And then the final thing that happened, no, the next to final. No,
the final thing was that. Uh, the human dies, right? You can say, is it possible that subject
verb human dies? That is possible because the human has burned themselves. So again,
if we try to comment this out and try to again, we have to say, is it possible that the subject
verb human dies?
No, the next to final. No, the final. The final thing was that the human dies. So again,
if we try to comment this out and try to again, we have enforced through our system of facts
in Prolog to the human dies. You can say, is it possible that subject verb human dies?
That is possible because the subject verb human dies. No, the next to final. No, the next
to final. No, the next to final. No, the next to the human dies. No, the next to final.
We have to do it again in the current scenario where you can query the human dies. That it's
not possible because the human can only die if the human has burned themselves or some
other underlying facts. So we have it up here that, uh, that there are many ways to die.
Uh, and you can say that you can die. If you're currently alive and you are now very old,
you can die if you are currently alive and you are sick, or you can die if you're currently
alive and someone burned you.
someone burned you, in this case, yourself.
So we are describing how to die in this world.
So let's have that as well as a fact now,
now that we know that this is okay, this is possible.
And then let's state that we have a horse also who is alive.
And then the final part of the story is to check
whether it is possible for subject, verb, object,
the horse, to eat the human.
Oh yeah, so this is not possible.
And why is that?
That's because we haven't introduced the fact
that the horse is hungry.
So the horse can only eat people if it's hungry.
So let's try again.
Is it possible to eat the human now that it's hungry?
And yes, it is.
So we can encode that fact as well.
And now we have completed our story.
And for each new sentence that we wanted to add
to this story, we made sure that it was not breaking
any continuity, not breaking any facts about our world.
And that's, I think, like a super great thing.
I think you could use this for movie scripts and so on.
You could support flashbacks.
So my story was quite simple, right?
Four steps, all in order.
In modern,
stories,
you want to have maybe some switching around
of time and place, flashbacks, flash-forwards.
You could support that by extending our system
to have like a predicate that says
you have this,
you have some kind of reverse where you take the order
in a different order,
and but you maintain the same facts
and the same relations with them
and make that equivalent with something in the original order.
I think that's doable.
So that's kind of what I thought about.
In the end here now, I want to talk about
some other applications for this.
Machine learning, I didn't take the statistics course
at my university because it seemed difficult,
but I think machine learning has gone quite a long way
and it's possible to use it quite easily,
I think, at this point.
So I wanted to do something that's this WordNet,
which has relations between words, and I wanted to,
I wanted to create a system that explores character attributes
and presents you, the creator,
with different kind of scenarios for your characters
and different choices based on those scenarios,
and then you have to pick the choice,
and then the system generates character traits
based on those automatically generated choices.
So you define the character,
but you are defining it by throwing the character
into unknown situations.
And I also would like to just experiment,
and I would like to try to use these applications
on real movie scripts, try to encode those properly.
That could be fun, but also lots of work.
Finally, some free ideas for game topics.
I went to the Baker once, and then they asked me
if I wanted a voucher, and I didn't really respond.
It was kind of confusing.
Maybe that's a game.
Also, I was at the cinema watching a movie,
and then this random dude talked to me,
and I didn't know how to respond.
Maybe that's a game.
And also, I have this concept of having too many
side projects and never finishing any of them.
And I thought, well, maybe I should do this.
So maybe the game, you would have,
the goal would be to finish just one side project,
and then you would have constant things coming in your way,
kind of stopping you, and that could be fun.
Also, what about an inverse game
where the game is presenting you with parser input,
and then you have to respond,
and then something else exciting happens.
In conclusion, I think the main degrees of freedom
that I'm interested in is this,
either it's parser-based or it's choice-based,
either it's a static graph of choices or it's a simulation,
or either it's single-player or multiplayer.
And I am probably picking a list of choices,
a simulation, and single-player.
I think that's what the game I'm making will be.
I think text-only development is great,
because game development should have
as few obstacles as possible,
and making graphics is time-consuming.
I think writing is fun, so it's fun to make the game.
And it's easy to really do effective,
iterative development, because you can just move text around,
and you can have systems in place that's guarantee
that you're not doing something that is invalid
within the game world that you're trying to define.
Yes, thank you.
Thank you very much.
Do we have any questions for Nils?
Oh, there's one all the way down there.
Could you have Prologue say that the horse needed to be hungry
to enable a solution at that point?
Yes.
Yes, indeed.
You can just say that
this particular state of horse is hungry,
that state can...
You can make it even more complicated.
You can say that state can only exist
if we introduce a concept of time,
and there has been so and so much time
since the horse last ate,
such that we don't have this explicit state,
but we have a set of actions describing
what actions the horse did in the last 24 hours, and if it didn't, then it's gone.
So, I think that's a good point. I think that's a good point.
And if it didn't eat as part of any of its actions,
that would constitute it being hungry.
I didn't respond to your question, I'm sorry.
I just thought of something else.
But yes, for sure you could do that,
and you could do so many more things.
Do we have any other questions?
Then let's give a big round of applause for Nils.