Tanya Cushman Reviewer:"Tanya Cushman Reviewer:"
Right, let's begin.
Blinking lights, friend or foe,
a history of sideline attacks through the ages.
First of all, who am I?
I'm a security consultant at WebSecure.
I'm also a CTF player for a camera union,
and I'm also a Bonhack participant here in the Pyjamas camp.
So a quick TLDR, what is this talk going to cover?
First of all, if you were expecting it to be about the hit 2000 movie,
Blinking lights, it's sadly not going to be about that,
but it is a good movie.
What we're going to talk about first is what are sideline attacks,
a history of the sideline attacks starting around the 1940s going up to the 80s.
We're going to talk about a bunch more sideline attacks,
how they work, how can we categorize them,
why attacks like these pop up, and why they matter.
So first of all, what is a sideline attack?
And this is the formal definition you'll find if you go on Wikipedia.
It's a sideline attack is any attack based on extra information
that can be gathered because of the fundamental way
a computer protocol or algorithm is implemented,
rather than flaws in the design of the protocol or algorithm itself.
I don't agree with this definition.
For me, it's just any attack being based on...
information gathered in a fundamental way
because of how the system is implemented.
It doesn't have to be on computer protocols or algorithms.
You can do side channel attacks on anything.
So start an example, you are a baker in a small town,
like Gilstedtel here, for example,
and there opens up a competing baker who starts stealing a lot of your business.
You're suddenly every single day throwing bread out
because you're making too much.
You don't know how many customers you've stolen.
And of course, you're a bit mad at him.
You can't just go up and ask him,
hey, how many people are you selling to?
So instead, what you do, you go first in the morning,
you go buy a piece of bread from him, first thing, as soon as he opens,
and you keep the receipt.
End of day, you go back, buy another piece of bread or whatever,
and you get the other receipt.
You now have two receipts with two order numbers,
and you can see exactly how many orders were made in the day
because on all receipts, order numbers like this are sequential most of the time.
There's nothing technical here.
It was just a system that was implemented for the rival baker to keep track of how many,
how many orders he's had.
You used it for your own advantage to figure out how many customers he's gotten.
So we start our story in the Second World War,
where this was what side channel tax started popping up and becoming a thing.
So right before D-Day, we had the Panzer V Panther tank.
It was new, created by the Germans, and American tanks,
it was unknown how effective they were against them.
However, they had only been seen in Italy so far, so no stress on that front.
However, in the couple of days
leading up to D-Day, there were suddenly lots of rumors about these tanks appearing
in France and Normandy, where the landings would happen,
and the Allied forces really needed to know how many tanks are going to be there.
So what did they do?
For the tanks they already had destroyed or captured,
they started tearing them apart.
And inside the gearboxes, the cogwheels were sequentially numbered with their serial numbers.
And also importantly, it also had the number of what gear mold produced the cogwheel.
Based off this information,
they could actually estimate
how many tanks they had been able to produce,
because they knew how many gear molds they had,
and you can't have a tank without a gearbox.
And they estimated 270 tanks had been produced in February 1944.
And this was substantially higher than any rumors that they had.
So this was really important information to get.
They could prepare for this.
After the war, documents confirmed 276 Panzer V Panther tanks had been produced.
They had estimated this just off the serial numbers on gearboxes.
This is honestly where I would start saying side-channel attacks.
This is where they started getting used in military applications or by governments for attackers.
There was a system that was introduced.
Without consideration of every single part of it,
they didn't consider how could the serial numbers on gears be abused.
And it was abused.
Next up, we have the 131 B-2 Mixer.
This was an encrypted teleprinter in use during the Second World War,
and it was built off the one-time pad principle.
And it was basically built with a whole bunch of electromechanical relays or switches,
which turns out they actually gave off quite a bit of electromagnetic radiation.
And turns out by observing this information here,
you could actually figure out the plain text.
And this was actually Alexander Graham Bell of the Bell Telephone Company
who discovered this attack.
And he researched and he found there was three different radiated signals that were of importance.
There was just signals, the standard EMF radiation in the local area.
There was noise being carried by the communication wires in which the plain text could be snatched up.
And there was through the magnetic fields as well.
So we created a new version, the 131 A-1, which had shielding and filtering and stuff like that.
But it was large. It was unwieldy.
It didn't really work on the battlefield.
Turns out we just implemented a 30-meter perimeter around the thing,
and that kind of solved most of the issues at least.
Made it safe enough to use.
However, it turns out later in 1951,
the CIA discovered they could retrieve the signals from this half a kilometer away
due to the noise being sent through the signals.
And we're like, oh no, we've got to fix it because they'd still been using the same system.
And then they started developing signal and power line filters.
They started isolating it as much as they could.
And it kind of turned into a cat and mouse game
because this machine was also quite loud while it was encrypting.
All these switches were triggering.
Turns out you could also, through just listening to it,
you could extract the plain text as well.
So they soundproofed the room and they soundproofed the box the room was in.
Turns out it just made the signals easier to record.
So they just created a 100-meter perimeter and said,
okay, you know what, let's get onwards with it.
We kind of got to get something else.
But this is where they were like, oh shit,
we've got to do something about these signals that are being radiated out.
Next up towards the end of the war in 1944,
the Russians and the U.S. were still in good terms there.
So, I don't know if you've heard this, but the Russians and the U.S. were still in good terms there.
A bunch of Russian boy scouts, they gifted this lovely wooden seal
to the U.S. ambassador in the Soviet Union.
And yeah, okay, it's still something gifted by the Soviet Union,
you don't really trust it.
But they scanned it with nonlinear junction detectors,
which basically just search for active electronics.
They couldn't find anything.
As far as they knew, it was just a piece of wood
carved into the U.S. seal there.
Key word was active components.
Inside there was a complete,
completely passive bug where it consisted of an antenna
and a membrane.
And the membrane essentially being just a piece of plastic.
Sound waves inside the room would vibrate this membrane,
which was attached to the antenna.
And what happened is this antenna,
when you hit it with the right frequency radio signal,
it would then resonate and it will give off its own signal,
which could be picked up by radio.
And the sound waves would then modulate the people talking
within the room, this signal onto the,
repeated signal.
And so it turns out you could,
they sent a 300 kilohertz signal, I believe it was, to it.
And then they could hear everything that was going on
inside the ambassador's private quarters,
which is quite a lot of information leaked.
Turns out then in 1951, a British radio operator
at the British embassy, just down the road,
he was listening to open Soviet Air Force radio channels,
and suddenly he heard the U.S. ambassador
to the Soviet Union talking.
Kind of bad, doesn't really work.
And turns out, just a couple of fun facts about this.
One, it was created by Leon Farriman,
the guy who created the Farriman instrument.
And it's also essentially how RFID works.
You send a radio signal, resonate an antenna,
and you get data out from that.
But this is where side channel attacks had begun.
Introducing Tempest.
Tempest was then a U.S. code word
for dealing with side channel attacks.
It has then been backronym to telecommunications electronics,
material protected from emanating spurious transmissions.
And I will not be repeating that.
But it's both a set of standards
for protecting hardware from leaking signals.
It's also just the term for all side channel attacks
that the NSA use.
It's just attacks that attack systems
and not attack it directly,
but what's getting leaked out of it.
These standards, it leads to development of things
such as red-black separation,
where there physically has to be a few centimeters
of separation between red wires and black wires,
where black wires carry plain text
and red wires carry only cipher text.
And then 1958, first policy regarding EMF radiation standards
for military use was put in place.
It was stopped, U.S. came with it first,
but it was quickly adopted by Canada, UK,
and other allied forces at least.
And with the Cold War well underway,
they really needed to start controlling these signals.
Because at the same time,
over 900 different listening devices and sensors
had been found in U.S. installations
behind the Iron Curtain.
You could not just ignore tempest leakages.
This was something they had to take care of.
This led to a whole bunch of developments,
such as what's called inside rooms.
So they took an anechoic chamber like this,
and they put another room inside of it
to avoid any signals leaking out.
And we also have rooms like these, which just isolate,
isolate completely for RF radiation as well.
And what was our one issue is all the employees
of these embassies and that,
they kind of refer to these as the meat lockers
because they were really hot,
so we just left the door open,
kind of ruining the entire attack.
But you can buy one, first of all,
you can buy one of these boxes for yourself,
a couple of million dollars if you want.
Second of all, they're not just used
for protecting against military attacks,
so that if you do any research regarding radar waves,
for example, you're going to be doing it
inside one of these rooms.
It's essentially a big Faraday cage.
But also, if you have an installation
where secure numbers are being generated,
such as in banking sector, stuff like that,
it also occurs within one of these rooms
because this security needs to be taken seriously.
And so on, this cat and mouse game
between both the Americans and the Russians
and side channel attacks on both sides
continued at least until the 80s,
beginning the age of hackers, at least
in the 1980s,
and then the 80s,
when the 80s came along,
and the 80s was the time
when the world was going through a lot of chaos.
And so far, all these attacks,
they had been government only.
It was quite massive amount of resources in that.
But the 80s, computers starting to become pretty popular.
I'm pretty sure there's several people in the audience
who were already playing with their first computers back then.
And I'm just going to cut to a BBC video clip from the 80s
because it just explains what happened
so much better than I ever could.
This receiving system here,
that's not linked to it in any way at all.
It's only £100 worth of equipment,
so it's not the greatest picture,
and I'll try and stabilise it a bit there.
And if I move the aerial,
you can see that the information disappears off the screen.
Move it back, and it returns.
Now, all we've got here is an ordinary television set
with an aerial and an amplifier
and a rather special, if cheap, box of tricks.
But we had to go to the Dr. Nair Laboratories in Holland
to get hold of it.
And actually, they use this equipment quite legally
to investigate this very problem.
And they were the only people who we knew
who could find out and would admit to having it.
Well, we've seen it working in the controlled conditions of the studio,
but yesterday, we set this up to see how it would work outside.
There you go.
So, as you can see, we're outside an office block in West London,
and we found that there's a VDU screen operating
about halfway up the building, probably on the seventh or eighth floor.
And in fact, it's a letter being typed out on that screen.
I can actually read it here.
It says, Dear Mr. Jackson, thank you for your...
Whoops. Thank you for your letter requesting the use...
Whoops, I've lost it again.
...requesting the use of our facilities.
At least stop the video there.
But what had happened was someone called Wim van Eyck,
he had discovered what's called van Eyck phreaking.
And they even said they could do it
for a hundred pounds.
Turns out you could actually do it for like a hundred kroners' worth of equipment.
You could read the signals being...
that were coming off from a CRT monitor remotely from large distances.
And this was kind of a big deal,
because he had done it as a private person
with a hundred kroners' worth of equipment,
antenna and something, bought a radio shack, basically.
Everyone thought so far, oh no, attacks like these,
only... it's only governments we need to take care of it, threat actors.
But turns out everyone could,
and this kind of split the entire field.
Everyone was rushing.
And from here, we kind of can't really talk about like,
historically, what side channel attacks come on next,
because there are just so many attacks.
It's more important to talk about them in general.
So for next up here, the implications of aesthetics.
Everyone's seen a network switch,
and on every single network switch in the world,
there is a small activity LEDs there saying what ports are active.
Or as we like to call them, blinking lights.
This led to this lovely sign being created,
which it turns out this sign had actually been hanging around IBM computer rooms since 1955.
And it says,
.
But back to the diagnostic LEDs, back to the network switch.
And let's put yourself in the shoes.
You are an engineer that's been tasked to build the network switch,
and specifically, you have to create these activity LEDs.
We have the pin out here of an ethernet cable, RJ45 cable,
where, of course, you can see there's
just RX plus minus.
So why don't we just hook the LED directly up to that wire there?
And then we don't have to create any fancy electronics
to handle to figure out when these ports are active.
Does anyone see the problem here?
In 2002, Joe Lurie and David A. Umphress,
they had a research paper came out titled,
Information Leakage from Optical Ammonitions.
They had realized you can just record the LED, and that way,
you can get all the data coming off the cable.
Bit of an issue.
And this, everyone, when this paper came out, were like,
holy shit, we've been idiots.
Why did we not think about this?
So we're now just going to go talk about the different types
of side channel attacks of these, because there are a lot.
And this is generally how they do get categorized.
So for timing attacks, if we have this little snippet of code
here, which checks passwords, we can see we loop over.
We can see the correct password and the input.
And we check each character if they match.
If the character doesn't match, we break.
Obviously, what we can do is we can just
start checking the first character
for every single A, B, C, D, E, F, G.
And at one point, we're going to have one of these calls
to the password checking function, which is going
to take a little bit longer.
When we have that one that's a little bit longer,
we know we have the correct letter map position.
We go onwards to the next position.
This is a timing attack.
It's easy to abuse, at least, if you just
can get accurate timing out.
Next up, we have power monitoring attacks.
These are mostly known for the AES differential power analysis
attacks.
This is where, by looking at the power usage of a CPU
doing AES encryption, you can actually extract the key.
And honestly, I could talk about power monitoring attacks
for absolutely ages.
So I realized I just brought the hardware with me here
to bone hack.
And later today, like midnight-ish,
going to hold a very impromptu hardware hacking workshop
where we're going to do a power monitoring attack like this.
Next up, we have cache attacks.
This was Meltdown and Spectre.
These were two attacks which came out in 2018.
And for those of you who aren't massive security nerds,
you might have heard your security nerd friends
talking about this.
But essentially, all processors nowadays, or back
before this tech came.
And they still do it as well, did what's
called speculative execution, where they just
try to guess what you were going to do next.
If you had an if statement, it would execute both branches.
Because why wait for user input when you can already
get the data ready?
Issue was, this meant you could load secrets into cache
and then not go down that execution path.
And you could then read those secrets out of the cache
because the cache didn't get wiped.
This could then be used to, example, leak passwords
from another browser's app.
And quite frankly, this is not the case.
This is not the case.
Quite effectively, these attacks here,
they were in charge of massive slowdown
for cloud computing systems.
And if you ever start up a VM nowadays,
you'll get that option.
And it will often be recommended,
which is in your own laptop, to disable side channel attack
mitigations, which mitigate attacks like these.
Next up, we have acoustic attacks
where there's small video running in the background here.
But this is an attack where someone
has trained the machine learning model to listen to what's,
listen to what's being typed.
And you see here, he's running it on his phone.
No cable plugged in there.
Goes down to the bottom of the screen there.
And he just starts recording.
Of course, permissions pop up.
Starts recording what's being typed.
And very quickly, we'll go on here.
You'll see he's going to hold up a phone,
and it's basically going to be a one-to-one recreation of what he typed.
Now, he did train this specifically for his keyboard.
However, if you can get enough training data for your victim's keyboard,
then you could also easily execute this attack.
There's also research out there which suggests you can do acoustic attacks
by listening to the stresses in a heat sink
that occur from the changing temperatures during encryption.
That is my face when I read that.
It should not make any sense that that happens,
but apparently we can listen to heat sinks.
Yes.
And that way gain useful information.
There's also software-initiated attacks
where Rowhammer, a lot of people might have heard of,
but if you haven't, what you did is
you had your victim row in a memory
where you could figure out where this was
with some low-level Linux knowledge.
At least, and say, for example, in this victim row,
there was the bits being stored which said what permissions you had.
Turns out you could then aggressively toggle the rows
next to each other.
So you could do that.
And then you could actually switch bits to it on and off repeatedly,
and it would actually flip bits in the victim row
if you didn't have error-correcting memory.
And you could then, for example, flip bits,
and if you got lucky, you suddenly got admin
because you flipped the bits correctly.
There's also optical attacks, and this is a really fun one
because I'm pretty sure someone here upon hack
has all the equipment needed.
And while we already covered stuff like looking at activity LEDs
on switches, we can also use lasers for optical attacks.
So here, by taking a laser pointer, pointing it at a window, and then capturing the reflected beam from the laser on a photocell, soldering that photocell to an AUX cable, plugging it into your laptop and opening Audacity, you can record what the laser is picking up by what it's pointed at.
So if it's pointed at a window, the glass will vibrate, and you can then listen to it from there, from a distance.
We also just covered that you can listen to keyboard recording and capture text like that, and lasers can go pretty far if you have a strong laser.
Now, just one thing, this is very illegal if you don't have permission to do it, so don't go about just doing it regularly, even though it is that simple.
And it also doesn't have to be on a piece of glass that you're recording from.
It could be anything that vibrates, so a bag of chips.
If you've ever been in a really top-secret meeting, there's going to be no...
No recording allowed, because you don't actually need the laser pointer.
A video from the room, and something vibrating in the room, like a leaf or a bag of chips or something, that's enough if you have a high enough budget.
And that's back in the NSA government-level area.
Another optical attack, which I like to include, because this one was actually covered a lot back in 2019,
it was laser-based audio injection on voice-controllable systems.
So if you had a smart speaker...
And you placed it by your window, you could trigger the smart speaker with a laser by doing essentially the opposite of encoding your voice into the laser.
And by pointing it at the right place on the smart speaker, on specifically on what's called a MEMS microphone,
which, again, all these home assistant smart speakers have, you could inject the sound into it from kilometers away.
So imagine if you have a nice, fancy smart home, and you put this smart speaker in your window,
because it looks nice.
It looks nice in the window.
Then, as me, as a thief, I could point my laser at it, and I could say,
Hey, open the garage doors.
I have access to your house now.
There are also many, many other kinds of side-channel attacks.
Recently, there was the Satan attack, it's called, where they turned SATA cables into antennas,
and then they could get around air gap security by sending the right data, by encoding the data through the signals coming out of these antennas.
There's really no limits to what side-channel attacks can do, and there's so many of them.
And before people ask, yes, data exfiltration is still a side-channel attack.
You're still abusing this system in a way it wasn't supposed to, to gain information.
In this case, it's just to get information out, but you're still gaining information.
So what can we learn from all of this?
Systems are hard to implement, and if there's a design consideration, for example, stamping the gear mode serial number
onto a call, or a message, or something like that, it's not going to work.
If you have a call going to a tank so you can track down defects in production, it can be abused.
This can be if you send out any IDs from your web app, who knows what.
And for the love of God, use someone else's cryptographic libraries.
And this is what people mean when they say, don't roll your own crypto,
because other people's libraries have hopefully been tested for these kinds of side-channel attacks, and you can minimize it.
Because there's a lot of these attacks.
Like the timing attacks and power monitoring attacks that are quite easy to do, and it doesn't take more of an afternoon to learn how to do it.
If you want some further reading, I can highly recommend Silence of the Wire by Michael Zaleski.
Great book.
Talks in general just about side-channel attacks.
There's also Art of Intrusion by Kevin Mitnick.
Not so much about side-channel attacks, but does have a quite cool cryptographic attack on a
on a
slot machine in the casino they talk about, and how they could predict the random number generator.
And there's also A Cuckoo's Egg by Clifford Stahl, which is just a great book about hacking.
Not really too much about side-channel attacks in it.
Thank you for coming to my talk.
I'll be putting the slides up on my website at some point.
I just need to fix some attribution stuff a little bit there.
You want to follow me on untapped, because that's really the most important communication media.
You can follow me there.
And there's just a CTF flag.
Just ignore that.
It's going to be using like,
90 days or so.
Thank you.
Thanks.
Are there any questions?
What is the best way to introduce some noise to make this less effective?
Introduce some noise to make it less effective.
It depends on your threat model.
I mean, depends on what you're building.
Of course, starters don't use sequential IDs.
You can always guess those because we're sequential.
But again, if you are using some, say, we have a cryptographic system running on a processor, but you made your own.
This can be making sure that you have some background tasks running to make sure power usage is linear and you can record that.
You can make sure that you add just some.
Make sure the programmers run for X amount of seconds, at least, no matter how fast it runs to avoid timing attacks, stuff like that.
Again, it depends on your threat model and there are just so many attacks.
So you can't really add noise for every single thing.
You cannot fully protect yourself from side channel attacks.
You can't fully protect yourself from any kind of attack, really.
Security is always about knowing your risk and doing what you can to defeat that risk.
As we were talking, I was talking about the Tempest Room.
The rooms that they made, the rooms inside rooms, this was a large, extreme security measure, but it was just too inconvenient for users to use, so they left the doors open.
This is what we mean when we say security is a bit of a balance.
You can't just go all out and make an unhackable system because there's always a more dedicated hacker and there's always users you have to deal with.
No more questions?
No, in that case, thanks a lot.