The next presentation we have is Arma Rohn,
who's going to talk a bit about the danger of client-side scanning.
Let's give a round of applause for Arma Rohn.
Thank you.
The European Union is proposing something very bad,
and I'm going to tell you about it and why it's bad.
I am the one person presenting this,
but we've actually been talking about it in CryptoHagan,
so it's not just... I don't deserve all the credit.
So I don't really have slides,
but I will put the outline over here.
Oh, that didn't work so well.
Let's try it.
First is, I'm going to say,
proposal.
Second, why.
And third, like, things you could do.
So in the last, like, three years,
there have been proposals that are effectively, like,
we're going to surveil everyone more
in order to do something about child sexual abuse material
and the solicitation of children on the Internet
for sexual abuse.
And the first one is abbreviated,
CSA,
and the latter is abbreviated, grooming.
So these are, like, bad things,
and the proposal is we're going to surveil people more
so we can find these things and stop these things
and bring the perpetrators to justice.
There have been proposals in 2020 and 2021,
and they were both, like, people said they were bad,
and they didn't go anywhere.
And then 2022, in May, there was another proposal.
This proposal is number...
I'll have notes on the page for this presentation
so you can see everything that I'm saying
with all these references and links to papers and stuff.
But I'll put the key stuff here.
So this number proposal, it hasn't been passed,
would require that tech companies screen their platforms
for child sexual abuse material
and establish the EU Center on Child Sexual Abuse
to coordinate the screening.
And supposedly, these rules are supposed to rescue children
from abuse, prevent CSAM from reappearing online,
and to bring offenders to justice.
The proposal is quite vague about how it would be implemented.
So I'll tell you some things that could be related
that already exist.
There's...
So one technique that I suspect would be used,
but...
might not be adequate,
would be to effectively...
We create a database of sexual abuse material,
and we compare every message on, like, Facebook or Signal
or whatever to this database.
And it would probably only work for images, so simply.
So a very simple way is you hash every known...
You have some, like, central party
that collects all the child sexual abuse material
that's been reported,
and it takes a hash,
and you take a hash of each image.
It could be, like, an MD5 hash.
And then on every client service,
you take an MD5 hash of every image that's ever shared,
as it's shared,
and you compare them,
and if there's a match,
you send it to Big Brother.
Um...
There...
There are...
I found...
I know two systems...
I found papers saying that two systems like this exist,
and I'm sure there are many more.
One I found is from the Canadian Center for Child Protection,
and another is from Apple.
And I'm sure there are others,
but these two I have linked to the...
some papers about them in case you want to read about them.
So one way you could do this is with, like, an MD5 hash.
You can also use what is called a perceptual hash function
so that if you have two images that are similar,
they will have similar hash values.
And that way, I guess, like,
if the image is resized or something,
you can, um...
I mean, the simple version, if it's resized,
you can match it, but also...
it can be a much more distant match.
And later I'll mention
you can have really bad false positives.
So, uh...
Still...
Like...
Probably, like, hacker people don't like this already,
but, you know, the people who like this say that this is good,
but we need more
because we're having more child sexual abuse material,
and we need more advanced methods than even perceptual hashing.
And this is where, like, artificial intelligence,
whatever that is, will come about.
But still, a system, an image-based system,
only works for detection of known...
probably known child sexual abuse material.
Maybe with some more advanced system,
we could detect, like, child sexual abuse material
that we didn't know about before.
Or maybe we could detect stuff that's happening by text,
such as solicitation for sexual activities, grooming.
Um...
And...
In practice,
like, the...
I don't think the regulation says
you need to have a human review this.
I guess it would be really scary to me
if they implemented this and there was no human review.
But because there's human review,
at some point,
someone's going to read your private communications
if there's a false positive.
So if, like, you have an image of your dog
that's marked as child sexual abuse,
or child sexual abuse material,
someone will...
Someone will have to review this image
and see that you took a picture of your dog.
And, um...
That's...
I think even if we have, like, MD5 as the hash function,
we will have false positives
because you can have legitimate purposes.
Like, if you're two organizations that, um...
are stop... trying to detect and stop
child sexual abuse material,
they might share images between each other.
So, um...
Even in that case, you're going to have false positives.
But if we use some complex artificial intelligence,
surely there's going to be a lot of false positives.
Um...
And...
One more point before...
Actually, no, I have a fun story on this last point.
I, um...
Years ago, I introduced two people
who happened to work on, um...
Like, stopping...
Like, detecting...
Uh...
Child sexual abuse material and other bad stuff.
And they were, like...
One of them had some really cool idea that the other one
really liked, and they wanted to share the information.
So the one sent an email to the other.
And I was standing right...
Like, I was sitting right with them.
And he said, okay, I'll send you the email,
but I'm not going to say what we were talking about.
So, like, even two people who are employed
in the business of, um...
Like, stopping child sexual abuse
can't say in their email
that that's what they're doing.
Um...
Anyway, uh... So...
Before I... So I'm still on the topic of
what is generally being proposed
and how it might be implemented.
Um... One more point on this.
I called the talk
Clydeside Scanning, and, um...
I don't really like the name.
Clydeside Scanning, um...
Means...
I'm going to scan...
Before you send...
I send you a message,
and before you receive the message,
some third party is going to scan it.
Uh...
Against... Like, compare it against the known
bad images. And...
That is one thing that would probably be part of this.
But there are many
other things that would be...
Um...
That could maybe accomplish this.
I think the Clydeside Scanning is particularly relevant
if we have end-to-end encryption, because...
If there's end-to-end encryption,
we need some way to...
Um...
Like...
Do the scanning while pretending to still maintain
the end-to-end encryption.
Um...
I wonder, did I, like, lose everyone?
Because I don't have slides and pretty pictures,
and maybe that helps.
Okay. Great. Thank you.
So I said I would do, uh...
Let's do this again.
I said I would do the...
What the proposal is.
Now I'm going into the Y...
The Y section of, like, uh...
Actually...
Oh, I actually have two Y sections.
I have why it's bad, and then why
people might have proposed such a bad thing.
And I'm going to start with why it's bad.
And I learned once that if you want to
convince people of something, you should do three things.
You should say... They're called in Greek...
I mean, I'm going to say it wrong.
Like, pathos...
Uh...
Logos and ethos, maybe?
One of them is logical arguments.
One of them is
some very emotional example.
And the other is some authority.
And I think people here care most about the first one,
but I hope the...
I won't bore you too much with the other two.
The logical reasons.
I think the privacy risk
is kind of clear.
And, uh...
Yes.
And at some point, like...
Well, yeah.
I pretty much already said that.
There's going to be false positives.
Someone's going to have to review it.
And, like, do you actually trust everyone in the...
Whoever, like...
It could be the EU center for whatever they're calling it.
Or it could be, like, any of these companies
that have to implement this.
They're reviewing it, and it's probably
not someone who, like...
It's probably not a very, uh...
You're going to need a lot of people reviewing it.
So I don't really trust that they're going to
do everything properly.
Um...
And...
Like...
If we have to scan...
If we have a communication between me and you,
and we're doing end-to-end encryption,
we can't do this.
There's a method of breaking the end-to-end encryption.
Like, one way to do it is we scan the image
on your laptop
before you encrypt it.
Another is there's some
master key that can decrypt your encryption.
Either way,
uh...
If you're going to follow the rule,
your end-to-end encryption is broken because
maybe there's a false positive.
I mean, if you're actually...
Of course, if you're actually, like, sharing child sexual abuse material,
the end-to-end encryption will be broken.
But if you're doing a false positive,
it's supposed to be broken.
So, um...
That's the, like,
freedom reasons.
But there are other reasons why it's bad.
First is, um...
It's not known
to be helpful for stopping
child sexual abuse.
Yes. So, um...
I... Two points
related to this. One is
this new fangled technique
is not shown to be effective.
Um...
And a specific reason why it's not...
Why, uh...
Okay, and then there's...
First, it's not known to be effective.
Now we can speculate why it won't be effective.
One reason it might not be effective
is that, according to
a board member at the
Child Protection Association of Germany,
Joachim Tschurk,
most illegal online activities
already occur via forums and the dark web.
And I do not think that the dark web
will implement this.
And then even if you implement it,
um... I mean, even if, like,
I'm a criminal and I'm gonna keep communicating
by some place that's gonna
implement it, maybe I can find a way
to work around it. Especially if it's...
If it's, like, implemented in something like
on the client application,
I can find a way around it, you know?
Um... So...
Yes. Not shown to be
effective. Good reason to think it won't be effective.
Also, there are already
effective methods.
And maybe we should just use them more.
So, like...
I found some, um...
articles about, like,
police say that they can't get
content like child sexual abuse material
removed, but if just some random
guy emails the service provider
and says, this is illegal,
remove it, the, um...
provider will remove it right away.
So... I don't...
Like, I didn't really look that much
into, um...
So I saw what the
guy wrote, but I didn't
check how correct it was. But there's
something about that.
Um... But also general...
Some other guy was writing,
like, just normal police work
works. You don't need this
mass surveillance.
Um...
Then...
So I said, the reasons
it's bad, it's bad for freedom,
it doesn't work,
it's also, um...
I said it breaks into
an encryption. It also creates a bunch of
new attacks.
Because, um...
I found a paper
that does this. You can read it in more detail.
And he went to, like...
Depending on how you implement it, there could be
different new attacks.
I, uh... You can imagine, like,
if you have some...
some master decryption key,
or if we have something running on the
clients,
there could be new attacks.
Well, the thing is
the proposal is vague
about what would be implemented, so you need
to have a bunch of different
um... possibilities
of what might be implemented, so that you can say
why they're all bad.
Okay, and then the last reason
why it's bad
is that children also need
privacy. So...
You're monitoring...
Like, the main thing is you're monitoring
if, like, a child is having a...
is being
solicited for sex or something.
Um...
And so you're scanning...
You're scanning everyone's message, but you're also scanning
the child's message to protect the child, but in doing this
you're reducing the privacy of the child.
So...
Those are some reasons
why it's bad. Now I'll give you
a practical example that will make you feel so emotional
to see why it's bad.
Uh, does anyone here use NN encryption?
Uh...
I think a lot of you use NN encryption, yeah.
Um, like...
I'll count Signal, or CryptPad,
for example. Um...
So...
These...
Like, if you use Signal or
CryptPad or email with GPG,
I guess
the encryption would have to be broken in order for this to
comply. So suppose,
like, you're using
something like this to communicate
with your spouse, and one day
you share a picture of your dog, and that's marked
as a known... that matches...
That's a false positive match with an image,
and there's a...
I found a paper that they, like,
they were able to contrive a...
There were some, like, examples they found that were
like, in the wild,
collisions that didn't look anything
like each other, but then they also were able to find one that
like, a child looked
like... a child looked like a dog.
So, it's totally
conceivable that a picture of a
dog could match some known child's
sexual abuse material.
And...
So, if you
share that, and then also
maybe you say something
about meeting somewhere,
and maybe all
together this is gonna be a false positive
for child sexual abuse
material and grooming, then
probably a lot of your correspondence
gets shared, and if you had
like, passwords in your correspondence,
that's bad. If you mention
something that's... like the normal things.
If you mention something that's legal
where you are, but not somewhere else,
or it's
illegal in the future or something,
so everyone has something to hide, so
you are, uh,
now your privacy is gone
and you didn't do anything wrong. Meanwhile,
the people who are abusing the children
know to use illegal stuff that
doesn't have this surveillance implemented.
And then, so that was the
sad feeling example of why this
is bad, and now the last thing
is bad is what some authorities say,
and I think usually
hackers aren't so into this, but I hope
these are okay. There was a similar
uh, there, so these
examples are not directly
on the proposal, but
they're related enough, I think. There was
an issue where German police
was doing some general
scanning for terrorists,
and this
went to court in Germany, and it
was determined that data screening is legal
only in the presence of concrete danger.
So a general threat of terrorism
does not suffice, and that was determined to be
bad.
There was also
from the 2020 proposal that
was similar to the 2022 proposal to
to surveil everyone
in order to stop child
sexual abuse. Um,
the European Data Protection
Supervisor had some report on this,
and it said a lot of great
things, and one of the things it said is that
confidentiality of communications is a cornerstone
of the fundamental rights to respect for private
and family life. Even voluntary
measures by private companies, and the
proposal is a requirement,
not a voluntary measure, but even voluntary measures
would constitute an interference with these rights
when the measures involve monitoring and analysis
of the content of communications
and processing of personal data.
And then the last
big authority is the UN
Human Rights Council, which did not have, I didn't
find some report specifically on this,
but they had some report on
freedom on maybe the internet or something,
and, uh,
I think, like, the German
Constitutional Court is, like, kind of a
maybe
a
normal, normal, kind of mainstream
opinion that, like, we shouldn't,
we can't, it's illegal to scan for terrorists,
um, just
general scanning. The, um,
European Data Super,
Protection Supervisor I got, who is a little bit closer
to the hacker one, but the UN Human Rights
Council report, I think, is
like, crazy hacker
level. Because they say that encryption
and anonymity play a critical role in securing
the rights of freedom and expression,
and they specifically mention TOR,
that TOR should be protected
and promoted. Like,
instead of saying we need to,
um,
scan all the children's
communications to protect them from
sexual abuse, we say
we need to give children TOR.
So,
I think the Human Rights Council
would also say this is a bad
regulation.
And this, of course, begs the question,
why would people propose
something so bad?
And I have two, um,
ideas.
One is that people don't realize
it's impossible to do what they want.
Because all these proposals say that
we are going to protect the children and
at the same time we need to preserve everyone's privacy.
Including the privacy of the children.
I found one report by
one civil society group that
I thought demonstrated
this, uh,
if there's a lack of understanding,
it demonstrated it well.
I, um,
I don't want to
call out this particular group because I imagine
it's just the report that I happened to find.
I suspect there are others that have the same, um,
view, but I did
reference the report.
So it's some group that does
some, um, it's called Five Rights.
I guess I'll call it out, but I said it.
It's probably not just
about them, uh, that do something
related to protecting children. And they had this
very long report about very wonderful
things about all the rights that children have
and I think all humans should have these rights,
not just children, but all these wonderful
rights that, uh, they need.
And then there was just one paragraph in this
very long report
saying that, um,
the children need privacy, but the privacy should not
protect the child sex abusers
nor interfere
with child sexual abuse detection systems.
But that's all they said on it.
Like, one or two sentences.
So they didn't say how you're supposed to
protect the privacy, but
not interfere with the child sexual abuse detection
systems.
And
like, maybe they
maybe they were hiding that they didn't know
or maybe they truly didn't know, but
the point here is one theory is that people actually
think it's possible to
um, scan
all the messages for child sexual abuse while
not destroying
freedom.
But, uh, the other
theory is maybe more fun. It's a conspiracy
theory. There is this group called
THORN that is, like, started by
this famous guy, Ashton Kutcher, who
uh, it's, they're like
stop child sexual abuse
on the internet thing.
And, so
Ashton Kutcher
and other people from THORN have been
lobbying the EU to
have proposals like this.
...
Um, so
you could say, like,
they're just another people who
don't know better, like, they think it's possible.
Um, but actually they also have a
proprietary screening service that
I, it seems to me like they sell it, actually.
Even though they're, THORN is a foundation.
They have this proprietary scanning service
called SAFER
that I think they sell.
Um,
and
it could be that
SAFER requires the client side
it requires
I mean, they already have customers
maybe if it were required that we
surveil everyone, they would have more
customers.
Um, so they've been lobbying
the EU government
and the person
um
someone who's been involved in this
uh, I don't really
know anything about government, so I don't
I'm not gonna say, like, a big word
like a proposed, cause I don't actually know
what that means, but um
uh, Ursula von der Leyen
has been involved in
quite involved in this particular
um, proposal
so it could be, like
they talked to her because
the lobbyist talked to her because she's actually
proposed similarly
similar style of thing, like surveil people
to protect the children before
which gave her the nickname
Sensusula in Germany
apparently
when, like, ten years ago
so, uh
yes, so we got to the
like
that was why
uh, it's bad and why people might
want to do it anyway
now the last point
maybe there's something we can do about it
there's already, like, a bunch of groups
writing about how bad it is
which made it easy for me to tell you how bad it is
um, and
I linked to some of those in these notes
that you will be able to find in the program
but also
this was proposed in May
so, there hasn't been a big
European election since
it's been proposed, and it's possible
that this, like, whenever
the Danish election comes up
it will be the first big election that
since this has been proposed, so it might be
something we should keep in mind
and, like
yeah
so, that's all
thank you
any questions?
hello, I'm Henrik
there's at least two problems with these
things in general
one is about the very emotional
that we talk about child sex abuse
and everybody wants to protect against that
but they spend a lot of time
arguing about that
before they get to the second part
where they say we must protect the children
is something that you really can't do
these systems that detect it reliably
and we've seen it with
anti-virus systems, and we also have the same
similar parallels with terrorism
where you cannot detect terrorism
because we have like 200 definitions of what
terror is
so, they skip the part of
what is possible, and then they use a lot of time
on the emotional part, and I'm not sure how we could
combat that, or how we can argue against that
I typically try to shut down
the first part, saying that we all
want that, so you don't have to talk about it
but any ideas about
how we can fight it would be nice
Well, I've given you my ideas so far
one is to say it doesn't work
and the other is to
oh, I said it doesn't work
I did all three
I gave the emotional argument
and I gave the authorities what they're saying
another point is
this is one of the reasons I like the conspiracy theory
because I think it makes more sense
than
people really don't know
I mean, it could be combined
you hire people who
don't know better to lobby
maybe that helps
but anyone else have ideas?
Not an idea, but another question
Which legislation is
superior if I have an iPhone?
Is it the American
legislation that needs to scan
my phone, or is it the European that has to
scan my phone, or is it the Australian that I
communicate with?
I don't know
No, that's also a problem
Wait, which is
do you say which is better or which applies?
Which applies, which is superior
Oh, I see
Or should they all?
Probably they all
I mean, it's also not defined
the internet is, yeah
Any more questions?
But yeah, that's a good point, that's the problem
Oh wait, actually no, I do have some
I can say something vaguely related to that
So this article
that I read about, like it was some journalist
who was trying to
who was questioning this idea that the police can't
take down stuff
He was saying
the police say there's like
the abuse material
is in offshore servers
so we can't do anything about it
Well, first thing is, if you just email them, they'll take it down
regardless of where it is, but usually
it's like
in some place with good internet, like Europe
you know, so
it might not even matter
which one's superior, like
it might all just already be covered
Hi, I'm Karen
Thanks very much for the presentation
There has been
some debate about the proposal from the commission
already, but mainly from
I'm in the European Parliament
and mainly from colleagues from Germany
that have been aware of this chat control
proposal
How will we be able to
unify sort of
the populations
and the opinions in other countries
because I can do some stuff in the European Parliament
as a Danish MEP, but
unless we put pressure on the Danish
government to stop it at the European
Council and in other
European countries do the same
then how, is there
a debate about this in
other countries than Germany
and for the audience, how do we actually
make this a debate that's going to
be going on in Denmark
and some suggestions for that
and then also you were mentioning the lobbying
towards the EU institutions
has there been any proof of
that, has there been any questions asked
because otherwise that is something that we
perhaps should look at, asking questions on
Yes, so to the
first point, how to unify
people, I don't know
maybe you can tell me, if I knew better
maybe I would go into politics
To the second point, yes
a bunch of people have made freedom of
information requests to competent
authorities to get these
meetings with Thorn
and I
in the link
that you will see in the
program, you can see all these
actually I can even open them right now
Okay
So
Yes
so like, there are so many
but here we go
like someone requested
a list
of all the meetings with Thorn
from a Swedish government
and this has
like, here are all the meetings
there are a bunch
So I guess
actually the list of meetings itself
isn't all that interesting but the person who
requested maybe is quite interesting
Does that help?
Okay
Then we go on to the next question
Yeah, maybe it's also a comment
I think the last success we had was
11 years ago with
Akta and here it
actually managed to go into the
public media and we went to the
streets and we did everything
I just don't know why it happened
but at some point we
made it to a critical mass
and then it was actually
easier at least so
we mass mailed politicians and we
did a lot of things so
I think that could
at least teach us a little bit about
what is possible instead of
us saying, okay, nothing is possible
Do you agree?
I don't really understand
how normal people work. I mean
sometimes in very special contexts
with many years of study I can learn
I do happen to have
like a
qualified source
had a theory on the Akta thing
maybe I'll tell you later but her theory
was that
it was because of Polish
soccer fans who couldn't watch their
soccer
I think
that's
why it
I might be remembering it correctly
whether it was Akta or something else
but I definitely remember
there was Polish soccer fans
that couldn't watch their soccer
Any more questions?
Here?
You mentioned
that already but
there is definitely
also an unwillingness
of the police to do
what is necessary to
get these materials
offline. There has been
a report on public German television
where the reporter
sneaked himself into several
child porn forums
where there were sharehoster links
to such material
and he just
reported that
to the admin
of the machines where
the stuff was
and it disappeared within hours
or
in the worst cases days
and like 80% were hosted in the
US and Germany
so it really works
and that begs the question
if that was
really the thing
it's all about
why don't they just do it
because it's proven
that it works
so there might be other
other ideas
behind constructing such
an infrastructure
to do
other things than going against
child porn
Yes, I suspect that's the exact
same article that I read
It's a TV report
Well
I messed with something
um
the uh
the person
uh
it was either
no it was
Robert
and Daniel
Mosbuecker
was what I have
but you know since
I just want to point out
because you bring up the topic
of reporting
when you see the child sexual abuse
material on the website and reporting it
that is just part of this
and that's like
that's kind of like the easy thing
because if it's
if it's known to
if you've already established
if it's already in the database
it's pretty easy to do this
and this regulation would
the proposal would do much more than that
I mean maybe it wouldn't actually
but like the way it's written
in order to comply you would have to do much more than that
than
than just taking down the material
I think 11 years ago
with ACTA there was
the luck that the digital rights
community and the sort of
anti-globalization and
anti-capitalist movements
came together in a common cause
and therefore managed to
stop a trade deal with the US
and I think that was perhaps why
it succeeded 11 years ago
I think
in order to stop the proposal on
chat control I think we need to
emphasize on the fact that it doesn't work
that it will not make
lives safer
for children because if we just say
it's bad for all of our
privacy even though that we feel that this is
an important enough argument
others will say well if the balance
is saving children
on the internet and
giving up a little bit of our privacy
then we will prefer saving the children
on the internet so we'll have to say
that this is not something that is
going to work and it
is going to be cost
too much where the
lobbying from the company that wants to perhaps
sell their
filtering mechanism
might come in handy
and then also saying well I mean we need to use
police resources in an effective
manner to actually help
children that are being
groomed or abused
and I think those are sort of the arguments that we
need to play on because if we just say it's
bad for our privacy and it's
not in order
to save children then I don't think we'll
mobilize that many people so I think we
really need to emphasize on what would
work rather than
and then we might be able
to stop this throwing tech at
a societal problem which
I think this is they
had the original proposal from
2020 that didn't
come forward and then now trying
again saying okay we have this problem
that we don't know how to deal with and therefore
let's just throw some technology
at it and see if it sticks
Thank you
Actually if I may just also
bounce off of that point there's another aspect
to it which I think is really important it's not
necessarily that it doesn't help it can actually
make the situation much worse
because as it currently
stands the people
who are distributing this material feel comfortable
distributing it over WhatsApp catch
one of them and you've got the phone numbers of all the others
if we pass
this law we will push them
onto the dark web or other
distribution means which
are more difficult to trace so
as a result basically it will actually make the
lives of these people easier
and it will make it much harder to catch them
so I think that's also something that we should push
that not only will it not work it might
actually make the situation worse
It gives me two
actually both of the last two comments
give me
one of the thoughts is
we don't have any
evidence to say it will work
which is a reason not to do this
but unfortunately we don't have any
evidence like where someone
implemented it and it didn't work so that we
can point to
it would kind of be nice if we did
it would be a very easy argument
and then
to your theory that
they are already comfortable using WhatsApp
so they would be pushed onto another
service
there is a competing theory
that because you can
share it on
like normal
protocols
then it becomes normalized to
distribute child sexual abuse material
and so more people will do it
so I think that argument itself
like
with an experiment
or something that would work
but on its own I don't think it works
Any more questions?
No?
Thank you very much
for a very interesting talk
Thank you