If you are anything like me, when you want to cook something at home,
you visit your favorite search engine and just type in something like chili con carne.
If that's what you want.
And then you typically end up on the same food blog where you have the recipe
that someone who made the blog think is good.
And if you have made it a couple of times, then you might have some changes to the recipe yourself.
Maybe you always add in a smidge of something or change some ingredient up
with something.
Or something else.
And, of course, that's something that you can just remember.
But there are other ways to do it.
There is this tander or tandoor or what it's called.
And that's an open source application for cooking recipe management.
And, yeah, it's open source.
And you can host it yourself.
And you can also use a paid version if you live in Germany.
Something that it's the same product, but the guys that wrote tandoor just hosted the application for you.
And, yeah, I'm just going to show you the hosted version.
Okay.
All right.
And, as you can see, you have all the ingredients, and it is already formatted like this one
tablespoon of something I don't know the name of in English, because this is a Danish recipe.
But, yeah, this makes it very easy to, oh, yeah, and the steps, that is markdown format,
if you know markdown, it's pretty easy to change that.
Yeah.
But when you have the ingredients like this in a nice data format, then you can start
using it for stuff like shearing.
You can add it to a shopping list, and you can just edit how many people that you have
invited for dinner or something like that.
And you can also create the meal plans.
For example, if I want to cook chili con carne on Tuesday, and we will be four persons, then
you can just put it in like this, and you can add it to a shopping list.
And this is nice, because if you have a lot of the same ingredients for different meals,
then it will just aggregate the amount of what you need.
But of course, you would want to use the same units, like if one recipe says that you need
100 ounces of something.
Yeah.
And if another recipe says that you need kilograms, then it won't get aggregated correctly.
So yeah, and of course, you would want to use the same language as well, because otherwise
it will not get aggregated.
So yeah, and this works on many different websites.
You can just look for lasagna as well, and all, yeah, just all recipes.
One looks like this.
Just take that as well, and plop it in here.
Yeah.
Oh, it goes up there.
We'll leave that there.
And you can see that it works with this one as well just fine.
And there might be some issues with some of the recipes, as you can see this one, too,
and then the...
There we go.
the unit is six and then ounce and cans over here so that doesn't really make sense so sometimes
there can be some passing errors that you have to correct like this is actually six cans and
then just remove what was that tomato paste and then that's fixed right okay and this works on
a lot of websites I haven't really come by any sites that doesn't work on and I was surprised
as how this worked and it turns out that there is a schema on schema dot org
I think this recipe and actually there's this standard structure for recipes cooking recipes
and that's not something that you see on the website but it is there in the HTML last
sides uses RDF H format and you can see why we had the error before because the recipe ingredient
is eight- rallied and it doesn't have to be all the way to the hamsaver again we hook it up to some
in RLDV anymore and there's the error here also one of theoten so we really want to clarify
what does this mean um I don't know any way that we can just show it and show it in the end so everything
here some Hannah marine ones showing on the other side you be all right and we've got to start maybe
we can actually let's have the same behavior one see here we've got a little delete and see here we go okay and motions
just a string it's not how many of some item it's just a string that has to be
passed yeah and I think that we can see for example what this website is using
and maybe recipe oh well it is these item props recipe ingredient that are parts of the schema
and you can see that they use the RDF age based on that format so that's basically how it works
yeah
it would be nice if there were some integration with if you use online shopping or something like
that where you could just copy the shopping list to some supermarket that you use but I haven't
found any integrations like that so you have to copy all the stuff over but at least it gets
aggregated for you so it makes it quite easy if you cook for like a week or two at a time
um
yeah
so
I think that's it
applause