I
Would like to welcome our next speaker
This is Paul Henning camp who is going to give us a talk about
Surveillance too cheap to meter. Please give Paul Henning a big hand
Thank you
So how many here do not understand Danish
Okay, we'll do it in English
Some of the illustrations will be in Danish, but I'll explain what the show
so
Many years ago. We had a lot of fun about this t-shirt
And since then we realized that this may actually be correct
And we talked a lot about the political layer, but this year I want to look at their financial layer
Because we generally tend to ignore that and I think it's incredibly important for the surveillance
situation
So I'm going to rewind very very far back
in
1954 the chairman for the US Atomic Energy Commission
gives a speech for the National Association of Science writers
and
one of the things he says is that
We will probably soon have electrical energy too cheap to meter
That has become a problem for the atomic energy
Business ever since
People have been rubbing their nose in this statement. This is from the US Nuclear Regulation Agency
they have a
Frequently asked question to try to explain this thing
But he actually has a very precise and very good point
This is a cut from the Danish newspaper The Engineer from 1959
containing statistics about the Danish grid in
1958-59
They're seeing growth of 7% per year
But only a doubling over the last 10 year though, but if you take those numbers and you look out and say what will a
normal house use of electricity in 2020 you get a number between
Megawatt hours and 2.6. Megawatt hours. The reality is only 1.5
But if you were in the business of producing and selling electricity at that point
This scared the shit out of you
They looked at growth curves like this
This is a semi-locked scale. The y-axis is logarithmic. This is like, you know, COVID-19
Exponential functions
They also knew that the oil reserves were finite
There might be oil we haven't found yet, but at some point we'll have used all the oil
And if you look at a finite resource and exponential growth, it runs out really fast
So at this point the only technology available to them that would be able
To follow that curve, however far it would go would be nuclear power
It was the only energy that had sufficient density
That we wouldn't have to put down a coal-fired plant in every town throughout the West
So it was more or less
Totally assumed, given, beyond dispute that we will be building nuclear power plants because it's the only way to continue the curve
this is a
big spread from same engineers newspaper from
1966 where they say that they're starting to save up the money now to build the first plant in
1975 and it's not
It's not if they will it's when they will with an option of building it
A little bit earlier, maybe
There's no I mean yeah, there's some problems we need to deal with but there's absolutely no
Public debate at this point nuclear power is going to happen and that's going to happen and that's just going to happen
There's no choice
But nuclear power has a big problem you can't regulate it
The curve you have on your left side here is the Danish electricity use over a day in December in
1961 and
We have a very big peak in the morning and in the afternoon and it during lunch everybody
cools down or something
at this point
moving major users of electricity was
Unthinkable, we're back in thehsts everybody go on summer vacation in the same three weeks
The problem is you can't regulate a nuclear reactor
its physics
It's not something you get to debate.
The top curve shows the regulatory domain in Belgium today.
You can regulate a nuclear reactor 25% down for less than six hours, but then it has to
run continuously for three days at full power again before you're allowed to regulate it
down again.
And this is simply a matter of neutronics in the kernel.
The fundamental problem is that a nuclear reactor is a cylindrical device.
You have fuel rods going vertically down through it, but the nuclear reaction is a spherical
phenomena and the more power you have, you generate, the larger the sphere.
And that means if you, when you cut it, when you reduce the power production, you reduce
the radius of the square in the middle where you have sufficient neutronic density and
it gives all sorts of problems.
Both in terms of fusion results that eat neutrons, but also in terms of burning up spent fuel
and so on.
The bottom one, I'm not going to try to explain it, but it's basically regulating a nuclear
reactor is like sailing a supertanker in a very narrow strait.
Or maybe I should say containers, Shiva and Suez Canal.
You really don't want to try to wiggle around.
The small gray area here at the top is the normal fuel.
It's a normal frequency control area.
That's where you can run your nuclear reactor without any questions under normal circumstances.
So the question is, what do we do about all this electricity?
We'll have the nuclear reactors running up here and then we'll have a couple of peak
plants we'll use for the peaks.
But then we have all this electricity, what are we going to do with it?
I mean, we can stop the turbine and just have the heat go out into the air, into the water,
whatever.
If we let the turbine run, that's actually better for it, running constantly also.
So we have all this electricity.
So we have a situation, an economic outlook, where we will have power production that way
overshoots the average demand.
Too cheap to meter comes in because power meters are actually expensive.
You have to buy them.
You have to install them.
You have to read them.
You have to do the bookkeeping.
You have to handle the people who don't pay their bills.
You have to do statistical tests that they're still precise.
You have to calibrate them and so on.
It's actually a big business.
This is what bookkeeping looked like in the 1960s when we were looking at this.
Remember this is, computers are starting to get into it.
But it's very attractive to think things like, maybe if we remove the variable element
of people's electrical bill.
We don't have to do, we'll have four different kinds of electricity bills.
If you have one phase, if you have three phases, if you have a big fuse, if you have an even
bigger fuse.
Right?
We can have them pre-printed.
We just need to stamp the name and address and send them out.
It's much simpler.
We don't have to have people go out and read the meters.
Right?
We don't need to care about the calibration because there's no meter.
You'll be limited by the fuse, the top fuse going into your house, end of story.
So the place where this comes from is that we'll have these enormous fixed costs and
the variable cost will be marginal.
So there's no point in spending money metering the variable part.
Transpires, things didn't go that bad.
The curve kind of leveled off and we got taught an idea about oil back in 1973 and we've never
forgotten that again.
We never made ourselves dependent on fossil fuels from unstable regimes ever since.
Not a problem.
Solved.
Um.
And the idea that we could ditch the electricity meter was not something he was alone about.
This is an editorial from the same paper again.
Throw out these, just waste of money and administrative overhead, right?
This was literally how the electricity business thought at this time.
So back to the future.
So today the major fight on the Internet.
The major fight on the Internet.
The major fight on the Internet is for lower latency.
The first thing that happens whenever you go anywhere with a mobile phone is a DNS look
up.
And since DNS is very useful in tracking people, all the DNS records have very low TTLs.
They're not cacheable for very long.
In the ultimate case, you have one big company that basically has no TTL on the DNS records.
And then they fuck up the DNS server so nobody can reach them.
And it transpires their own systems cannot reach the DNS server either.
And since they have everything probably done on computers, they end up having to drive
three high-level managers down to a data center in the South Bay so that one of them can say
to the guard, which is his responsibility, that the next one is okay, and the next one
can say the third one is okay, and he can say this guy is allowed to go in and muck
with that router.
And I'm told it was not going any faster because somebody called, I don't know, Mark or something.
I don't know.
I don't know, Mark or something.
Kept calling everybody on the phone and yelling at them something about owning the company
and stuff, but nobody knew the phone number.
So, and I mean anybody can say that, right?
But, they have larger TTLs now, by the way.
The primary argument for HTTP 2 is to reuse the TCP connection we already have open so
that we don't have to have the three-way handshake before we get the first contact.
The primary argument for HTTP3 is we have a persistent session, so that even if our
mobile phone moves somewhere else, get a new IP number, we can get the first request with
a single packet to reduce the latency.
It's all about getting the latency down.
So why is that priority number one?
Because when you go into any well-monetized website, it throws around 50 to 100 HTTP requests
out.
Targeted advertising, the actual content may come at some point, third-party content, social
media tie-ins, analytics engagement, all this crap.
This is an example of it.
Some of it is in red because I run no script on my browser, so they don't get to start
the entire cascade.
Targeted advertising is a major part of this because to do targeted advertising, you have
to ask who wants to advertise here.
When you go into websites, there's an online, real-time auction going on about your attention.
It's run by Google and Facebook, but below them is an ecosystem of a couple of hundred
brokers who will bid in these real-time, very rapid auctions and say, oh, I have an advertisement,
I want to show this user, and so on.
Some of these brokers never win to show any advertising, which is kind of a funny thing.
They're just, you know, listening in on the traffic.
And this is basically why the mobile experience sucks.
All the crap they have to do to do the advertising on top of it.
But everybody blames their telco.
Not entirely unfairly, I would say, but the soggy experience is mainly blamed on telcos.
So telcos roll out a new network, 5G network, to improve things.
And this is their number one priority.
The fight for 5G, shorter response time, bigger bandwidth.
But the shorter response time is the big one.
The bandwidth is sort of a secondary thing, really.
And it's not been a secret.
5G were ready as far as everybody thought, until somebody came and said, we have to get
these latencies down.
That delayed 5G for about three years, the standardization process.
Getting latency down, getting latency down, getting latency down.
When you want a higher bandwidth, you need to use a higher radio frequency.
That means you have a shorter reach.
When we had the NMT, the first mobile telephone network.
Well, the second mobile telephone network in Denmark.
We had 28 base stations for all of Denmark.
That was all it took.
And you recovered sailing all the way to Sweden, too.
Then we got GSM, which under normal circumstances is limited to 35 kilometers.
You can do a trick with dual time slots, so you can double that, but then only have half
as many handsets and stuff.
LTE reduced it to 10 kilometers.
5G.
In many instances, reduces it to 100 meters in high population areas.
This also means now they know where you are equally precisely.
With GSM and LTE, they're new within 100 meters, a radius of 100 meters on certainty, circular
error probability.
With 5G, they will know where you are within a few meters.
This means they will know what ice cream shop you are.
They will know where you went into, if there are two.
They can tell whether you went to Burger King or McDonald's, even when they're next door.
But this is purely a side effect.
That's not why they built the network.
But it comes out of building the network.
And these data pours out of the network constantly, because the network needs these informations
to work.
You cannot get the 5G network to move.
You cannot move the data if it doesn't know where you are, which antennas and so on.
And historically, telcos have been data dependent.
They were almost paranoid about call data records, because they would have to go to
court with customers who said, I never called this number of this sex line you claim I called.
They'd have to drag them into court, show here's the call data.
They'd have to drag them into court, show here's the call data record from this switch,
this switch, this switch.
We can show you made this telcom call.
It's valuable data.
It used to be valuable data.
And there's this little build over, you know, how many people called their grandmother on
Christmas Eve to say Merry Christmas.
That was a very big thing in the US.
And how many people went to the Justin Bieber concert or Roskilde Festival or Black Friday
and City 2 and so on.
Customers don't complain about phone bills anymore because they're flat rate.
It transpired that the volume of traffic made teletraffic too cheap to meter.
All this paperwork was too expensive.
And I can semi-happily, unhappily say that I was there when it happened in Denmark, when
Cyber City introduced flat rate internet access.
Because it was simply cheaper for us to give people a fixed price than to do all the paperwork
and print all the lines about what they had used and when they had used it.
So today telecommunications is flat rate.
When people complain it's because they've been sucked up by some cruise ship or other
predatory network, which is now illegally used so that shouldn't happen anymore.
So the entire go to court thing with the data is gone.
It's gone.
So why don't the telcos stop?
Well they need to change the equipment to stop it.
They can't change it from the operational network.
It will pour out of the operational network whatever happens.
But they could stop collecting it, couldn't they?
Yes, except there may be a court order on some of it.
So they still have to record that.
And they may be doing technical experiments.
Experiments of their own to find out where to put up new base stations.
So they also have to keep that data.
And there's probably more special cases than that that I don't know about.
And then there's politics.
But we're at layer eight.
We're not doing the politics so we'll skip that one today.
And recently there was a bit of news about the New Day which is basically TDC, the incumbent
telco in Denmark.
They're going to spend a billion kroner on a new back office system.
They had the same news about ten years ago.
They gave it up back then.
This is expensive stuff.
They will have to pay money to stop the collection of the data.
Nobody pays them to say stop, please stop monitoring everybody in Denmark.
There would be money out of the telcos pocket to stop it.
It's cheaper for them to continue because they have it in place.
It's running.
I seem to have moved the slide around now.
Oh, yeah.
No, that's the second part.
The other part of the 5G network is the communication with big numbers of Internet of Things units.
This is also a big one.
So we're seeing more and more consumer items getting over the air upgrades.
There was an interesting case recently where the AEG.
AEG.
Did a software update on an Internet-connected microwave oven and gave it the wrong file.
So it thought it was a steam oven.
And the steam oven or the microwave oven doesn't have the keys you use on the steam oven to
get into the software updates menu.
So they have to send a technician out and do the...
And turn it back.
But we're seeing increasingly that...
I'm sorry.
Sorry.
I mean, there is a built-in SIM card.
There is a built-in Internet connection to download all the air updates without the consumer
being involved.
The vendor gets a volume agreement with a Telco.
We need a hell of a lot of SIM cards.
They will be in one place, they will never move.
Well, maybe once or twice in ten years.
But they're not going to run around, never going to run to big events.
events, they're not going to bother you. There will normally be no traffic on them. And we
can schedule burst traffic. When we do a software update, we can call you and say, when is a
good time for you? So, the telco can give very good rates on this. You would be amazed
how cheaply you can get a SIM card when you call up with conditions like this. My lawnmower
robots come with a SIM card. I've never paid a thing for it. Because, volume, high-end
cars, high-end white goods, built-in SIM cards these days. The legal business case for this
or the moral business case for this is that you won't have any trouble with customers
who cannot figure out to attach their...
dishwasher to their Wi-Fi. You also won't have troubles with the ones who don't want
to attach it to their Wi-Fi. You can tell very precisely when the warranty period starts.
You can tell exactly when it was used first time. You can know if it has been misused,
if it's been overloaded, if it was not installed level, if it was not... all these things.
If it was outside temperature limits, lower voltage, higher voltage, all these things.
You know that now. So, you can reduce fraud from almost nothing to nothing, right? Whether
that's a good investment of money, well, that's the interesting thing, right? You also get
telemetry for optimizing your product, so that the next model will last exactly the
warranty period plus two weeks. That's legal.
The shady business case is that once you have the new model on the market, you can
handicap the old one. Nobody would ever do that with a mobile phone, I'm sure, right?
I have credible information that something happens to high-end cars of certain brand
when the new model is out. From somebody who's pretty upset about something happening to
his car. Whether that's legal is a very good question. You can also brick the product
if somebody attempts to do third-party unauthorized service on it, or tries to drive the tractor
from Ukraine to Russia. And then there's the outside business case. The data is not going
anywhere. The data you collected, whether they are GDPR or not, we can discuss that,
unauthorized access. I will argue that certainly GDPR data, but most data should be, we should
think about it as helium. Whenever you have some physics experiment that need to be vacuum
tight, you try with helium, because helium will get through anywhere. It's a very tiny
atom. It's a very tiny atom. It's a very tiny atom. It's a very tiny atom. It's a very
tiny atom. It's a very tiny atom. It's a very tiny atom. It's a very tiny atom. It's
not electrical charged. If there's any kind of hole, it will leak. And it seems that
personal data is the same kind of thing. Nobody seems to be able to keep a lid on them.
They leak out, one way or another. We have police officers looking up potential girlfriends
still, after I think four or five of them have been fined for it. It still happens.
It's just impossible to keep it tight.
And that means if you're a vendor of something and you collected all this information, if
there's any way to exploit it, it probably will be. If nothing else, when your company
gets ransomwared, we'll break all your customers' dishwashers. Christmas morning. If you don't
pay us. Right? And then we have the downright trivial with baby monitors being connected
to pedophile networks because apparently a lot of scantily clad women appear on baby
monitor cameras. Who saw that one coming? But the general problem is all this surveillance
is too cheap to meter now. The benefits of putting a SIM card in your high-end product,
the fact that you can't do anything about it remotely, outweighs the disadvantages of
all the shit data you collect on the cars as a result of it.
The telcos probably don't want to be in the surveillance business, but it would be more
expensive for them not to be. But we're seeing this go into more and more products. Televisions
with cameras, so they can sell audience data back to advertising networks. How many people
watch this ad? How many people watch this show? This is not a problem we can solve technically.
I know some people are very enthusiastic about slapping encryption on everywhere, but this
is not going to do shit for it. Problems at layer N can only be solved at layer N plus
one and higher.
all those fucking layers to begin with.
So these problems are something that will have
to be solved politically.
We cannot solve
them economically. They are economic problems.
They have to be solved politically.
What we'll probably see is
that you can get high-end models and you can pay
a surcharge for privacy.
Privacy has always
been a luxury good.
The way you avoid
having your credit card transactions
tracked is you don't
have a credit card. You have people
to have credit cards for you.
When some
crazy expensive yacht
lands in a harbour,
it is not
some Russian rich
asshole who goes down to show his
passport. It's the first
mate who comes down with a bunch of passports,
shows them to customs and then
clears everybody on the ship.
Customs.
Customs don't go aboard the ship to see if those
are the people on the ship.
They just see a pile of passports, stamp them
and everything's okay.
Privacy is a money thing.
I think we'll see that. I think we'll see
that you can buy your new
sports car and then do you
want the privacy option or do you want the
real-time service option?
We can probably also get to cases
where you buy a new television and
then you'll either have to sign up
for all the advertising and log in
to get the account and the network and all that crap.
Or you'll have to buy a subscription so you don't have to.
Or you'll have to do like people like us,
spend the time and money to
lobotomise the surveillance to get rid of it.
If we look at the possible political solutions,
one would simply be to tax transmission
of surveillance data.
Tax telemetry.
We can tax everything else
so we can also tax telemetry.
So that
it becomes a more
balanced business case.
So it's not for free.
So that maybe you shouldn't meter it
because you'll be paying tax on it.
We could tax
person data.
I think that's a very good idea.
Have an exponential
exponential scale that says
if you have data about 10 people
because you have an association of whatever,
you pay one crown a year.
If you have 100 people,
you pay 100 crown a year.
If 1,000 people, you pay 10,000 crown a year.
Let it go up with a square of the number of persons involved.
To make people think about there being a cost
to collecting all these data in the same place.
The same way where there's a cost of collecting data,
there's a cost of collecting dangerous chemicals
or explosives or anything else in big piles, right?
Or we could ban things.
A lot of things are banned.
A lot of things could be banned.
We could simply ban collecting any data
that can be used for tracking purposes.
Unless there is a approved application
with the Ministry of Privacy or whatever.
There's many ways that could be banned.
There's many ways that could be structured.
But there are political things that could be done
to turn this economic situation around.
And they will have to be done if we want to turn it around.
As long as this is purely an economic issue
for the people in layer eight,
surveillance is too cheap to meet it.
Of course, the problem is that
the politically possible solutions,
that's basically an empty sheet.
Nobody at the political layer
are willing to even talk about this at this point.
There are things coming out of EU,
but they're not addressing the economics of the situation.
They're addressing it on the,
should we say, ideal level of privacy.
But never looked into saying whether the economics
of the situation should actually be addressed.
That's a way we as nerds are not used to think.
And it was a bit of an eye opener for me
when I started to think about it in these terms.
So I hope I've shared my problem with users,
not just my worry anymore.
Okay, thank you.
Questions?
If there are any.
Any questions?
You won't have to pay for them.
No, no questions?
Really?
Then, really?
No questions?
Oh, that was a question, good.
so you mentioned data retention basically earlier so the the system of billing uh on sim cards on
mobile phone data and the fact that yeah up until now we've been we've basically been keeping track
of the calls of the use of data etc and that because of flat rates that's no longer necessary
um how does this so i i'm if i remember correctly there was a ruling by the european court of
justice precisely on the question of of retention of telephone records saying that telephone
companies were only allowed to retain them for the purposes of uh billing so what does that say now
should it really be the case today that uh the danish telecoms operators are still retaining
that information if it's no longer necessary for billing that's kind of my question but maybe i
missed it so so so that's basically a political question right
um
and i've skipped that in this talk but but basically there's an economic thing about making
criminal investigations cheaper also right if you can just look up where the potential
criminals were that's a lot cheaper in police work so there's a political pressure also on some of
this surveillance but so far we have not had the danish parliament try to get data from
dishwasher many times
CDаешь
um
we want a criminal justice system to be able to work and there's some checks and
balances that need to work and and that's the political uh struggle to get that right but um
without that there's no doubt that the eu justices basically said you have to leave
your data once you've done the statistics i mean the telco is still here when the telco is being used
still has a right to do, say, how much traffic
do we have Monday, Tuesday, Wednesday, and so on
at a statistical level.
But tracking at the individual level, no.
That's clearly out without one.
But in that case, the politics have trumped it
on interesting and pretty rocky ground in Denmark.
But that's a battle on the layer one level up, right?
It's a little bit difficult to come with questions
after such an excellent talk, so I think that's why
the audience is a little bit silent.
And I'm going to start with some stupid questions.
A lot of the surveillance that you're talking about
is at the individual level.
But a lot of the data that the Internet of Things
and the companies will say that they're looking for
is on the non-personal level.
When we're looking at the proposals on, for example,
a data rack,
and sort of sharing data also across companies
and countries within the EU, having these data lakes,
how do we, at the political level,
make sure that we protect against having surveillance
built into our washing machines and our cars and our phones
while at the same time making sure that we can have
the best use of them possible?
Tax the shit out of it.
No.
I mean it literally.
Taxing can be used to raise revenue,
and it can be used to regulate behavior.
And tax SIM cards with no other purpose
than spying on people and things.
Why shouldn't it cost, I don't know, 100 euros a year?
I mean, the numbers of a discussion and calculations
and spreadsheets and so on, but there's
been a total unwillingness to tax anything related
to the internet so far because, oh, we shouldn't stop
the next Bill Gates, right?
I happen to disagree on that one.
But it's time for politicians to realize that this is now
not something adjunct to society.
This is an integral part of society.
And it needs to work with and in society.
And it needs to be regulated to work in society.
And I think, I don't understand why collections
of personal identifiable information is not taxed
at this point, simply as a way to reduce the accumulation
of it in larger and larger piles.
And the fact that it would bankrupt Google and Facebook,
I don't see that as a negative.
There's a question?
Yes.
Oh there's another person behind you.
Hey, I wanted to mention that start them brief,
the data letter, that's kind of an idea from the
key computer club that's been around for awhile.
And that was
to make a law that requires every company to sent
each and every person that they've got data on a
letter once a year detailing what exactly
they have on them and if they don't have a physical address they have to use some
like whatever means of contact they have but essentially the idea was similar to
your taxation idea that that increases the cost and in this case also the
awareness of the users or the people that whose personal data is stored yeah
it increases the costs for the companies I mean yeah and that of course well yeah
I don't know that much about it but I wanted to mention it yeah it's a
there's certainly an argument about making it more obvious for people how
much they're being spied on but on the other hand I don't think postal services
are good as tax collectors it would basically be a stamp tax right postage
stamp tax
but but yeah I mean anything anything that will will shift the balance in the
right direction is fine with me but I think I would prefer to use it to raise
revenue that could then be used beneficially rather than just to boost
up the postal companies of the different countries I know very little about
politics and how to implement laws and taxation so could you talk a little bit
about
how how it would be implemented practically would it require some
technical solutions or is it basically just asking every company to report how
much data they've been collecting I can imagine many ways of doing it but I
would prefer to leave it to people who are good at writing that kind of stuff
how to implement I mean companies are supposed to report a lot of stuff these
days and that seems to work mostly
so I think having them reported on the penalty of you know we're going to
nationalize your company if you lie that is ultimately what happens in I mean if
you lie about the the yearly accounts or whatever basically the company can be
dissolved that's pretty much the law of any land if it's badly bad enough they
can just hold a company right and I think it should just be handled the same
way and and similarly if you travel across the feelings which I that sometimes
can go sit in your car and having the company suit and popular on its own so
yeah and and similarly if if turbulence is okay in most countries the only improvement
there is no model you could live in that situation versus proportionally Кстати
that means three erstatement good rooms where villa managers can live Bob's all right so
you can have time and you can have different people and businesses so it's a good way to
If you have a company that's permitted to use dangerous chemicals and an inspection
shows that you have not lived up to the conditions of that, your company will be shut down.
This is perfectly normal regulatory business, I think, it's just it's cyber so we shouldn't
touch it because we need to get the politicians over that hump and tell them to actually get
on with their job.
Thank you for the very nice talk, very depressing talk.
I just wanted to add one thing which was you said many cars or expensive cars have this
and in fact it's all cars sold in the European Union after April of 2018 are required to
have cellular connectivity now.
Yeah, but that's for the emergency thing.
They're not required to use it.
They're not required to use it for telemetry, but since they paid to install it.
So I think if they have it, then it's usually it's going to associate with every tower.
It's online all the time in practice.
Yes.
Any more questions?
No.
Good.
We got it opened up a bit.
Yeah.
Well, thank you very much, Paul Henning.
That was an excellent and interesting talk.
Thanks.
Thank you.