Good morning everybody, or good afternoon.
So we are going to go through some stats for a token game and a little bit about what we
did this year with HackerJBD and other game related stuff.
So HackerJBD this year had 52 categories sent to the mailing list, but unfortunately only
12 of them run from outside the game team.
We would like more diversity in the categories, so the more who send in categories, the better
HackerJBD will become.
We experimented this year with a lot of new kind of categories.
We had a lot of constructive and positive feedback, so we are happy about that.
But
we think that we have gotten, both this year and earlier years, we need more network and
cybersecurity related topics.
So if anyone has any ideas, please contact us and give us some good categories with these
subjects.
So the token game this year, well, we had 17 tokens.
When the token game kind of dies out and nobody finds the token, yeah, it's kind of hard to
make new ones.
If people can't find them, then the fun stops.
We had almost the same participants as last year, but we didn't have as many registrations.
And an average of two tokens per participant is somewhat different than last year.
And only one participant found more than 10 tokens.
And nobody found more than 14 tokens.
And nobody found all tokens.
That's a little sad.
We had some different tokens here this year.
Hafnium made the handspring and it had a token hidden.
It took a while for people to figure that out.
We also had another, the movie of the day, there was some metadata hiding a token.
And then there was this one.
There were some token participants that called me evil for the first time.
They called me evil for making this.
But I was quite happy when 8dot one evening contacted me.
He was like he walked by and he looked at it and then was like, huh, and he actually
figured it out without finding all the hints.
So this was part of a bigger token game thing.
So the QR code was a token itself.
But if your base64 coded it, it told you to follow the lights.
The lights had two valid tokens.
25 invalid tokens unfortunately because we are missing input validation on the
token system so I didn't catch that error. I'm sorry about that. The tokens
have been removed from the system but if you followed those you would find a
number, a color and something that looked like a token that also told you
something about what the hell these number were. I'm not going to give it out
because I think somebody want to play with it still but if you followed from
the start of the main road to the end of main road you would have it if you took
the number in sequence have a token but at the end of main road there was a QR
code telling you the hint down below and that's actually also a token in
itself but if you use that you could correlate the colors and then
if the exchange them for the num numbers and you had a token. And if you
also base64 decoded all other texts that look like tokens you would have
had hints for how to decipher the wall of numbers at infoDesk. So yeah
lessons learned we need input validation on the token system that's very
important. There's a huge crossover between
continuing the CTF and the token game players, and that seems to have removed some players
from the token game this year because they focused on the CTF.
That's what happens, but we need to figure out how to balance that more.
Then we need not to hide tokens behind paywalls, so we had a Minecraft token and not everybody
owns Minecraft, so that's an important lesson.
Also, and I didn't know this, I posted a token on Twitter, and apparently it was marked
sensitive content for some reason, so people couldn't find it without having a Twitter
account and removing the filter for sensitive content, so that's not something we're going
to do again.
If possible, we need to prepare more tokens for next year, and we need to announce the
token game more clearly so people know it's on and what it is about.
Yeah, nobody found the cyber bunny, and I'm not going to go into details about the cyber
bunny.
Maybe he'll be back next year.
Any question about the token game?
There's a person here that has no video on that.
Wait a minute.
Look at the microphone.
I did manage to find the cyber bunny in the end.
But there's also...
Okay.
What other video token left I would like some hints on?
Should I just reveal it?
Well, if you look at the schedule for this talk, you will find it immediately.
With a bit of work behind it, but yeah, you have to reverse some things.
Any more questions about the token game?
Excellent.
Yeah.
So, like last year.
We...
Okay.
So, we have the same Pixabook machine.
It can do 80 gigabit per second.
This year, we...
I have a graph of it in a second, but we peaked about 30% of utilization of it.
This year, compared to last year, we had multiple 10 gigabit clients, which was nice.
You were being punished this year as well if you used IPv4.
Okay.
And instead of IPv6.
So, I fixed my clients, finally, and stuff worked.
So, we had two interactive games that were created by J-Wolf.
One was Pong, and one was Snake.
You can still play them if you want to.
Just go up and grab a controller and a friend to play Pong.
Yeah.
We made it so you could live stream.
Did you have any questions?
No.
Okay.
Thank you.
So, it was really, really good.
It's a great idea.
It was great.
So, we have this one last idea here.
So, let's just go back.
Let's start with the pixel flute.
At live.bunhack.dk slash pixel flute.
So, and you can also stream it on multicaster presses just because we can.
So, we had one movie that were being displayed on the pixel flutes and later it was also
converted into some streaming of the Jeopardy games.
Okay.
Most of the traffic was sent from a switch that was at the Pixelfluid server, but we
also had a machine and regular camping that sent on average 7.1 gigabit per second.
This image shows bits per second, if you can read it.
This is around 26 gigabits.
That's pretty nice.
That's better than last year.
We still need to use more bandwidth, though.
You can do 80 gigabit on it, so bring some 10 gigabit machines with you next year.
We may be able to help you create a client if you haven't done so already.
Just give some...
Some hints on what to do.
And this is packets per second.
It's around 2.6 million packets per second.
That's pretty okay.
Yeah, so this year we had a new gaming experience.
It was 10 Cattles by Melinda.
It was up in Kochi at night.
There were two sessions.
One last evening and the one the evening before.
I participated in the first one.
It was quite nice, and we're definitely going to try and make more of such events next year.
So yeah, next year.
And we're still doing Hackathopity, of course, and the token game.
We want more games like 10 Cattles.
So if anybody here knows something about some games that are easy to play and easy to set
up and could be nice for an evening in the dark...
Yeah.
Then let us know.
We're going to try and meet before the camp next year to plan stuff beforehand.
Especially with Hackathopity.
So we don't have to make everything during the camp.
And yeah, we want more game activities.
So if anybody has any ideas, you don't have to join the game team.
But if you want to join the game team and do anything, please do so.
Yeah.
Any questions?
No.
Do we have questions for the team?
Okay.
I see no hands.
Let's give a round of applause for the game team.
Do you have another slide?
Would you?
No.
Well, we would also like to announce the winner of Token Hunt.
Oh, yeah.
Right.
Sorry.
So there is a winner of the Token Hunt.
And the winner is getting a ticket for next year's Spawn Hack.
8Dot is the winner of this year's Spawn Hack.
8Dot.
Yes.
It's the winner of this year's Spawn Hack.
Absolutely the most tokens found.
So if you found the cyber bunny, then you are now up to 15 tokens out of 17 tokens.
So that's quite nice.
Yes.
Thank you.