Good afternoon, everyone.
Yes, welcome to this talk.
My name is Henrik Kramselund, or Kramse for short.
My pronouns are he, him.
And all of my slideshows and educational materials are on GitHub.
My user, Kramse, at GitHub.
And this one is called Getting Started in InfoSec.
It's in the repository of security courses,
which have all my educational materials for everything I do.
So please share and use and get inspired if you like.
There's some contact information.
And just to sum it up, I've been using internet for many, many years.
I've been a network and security consultant for about 25 years plus.
I have gone through, of course, a lot of education myself.
And what I'm trying to do today
is try to get you started in a more nice way
because it can really be overwhelming getting to know security.
So I'm trying to get all of my experience
from the learning network and security myself, being a consultant,
but also when I teach at KEA,
which is the Copenhagen School of Design and Technology,
I think is the English name.
And I'm also a little bit of an activist,
but we can take that over a beer in the bar.
The goals for today is to inspire you,
to create a goal for your education.
We have this quote, the old one,
a goal without a plan is just a wish.
And trying to learn something as big as networking or security
or even the two together can be completely overwhelming.
So many resources are available, so many places to look,
so many people to listen to.
And everybody that has gone through this education by themselves
have, of course, experience.
And maybe it has not been the best way they learned it.
I learned it from some old obscure papers
that were not very easy to follow or read.
And there are much better resources today.
So I'm trying to point you to some of the resources that I'm using.
So mostly this will be inspired by things
that I actually do in my day-to-day work.
I'm also going to point you to a few core concepts
that I think you should know and learn.
And I'm quite stubborn in this regard.
I can be an old grumpy man sometimes,
but I really, really feel that there are some key points
that you need to learn
if you want to work in networking and security.
Some of them are just a need to know.
And if you don't know these things beforehand,
it will be much harder to go further in networking and security.
But if you, on the other hand,
acknowledge that this is needed,
a prerequisite for learning networking and security,
I think you will have a better experience
and will easily learn some of the more advanced,
and of course, we all want to learn the latest concepts,
but it can be really hard.
And even though I have been working in the industry for 25 years,
I have a master's from the University of Copenhagen.
There's definitely papers that I just browse.
There's definitely things I don't understand about security.
And there have been large parts of security that I never look at.
I'm never looking at Bluetooth security.
I'm not looking at infrared security.
I have just decided these big areas are not something
that I want to understand.
I don't want to invest the time.
I don't have the time available.
So I'm trying to inspire you to make a plan for your own wishes,
what you want to learn.
And as an inspiration,
I have taken a security engineering as a job role,
which is one of the things that you could use to guide your adventure into this,
depending on what kind of job role you currently find interesting.
They will have a list of wishes.
Again, they have a wish from the employer who they want to hire,
should have everything, and the kitchen sink,
and should be unicorns, and have these 50 years of experience.
And if they are young and agile without a family,
so they can work 100 hours a week, that would be great.
So sometimes getting to these job role and jobs that you can apply
for will have a list of things that you may want to learn.
And this is actually quite a large list, and it's a list
that actually includes many different fields within security.
Okay.
So having a person that can do all of this,
that's like really, really difficult to find.
And especially in Denmark, we have a shortage of security people.
So they are going to hire.
They are hiring people that don't have all of these skills.
So don't be discouraged from applying for a job,
even if you don't have all of these subjects as ready knowledge right now.
We can also go to some of the core concepts.
And go to some people that have done various categorization
of these fields of network security, network and security.
And one of the categorizations that I really love is the one
from the IC squared, the common body of knowledge.
It has been developed over lots of years.
So it's kind of a nice categorization of the fields
of network and security into more manageable,
they call them domains, other models will call it something,
something else.
But just by looking at categorizations and not trying to learn all of it
at the same time may help you.
So you can decide, I would start with this one,
which is the one that I know most about,
which will be easiest for me to get started in.
And some of these will be quite technical,
but actually some of them are not as technical.
So network and security is a technical field.
But in many ways, it's not a technical field.
There's a lot going on with security.
And I think this one, the eight domains of the CISSP,
common body of knowledge, is a nice way of structuring this.
So I came from a network, communications and network area
and loved networking.
So I went into communication and network security
and found it very easy to read some of these resources.
But when we get to like risk management,
that's not a preferred area for me.
So that's quite hard.
But I know some people in the audience are experts in that.
I'm looking at one in particular,
who's probably more of an expert in risk management,
talking to C-level executives.
And I don't like to talk to C-level executives.
I would rather talk to nerdy people about packets,
which is already in the program in my village.
Later today, we're going to be talking about packets
and protocols, 10G, playing with packets.
So I love that more.
But using these various taxonomies or models,
you can decide which subjects to look at first.
As an example, I have also taken this one,
which is called the Juniper Network Certifications.
Juniper Networks is a large provider of network equipment
being used across the world.
Cisco is another one.
All of these big companies,
they have a very advanced and big programs
for getting certifications in their products.
And I love certifications.
I enjoy certifications because they make you look
at some of the areas
that are not very common in the industry.
Whereas if you're working in the industry,
you will meet these three out of five things
that you always do in the network.
And then there will be four and five,
which you very rarely use.
But getting a certification sometimes helps me,
at least, to read up on some of the parts
that I don't use regularly.
But when they are useful, I will know about them enough
to be able to research them and apply them in real life.
So I enjoy certifications.
I'm not saying that you should take them
or take certifications or invest the money in that.
Some of them can be found freely.
Some of them are more easily.
You can find vouchers
for at least some of the entry-level ones.
And I know that definitely employers
will use certifications.
I love certifications
because it's easy to search for the recruiters.
We're talking about getting into security
probably because you want to get paid
doing what you love, network and security.
So certifications is one of the ways
to also get to know an area.
And as you can see in this one,
it's also divided into cloud and non-cloud stuff
and enterprise routing and switching
and service provider, ISP, routing and switching.
So depending on what area you want to work in,
it may be applicable to other certifications.
You can decide which track to follow.
Then I would like to go back a bit
and restart how to learn network and security.
And I think some of this applies
to probably other technical skills
that you want to get to know.
I call it learning at different levels.
And as an example,
I will use the tool called the Nmap port scanner.
It's included in the movie, the Matrix movie,
which is one of the famous hacker movies.
There's been a bit of hacking in that.
They are running a tool called Nmap.
It's actually a real tool.
So it's one of the hacker movies
that include a real tool.
They are typing quickly
with gloves on and fancy clothes,
but it is actually a very useful tool.
It's also one of the tools
that I think is a need to know tool
because everybody is using Nmap.
You will not have a pen test in the world
that doesn't use Nmap,
or at least I would not consider that a pen test.
I would not consider that a good pen test.
Everybody will use Nmap
and they may use other tools,
but Nmap is a port scanner
that can check for open ports on the internet.
And you can perhaps scan a little bit here.
I'm pretty sure that we will get abuse messages
if you try to scan the whole internet from here.
And since I don't know who you are,
I cannot really forward those abuse messages,
but you can do some light scanning from here.
And all of you in the tent here,
at least you're very welcome
to practice Nmap scanning on my infrastructure.
I have the AS number 57860.
You can scan all my devices using Nmap from here
if you like to and want to play with this.
So this is an example of a must-have tool,
must-learn tool,
must be able to talk about this tool
and understand the output from this tool.
Because in this screenshot,
we are seeing them run the tool with some options.
We are seeing some output from this.
And at the very bottom,
I'm not sure you can read it at the back,
there's actually an exploit being used.
And in the movie,
they gain access to controlling the power
and can shut the whole thing down.
But understanding the output
can be just as difficult
as actually running the tool.
And in this case,
using Nmap as an example,
this tool has about 100 options.
And if you don't even know Linux,
you don't even know command line tools,
then it will be even an obstacle
to getting to run this tool.
It has 100 options.
But then you can look at the man page
because the man page
for all of these Unix, Linux tools,
command line tools
will of course explain
how to use the tool.
And then you can read these 3,100 lines
about how to use these options.
And this tool is actually so complex
that multiple books
have been written about the tool.
Some of them are outdated,
but some of the basic stuff
is still available and useful
and in the tool still.
And of course,
it has also been expanded
with IP version 6.
So that adds another dimension.
But which of the 100 options
should you use?
How do you interpret it?
How do you interpret the results
from this tool?
Looking at this specific tool,
using this as an example,
there are some prerequisite knowledge
to using it.
And to actually use it effectively
in a job role,
in an enterprise,
in an organization,
you will need to combine some knowledge.
So to get started using this Nmap,
you need to have some
prerequisite knowledge.
And the prerequisite knowledge is
what is a port scanner?
And what is a port scanner?
It's something to do with TCP IP.
But what is TCP IP?
Transmission Control Protocol
slash IP Internet Protocol.
It's part of the Internet Protocol Suite.
And actually,
that whole suite includes
a lot of functionality.
It's being used
across the whole Internet.
for multiple purposes.
It's being used
for HTTP port 80.
How many in here know
HTTP and web service browsers?
How many has run a browser?
Yeah.
Trying to activate you a bit.
So getting to know a browser,
having a little bit to know
with web technologies,
some of the people moving into security
may come from a web developer background.
So you will know
HTTP port 80.
And some of you may know
that it runs on TCP.
And now we already know
a little bit more about
what to expect
when we do the scanning
because of course
we will see web servers.
But we need to know
some basic stuff
before we can use
a port scanner effectively.
We also need to know
a bit of the inside
and internals
of the Internet protocol suite.
There's something called
a TCP session setup.
So you need to research
how does TCP actually work.
It works by sending a packet
called a SYN packet
and then it gets
a SYN ACK packet back
and then it sends an ACK.
And then you can actually
start sending a GET request
and get a web page back
from a web server.
And that happens
every time we use TCP.
And that is some of the things
that you need to know
before you can run NMAP
and understand the output.
Then you want to run the tool
and running tools like NMAP
requires some kind of platform
operating system.
It's usually not built
into your operating system
when you download it.
You buy it by a laptop.
I don't think there's ever
a laptop that has NMAP
by default.
They should have.
They should have
in my opinion.
It's one of the first tools
that I always install.
But luckily
this tool
that I always use
is actually
one of the first
tools that I use
to run NMAP.
It's actually
one of the first
tools that I use
to run NMAP.
This tool
which is one of the reasons
I also really,
really love this tool.
It is that
it supports Mac,
Windows,
Linux.
It's open source.
You can compile it
and run it on a mobile phone
if you like.
It's available
for all of us.
So that sorts out
one of the prerequisites
for the hardware
that you need.
But then also
NMAP
we are very lucky
because it has a
GUI front end
which is called
send map
which is the screenshot
shown here.
So if you're
a bit afraid
of command line
options,
that's great.
You can still run NMAP
and I recommend
people new to NMAP
to run this GUI tool.
And it's also
a very,
very nice
GUI tool
for learning NMAP
because it has profiles.
It has a way
to use the GUI
to select options.
There's a bit of explanation
for all of these options.
But also
this tool
actually
includes
the full command
that is running.
It's a bit
mangled
but you can see
NMAP
minus T4
minus A
minus V
and so on.
So it's actually
a nice tool
for learning.
But if you
start out
by watching
a movie
with techno music
and they're just
switching back and forth
between command lines
and running a lot
of options
it can be really hard
to learn this tool.
So running a port scanner
you need to have
a platform.
My recommendation
is to create
a virtual machine
with Kali Linux.
We can discuss
in another
area
which offensive
Linux distribution
to use
and there are some
do Bluetooth hacking, wireless hacking, SDR hacking, maybe some other Linux distribution
may be better for that purpose.
But the Kali Linux has been downloaded millions and millions and millions of copies and installed
around the world.
There are YouTube videos, more than 100,000 YouTube videos in different languages, with
different accents.
There are some in Danish even.
Some of them will be short, five minutes.
Some of them will be 15 minutes.
Some of them will be hour-long videos about Nmap.
So use the right resources, and Kali Linux makes it very easy, because then this tool
is actually installed.
So if you can follow the guide to install Kali Linux, which is also documented by YouTube
videos, then you have a platform to run the tool.
Then later on, when we have the basic stuff, we know how to run the tool, we need to apply
it in a job role.
And that is where it starts to become useful.
And you can actually start to use it in different scenarios.
Using scenarios is a way of, for me at least, and my students, to say we want to perform
some task.
And I have included a list of tasks that I have used in real penetration testing scenarios.
So I may want to do a full TCP scan, which is the first line.
So this is actually a specific invocation of this tool with specific options that will
produce an output file.
And then later on, in some of these, there will be all sorts of magical constants around
these commands that you may not know now, but splitting it up into different scenarios
and trying to work through each of these scenarios will start to make it useful.
And the first one with Nmap for all ports with the TCP, that's actually one of the commands
that some of my students have used in their home networks.
They have applied this.
They have applied this knowledge of scanning all the ports, just getting an output of the
open ports.
And in one case, one of them came back and there was a MariaDB, which was a SQL database
just connected directly to the internet.
Found out it was a consultant that needed access a year ago, and nobody removed the
access afterwards.
And that is things that you can start to use pretty easily and pretty quickly after learning
the basic stuff.
So I hope that describes the process of getting to know a synchro.
So I hope that describes the process of getting to know a single tool, getting started with
a single tool, and then you can expand on that knowledge.
So there's no reason to go and read all the options for Nmap because you don't need all
the options, especially there's a large part of Nmap options that has to do with being
a bit, what you call it, hiding who you are, spoofing addresses and stuff.
And if you are allowed to do Nmap, which is quite easy to get access to if you have a
network.
If you're running in a lab network, you can run it.
So we don't need these options immediately.
And some of them actually don't work really well anymore.
So I just recommend getting permission to run Nmap, and that's actually quite useful.
And try it out in a lab environment or some camp that you make with your friends in a
forest.
You can try out Nmap on a network.
So this is actually what I would recommend as a quality scan of an enterprise if you
did these scans, took all the output, focused on the output for the different parts.
That would actually be quite useful in many circumstances.
There's one called SSH scan, which scans for port 22.
22 is of course an administration port for Linux machines and other Unix-like systems.
And that is actually by itself very important and interesting.
Who can SSH to our machines?
And then you can ask people to say, hmm, maybe the whole internet does not need access to
SSH on our ports.
Or machines, because then they can try logging in.
And actually when you put something on the internet, people will try to log into SSH
immediately within minutes.
You can try it here on camp.
Put a machine on an IP that has not been active for a week, and immediately within minutes
you will see attacks on these ports.
Going back to some of the categorization, I also try to structure my learning, my teaching
into kind of following the OSI model.
Because the OSI model and the Internet Protocol Suite model goes from some physical layers
and up through the protocols.
And in many cases, I think it makes sense to secure the lower layers before the upper
layers.
So, for instance, removing the possibility of accessing port 22 makes it, it doesn't
care, we don't care if there's a bad password if you cannot get access to that port.
So securing the internet and the network from below is my recommended way, and you can also
use that in your learning if you want to get started.
Start from some of the lower levels, understand what's going on, and then of course you get
to some of the higher levels and different applications where it splits out.
And I can tell you there are hacking tools for all applications, all protocols, so even
if it's a niche technology, there will be some kind of hacking tool for that niche.
Already I have asked you to do a lot of different things, and it is difficult to get to know
all of these things without drowning, and one of the bad things is if you try to bite
over too much immediately, but there are some things that you need to know at a certain
point to be able to run security and network and scanning and doing all sorts of other
stuff.
And I actually believe some of these things should also be taught to some of our bosses,
some of our management should at least know some of these things, because then they would
be better at enforcing security.
So.
You need to know a little bit of basic protocols, and it may not be that interesting to read
about that, but that will make it much easier to understand NMAP output, but it will also
make it much easier to understand the output of a $5,000 tool, because it runs NMAP at
the bottom, it will report the same information as the NMAP tool in many cases.
And without this knowledge about the basic protocols, then you won't be able to understand
what's going on in these $5,000 tools.
And it's not a joke.
Some of these commercial pen testing tools actually cost $5,000, which is why a lot of
people in Denmark at least are not allowed to buy them.
So you need to know a little bit about Ethernet.
You can practice Ethernet on a camp like this.
You can connect to the network and can put up a Raspberry Pi.
You can see the Raspberry Pi getting hacked, and then you can turn it off and that was
fun and you can drink a beer at the bar.
And then you can reset the flash card and put in something different with a better password,
and then probably it won't get hacked.
You need to know a little bit about IPv4 and ICMP, which are some of the lower level
protocols, but you can later add Wi-Fi.
So you don't have to learn Wi-Fi immediately.
So some things are also okay to push to a later time.
And IPv6, even though I wrote my thesis about IPv6 20 years ago, and I love IPv6, you don't
have to learn it as the first thing to get started with hacking and network and security.
Transport layer.
Transmission control protocol.
TCP UDP.
You need to know a little bit about that because that's some of the core protocols.
Like HTTP using TCP, DNS uses UDP.
So you need to know at least a little bit about TCP and UDP.
And then there's a common upper layer protocols like dynamic host configuration protocol DHCP.
You need to know how to set up a small lab network so you can test out things.
DNS, of course, with the domain names.
But you also need HTTP and HTTPS because everything is running HTTPS today.
And many people in Denmark.
They are actually configuring HTTPS in a bad way.
So that's one of the most common findings in our reports.
People are using bad and insecure protocols.
Just using DNS as an example.
If you just look into that protocol, you can actually make an impact for your organization.
So that's just a single area of this where you can actually start to get useful quickly.
I like to learn new concepts from books.
There's lots of resources.
You can probably mention podcasts, YouTube videos, profiles on the internet, blog posts.
Blog posts are not as common anymore, but there's lots of resources on the internet.
They are great for a single subject if you know the area already.
But if you want to learn a new area, I highly recommend books.
And books can be found often freely, legally also.
The book at the bottom is a web application security book by Andrew Hoffman.
It's very useful.
It's a very useful book.
It's available for free from nginx.com.
If you give them an email address and a few items of information, and you can unsubscribe
to the newsletter, and they actually do unsubscribe you from the newsletter and don't think they
sell off the information, but you can get a book for free about web application security.
And the thing I like about books is that they typically have some kind of clear structure.
They have an editor.
They probably go from some level onto some other level.
So they go from kind of a basic level to some kind of complete level.
So they go from kind of a basic level to some kind of complete goal.
And often they will have exercises available.
Some of the books that I recommend also have things you can download, lab content, packet
dumps for networking and so on.
So it's quite easy to get like an introduction into an area at least.
And in the old days, books were like 400 plus, but I'm seeing lots of books that are only
like 200, 250, 300 pages now.
And it actually gives me a lot of satisfaction.
And some of my students have told me it gives them satisfaction to actually read a book
from cover to cover.
So we use this web application security in a web security for web developers course in
Copenhagen, and we read the whole book.
It was short enough that we could read the whole book.
You can also go to my courses and exercise booklets.
I don't have an editor, so they won't be as great as some of these books.
So getting a book is my recommendation for learning some of these things.
Then when you know these basic protocols, you have perhaps read one of these books,
you can then dive into a part of the area, you can start to go in different directions,
you will have the basic level that will enable you to explore on your own.
And that's actually what you want to do at a later stage because you want to learn something
specific, you probably got interested in some specific attack, some specific area.
And I think now you are ready.
You are ready to dig deeper into those parts.
For me, it's typically packets and packet analysis, capturing packets, port mirroring,
trying to work with network traffic.
And that's some of the things that we can do on camps like this.
We can just set up a machine, see that we're getting scanned.
And immediately after we got online, we actually got scanned in this network.
So your machine on this network, if you're running a public IP address on the Bornhack SSID,
you will get network attacks.
And that's something that we can do.
That's something you can work on in this network.
And you can actually also do that at home.
Maybe a little bit difficult if you have a very bad small CPE router from an internet provider.
Also, you should, in your learning materials, make sure that you cover different formats.
Because when I grew up, it was very common to have these ASCII text files, and it was
very common to have these academic papers, which are kind of in two columns and a big
abstract at the start.
And you should force yourself to be able to read these different formats.
So make sure that you include different formats, different resources.
And as you get to know different sources, you will recognize names, programs, peoples,
authors, sites, and some sites will be specialized in different areas.
So I kind of make a mental note.
So if this site is a good place to start, then you can do it.
So if you're looking for a good site, then you can do it.
If a spaffled person writes something new, I put it on a to-read list, and it's a professor
who wrote some of the old internet security text.
So if he writes something, I will definitely try to read it, because it's typically something
that has good content.
So I force my students to read old hacker text files, computer science papers, but there's
web articles, blog posts, books, chapters, standout documents, internet requests for
comments are the defining documents.
about the protocols that we use.
So you should at least be able to read the table of contents.
You should know it exists.
There is one that documents TLS 1.2.
It's horrible to read.
I don't force my students to read all of it,
but they should at least know that this is where it originates.
This is where it comes from.
I have a little bit of very, very stubborn, what do you call it,
focus on some things that I force my students to use.
I guess most people are getting exposed to Windows along their childhood,
forcing people and children to run Windows or Mac.
Some of these things are getting used by people, tablets and so on.
But I also really love open source.
So I force my students to learn open source
because there's just so much great open source
that ignoring it will make your life,
worse.
You can actually make your life so much better
by using open source, knowing it exists,
and you can probably solve 90 plus percent of your task
by using existing open source.
So I force people to use open source.
And then the next point is Linux Unix.
And I find that Unix Linux knowledge is necessary.
It is something that I force my students to do.
They cannot really pass my courses without having a virtual machine.
We don't have to do complex.
We don't have to do complex stuff with this Linux.
But we need to be able to boot it up, shut it down,
boot it up, run Nmap, shut it down.
That is something that you must be able to do
because a lot of the newest tools are written for Linux, Unix, and BSD.
So without having this knowledge, at least a little bit of knowledge,
you will be restricted in what you can actually do.
Talking about open source, I also point people to Git and GitHub.
Again, we can discuss if those are the best resources where you can find everything.
It is not.
But it is one of the easiest ways to find a lot of popular products.
So you can actually go to GitHub, search for something like port scanning, Nmap.
You can find analyzers.
You can find report writing tools for Nmap.
You can find lots of things with a few keywords.
So tools and libraries and applications.
You can find complete applications that often do what you want to do.
Then you need a little bit of what I call programming experience.
It is typically for automating stuff.
I am not a great programmer.
At all.
But I know how to connect a few things.
I know that there is something called XML that can be outputted from a tool.
And then you can convert it into something called JSON.
And then you can convert something like JSON into something called SVG,
which can be displayed in a browser.
There is a lot of things going on.
And if you know that there is a tool that can do SVG,
and there is a tool that can do XML,
you can actually perhaps go directly to SVG from XML.
And Nmap can output in XML.
Process that into HTML.
And there is actually already,
what is that called?
Not CSS, but the other one.
XSSLT.
Yeah, I cannot say it even.
XSLT.
So you can actually convert XML files from Nmap into HTML files,
which you can more or less copy into a Word document.
And then you are halfway to writing a small report for your organization.
Also, there are a few things that I really love.
Ansible provisioning for installing and configuring software.
Because as security people,
we also need to run servers,
a little bit of servers.
We need to be able to do it by ourselves.
If we have to ask server people to provide a server,
set it up for us,
install a small tool from GitHub,
it is just easier if we can do it by ourselves.
One of the tools that I also recommend a lot,
and I am not affiliated with Elasticsearch,
and I find the licensing is very much too expensive,
at least for Danish companies.
I think the API is a little bit too expensive.
I think the API is a little bit too expensive,
at least for Danish companies.
The entry level is something like 15,000 euros
for a smallest production cluster.
But you can use Elasticsearch for free,
and it is kind of a nice service,
because you can cover a lot of ground with Elasticsearch.
They have a lot of focus on security,
so by using this tool,
I can actually, from a lot of my tools,
integrate a lot of sources into this.
Which is also some of the tools that I recommend and use,
are tools that can be used for multiple purposes.
And that's very nice,
that you can use Elasticsearch as the backend
for receiving a lot of data,
and then you can actually work with that
using a GUI called Kibana on top of Elasticsearch,
running in a browser,
and they have a lot of sample data also.
One of the things that I highly recommend
is doing a hacker lab,
and you can start creating that on your laptop today,
because most of you will have a laptop
that can run virtualization,
you can run Docker,
you can run a virtualized tool,
VMware Player,
Sen, Hypervisor,
KVM on Linux,
you can run...
I'm missing one...
Hyper-V on Windows, thank you for that,
because that's definitely a nice way
of doing that,
and so most of you will have the opportunity
to run some kind of virtualized machine,
and you can get actual
experience using the tools.
And that will make it much easier to apply
in a real-life situation, of course,
you have tried it before.
Looking at especially Debian and Kali Linux
are the ones that I propose
that you look into,
and that's because they have a lot of good documentation,
they have existed for so many years.
There's a Debian handbook,
and the Kali Linux Revealed,
which are free PDFs that will walk you through
any part of the installing
and running a Debian server,
which is a virtual machine,
and then a Debian, which is a Kali Linux,
because it's built on top of Debian,
so they will be very similar, again,
to update both of them,
but it's coming from different repositories.
They will be described in these complete books
about the operating systems.
So they are different operating systems,
both based on Debian,
and the Kali Linux actually has more than
300 tools pre-installed,
so that's quite nice.
You don't need to learn how to install a tool
before you can start using it.
I think it's a must for working
in network and security,
and I'm luckily not the only one saying that,
so you will find lots of
more important people than me
saying that this is a requirement
for running network and security things.
Or you can go the other way
and be an expert in Excel,
and then you can take on a lot of these tasks
for people working in network and security.
That's also fine.
I just want to point you
to some of the resources that I have used.
So in this presentation,
there will be resources that I have used
and are using.
Open source Python is one of the languages
that I recommend, because most of the tools
are Python version,
and it may exist in other tools,
also including C-Sharp and PowerScript.
Is that the name?
PowerShell, sorry.
I could hear that it was wrong.
PowerShell and other languages.
But there's always a Python version.
There's always a Python library.
So Python is one of the tools
that I would recommend
that you look into.
And then you can find tools like Maltrail,
which can actually look at bad traffic
and immediately start creating data
from dashboards and stuff.
So that's, again, one of the tools
that I have used.
And just by turning it on,
I'm getting nice knowledge from the network
about people that were infected with macrovirus
and contacting bad servers on the internet.
Also, this tool Ansible,
I'm just going to point to Ansible
because I think it's quite easy
to get started in Ansible.
But also Ansible has a very broad target.
You can target platforms
such as network devices.
So this is a long list
of network devices
which are probably among the ones
that are being used in Denmark
and other places.
So it can be used for network equipment
and it can also be used for hosts and servers,
application servers,
running Linux, OpenBSD, FreeBSD and so on.
There is Ansible support in Windows
but it's not complete
and probably you would rather use
other tools for Windows.
But for anything else, basically,
you can use Ansible.
So it's very generic.
It can quickly lead you into Git.
So again, Git is a prerequisite
for working in network and security.
Elasticsearch
is the one that I talked about
which has different,
you could call them sub-applications,
applications that feed Elasticsearch with data.
So there's different parts
of this ecosystem
and they typically don't call it
the ELK stack anymore.
It used to be the ELK stack for Elasticsearch,
Logstash and Kibana.
But there's so many tools and components
in this stack of tools
so they typically call it
the Elastic stack today.
And I enjoy this
technology because they have done
what is called an elastic common schema
which are field definitions
for stuff like an IP address.
So if you're using and adhering to this
standard in a tool,
you can mix and match with other tools.
So like the dream would be that you could take
firewall locks from a Juniper device
or a Cisco device,
they end up in the same field in the database,
the document store that they call it.
Then you can actually do a dashboard
that will cover two different
network technologies in your network.
So this is one of the things
that I enjoy by using Elastic.
So this is hereby
passed on to you.
And there's also complete applications
available. The one called ElastiFlow
is just a single line in this.
But if you know how to boot a Linux
machine, git clone
a repository,
you actually get a complete
dashboard with network flows
in your whole network.
So if we were
monitoring the network using NetFlow
in this network, which we are definitely
not, we would actually be able to see
every IP inside the network
contacting servers on the internet,
servers on the internet connecting to us,
seeing who uses the most bandwidth,
what protocols and stuff. And that's a complete
application you could install
by just knowing a little bit of
Linux and command line
git.
I will just keep on talking
until they pull me down from this stage.
So I will now again
drop back a little bit
and try to make it more structured
so when you get back and read this slideshow perhaps
you can decide
what to do and where to start.
I'm going to take
as an initial starting
point, we have this called the
diploma in IT security in Denmark.
Which is a
government certified
acknowledged
education diploma in IT security
which is based on
different courses.
So this is a list of the courses
that are needed to get this diploma.
It's not to say that all of you should
take this, but you can use it
again for guiding your
path into network
and security.
So it will have something, sorry this is
in Danish, but this one says
governance. So governance is a large
part of security. There's something about
system security, servers
and all of that. Authentication
is a large part of security.
There's also software security because
software is quite important for security.
There's also network and
communication security which
is about IDS and packets and so on.
These courses
some of them are mandatory, some
of them are electives that you can take after
but you need to have at least 60
of these ECTS points.
And all of my educational
materials for all of the courses that I
teach is available on GitHub.
So you can just start out reading some of these
and the lecture plans
could be used at home
to decide that you want to read this
chapter and try to do these exercises,
read the next chapters and do the
next exercises. My
exercise booklets are quite easy
to follow I think and use some of
these tools that I have mentioned already.
One of them is the
communications and network security course.
Where I have selected some of the
books that I prefer for this area.
I know that I jump a little bit around
in these slides but this one called
Linux basics for hackers getting started
with networking scripting and security in Kali.
It sounds almost
as the title of this slideshow
and it is actually a book
248 pages
describes how to get started on
Linux. It's actually not a
security book or a hacking book
it's a book about Kali Linux and it
will explain stuff like the file
system. Something like
running on the command line using
grep for searching through text files
doing some basic
scripting. How do you
make a small script that can be run on
a Linux. So it's 248
pages and it's one that I
again force my students to read
and by using that resource along
with the virtual machine they get confident
enough that they can run the tools
when they get home in their own organizations.
So that's actually a proven
they can use this tool with
Linux. We also
have practical packet analysis which is from
NoStarch. I really enjoy that publisher
because it's very practical books
this is a dedicated
book about packet analysis
but it actually works through different scenarios
you can download packet dumps
you can start working on
using an actual tool. In this
case it's Wireshark which is one of the most
common tools which is also something
that I
recommend that you look into
just by starting Wireshark
listening to an Ethernet on his camp
you will see a lot of traffic and that can be fun
in just looking at what happens in a network
and a lot of
devices will just broadcast their names
and who they are and what
versions and actually the switches
on this side they will tell you what
Junos version they're running
we're not running the latest but you will
see some security problems immediately
by looking at traffic.
Then there's a link to a
lecture plan for this course this
specific course and there
are also the presentations so this
is kind of a package that you could use
and go through communication and
network security and I think
after reading these resources
or at least the chapters that I recommend
would make it possible
for you to do some actual work
within network and security
the books if you want to buy
them in hard copy it's about
a thousand Danish kroner it may
be outside the budget that
you may be interested in just
browsing some of this some of
the books can be found as
you can find what you call them
example chapters for downloads
you can check before buying it
but also going to some of these humble
bundles which I highly recommend
you can get some of these books for
as low as $25 for
15 books and just by
subscribing to the humble bundle
I have bought
I think 30 bundles by now because
I almost always buy the bundles
because then later I can go back and see
oh was there something about data science
yes there was and was there something
about network security and hacking yes
there was do I need to learn python yes
there was a python book there was
actually a python bundle with 15 books
so humble bundle is one of the places
where you can get it for cheaper
some of the other books that I recommend
like the debian administrators handbook
the Kali Linux revealed they will
describe everything about running a
server installing packages configuring
the network what to expect when you
boot up your
there's also this book that I have
recommended already the web application security
and then there's one called gray hat hacking
which is recommended because it has
bite-sized chapters
so if you want to work in different areas
of security this gray hat
hacking book has enough of an
introduction into various areas
that is a very highly
recommended book and it's also in the fifth edition
which probably speaks
to its value they decided to
upgrade it and release it upgrade it
and release it upgrade and upgrade
and release it so it's one of the books
that I am very fond of during
my work and my
teaching
you
also probably want to invest a little
bit in network equipment
I use openbsd I use
switches from juniper there's
actually a small pile of switches
at the end of camp near
the garbage because we have some
surplus switches that we're going to
throw out and they are actually
excellent for learning VLANs and
stuff they can do some of this basic
stuff they can run SNMP
for management so
probably get some switches some ethernet
equipment and running in a
small isolated network
running these tools is probably recommended
to avoid
attacking people on the internet
if you mistype an IP address
you might be attacking the NSA so
make sure that you do not
mistype addresses
and as I said at the bottom
above or similar can often be found like
this
I have taken home a lot of equipment
over the years and played with it at
home to get better in these
and being able to actually do stuff
with equipment is important
I also recommend getting
wireless cards and
it's always a problem recommending
wireless cards because they go through
a revision and changes all the time
but to learn a lot of these
methods and technologies for
hacking Wi-Fi you probably can get
away with it
but to learn a lot of these
methods and technologies for
hacking Wi-Fi you probably can get away with
a cheap one it may be that you have
one lying around already it may be
that it only supports 2.4 GHz
but if you're looking at the security
protocols you don't really care if it's
5 GHz or 2.4 because the security
protocols are the same
and the one that I have used a lot of
time the TP-Link TL-VN722N
that was about 80 Kroner
so it's less than a small
snack box at the food vendor
but if you skip one of these and
order a cheap card you can actually
start doing Wi-Fi hacking and then
later on you may want to buy one that
I think the one I have below here
that was about 300 or 500
Danish Kroner
but you don't need the latest and
greatest to get started and you can
typically find it in discarded piles
at work sometimes
also if you have money
for it buying a USB Ethernet
card is a card
just a dongle is recommended
because then you can actually do
very low level looking into
packets which is what I really love
doing and that will again
immediately start to
bring up something interesting to
look at
it's 47 minutes now and I would
love to have some questions
you can find me at CAM I will be
here until Friday you can send me
questions via email you can
find me on Twitter you can see my
mobile number it's signal enabled so
you're welcome to ask me questions
let's give a round of applause
nice talk Kramse
I completely agree with
basically everything
what is your take on the difference
between having a formal
education and taking certificates
and then learning the stuff yourself
I see that as three distinct
categories how do you see them
play together and what should you go for
it's a great
question and
beware when I
answer this question now I
am definitely
not trying to offend anyone
I may I'm not a native English speaker
so I may use the wrong words and
in my family we say it's okay to use
the wrong words and then people can ask and
we can do a more detailed answer
probably explaining more what I
mean and think about this so
I have a formal education
and I'm not using much of my formal
education I think some of the most
important parts that I learned from
computer science at
university was to read
to write big reports
which is a very useful skill in network
security but a lot of the network
security I have learned
informally over the years
by things that I have researched
myself today you can go to a lot of
security conferences but I have learned
a lot by investigating myself
so if you investigate by yourself
read some of these books that I have
recommended never take an exam
never take a certification
you can be an excellent resource
but I do think
that formal education has its place
because you are required
to go through some parts and
also the parts that you don't really like
so you are forced to do
some investigation into for instance
some of the juniper certifications
I had to read pages and pages of OSPF
which is a protocol for routing
and I had to learn all sorts of different
configurations that I
have never used
but it still required me to learn a little
bit about this OSPF
so you can definitely work
in security without having a formal education
but I think your job situation
will also be a little bit more
risky because if you get fired
you don't get a job for a year
people might not value the things that you did
in your previous job
so I hope I didn't offend anyone
and you understood what I meant
but I really do think
that both formal education
and certifications has its place
and that said
I think it's horrible the way
that we do these certifications today
because I have tried to take one
with a proctor that wanted to
investigate my underwear more or less
I had to put the camera under the table
and it does prevent some people
from taking these and I think we should
try to eliminate that burden
I don't know how we would do that
open source certifications is not really
taking off. I answered that very long
We have one more question
Thank you
You talked a lot about how to
increase your confidence with network security
a situation I've had for a while
that I think is quite common among hackers
is I know something about
computers
and I have no idea how to get a job
in computers
because that's like a completely different
world from actually knowing computers
Do you have any
advice on this?
I do because
since we have this extreme
shortage we have a very
unhealthy environment for
computer security people in Denmark
because they cannot fulfill the positions
so the ones that are working
are overworked and so on
and I have been
discussing how we could bring in people
into these areas
I think about computers in general
but also computer security
might actually be easier to get into
than the technical parts
because in many cases you want to do
like reviewing output from tools
you want to do like this excel
working with risk
and stuff like that
so my advice would probably
try to find some scenarios
where you can actually perform
some basic tasks
and then you will have to go to
one of these companies that cannot fulfill
the positions
and say that you are eager to learn
and you may agree
again I think it's a little bit
because some of the employers will
take advantage of this
but you can say that you want to
start working at a low salary
perhaps lower than your colleagues
because you do not have the same experience
and then you can make an agreement
like three months, six months from now
we are going to evaluate how much you can fulfill now
and you will get the same pay
so trying to get an initial low
pay and be able to do
some basic scenarios
from end to end
that's actually the important part
Do we have a final question?
I hope that helps
Nope, let's give a round of applause
for Kamsi