So, a little pre-part, if you saw my presentation from MCH, then this is exactly the same, minus
one slide.
So, the goal with this presentation is to talk a bit about some of the ongoing and upcoming
efforts that we're doing, specifically to the network component of sort of the Tor ecosystem.
Usually, when we go out and do presentations at different events, we talk about sort of
a general overview of Tor, where we enter things like the network, the browser, the
anti-censorship stuff, the community things, the, like, translations, and all the different
kind of things that we're doing.
But specifically in this talk, I'm going to zoom in a little bit more on the network side
of things and what's happening on there.
It's not going to be sort of a blue-sky presentation with all this stuff that we're hoping to do.
It's more like this is stuff we have funding for.
It's things that we're working on.
It's things that are going to happen in the sort of near future.
So, a little bit about me.
I joined Tor in 2017, and I became the team lead of what we call the network team.
That is the team responsible for writing the little piece of software called Tor, like
the Unix binary that you run if you're a relay operator and so on, and also what is used
in the browser to actually access the software.
I've been involved with, like, the free software community since I was a teenager.
I've been co-founding and co-organizing this BornHack festival that we are all at today,
and I absolutely love going to these hacker camps, and I went to my first one in 2013
in the Netherlands.
So, before we dive too hard into sort of the network side of things, we're going to just
have a general overview.
How many people in here know about Tor?
Is there anybody who don't know?
I don't know anything about Tor.
Okay, great.
So, we are a sort of an online anonymity and censorship circumvention tool and organization.
It's all free software.
We don't believe that we can deliver sort of the guarantees that we want to do without
everybody's ability to actually look at the source code.
We're an open network.
We had a lot of conversations about that during the relay operators meetup the other day,
meaning that everybody can start up a node and participate and help other people who
are using the network.
We're also a big community of both researchers, developers, users, relay operators, all these
different kind of groups that are working together on breaking and fixing Tor and making
it better.
We're also a non-profit in the U.S., and that mostly has something to do with when
you donate to the organization.
So, most of you who are working with the sort of software that you're developing will probably
collect a lot of metrics on what you're doing, how many users.
You have to be very careful.
How many requests you have, how many requests you see every day.
We cannot sort of measure how many Tor users we have, but we have some research indicators
that we have between 2 million and 8 million data users.
So, to give a quick sort of grand overview of how Tor works, in this case, we have Alice
and Bob.
Alice wants to make a TCP connection to Bob.
So, Alice has full knowledge of the entire network, knows every node that exists in it.
She has bootstrapped before.
And she sort of has an idea about the composition of the network, and she knows all the relays
that exist in it.
Here, we have a very small Tor network.
It consists of seven relays, I believe.
And Alice decides that she wants to go through R1, R2, and R3 before finally reaching Bob.
So, Alice establishes a secure session with R1, extends it further to R2, and extends
it again to R3, and finally makes this sort of TCP connection.
So, Alice has a secure connection to Bob.
This kind of sort of telescope-style connectivity is very similar to like the flagpoles that
you see here at the festival.
When we talk sort of about Tor, we will frequently talk about the guard node, the middle node,
and the exit node.
This is what you're seeing here.
For onion services, we have sort of the whole thing, again, mirrored where there's several
hops as well.
But an onion service should actually be seen more as something that's connected to the
Tor network.
It's a client rather than a server where we sort of duplicate this entire setup in
the middle.
A while ago, we did a survey to see what kind of things the Tor users were interested and
sort of frustrated with using Tor.
And we prioritized this ordering, and it turned out that speed was a great concern, blocking
was secondary, privacy, then security, and finally sort of the UI.
The UI was not something people were super frustrated with.
The speed is, of course, the performance of the Tor network.
That has to do with the throughput of the network and also its latency.
Blocking is these capture portals that people who are using Tor will occasionally see, where
you have to help an AI be trained and so on.
The privacy is, of course, the privacy and anonymity guarantees that we give by Tor.
The security is sort of that we don't have too many vulnerabilities and people don't
get hacked.
We don't know when using Tor because of the mistakes we make.
And finally, we have sort of the user interface of our products, which people didn't seem
to be too frustrated with.
So as I mentioned earlier, Tor is an open network.
That means everybody can join.
We right now have between 6,000 and 7,000 nodes.
And how many people in here have been or are running Tor relays?
Oh, wow, that's very cool.
Thank you for doing that.
So Tor is kind of hosted by people similar to you, but there's also these umbrella organizations
that go together and host them together where they also need some legal help for like exit
node operators and so on.
One thing that was very much up during the Relay Operators Meetup that was a surprise
to some was that we have these nodes called the Directory Authority nodes, which is nine
specific nodes that are sort of the sort of trust anchor in the network in that they can
remove other nodes that seem to be behaving in malicious ways using a majority of the
Tor network.
So they can't just vote.
There's nothing fancy sort of a distributed system, Paxos and so on in that.
We also have a bridge authority.
Bridges are entry points into the network which are hidden.
So they are like distributed to people who are in censored areas.
If we take a bit of a look at the relay count over time, we can see that we have sort of
started to flatten the curve here since around 2015.
The curve below is the number of bridges we have.
An interesting thing is you can see around these node revelations in the summer of 2013,
it starts increasing pretty rapidly, but we've ended up being somewhere between 6,000 and
8,000 nodes in total.
On the other hand, the bandwidth has steadily increased in the network.
The top one is the advertised bandwidth.
That is how much bandwidth we believe there is in the network, like that the relays are
seeing.
And the orange one below is the historic bandwidth that relays reporting back to the
directory authorities about how much bandwidth that has been passed through them.
We're going to return to these a bit later and specifically going to zoom in on some
of these spikes that we see here in 2021 and 2022.
So some of the new things that we have to do is these are like sort of pretty small
things.
But we...
When we are sending data around in the network, we pack everything.
We put everything into something called cells.
They can take payload.
They have a specific size, but we have an interest now to both be able to send multiple
cells grouped together to not have to waste a lot of bytes in the payload.
And we also have the need to do something called fragmented cells.
Fragmented cells is the ability to split a payload over several cells, because otherwise
we only have the 498 bytes to do things with.
So we're going to do that.
We're going to do that.
There is a proposal called 340 for people who are interested in sort of reading some
of these things.
They are a little bit like reading an RFC from IETF, but of course a little bit more
simplified and very specific to Tor.
The reason that we want to do fragmented cells is because we have this post-quantum cryptography
that some of you might be familiar with.
We have over the years with TLS and SSL started out with usually using like discrete lock,
but with the move to, especially to mobile, we wanted to have smaller keys and like move
to generally less wire traffic for the cryptographic material.
But the post-quantum handshakes are frequently very, very large, and we need to be able to
split those up over a number of cells.
There are two parts that we need to protect against an adversary with a potential like,
with the potential of having a cryptographic material.
We need to be able to split those up over a number of cells.
There are two parts that we need to protect against an adversary with a potential like,
with the potential of having a cryptographic material.
One is like a quantum computer.
We do not believe today that they have them, but we are worried about that there might
be people who are like sniffing all the traffic in and out of the Tor network and storing
it, and later will then be able to decode it by, if we get it, a quantum computer that
is big enough.
So there are two components to this.
There is the TLS layer that's the outer layer cryptography that we use when we are connecting
into the Tor network and like when the relays are used between them that we need to protect.
Then there is the circuit layer where we establish these circuits through the network, so a malicious
relay cannot intercept traffic as well.
One of the big things that we have recently released is the congestion control system.
For people who have used Tor, you will probably have noticed that you sometimes hit a limit
of around 500 kilobytes a second when you're downloading stuff.
This is the speed component of the big survey we did a while ago that we're trying to approach
here.
The team implemented a number of classic congestion control algorithms, and while a number of
them had some issues that made them unusable while we were experimenting, the Tor Vegas
algorithm seemed to be doing exactly what we wanted.
We can see here that the blue plots in the middle are the speed components.
In both of them is the old Tor version, 046, and the orange-yellowish kind of thing is
the 047 with congestion control enabled.
What we see here is that we see a much larger distribution of clients in the simulation
that seems to be getting much faster traffic through.
The first plot on the left is from a simulation based on a German client, and the one on the
right is a simulation of clients in Hong Kong.
Which...
If you want to know a little bit about the topology of Tor, you will know that a significant
amount of the nodes is centralized in Germany because of some of the ISPs that exist there.
Now we are back to the relay bandwidth plot that we looked at before.
As you can see, there is these two top spikes here.
This was an experiment that we did because we were suspecting that there was a lot more
traffic in the network that we were not aware of, simply because the network was underutilized.
So...
Essentially, a team of researchers did this very simple experiment where they started
sending a large amount of traffic over each Tor node in the network, simply so the relays
would quickly discover that they had way more capacity than they used to think, and would
report it back.
That is what we are seeing in those two big spikes.
We could, of course, continue to do that, but it doesn't really mean anything.
We are going to instead be working with our bandwidth scanning techniques.
The interesting part comes with what we see here.
This part of the plot is where we finally start seeing that the traffic goes up a little
bit in the historic bandwidth amount.
This comes from the time where we finally got the Tor 047 in Tor Browser.
So we are actually starting to see that the congestion control is out in many of the relays,
and it's now also out in the browsers, and we finally start seeing that we are starting
to utilize more of this traffic that we believe we have access to.
Unfortunately, you can see that the graph also goes down again.
For some of you who were at the relay operators' meetup, I was talking a lot about this DOS
that's happening right now.
We unfortunately have this denial of service attacks going on with some kind of adversary
who is flooding through the network, and it's causing us to significantly impact the performance
of Tor users.
We are having some ongoing efforts right now to sort of do something about it, but for
people who are familiar with sort of how networks work, sending traffic is a pretty easy way
to significantly hurt performance, and it is a bit of a whack-a-mole game.
I will return to some techniques that we are looking at using that is for sort of mitigating
some of this denial of service.
Slide 10.
1.
One thing that is really nice is some outreach that has been happening over the time with
regards to trying to get more Tor relay operators to upgrade quickly.
We had Tor 047 was released around the end of April, and it is the curve we see beginning
to go up in May, and the previous release, 046, is starting to be reduced in the network.
This is really, really good when we have a network where a single individual cannot ever
run all the nodes.
That would be terrible for the anonymity and the privacy.
We are very happy that people are upgrading so quickly because it means that we can more
quickly start testing some of these things that we are doing and seeing whether they
work.
So, a massive thank you for upgrading to 047 so quickly.
That has been really, really nice.
We have a little bit more of some further tuning we need to do with this congestion
control system.
Slide 11.
1.
We are planning on changing the cutoff values for this flag called fast.
For people who go to metricstorproject.org every now and then and look at their relays,
you will see that you have different flags that are allocated to you over time depending
on how your relay is set up and how fast it is and these kinds of things.
We unfortunately today give the fast flag to relays that we probably by today's internet
standard would not consider to be fast, and we are planning on making that barrier sort
of a little bit higher before you are getting the fast flag.
Slide 12.
1.
We are also planning on changing the cutoff values for the fast flag and the same thing
for the guard flag because the guard flag is used for like the entry point into the
network which means that if the guard flag, if the guard note that you have in your three
hops is slow, it will significantly impact the performance of your use.
Slide 13.
1.
The good thing is Onion Service operators who will also benefit from these changes.
Some of you may know that we are live streaming this event over on Onion Service as sort of
an experiment to see whether it works.
Slide 14.
2.
Relay operators should in general probably be more prepared to set bandwidth limits as
we start getting closer and closer to a larger fraction of the network running this version.
Slide 15.
If you are interested in more information about the congestion control subsystem, then
Mike Perry has a really good blog post.
Slide 16.
We have a really good blog post on sort of the entire implementation, how the team was
working together with simulation.
We collaborated a lot with the people who developed the tool called Shadow which is
a simulation tool for sort of simulating large runs of Tor activity with the Tor software
built in.
Slide 17.
Slide 18.
Slide 19.
Slide 20.
Slide 21.
Slide 22.
Slide 23.
Slide 24.
Slide 25.
Slide 26.
Slide 27.
Slide 28.
Slide 30.
Slide 31.
Slide 32.
Slide 34.
Slide 35.
Slide 60.
Slide 31.
Slide 32.
Slide 36.
Slide 37.
Slide $1.
Slide 38.
Slide 39.
Slide 41.
Slide 42.
Slide 43.
Slide 45.
Slide 46.
Slide 47.
Slide 48.
Slide 49.
Slide 51.
Slide 52.
Slide 55.
congestion control system like is the path that we are on right now currently congested.
So what we will be able to do with ConfLux is that Alice establishes two paths into the
network and sort of meet at the exit node and is able to then over time figure out which
of the path is the least congested one and start transmitting and receiving on that one
where we then rebuild like the packages at the exit node.
This is likely also going to impact a little bit with the memory utilization that we're
using at the exit node, but that should be fine.
I mentioned before that we are looking a bit at these kind of denial of service techniques,
like how we can mitigate this.
One of the things that we're looking at right now is also using proof of work for onion
services.
People are usually in these communities, either some people are into cryptocurrencies and
stuff like that and knows that proof of work is...
Is probably harmful in that it's just standing and wasting energy.
The proof of work system that we're looking at using for onion services is dynamically
enabled and disabled whether there's sort of something that appears to be a pathological
situation towards the onion service.
So the onion service can enable it and the clients are then forced to solve a little
puzzle in the connection to the onion service.
There's no interactive part.
It's just a part for the user, like you are not seeing anything.
You won't be able to...
You won't be prompted by anything.
You won't have to solve any CAPTCHAs or anything like that.
This is very new.
This is something that the team was working on together with someone called Tivador who
was helping out with these things.
It's all specified in this proposal 327.
We are considering a little bit now to...
Originally the plan was that Tor 048 was going to include ConfLux.
But we're considering...
We're considering a little bit to have a proof of work go into 048 and then let ConfLux go
in for 049 or the next release that comes.
Very good.
Another exciting thing that we're doing to the network right now is that we are rewriting
Tor in the Rust programming language.
We have...
Tor is a pretty old piece of software, right?
It's from around the beginning of the zeros.
It's a single...
It's a single binary right now that is both working as a directory authority, it's a relay,
it's an exit node, it's a client, it's an onion service sort of proxy.
It's a lot of different tools in a single binary.
It has been very complicated for us to take this binary and turn it into a library and
make it usable for mobile developers, especially on the two large mobile platforms that exist
today.
This is the first time we've done this.
We've had a lot of people who have been talking about executing binaries.
They ideally want you to link things as a library.
We've spent a lot of time working with partners and that, and trying to make that entire experience
better.
The goal with RD is to build a library that we can work with the entire Tor ecosystem
in.
For people who know things like metrics, toroproject.org, a website where you can see data about the
network, we have a lot of different tools to parse the different kinds of metrics.
That's the goal with RD.
We have a lot of different tools to parse the different kinds of metrics.
network objects, like the documents that exist with relay descriptors.
All these different components is something we want already to sort of centralize so we
can write small utilities that, for example, does analysis in the network and these kind
of things.
Additionally, we also want to have a library that you can use for onion services.
So you can actually have onion services just existing inside of an application instead
of having to be over a Unix domain socket or a TCP connection and so on.
So, why on earth would we rewrite Tor?
So one of the things is that writing save C is pretty hard.
I think people who have experience working with that is aware that it's a really difficult
task even for very experienced developers.
We, Nick Mathewson, one of the co-founders of Tor, did a bit of analysis of our internal
sort of security tracking mechanism called Trove.
It's a bit similar to CVE.
But we just use it to sort of keep track of what kind of classes of bugs have we seen
in Tor.
And 21 out of 34 of those was related to memory issues that appears more frequently in C-based
applications.
Additionally, this is also, of course, important, a lot of the network team at Tor was very
interested in and excited about developing things in Rust, and we've, over the years,
been playing around.
We've been playing around with it for different reasons.
We started initially with trying to rewrite parts of Tor in Rust and have sort of this
hybrid binary where some of it was Rust and the other part was C. But it turned out that
task was incredibly hard because all the different interfaces in and out between Rust and C had
to be handled extremely carefully.
So instead, we decided to focus on this from scratch implementation, and it seems to be
going much better than the previous attempt.
Thank you.
If we look a little bit at the roadmap for Arty, the first version is mostly about API
stability, trying to figure out how should these API looks when we are working with them.
Usability, performance, and stability is, of course, also going to be an important part
of it.
Eventually, we will do anti-censorship, that is, being able to connect to bridges, use
pluggable transport, all these different kinds of things that we need for people in censored
areas.
Onion services is targeted from one point of view.
And finally, the 2.0 release is hopefully going to be ready to replace the C for client,
like the C client, not for relay and bridges and these kinds of things, but only sort of
what we have in, for example, a product like Tor Browser and so on.
Once we are at that point, we are going to start looking into getting a relay support
and bridge and directory authorities and so on.
And at that point, it's going to be really interesting to get a lot of the, you know,
the relay operators to help try to experiment with this new software also when we get to
the point where we want to do it in production.
So a lot of people ask us what's up with what we can now call sort of the legacy Tor or
the Tor that exists today.
So right now, we have three out of the seven members of the network team there working
full time on our Rust deliverables.
We hope that the entire team is sort of slowly moving over to it.
We see that we're going to reduce sort of feature additions pretty drastically in C Tor,
but we will continue, of course, to support it and like do security updates and all these
different kinds of things.
There is an interesting thing with many of these things that I have mentioned here with,
for example, congestion control and also some of the stuff I'm going to talk about in a
moment, which is that you only need to upgrade the exit nodes or onion services and the clients
to benefit from, for example, something like Tor.
Okay.
So we're going to do a lot of things like the congestion control system.
This is something that means that we will likely do feature additions, but they will
be focused around things that we can do these very nice upgrades for adding new features.
So one of the big things we want to do soon is UDP support.
UDP support has been something that I believe many people have wanted in Tor for a very
long time.
There's a lot of modern applications that are using it.
There's a lot of modern applications that are using UDP in various ways, especially
things like WebRTC, like voice and video communication.
And again, this is one of those features we can add by only having the client and the
exit nodes upgrade for us to deploy.
We will use the congestion control system to sort of decide when we need to drop packets
if there's any buffers that are starting to be full and generally behave a lot like a
NAT router at home.
It just handles these tracking of UDP sessions.
So the way it will work is that here we have Alice trying to reach Bob over a UDP packet
stream, so to say.
So what Alice does here is that she does the usual session to the exit node and then starts
transmitting UDP, but it will all be wrapped in a TCP connection from Alice, and I'm going
to return to how we're going to do this.
So for example, we have a HTTP connection, and for HTTP, we have, for example, a SOX
proxy and we have HTTP proxy and these different kind of techniques for proxying connections.
But many UDP applications don't support something similar to that, so we have to do something
different there.
And the idea here is that we instead start focusing more on having Tor behave a lot like
a VPN.
So instead of working on these proxy connections, we instead start looking at taking packets and
adding them to the server.
gates and start transferring them around. People who have used operating systems such
as Kube that has these kind of virtual machines where you can have a Tor VM where you send
all your traffic through, it will be a very similar flow to that, but it will then also
be possible for mobile platforms and different other kind of platforms.
The goal here is to release something in 2023. The first target is Android, but we're of
course also testing on the different kind of platforms that we eventually need to support,
but Android is our first target here because it's a little bit harder to do these things
on mobile, so we don't want to be surprised afterwards. Of course, desktop Linux will
be a part of the first version as well because that's necessary to get Android working.
The implementation of the VPN part, there's of course an app that needs to be done that
will be the application team, but we have a little sort of the engine of this that we
need to implement. We're going to have a little bit of a demo of the application team,
but we're going to have a little bit of a demo of this that we need to build.
This is one of our first projects that are using RD as sort of a library. We are writing
this in parallel with that we're also doing RD. The goal here is for the Onion Mask application
is to have sort of a layer three packet engine, which takes a ton interface and starts reading
packets and working with packets, and generally handling this sort of multiplexing between
incoming TCP and UDP flows and forwarding them using RD's TCP and UDP socket interfaces.
Onion Services is going to work very similar to the way it's done on things like the Kube
SoAs right now with the Tor service there, with that we are faking sort of a DNS server
and responding with these kind of cookie responses that we are then able to map to an Onion Service.
We will also need to have sort of basic, some filtering mechanisms so we can disallow certain
flows that we don't want to see, particularly for the Android platform. We've identified
some metadata that we can go and get the DTS, which is the network, and all of these things.
can get out from the different connections that we are seeing.
And this is the application UUID.
This is the way when you install an app on Android, it gets its own UID.
We have the host name, of course.
If the client is making a connection to something that has a host name, you can also connect
to just an IP.
And the DNS cookie.
And we, of course, still will continue to have the five tuple that you're used to seeing
in NetStat, whether it's UDP, TCP, the source and destination address, and the source and
destination port.
How can you help?
You can either run a Tor relay or a bridge.
It sounds like a lot of you were already doing that.
You can teach others about Tor.
You can help us find some bugs and test some of this new software that we're working on.
And especially if you're running some kind of platform that may not be something that
we're dealing with usually.
And you can also donate to the organization to help us build some of these things.
Do we have any questions?
Yes.
Can you talk more about how the UDP thing is going to work?
Like, if it's operating as a VPN, then your TCP traffic is also going to be sent as packets
now?
So Tor will suddenly have the TCP over TCP problem where...
Yes.
So I think the question is sort of how the engine will handle this right now.
So the idea there is that when we receive a TCP package, we will extract the payload
and have a normal, a completely normal connection.
And you know the technical details of this, but it's called like a stream.
And we will then also have a new kind of stream, which is for packets like datagram kinds of
connections.
A very good question.
Other questions?
Yes.
So I have a...
I have a card relay that keeps on crashing, and I would like to do some statistics why
it is crashing.
What is your stand on, you know, kind of like snooping or doing like statistics on traffic
in and out?
It's a very good question.
So you should be able to debug, of course, what you're trying to figure out, and you
should not save the data.
But there is also a new feature in Tor called metrics port.
It doesn't do a whole lot right now, but the next version is going to have things on which
kind of buffers is it that is taking up a lot of memory allocations and where is it we're
spending time and these kind of things.
So having some kind of Prometheus-like setup pulling from this every now and then is a
very good idea.
And hopefully in the next version, you will get a lot more stats out.
Any other questions?
No?
Thank you for the talk.
Thank you.