So, yeah, welcome to the batch talk of 2022.
Most of you probably got your batch at the check-in.
And in this little presentation, we'll go through some of the specs of the batch
and sort of little ideas on what sort of why stuff has been made as this.
And also, at the end, answer questions if you have sort of what's what.
This year's batch is based on the RP2040.
It's a dual-core ARM processor.
It's the one made by Raspberry Pi like a year and a half ago.
It has 16 megabytes of spy flash and a color screen so that sort of the software side is
very easy to sort of get going with.
There are four buttons sort of to make easy sort of game navigation.
And it also has a quick connector for adding other stuff to it in addition to the shitty
add-on.
And then a bunch of...
Oh, sorry.
There are extra IOs on the edges and little prototyping areas.
So the main processor is the RP2040.
It's the Cortex M0+.
It's actually dual-core.
It runs on 133 megahertz.
It has quite a lot of SRAM actually compared to this smaller processor, which makes them
nice to use with stuff like CircuitPython or MicroPython to have the little extra RAM.
The chip itself doesn't have any built-in flash, so we have that little extra chip next
to it.
And we've added 16 megabytes.
Sixteen megabytes is a lot of space for microprocessors in general.
But as we're using the same flash for media files, images, and so on, having extra space
for extra things is pretty nice.
This chip from Raspberry Pi is a little bit bigger.
It's a little bit bigger.
It's a little special.
It is a dual-core ARM Cortex M0, but it has these programmable IOs.
So it's like normally you have serial UARTs, and we have I2C.
You have SPI.
These programmable IOs are little extra registers, and you can sort of program them to do sort
of similar things to these regular peripherals.
.
That way you can actually achieve sort of some speeds in some areas where writing regular
code is not really, and you can sort of offload tasks to these program BIOS.
The badge comes with CircuitPython, and CircuitPython itself in some of these libraries utilize
those so you don't need to directly interface with them, but CircuitPython will use some
of these features.
The chip comes with a hard-coded bootloader.
So if you don't want to use the CircuitPython that comes with it, it's very easy to go into
this bootloader that you can't remove, you can't delete it by accident or anything, and
then you can put whatever you want on it, either a MicroPython or C or whatever.
We have the QUIC or StemaQt, QUIC is the SparkFun name for these little connector.
StemaQt is the name that Adafruit uses for a connector.
It's a connector that is identical, both electrically and sort of spec-wise.
So it's VCC and ground in the connector, four pins, and then there's SDA and SCL.
It works with many modules.
Many companies make these compatible modules to one of these systems, and you can mix them
as you see fit.
It also has the shitty add-on, or it's the six-pin version, so it has the key on the
top.
So if you use the correct connector on your shitty add-on, you can sort of put it on incorrectly,
and also has the mechanical strength of the slightly larger connector.
This connector also uses I2C.
It's a very simple protocol.
It's easy to add it to your add-ons.
In the hardware hacking sense, SparkFun has sponsored a bunch of these QUIC modules, so
if you want to play with reading the code, you can do that.
So if you want to play with reading the code, you can do that.
If you want to play with reading the code, you can do that.
If you want to play with reading from a sensor or changing a relay or something, there are
some modules there you can play with.
If you make something awesome, you're welcome to keep the module.
If you're just playing with it, you can just put it back in the box again, and then others
can play with that afterwards.
They aren't enough for everybody, but to play with, that should be okay.
Kamsa also brought a large box of various other bits and bobs, and you're welcome to
just play with those and integrate them into your projects and make awesome things.
The batch has four holes in it.
Those can be used as a lot of mechanical mounting.
You can, if you make a case or if you want to add these proto boards, there's a whole
bunch of proto boards up in the hardware hacking also, you're welcome to take those and add
stuff to them, solder through them.
The screw mounting is actually used to carry VCC and ground from the batch up onto the
board.
There are little spacers in the box down there, these little brass spacers and screws that
are, the shorter screw you find down there will actually work from both, like one set
from the front and one set from the back, and they will hold on the board nicely.
You can solder on the little quick connector and then you can break I2C up to this VLL
cable if you want to.
If you sort of think, ah, maybe these four buttons are a little too little for me, I
don't know, for my game, then there are extra add-ons, extra sort of IOs for the chip.
They're put on the edges of the board with these little, round in one end and flat on
the other.
You can either use these alligator clips to grab onto these, or you can wrap some like
a conductive thread around them and tie a little knot, because they're plated in there,
in the hole, so the connection should be fairly okay, otherwise you can of course also solder
a wire to it.
I think maybe one of these PIOs can maybe be used to do some capacitive touch sensing
on these.
I haven't tried it, but I think it's, if somebody wants to play with that, it should be possible
I think.
On the inside of the badge, so if you had the badge here, these two are analog inputs.
They could for instance be used for a little analog joystick on this side.
Kuro has a little bit of a...
Kuro has made a little add-on, and so if you're interested in something like that,
go find him, and I'm sure he can sort of assist them in there.
I've heard something about a game that may be used that could run on the badge.
The other ones are just regular IOs, the 10 and 11, they're called D10 and D11 inside
the code.
And then there's a TX2 and RX2, those are just serial UARTs, you can also use them as
just regular pins.
But they can be used as UARTs also.
Okay.
For serial communication, maybe you can connect two badges together with the wires.
You might need the ground wire also to have it fully working.
The badge comes with CircuitPython preloaded.
It's very easy to get going.
There's a code.py file in the root.
That one includes the menu that Isaac has made in recent days.
It lists all the apps that are inside the application.
There's an apps folder.
So if you copy one of these, there's a little about app that just sort of shows some text.
But if you copy that one, name it mycoolgame.py, it will be listed in the menu.
And then when you click it in the menu, either X or Y button, it goes into that py file,
loads it, and it will run your app.
And when it's done, it will return to the menu.
The lib folder is for CircuitPython libraries.
You can just copy in libraries.
And share them for your code on the badge.
There are also some other folders right now.
There's an image folder that shows the splash image when the badge starts up.
And there's a sponsors folder that holds all the sponsors logo that the sponsors app use.
It mounts as a mesh storage device.
But at the same time, it also presents a USB serial port on your computer.
So if you want to have like debug output while you're sort of coding,
or changing the files, you can actually connect to that serial port and you will get the output
when it reboots.
You can also go into rebel and run the Python commands directly on the badge.
For inspiration on doing all sorts of things, maybe making your badge into a keyboard where
you can use the buttons for up, down, right, left, or other things, macro pad style things,
learn.adafruit.com is a giant source of a lot of examples.
And I think it's a great tool.
I think it's a great tool.
You can also make it into a midi device that sort of presents, you can send midi commands
to your computer and have synthesizer software in the computer, maybe do audio and so on.
If CircuitPython is maybe a little too slow for you, it is not the fastest, but if you
want to have more performance, it's very easy to get into this UF2 bootloader.
Just hold down the boot button while you click the reset, or you can hold down when you power
it up.
When it goes into the UF2 bootloader, it'll show up as a RP2 UF2 device.
When you just copy over a firmware UF2 file, or whatever it's named, it will reprogram
the badge with that firmware.
So whatever tool chain you're using, it could be C or Rust or MicroPython or whatever, copy
it over that way and you'll be up and running.
Many examples that you can use for Raspberry Pi Pico will run more or less unchanged.
I think it's a great tool.
You might have to change pin assignments and so on, but otherwise it'll be pretty much
exactly the same code.
So if you find an example that's, okay, I can use my Pico for this, you can probably
also use the badge here.
If you want to use the screen and so on, you have to load libraries for that.
The screen is connected via SPI.
This is actually the same as for previous badges.
You don't have to put batteries in the badge.
You can simply just plug a USB cable in and it will be powered via USB.
You can also put two AA batteries in.
They have to be sort of with the plus going up in both sides.
I know many times it's sort of one of them the other way, but this here is a plus up
in both of them.
If you have USB power on the badge and the batteries in, it will always prioritize USB
power.
And even the power switch only affects the battery.
If you plug a USB cable in, it will always prioritize USB power.
You have to plug a USB cable in, saddle the key, plug the battery in, then cosas.
This has to be been done quite seriously as well.
It will offer it's full protection, very secure defined as smallinars.
Remember, it'll change your battery power softer or smallerhan, and these are the options
for any backup También us shaped or others and sort it hair.
You can plug a USB in, it'll turn on the badge.
You plug a USB in, it'll turn on the badge.
the RP2040 to those pins.
The idea is that you could connect two batches together with the USB-C cable, though this
USB-C cable has to be some of the slightly more fancy ones as these wires need to be
inside the cable and normal cheap cables might not have these.
But it could be super fun to have a little two player game, maybe shooting on one batch
and shooting out of the top of the screen, shots from the other player can come down
on top or something like that.
The other thing is that RP2040 can do host mode, so you can also set one of the batches
up for host and the other one for device and that way actually communicate via USB, but
that's a little more advanced on the communication side, but there might be libraries that can
be found and used.
Okay.
All the details are available on our GitHub repo.
The default branch that is shown on GitHub is the hardware branch that has all the design
schematics, hardware designs, there should be a PDF file with a schematic to find sort
of if you want to do Rust programming or C, you can find the pinouts for each of the buttons
and screens and so on.
There are also other branches, it might be a slightly unorthodox way of doing it, but
the other branches are not so important.
They are sort of variants of the hardware, they are like the software, the firmware that
goes on there.
So these branches are just, could be, have been other repos, but having one URL, we've
decided that it's easier just to have that single URL to find everything and then switch
between branches.
You can check out multiple branches if you want in different folders if you want to have
access to all of it at the same time.
Some of them include, yeah, example code, the menu is there, the little test apps and
so on.
If you guys make other little games or whatever, you're very welcome to just do pull requests
to that repo and we'll do our best to sort of get them in there.
We dream of having like a whole collection of little games or apps or name tags or whatever.
There are also brands with the add-on, the white add-on balls that I showed earlier.
PCBWay has sponsored the PCBs on the batch and also the add-ons.
So if you have a PCB, you can get the PCBs on the batch and also the add-ons.
And they also assemble these boards, I would say some modern record time.
I submitted the files in June 20th and July 20th.
I had them in my hand.
Normally it takes five weeks and that's a normal year.
Right now getting parts is somewhat tricky.
And that is one of the reasons we are using this RP2040, because that's actually one of
the chips that currently in the world are available.
My guess is because this is a very new chip.
the car industry doesn't use it and other sort of that type of companies.
So most of the other parts except for the RP2040 are actually Chinese branded parts
sort of in an attempt to have it easier to source the part and not sort of run out and say,
oh, we need this part, we have to wait four weeks for that.
With the timelines we use for these batches, waiting four weeks is sadly not an option.
So, but it actually worked out very well.
SparkFun has sponsored these modules.
They're in a box in the hardware hacking.
You just go have fun.
There's also a coupon code if you want to make your own little add-ons.
It's not a lot.
It just, it pays for 10 boards of this size roughly.
But you have to pay shipping yourself.
They also do other things like metal cutting and bending and 3D printing.
On software.
On Sunday from 15 to 16-ish, there'll be a batch live meetup in the hardware hacking
and in the start and outsides.
Come hang out.
Bring your best hacks or whatever.
The idea is to just do the informal hanging around, chatting about batches, electronics,
hacking, that sort of things.
But of course also use the hardware hacking until then.
It's open 24-7.
There are soaring irons.
There are a bunch of parts.
All the parts that we had last year are also there and a bunch more.
So it should be a nice place to hang out if you're sort of interested in electronics.
You can also do other stuff.
It doesn't have to be batch related.
So very welcome to just use the tools there.
Any questions?
Yes.
It's a pleasure.
Hello.
When you decided the names for the buttons on the side, how come you didn't go for either
Nintendo or any of the known ones?
So the buttons are actually the same naming as has been on all the previous BornHack batches.
So all the way back to I think 17, which was the first year we had four buttons in that
batch.
So I went with that.
And I'm maybe not enough of a gamer to know all these standard patterns.
So that's why they are like this.
One of the ideas is that some of the previous batches, you could rotate them and use them
in both in this way or in this way.
So having X and having them sort of, you could flip them is one of the ideas.
But yeah, that's the reason they're nameless there.
Other questions?
No?
Well, thank you, Floma.
Thank you.