I arrived about two hours ago and I didn't know I was making a talk so I made these slides very fast.
Yeah, so I'm here to talk about Data Co-op and so briefly Data Co-op is an association
and formally we are based in Copenhagen but in reality we live on the internet.
So collectively we own two physical servers that we run together and we deliver services
to our members with a focus on privacy protection, encryption, zero knowledge and decentralization.
Okay.
Thank you.
This is really difficult.
So we offer email hosting.
Here's my email if you would like to get in touch.
We have a Git hosting using Gitia and Matrix chat.
And we have our main channel.
Okay.
So we are based in Copenhagen and we have a data Co-op on data.coop which is bridged
with Data Co-op on libera.chat, the IRC network.
Then we also recently got Mastodon at the domain social.data.coop.
And something new that I'm experimenting with is Mirasroas unikernels.
Small virtual machines for data.coop.
Okay.
Thank you.
Bye.
And this website is also using that.
And we keep adding more services as we go.
So we have a membership of 300 kroners a year.
It seems I forgot to add that it's per year.
And if you are students or unraged, we have a greatly reduced membership fee.
So the best place to check for how to become a member is on the website,
but the idea is you send us money and an email, and then you're a member.
Oh, and our website is data.coop.
So we have a meetup tonight at 11 o'clock in the bar,
so you can come and meet more of us and talk about Data Coop if you like.
Ah, I messed up the HTML.
Yeah, so it's hosted on a unikernel.
There's a Git repository with the slides.
It's horrible.
More or less valid HTML.
And we have our infrastructure set up using Ansible,
so you can check out how I made this website.
So some darker stuff.
Yeah, I think that's it.
Thank you.