Tanya Cushman Reviewer.
So, a long time ago, I scraped Just Eat,
and the reason I did it was I had a coop.pizza domain,
and I needed a project.
The database consisted of over 200,000 pizzas.
And here's an example.
So, I have some columns here.
We have a description, name, price,
and I also have restaurant data.
So, let's explore.
If we look at a heat map of the restaurants,
we can see Copenhagen is very popular.
And if we zoom in on Copenhagen, we can see lines.
These are actually the regional S-trains.
And with all heat maps,
with geography, it's just a measure
of how dense the population is.
Now, if we look at the descriptions of pizzas,
we can see they list the ingredients.
So, with some tricks, we can pass the ingredients,
and then we can embed the ingredients in the vector space
using Google's Word2Vec,
and now we get pizza2vec.
So, I have, I don't know if you can see the vectors,
but ingredients,
that are used together in pizzas,
are close together in the vector space.
So, now we can ask interesting questions like,
what is the most similar ingredient to pineapple?
And the answer is peas.
And which ingredients are the most similar to pesto?
And it's like, ingredients on fancy pizzas.
And like, in general, we can see,
if we use clustering algorithms on the vector space,
we can see clusters of typical pizzas,
like pepperoni pizzas, or salad pizzas, or fancy pizzas.
Another interesting thing,
when we consider the ingredients,
is how much value does an ingredient add
to the price of the pizza?
So, can we predict prices,
pizza prices, from the ingredients,
and then look at how much does an ingredient affect the price?
So, I did that.
And like, I think we can, for certain,
say that pineapple on pizza, like, is bad, economically.
So, if we like, ignore causality,
like, you could pull away the pineapple on the pizza
and sell it for more, in another place.
And like, we can definitely see, like,
more fancy pizzas at the top,
like adding pesto to your pizza increases the price
by, what, eight kroner?
Another interesting thing,
is to look at something I call the margarita index.
So, like, we can just look at normal-sized margaritas
on all, like, on all pizzerias.
The problem is, margarita is, like, very hard to spell.
So, it's more like this.
This was hard to visualize.
But, like, in general, we can see that slices,
like, pizza slices, cheaper in bigger cities,
and whole pizzas aren't cheaper in the bigger cities.
And that's it.
Like, I think there's a lot of interesting further research,
like what's the opposite of a pineapple pizza?
Like, we can embed pizzas into a vector space, as well,
and just look at, like, the opposite vector.
But also, like, I noticed that I had a database dump
from, like, several months ago,
so I can actually track inflation...
Quite well.
And also, like, looking at purchasing power,
so we can look at these, like, prices of pizza.
like prices of pizza versus how much do people earn in that region.
And I think this is a really interesting indicator for the stock market.
And I think I can find spurious correlations that gives that result.
And that's it.