Hello, everybody, and welcome to Bornhack 2023.
The first organizers arrived here about a week ago, and it is insane to look around
and see how much has changed, and all the volunteers who have helped have done so much
work and deserve all our gratitude.
We'll get back to that later, but it is fantastic to see everybody putting up camps and moving
into the field and unpacking and starting to build our temporary home for the next week.
Well, I mean, technically, Bornhack is a two-week event, right?
It's only the volunteers know that secret, so you get to be here much longer if you help
out with build up and chat out.
We are very excited.
This has been a year of many challenges, and well, it always is, but maybe some particularly
big ones this year.
In particular, some sad news.
We lost one of our organizers, Jesper, this year, or last year, in October, very suddenly
and way too soon, and it hit all of us hard.
We dedicated the tagline for this year to Jesper, Make Legacy, because we feel that
everybody wants to leave a legacy, and Jesper absolutely did leave a legacy.
He had a tremendous impact on Bornhack as an organization and on all of us personally.
He left a giant void.
Thank you to the people in info and the people in wellness who have stepped up to fill the
void after him.
Thank you in particular to the new radio team and to Maunus who have sponsored the new radios
and the new repeater and everything so we can continue the work that Jesper did in every
sense of the word.
There's nothing really we can do to properly mark this, but I wanted to do a minute of
silence, but instead I think that doesn't feel right because Jesper wasn't the silent
type.
Instead, we'll do 30 seconds of silence and then 30 seconds of applause to celebrate his
life.
Starting now.
Thank you.
Thank you all. It means a lot. Give me 30 seconds. Cheers. Cheers. Cheers. Cheers.
It's not a fun first slide, but let's pick it up from here. The Code of Conduct is pretty
basic to Bornhack and it's actually one of the things that Jesper also helped out a lot
with. I forgot to mention that Morten from the NOC team stepped up and took Jesper's
place in the Code of Conduct team, so thank you also, Morten, for that. The Code of Conduct,
you probably have all seen it by now because it's taped to the inside of the toilet doors,
so it's pretty hard to miss. We take this seriously and we expect you to do the same.
It is about being nice to each other and respecting each other's personal space. It's a photo
policy and much more. Make sure you read it. Make sure you follow it. If you have questions,
we are available. There's a contact team that you can speak to and we usually don't have
to resort to any major Code of Conduct things. People are generally very, very nice to each
other here and we really appreciate that and we think and hope that that will continue,
of course, but the Code of Conduct is there to be a guideline in case some people have
questions about that. Reach out to the Conduct team, please.
Like I said, everybody who some people even showed up on the first day or second day,
so have been here almost a week along with the first organizers who arrived, it is such
a big job putting up all this stuff and the rain has not, the weather has not helped one
bit. It has been not only raining but very unstable, so occasionally raining and occasionally
very hot, so you have to change in and out of outfits every 10 seconds. It's been a lot
of work and to the people who take extra days off of work and stuff to come and help make
this happen and also in the other end who stay for the tear down and an extra special
big thank you. Can you please all stand up, people who helped with the build up so we
can see how many people there actually is.
Born Hackers like the bar always a work in progress and even though we have had a bit
more of a less stressful build up because we had a few more days and some stuff got
delivered and put up earlier than usual, so it's been a nice example of a build up the
way it should be and not too stressful and not too many long nights and stuff, but it
would be crazy to think that we have remembered everything and gotten everything done, so
there are still small things to do and there will be stuff that keeps popping up over the
week and stuff that we just plain forgot about. We'll put the jobs on the whiteboard
by the info desk, so if you come by and see something and think I can do that and I have
some time and I want to help out, then by all means please talk to the info desk or
somebody and if you need to or just do the job if it's easy to do.
If you see something wrong and you can't fix it, then please let us know. We will find
somebody who can fix it. I have a venue map at some point and the venue continually evolving
over the week is exemplified by, I made these slides two hours ago and the map is already
outdated, so bear with me on that. I'll try to explain what happened when we get to it,
but we are rolling with the punches and we'll make everything work, of course.
Oh, here it is. It's not terribly big, but...
I'll just use the colors. We are in the white square in the middle of the light blue triangle,
the general camping and this is the speaker stand. Across the road straight ahead is the
bar, it is hard to miss, it is a big colorful loud place with all the beers. We have north
east of this general camping and the pointy end, we have the caravans this year, they
moved to the other side of the road and across the road from them we have some more general
camping for attempts. On the other, between the bar and general camping is the auger area
with the info desk and all that. It is also the organizers personal village and where
we go to chill out and get away from people and like everybody needs to occasionally,
so please, unless you have something urgent, try to reach somebody in the info desk or
somewhere else and please stay out of the auger village as much as possible. Not that
we don't love you all, but we also have our stock of booze and everything in there, we
want to just keep it free of people. That is for us to drink, no.
So following the general, the central main road south, there is an entrance into the
food area and past the food area there is the noisy camping area, sorry, party camping
area, you don't have to be noisy down there. And on the other side of the road from that
is the cozy camping area which we introduced last year when we moved the speaker's tent
down here. It has turned out to be quite a nice little camping area and it is very popular
this year, it is nice to see. Going further up the road, there is a big shower and toilet
building, all the showers are down in the south end of the venue. There is a separate
building that has two showers and four toilets and inside the main building there is two
more showers and two more toilets and also there is two toilets down here by the bar.
That is the venue, if you have questions, oh, and the silent area, the neon or light
blue area in the top is the silent camping and the eastern part of that or maybe the
western part, it is not fully clear yet, will be converted to an extra caravan area because
we are kind of running out of space and there is ample space down there so we will kind
of remodel the venue a little bit last minute, forced by, well, we kind of estimated wrong,
I think how much room caravans take or something. Okay, the info desk is across the road from
yeah, and a bit down the road from where we are now. Many of you have probably been there
to get your wristband, you can come back to get more hacks, get some money if the bar
is not open, ask questions, pick up merchandise, pick up the badges when we get to that, they
will be ready soon, I think tomorrow or the day after or something. The team needs people
to help cover the shifts, it is not difficult work, you sit down and just help people and
they have a thorough interaction so most people should be able to do it and they really
need some help so please go to the info desk and ask them if you are interested in helping
out, they would love to be able to cover the shifts without having to work all of them
all the time. For those of you who haven't been here before,
we have something called hacks, you might have heard about it already, it is our internal
local currency, we packed it to the Danish Kroner so it is worth the same as the Danish
Kroner so if something costs 150 hacks it is the same as 150 Danish Kroner. They can
be bought at the info desk or at the bar when the bar is open or you can buy them online
and just buy them on the webshop and use the ticket in the bar or the info desk. You can
also use them at the food vendor, apart from the info desk and the bar, the food vendor
accepts them and they can basically be used like real money except the only way to buy
alcohol is with hacks, you cannot buy it with real money which is the main reason we have
them and so if you want to go to the bar and buy anything with any kind of alcohol in it
you will need to go get some hacks in the info desk to do that. They are these little
coloured coins, you will see them everywhere. If you ordered village tents or tables and
chairs and stuff, the tents you probably found, tables and chairs, if you still need to get
that you can go to the info desk, please coordinate with the info desk, don't just take stuff
because then we have no chance to keep track of it, it is not logged in, we know you can
just walk up and take it and we know you have paid for it and stuff but please coordinate
with us, it is really tricky to keep track of stuff when people just take it and tell
us in the bar at 1am, I took two chairs and four tables. So please go do it properly in
the info desk when they are open. We may have a few extra tables and chairs and benches,
go buy info tomorrow and check if we have any surplus, if you forgot to order or you
need some extras. We have electricity all over the venue thanks to the hard working
power team, they have rolled out more than a kilometre of the very heavy cables and the
power points are more or less all over the venue. Please keep them covered from the rain
so we don't have any outages because something got wet and if you see one without cover please
fix it yourself or notify somebody who can fix it, please don't just ignore it and leave
it and think somebody else will do it. Let's everybody help out and things will get fixed
much quicker and stop from breaking. There is an example here of it is not the biggest
picture but a happy looking power point, it has a bag over it and the bag is secured with
some pegs in the back, secured in the bag. It is cloth pegs, just the other kind of pegs.
Connect your cables if you need an adapter because we have the weird Danish standard
here, maybe we have some, do we have some in the info desk or not? I don't know actually,
ask somebody who knows. We don't. We will figure it out. Come ask us if you can get
power because things don't fit, we will make it fit somehow. Along the same lines the network
team have been working hard to get the network up and running, you can get gigabit ethernet
to your table, you can get wifi, you can even get a fibre link if you arrange it especially
with the network team. If you have special needs other than wifi you can absolutely get
that sorted. We have three SSIDs, the born hack net is the one that acts mostly like
a home internet connection, the born hack 802.1X is with 802.1X authentication fun enough
and the IPv6 one is with the modern IP family without the legacy, the IPv4 one. We get constant
requests to use more bandwidth and I guess that applies this year as well, does it not?
Great, so please use more bandwidth. The bar as you can see is progressing nicely, it is
always fascinating even to the people building it, how it is going to look, but to everybody
watching it during build up and in the first days so much happens and it becomes increasingly
more awesome as the days go by. Please use the bar, it is an important part of the money
that we use to make this event work, especially this year, we have been working on it for
a long time and it has been difficult to make ends meet so we have had to cut a few things.
The hot tub for example is not here this year, very sad to say, but we had to make some difficult
cuts here and there and that was one of the things that we had to take away. We hope it
will be back next year. Please use the bar, we absolutely depend on the profits from the
bar to make this whole thing work. We have a very nice selection of craft beer and booze
and can make cocktails and there is all the matter in the world, we might have slightly
overdone it on the matter this year so please.
There are many kinds and many bottles of each kind so that is great.
The bar has closing hours, we have a permit to sell booze from the authorities and that
ends at 2 a.m. every night so there are last rounds at 1.50, get your purchases in there,
get in line because we have to stop selling alcohol and the bar doesn't necessarily have
to shut down entirely but we cannot sell any more alcohol so buy your bottles and stuff
before 2 and then stick around.
That is thinking like a hacker. No, we better not play games with them but it opens when
the first bar staff wakes up the next day, usually around noon-ish I would say.
When we are a lot of people gathered we generate a lot of trash that is inevitable both from
food and drinks and everything and it is a lot of work handling trash from just a few
hundred people like we are, generates so much trash and so much deposit like empty bottles
and cans and stuff that we need to handle it properly from the beginning to not generate
massive amounts of work and also if it is not handled properly we get wasps and a thousand
nasty things as a result of not handling trash properly.
We have some trash cans around and there are signs on them, please look at the signs before
you put stuff in so you use the correct trash cans. We have five different ones, two of
them are for deposit, they have this circular logo thing, it is on the trash cans as well
and if the bottles have that you know the system from wherever you live and the deposit
cans and plastic bottles go in one container and the deposit glass bottles go in another
container. Apart from that there is a glass container for just like boost glass bottles
or whatever glass that does not have deposit and one for cardboard and finally one that
does not fit for all the trash that does not fit in any of the others. Is that pretty clear?
Two different kinds of deposit, one for cans and plastic bottles, one for glass and then
there is glass, cardboard and the rest. Ok? Fantastic. The people sorting it at the end
will send you happy thoughts forever if you do not generate too much sorting. As you can
imagine sorting three, four hundred people's deposit after a week or two is not fun work
so the less stuff that has been put in wrong, the less we have to sort, the better. So please
please spend the extra ten seconds, check the signs, put it in properly and please and
thank you from the sanitation team. Yes? Plastic what? Just general plastic that is used in
this municipality, they have not joined the rest of us in the 21st century. So it is not
for exposition? No, absolutely not. We would sort in ten kinds if we could but they are
just going to mix it all together when they pick it up anyway so there is no reason, sadly.
We hope next year we come back and see ten trash cans outside but we have been hoping
that for four years now, let's see when it happens. Sure, good question though. Ok, like
I mentioned we have had a rough time of it with sponsors this year but we have managed
to find some new sponsors and we are of course always tremendously grateful for all the support
we are getting, some sponsors pay cash and help just with the general finances of the
event, some lenders stuff that we would otherwise have to spend money on getting which is just
as good as getting money and it all helps out and even small sponsors that may not be
big companies and can't put in that much, it all helps because I would much rather have
five small sponsors than one big one if the amount is the same because it is just nicer.
So to all the sponsors, big and small, thank you to all the people who jumped in when
the shit hit the fan and we really needed to find new sponsors on pretty short notice.
Thank you all for jumping in to assist me and the others on the sponsors team and coming
with new leads. If any of you have an idea for an organisation that might want to help,
please send them my way or to watch the sponsors email and we can reach out to them. The absolute
most successful way to do it is if you know somebody who can make the decision about giving
some money or not and prepare them and then put us in contact with them. That method has
close to 100% success rate and just getting a contact, call this dude in this company
has close to 0% success rate. It is a massive difference. So if you know somebody, can go
poke your boss and say, hey, we should pay 10,000 to this event next year because they
are really cool and they help the community a lot and such and such. It helps us a lot
and it's barely any money in a company's budget for the whole year, almost no matter how small
a company, except ours. So thank you to all of you who helped find sponsors. I'll go through
them now and there will be their logos on the website and everything. We have a small
paper with badges this year that also have the sponsors logo on them. Please send them
your thanks and thoughts and use their services if you at all can. The big ones this year
are DKNOG, which is another event and full of lovely networking people and they stepped
in when they heard we were struggling and helped out a fellow event. Samdata is a big
labor union in Denmark that among other things has HK is a big labor union and Samdata is
the IT department for IT people and Sibyl Group is my employer that has lots of companies,
among others, the one where I'm employed called Mindfuture. Silver sponsors, Epson
has for the fourth year in a row, I think, sponsored this very nice video setup with
a high intensity brightness projector that works even when the sun is shining and the
weather is sweet. So thank you for that and that's a good example of something we would
have otherwise have to go out and rent and they are very expensive. Job Index and Sima4
are both new sponsors and thank you to those as well.
Among the sponsors are also Bornholm Spirits who continue to supply, we started out at
Bornholm but they continue to supply Saberblöder and other nice things for us at a very nice
price. FibreVue is providing the internet connection, not the fiber but the actual uplink
to the internet. Magenta PCBWay are sponsoring the PCBs for the batches and Ramion are sponsoring
speakers and Roskilde Auto and Skade Centre is sponsoring the shuttle car and the rest
are financial, no, TukTek is hosting sponsors for the Bornhack stuff. And the rest are financial
sponsors and thank you so much to them. There's a full year and a half to go and I think we
are now until the next Bornhack and a lot of the sponsor stuff takes some months to
settle and it's really tricky to do two weeks before Bornhack. So if you have an idea, get
started in the start of next year, not in June or July because it might be too late
for decision makers have gone on holiday and everything. So think spring is a good time
to be thinking about sponsors for Bornhack. Oh, that's quite the segue. So we are in an
area that sometimes has, well, it all the time has ticks and sometimes they latch onto
people and sit down by the ankles or in humid places on the body. They are nasty, they can
sometimes rarely but occasionally have a disease and it can infect people and can get
really nasty. So if you discover a tick, get it removed as soon as possible. We have tick
removers in the info desk and SIRT can help remove them. It can be difficult to check.
It's the back of the knees and weird places. Have a friend help you in the tent, might
be fun. Make sure you check when you are in the shower and if you feel that might be,
they are very, very small. They can look like just a little piece of dirt. Some of them
incredibly tiny. So make sure you keep an eye out for those little fuckers.
Okay, bicycles. The info desk is the place to go if you need to ride a bike somewhere,
maybe go shopping or maybe just go for a nice ride around in nature or whatever you need.
We have helmets and locks and lights and stuff for them. Different sizes. There's a few children's
bikes too and there's a trailer or two as well. They are free still. This is one of
the things we considered introducing a payment for when we were, because we are struggling
a bit financially. Instead we suggest a small donation to cover the cost but they are free
but please consider donating something if you take a bike.
The parking lot, most of you arrived by car so you will have noticed the parking lot.
I just wanted to mention please park sensibly and like don't, goes without saying, don't
double park and don't park so other people can't get out. There's plenty of room down
there for all the tickets we sold if people park sensibly. Last year we had, I don't know,
two years ago, an annoying incident where we had to run around and find somebody who
was parked so other people couldn't get out. So please consider everybody when you put
your car down. If there's any issues in the parking lot, please notify the info desk.
We don't necessarily know because we're not, not all of us are driving around. We arrive
here and then we leave two weeks later. So we might not notice. So please notify us if
there's something with the driving plates or someone is parked badly or something.
If you ordered T-shirts, hoodies and merchandise, it will be produced during the week and when
it's ready we'll announce it and you can pick it up in the info desk. It is being produced
by, yeah, Floma and a few other volunteers. We're doing a lot of work for it and it's
always such nice merchandise we get. So thank you for all the work you're doing.
Badges. This year's badge is NFC focused. It consists of two badges actually. There's
a reader which is the active part that has the computer and a tag which is a passive
thing that can be read with the active part. It's a very cool setup and it enables a lot
of fun NFC hacking and we hope to see some cool things, cool applications of it.
As mentioned quite a few times by now, we are kind of broke and other events have charged
for badges for a while and we've never done that because we kind of feel that we would
love for this to just be a part of the ticket. We haven't announced this earlier because
we've been trying to secure sponsors to make it fully free. That has not been possible.
A badge is 100 hacks. If you have a full week ticket then you have QR code in the same PDF
as your ticket and you can use that to get a badge for 100 hacks. If you want additional
badges or you are here on a one day ticket or you want one to take home to a friend or
something it's 150 hacks. Hopefully next year we can go back to the full week tickets including
badge enterprise. Sadly this was the best we could do this year. The badges will be
presented tomorrow. Thank you. The badges will be presented tomorrow at 1300 by Flummer
from the badge team who will talk about the design and what it can do and I'm sure there
will be a lot of fun things about it. I wanted to include a picture but I didn't have time.
They look fantastically cool. I'm looking forward to seeing them all around the venue.
We still have a few teams that need members. The info team is continuously onboarding new
people. They always need people to set up there. Sometimes they have to sit two or three
people to manage the load. It just takes a lot of volunteers to keep the info desk open.
The video team manages this stuff right here. Makes sure stuff is recorded and streamed
and we can watch the recordings later or at least sit in the tents and watch the streams
live. Not everything is recorded. Please make sure you note in the program if there's a
little recording icon or not and if not you have to be present here if you want to see
it. The stuff that's being recorded, if you're prevented from seeing it, you can catch it
later on the stream. If you want to join the video team, there's an onboarding meeting
tomorrow Thursday at noon here in the speaker's tent. They have a very thorough onboarding
and it looks a bit intimidating, all the equipment, but it is easy to do and you get a first row
seat for the talks and we would appreciate help with that. The sanitation team colloquially
team shit handles, they do not clean toilets, might occasionally unclog one, but cleaning
is handled by an external cleaning company, but they handle stuff like making sure there's
hand paper towels and soap and stuff in the toilets and the trash being emptied and put
in the container and the deposit bags being emptied and stuff like that. So it's handling
all the waste, but not actually cleaning toilets. We have people for that. They're also onboarding
continuously and you can go to the info desk and speak to Anke, I guess, if you're interested
in joining. On the website there's a list of teams and you can see there which ones
still need members. We've also, as a new initiative started, a daily volunteer meeting, which
every day at 1400. It is in the start tent across from the info desk and it is an attempt
to keep some of the awesome communication going. We've had, during build up, we have
meetings after each meal and we have breakfast, lunch and dinner prepared by Jonathan, which
is always fantastic, and after that we have a talk about what needs to be done and people
put out their hands and go do stuff. And that kind of stops when the event starts because
we lose contact to all the volunteers. We don't have these regular meetings anymore.
And we want to remedy that by doing this daily volunteer meetup at 1400. Everybody, you don't
have to be on a team. If you don't have anything to do, if you want to help out, show up at
the start tent across from the info desk. One of the recurring themes will be, since
we are a bit broke this year, we could not afford as much cleaning as we normally can,
so the food area will not be cleaned for us. We have to do that ourselves. And one of the
things we will do every day at two is to take a bunch of volunteers, go down there, do the
tornado, make it look really nice, and hopefully we can keep it going. You are also, of course,
all required to clean up after yourself. When you use the food area, when you cook, when
you do dishes, if you spill something, please fix it yourself. It's not necessary to say,
but we know that when many people use a kitchen, no matter how careful everybody is, there's
going to be spills and stuff that needs cleaning. And since there are no cleaners doing it,
we have to do it ourselves. If you see something, clean it up. Absolutely. That would be fantastic.
But we are planning to take a team of people once a day and give it the once over so it
stays nice and inviting to use. So if you feel like helping out with that and other
stuff that pops up, it will be every day at 1400 in the volunteer tent. We hope to see
many people and we are excited to introduce this new. We think it's going to be a great
addition to an already great event.
CERT are here to take care of us in case something happens. It is our medic team. They can take
care of small and big things like ticks or small cuts or worse. We haven't had much of
the worse, but we have people to handle it in case it happens. We have a hard starter.
We have first aid kits. We have educated people who have been in situations where they have
to take care of people before. And we are in good hands. They are wearing orange vests.
They can be called on the radio. You can call the born hack phone. If you have a deck phone,
then you can call 112 on the deck phone. There's a lot of ways to get in touch with them. And
they will also be visible on the side. There's always 24 hours, a CERT person on duty. They need
more people, if I recall correctly. Yes. And they have a team meeting Thursday, that's tomorrow
at 11 in the cabin. I can't see if you're nodding. Yes. Thank you. In the cabin. And they need
members, yes. You don't have to be trained anything, but it of course helps if you are.
Photo team will wear white vests. They are recognizable for a good reason. We have a code
of conduct, like I mentioned, and one of the important or one of the parts of it, they are
important, is that you're not allowed to take pictures at born hack unless everybody, all people
in the photo agree to the photo being taken. This means I cannot take a crowd photo here. It would
take forever to ask everybody. Well, I have a microphone. But still, generally, you can't
take crowd pictures. It's tricky and it's sad. But we have to protect people's privacy and
prioritize that over people's desire to take cool pictures of crowds. We do, however, want to see
cool pictures. And that is quite the dilemma. So we have a photo team. They all know, well,
you all know the code of conduct because you've used the toilets, but they know a lot of people
here personally. They know who they can take pictures of and who has already said no. And if
they see new people, they might come and ask, is it okay to take a picture here? You are free to say
no and stay where you are. You are free to say no and step out and the photographer can take the
picture, make it work somehow. But they are visible in white vests and, of course, a piece of huge
optics around their neck. And they will ask permissions for pictures. And if you feel like a
picture has been taken where you weren't asked or maybe you were in it or you are not sure, you are
very welcome to go ask the photographer to see the pictures and browse through. And if you feel
like you are on one of them, then it can be deleted. But it shouldn't happen. They are careful and
they know what they are doing. I'm not sure. Does the photo team need more people?
Yes, everybody is welcome.
So if you like taking pictures and this sounds like something you could and would do, then talk
to Tobias and he can introduce you to the whole thing. There's a meeting tomorrow at noon. Is it also in the
cabin? Also in the cabin. Great. The game team has prepared a token game again this year. The tokens
are little text strings. They are hidden around the venue, offline and online, on physical signs
or it could be on servers or networks, all kinds of things. There are hints in your profile on the
website. And I think they will keep adding tokens throughout the week. And the hunt is usually great.
The hunt is usually competitive and fun and it's kind of like a treasure hunt for nerds all around
the venue. It is a great tradition and I hope many of you will play. I know the game team has put a
lot of work into it. The last slide is just a thank you to the volunteers. This event would not be
possible without the volunteers. That goes without saying. We are 11 people in the group and it would
absolutely not be possible to do all this without 30 or 40 people helping out with carrying stuff
around and helping us with our crazy ideas. And hey, we want to build a weird thing here, can you?
And people just run over and start building. It's just fantastic to be around people with this kind
of drive and this kind of passion. And it's so nice that you throw that drive and that passion
towards helping us make this event even more fantastic. So again, thank you all.
Please consider showing up for the meetings at 1400. We've been a bit cheeky and added it to the schedule
so it will show up in your gigaday and in your feed readers and your calendars and stuff. So give it a try,
show up if you have nothing else to do. I added this slide in case I thought of something to say while I was talking,
but I haven't. So I don't think I have anything else. But if any team leads may have comments or stuff
I forgot to include that would be relevant to include now, then we can do that.
We are getting a microphone, just a second.
Is there a regular Bonhack network?
Is there? Oh, I didn't see. Oh, sorry. There's four SSIDs and one of them is just called Bonhack
and it's a plain old public B4 and B6. You get a real IP address, make sure your firewalls is properly configured
because that's like going on the old school internet back in the 90s.
If you collected your footage here, this is on. It's supposed to be. It's not.
If you collected your footage here from the pedestrian area and you had a dark chair, the white plastic one,
but accidentally took the hold of one, one was sitting on it and the other was on the floor.
Oh, damn. Okay. I'll repeat because the audio was a bit low. If you ordered village gear and you ordered the black upholstered chairs,
no, sorry, you ordered the white garden chairs and accidentally instead took the black upholstered chairs,
please bring them back because we need them. The people who actually ordered them need them and come back and get some white garden chairs instead.
Basically the garden chairs, the white ones are good for the grass and the other ones are good for when you have a floor in your tent.
It's kind of late to change now because we can't change the order, but if you did get the upholstered chairs
and you have those on your receipt and you know what I'm saying. If you took the wrong chairs, please bring them back. Thank you.
Any other questions?
Oh, that's a very good question. The Hacker Jeopardy will be on tomorrow and then again Saturday and again Monday for the finals.
Sign-ups is to info at bornhack.dk by mail. We already got the first sign up a few days before the event
and we always, the game team always needs more categories. If you've played Hacker Jeopardy before or been a spectator,
you know what this is about. It is find a fun category, find some questions that are not too difficult.
The one trap people always falls in is like, okay, I'm an expert on this. I'll make a category so difficult that I'm the only person in the room who can answer it.
And that's just not a lot of fun to other people than the person who knows all the answers.
What we want is categories that go from the most difficult one, maybe 25% knows it and the easiest one, almost everybody knows it and it's a chase for the buttons.
It has to be, it's much more fun that way. Trust us, we've tried both ways and take our words for it.
So please send categories. Is there a...
Game-team at bornhack.dk
and send your categories or send questions. If you don't know quite how to formulate it, they will be happy to get you started.
If you're playing and you submitted a category, please let us know the day you're on so we don't accidentally schedule your own questions when you're playing.
Yeah, yes?
I missed the POC in this one. It would be fun to say that that is working now.
For the first time in a few years, we have a working DEC network. Thank you to the POC team for getting that up and running.
This means you can go to the website, register a phone number in the phonebook there with your account and then you get an activation code, you dial that on your DEC phone and you are rolling.
It's easy and it's fucking awesome and I'm looking forward to getting my own phones hooked up as soon as I don't have a million other things to do.
So, any more questions? I can't really see. There's one down there.
You forgot to give a hand to the hookah team.
Thank you.
Thank you. We love you too.
We forgot to say you can spot the organizers from these very snazzy latest fashion black vests that we're wearing this year.
So, black vests for Orga, white vests for Photo Team, orange for SIRT and the yellow vest is other volunteers.
So, that's the color scheme for this year, hopefully going forward.
Okay, fantastic. We got through it in under an hour. That's a new record and I almost didn't cry and we're pretty good.
See you at the bar!
Yes, exactly. See you all at the bar. Thank you for everything.