Okay. We're about to begin the next presentation. We have Benjamin who is here to talk about
an introduction to digital consent, why a new definition with new tools and specifications
are needed. Let's give a round of applause for Benjamin.
Thank you so much. I have a quick sponsorship message before starting the talk, so I just
want to start with that so I don't forget it. A Danish organization called Django Denmark
is hosting Django Day, like an annual one-day event for Django people. It's in Copenhagen.
We found a really lovely venue on Nørrebro, and talks are coming in, and tickets are on
so on. That's on the 6th of October, and that's the website for that. So I hope that maybe
you're interested. There is also a little Django perspective in this talk. Yeah. So
I'm a software developer, and I want to talk about consent with the background that I have
as a software developer. Maybe I'm not so precise on the legal aspect, so this is not
like legal advice about how to do consent, but I hope it aligns with your understanding
of GDPR and those sorts of legal obligations that we have when we build systems with data,
basically. So it's also the first time in a long time that I'm doing a talk, and the
last time I was preparing a talk, I found out that I was very confused around what to
do, what focus to find. So now I ask why do I think this is a talk to present here for
you and for your sake, for my sake, and let's just make those terms clear. Let's make the
purpose of the talk clear. I really want more people to care about the question of
consent, digital consent, but in order so that we can build something and so that we
can build something together. So I'll try to, as a software developer, maintain the
aspect that we'll talk a lot about consent, but in the end, let's try to make it turn
it into a tool so that when we want to have consent for something in an application, we're
doing it the best possible way. So I hope you agree to that. Some of it is below the
falsehood. It's also Latin. So I'll try to cover these four aspects here. First, those
pesky cookie banners that we all know about. They're everywhere. And then I'll talk a bit
about consent, like what can we say, what sort of properties can we attach to consent
in order to have a definition of it. Then from that definition, can we specify something
that we can use to implement software? And then finally, I'll just share a little bit
about what I've been trying to do. I hope that people can hear, because it's very loud
for me up here with the rain. Okay, cool. So those pesky cookie banners, I'll just show
you a few examples to get the thought process started. What's happening right now with consent
is basically that people want to continue to use and share data. It's still okay. They
want to continue to use and share data the same way. Kind of business as usual, but we'll
just add even more layers of terms and conditions. And I've been annoyed at it and posted stuff
on social media when I saw a dialogue that I didn't like. And I was trying to figure
out some examples before the talk, and basically I just went to the first two kind of random
pages that I found. So these examples are not the cherry picks. I just went on the normal
internet and looked. I went to wordpress.com, and they say they're the world's most popular
website building tool. So let's hope they get consent right. I would say they don't.
You go to the front page, and there is no consent dialogue at all. But there is trackers.
There is trackers on the website. For the stream, people, I can say there is very heavy
rain coming down right now, so we have a lot of problems with the sound in here. I'll
let folks move a little bit. Yeah, okay. So people are just moving around in the room
here so that we can sit a little bit closer, and then we hope the rain will cool off.
That's a lot better. Okay.
So now the sound is better, and people are closer to the microphone. I guess we continue.
I went to the front page of wordpress.com, and there was no consent dialogue. I click
get started. I go to the second page, and then the consent dialogue pops up. I think
the designers of the website have decided that the consent dialogue is probably not
a good user experience, so they want to hide that on a secondary page. I looked at the
trackers, and they were the same on those two pages as far as I could tell. And then
of course they have this silly thing where you need to click customize, and then you
have to toggle something in order to actually reject it. That's a pattern of trying to make
people accept things. I have a different example here. That's when you go to Bloomberg.com.
It's a giant thing. You have to either accept all or reject all. What I thought was very
interesting about this one is a text that reads that you can actually manage those choices
any time, which I would understand that it's a good effect for this dialogue. You can
manage those choices any time you want, but that doesn't really make sense because if
I go to the website again with a different browser session, how am I going to manage
those choices from the previous visit? It's bizarre. The link just points to a generic
page that's dependent on the cookie. So that's one of those real absurdities of revoking
cookie consent. You may need to actually store those cookies yourself in order to revisit
the sites. You may also need to have a log of your own IP addresses you've been delegated
and whatever goes into your fingerprint that's used for this kind of ad profiling. Looking
at those terms and conditions, those consent dialogues, they all contain something about
profiling. So that's not profiling that is explicit, but it says that it may contain
this and this and this element. So in order to revoke it, I would pose that then the user
needs to be able to know that about their own web browsing in order to, for instance,
invoke the right to be forgotten or the right to see your own data. All those individual
GDPR rights. And that is absurd. I think no one's going to do that. Even on the highest
level. Knowing that and putting it into practice seems very far-fetched. So some other absurdities
that we notice is that there is actually a great HTTP header, the do not track header.
And it seems to me that it would be easier if the ones that own websites instead would
read that header instead of letting everyone have to read those awfully long terms and
conditions. That's just a very simple solution to not consent to tracking. And then if that
header is set, you don't even have to show those dialogues. You can give the user a better
experience. And then there's browser extensions kind of doing the same. Let's say you own
a website and you can see that people are using tracker bloggers or ad bloggers. That's
probably because they do not consent to the tracking, right? So you don't need to show
them the dialogue. And then there is the very strange behaviour of saying, like, if you
continue browsing this website, then you automatically agree. Like, how do you note that
someone actually saw that dialogue? And you might as well have missed it. That's the case
of the Bloomberg thing here. They have in the background there, you can see there is
a tiny, small, like, yellow thing that says that they have updated their terms and conditions.
And if you continue surfing the site, you just automatically agree to those changes.
Very strange, I would say. Okay. So let's be a little bit positive now.
I would say that there is maybe an okay thing to think about during the past, like, GDPR
times and maybe the past, I don't know, maybe it's a decade now that the cookie banners
have been out there. But they did spread an awareness of tracking and so on in the larger
population, right? And maybe that's an advantage. It could also be a disadvantage, though,
because we get this consent fatigue. We have to look at way too many things and consent
to them. So, of course, we just stop looking. We stop caring. And that's quite human.
Oh, this talk just keeps getting gloomier and gloomier.
So, the normalizing is part of the fatigue, you could say, but it's also part of maybe
saying, you know, oh, this tracking, it's innocent. Everyone does it. Like, it's completely
fine that we have a list of, I think, one of the consent, cookie consent frameworks.
They advertise that they automatically have an updated list of 2,000 third-party tracking
companies, data processors. It's quite a lot, but then that's kind of just normal.
And I think even worse is that we get a bit, like, nihilism is creeping in, like, big tech
is just doing whatever they want with our data, and we can't even read all these dialogues
that we keep getting thrown at us. But, yeah, good news. I think that cookie consent is
not really any consent thing. Maybe we should find a better word for it. It's very hard
to claim that this is informed consent. And we already can see how, like, very explicit
revocations of consent that are being indicated in HTTP headers are being ignored. And, yes,
I think I've argued the case that it's in practice, it's not possible to revoke this type of
consent. I asked a bit around, and I was happy to see that the general Born Hack audience
in the Fediverse also had a majority of saying, let's reject this as a solution to tracking.
Like, asking for consent in this way doesn't make tracking okay as how I would interpret
the response here. But also that some people have kind of given up hope. Some people also
believe that we can improve cookie banners so that the consent can work. I'd like to
really like to hear from them also. Let's say that we had a workshop and we could talk
a bit more about our experiences with both cookie consent but also other types of consent
where you agree to some terms and conditions in a shop or with a public sector. Then it
would be a great fit to ask these basic simple questions. Is the consent I'm dealing with
here, is it informed consent, meaning that the user knows what's going on, and how to
withdraw that. And also the curious case because often this legitimate interest is being mixed
up. Often there is a blurry line that it looks like you have to consent to something but
actually it's called legitimate interest. I'll try to come back to that. But that's
a great idea for a workshop, I think. I hope someone would be interested in that too.
So, moving on from the cookie banners, let's try to define something. Let's try to say
what properties should real consent contain. I don't know, strong consent, true consent.
Just trying to distance it from this mix up with the cookie banners. First of all,
real consent should be a voluntary thing. If there is only one button called accept
and you need to accept in order to access something, it's not consent. It's an agreement
or it's like the terms. But that's nothing to do with consent. We want the term to have
meaning. And that meaning comes when it's a voluntary declaration or agreement between
two parties. And secondly, it needs to be informed. So all this stuff about agreeing
without reading. We need to get into a situation where someone consenting to something actually
has an incentive to be informed about it. Then it should be revocable. That's also a
very hard technical task. So to implement that consent is suddenly being revoked, that
could happen any time to the system, needs to get a signal, needs to do something, needs
to scrub data, maybe tell other systems that they need to do the same. That can become
quite complicated. Then it needs to be manageable by the user. So what does that mean? That
could mean that the user needs a copy of what they're consenting to or they need some kind
of permanent access to the system. Maybe they need to store it in a wallet. There's many
ways probably of implementing this. And then it needs to be auditable. So we need to be
able to say when we did this and this action requires consent, then we need to track the
action in a way that we can prove that we had the consent when we did that. So it needs
to be auditable by someone and especially when it comes to GDPR, then users can at any
point in time require that you show proof that what you did was based on consent or
legitimate interest. But you need to be able to prove that. And other functions from GDPR
is this right to be forgotten and also the right to have your data corrected and so on.
Good to have all of that. And then it's a task now to implement. I just want to show
this table, though, because what we found when working with specification for consent
was that people working with other systems that needed consent, they were sometimes confusing
it with a normal agreement, but also they were asking the question, can't we also use
this consent system to store regular agreements, any kind of contract? And that's where the
consent specification gets too muddy. So we want to be strict on what is consent and what
is something else like a regular contract. The first thing was this point of it being
voluntary. If there is a reject and accept button, then we're good. Then it's voluntary.
People can reject it and the system understands the rejection. Then we need to have a purpose
declared and intention. That's kind of what consent does. You say yes to something that
then happens, probably also has expiry. But with contracts, it's not always the case
that you have contracts and agreements. Then you have more requirements or obligations
that have to happen. And they probably also will happen. Because contracts and agreements,
they have things about what happens if you don't do that. It's a promise of some kind,
whereas consent, the one that gives the consent can just revoke it. So I put those in contrast.
And then the auditable part is something where I would say that the contract and agreement
often is signed in a way that in itself it becomes the object that upholds its own consent,
where the consent relates to a lot of actions that need to prove that they are related to
that particular consent. So some examples that are not very clear,
cookie banners is that government, for instance, I'll just mention the two last ones, but very
typical government will want to, institution will want to get your personal data from registry
somewhere or exchange data in some kind of way to do an administrative task. That needs
consent often. But that's because you can reject it. So if you reject it, you replace
it with another process. Then you can just give them the information by showing your
ID or by fetching it from somewhere and manually handing it over and so on.
Another example is communication, where you accept that someone sends you a newsletter,
and when you withdraw that consent, they stop sending you the newsletter. And then the one
sending out the newsletter can of course store, like now I sent to these people, based
on this consent, you can anonymise or hash the email addresses. So you can build a nice
little system that's consent based. And actually it's the subscribe unsubscribe function of
the newsletter. So when we build this, we need to ask some
questions, like in order to establish informed consent, there are some risks. And the best
example of consent is when it comes to risks, is medical consent. There will be a lot of
risks implied with a medical procedure. And if the patient is conscious, you want informed
consent, and they are incentivised to read it because the risks are very high. Whereas
in the example of data exchange, the user can perceive no risk at all and not want to
read it. And that's where it gets a little bit more of a UX task, like how do we present
this thing so that the user actually perceives an incentive to go through it.
And that's a task not just for the legal department. I think if you just ask the legal department
to do the whole consent thing, you're going to get a legal text. And then you will have
the problem of turning the legal text into informed consent. You need something that
feeds people an understanding of the purpose and the risks and so on.
Then the last part is also to ask, like, is any of this in the user's interest? Maybe
ask that. And then if the answer is no, then ask if consent is really the solution then,
if you're doing something against the user's interest or not zero interest in it. It's
hard to push in consent because it will not be informed consent.
So try to put this proposal, kind of now it looks a little bit academic, that consent
is understood as a voluntary, well-informed and revocable declaration by an individual
for another party to use and process that data in a specific way. And we have established
a similar definition in a project that I'm part of that is government-oriented. It's
a little bit like a slightly simpler version of it. So before giving the talk, I decided
to add some more to the definition to make sure it's like a good and strong definition.
Then in this project called GovStack where we are working with a specification for consent,
we have also had to add something as an example of what consent is not. And that's like the
second clause to the definition is, let's say, the use of consent should be avoided
in these cases when a person is simply informed by an organization. It's like it's just an
information and you cannot project it or whatever. And when the consent is simply informed,
the system or platform that is dealing with consent has no way to identify the person
or has no way to establish the consent is actually real. Because then the owner of the
consent platform can also suddenly invent consent that's not so good. So we want a system
that's tied up to some other system that can ensure that there is a signature or some kind
of stamp on the consent. I'll get back to the data models for this because now is the
time for getting closer to, I've made a typo there, for the specification for digital consent.
And I have copy pasted the typo to each and every of the following slides. So the high
level requirement is to say we need privacy by design and privacy by default. I hope that
you've heard the terms before because I just really like those terms and they're a very
good starting point for specifying the system. And in privacy by design, we want to say we
start to design our whole system of data models, not just the consent models but also in the
rest of the system when something has to do with consent, we need to sort of plug it
into our consent system so that we know what to do when consent expires. So do things based
on the fact that consent should exist. If you are doing an operation in a system, maybe
you need to check for the consent before even proceeding. That could be a way. Then we also
want the privacy by default. So that's very simple with this. Like we just assume that
the user hasn't consented. That's how we design the whole system. There is no consent. And
then we have the entire track of how the system should work without the consent. So the advantage
is that actually consent can be a liability in itself. If you're storing a lot of consent,
with person identifiable information next to the consent, then the consent system in
itself contains things that are privacy related. And if people are rejecting something, and
you are then storing the rejection, then you're storing the fact that this person doesn't
want to do this. So we can get rid of that by defaulting to having rejections. So we
did some work in the GovStack project. And these are five pillars of the work. Firstly,
we have done this based on some use cases. And the first use case is related to a model
mother and child that goes to a health care centre and how this child is being registered
in the health care centre. And the second one is about payment in a public sector also.
So benefits, you can say. And how to do those payouts and sort of manage data around citizens
and we're not quite there yet. There's a lot of complexity in this. But we've started now
to have enough that we can say that we have a functional specification for the most simple
things. And there are some requirements, some UX requirements, some data models, and an
open API specification. In the functional requirements, you need the administration
part of the system. Someone needs to be able to configure and set up everything. So the
administrator or configuration owner, those are the ones that are responsible for adding
things that are like the texts that the user sees and should be able to update those texts
and see how things work out. Maybe mass reject everything when the consent is updated. And
the administrator also needs to be able to administer the general policy, privacy policy
that guides maybe all the handling of data inside the organisation. So we've got a bunch
of functionality there. Then we've got the individual user who is in need of seeing her
consent agreement, as we call it, so being presented by something to consent to, and
then actually accepting or rejecting that. What we're used to seeing is like mega collections
of a million things to toggle on and off. And we've just kind of envisioned that there
is one thing at a time, and then you click accept or reject. And of course they need
to be able to look at what they have consented to later, and they need to be able to send
revocations for things later in time. Yeah. So it's kind of obvious. The other part is
not so obvious. That's the auditing part, and we've kept that separate from system administration
and users' individual functions. So this is an area that I think we will have a lot of
future work with, and kind of understanding this whole aspect of what does auditing versus
privacy mean, like what are we actually now delegating the auditor to have access to.
Auditing can also happen through that someone looks into the consent system to see what
is stored in the system, but it can also happen that auditors should be able to access the
system that is doing stuff based on consent to see that things matches. Auditing can also
be that a third party is owning copies of what is happening in this consent platform
and then able to do their own auditing afterwards. We've tried not to specify exactly how that
happens but to have a larger palette for that. Then we have the UX requirements, which I
really wanted to have shown some of the mock-ups, but I didn't have the latest copy, but it's
fairly simple requirements. I think that's the common sense that you would have if you
thought about consent from your own perspective, like how would I like to be asked. So the
first requirement that I really liked in this UX specification was that we want to just
be clear about what data do we need, what are we doing here, why are we doing it and
what does the user benefit from this or risk from it. And then the duration is also really
important, like is this indefinite or is it just some data that we have for a week and
then we nuke it again. Super nice things to be reminded of, and I think that reading the
UX specification can even end up being the entry point for understanding this platform,
however it's made up. They also had a really nice note in the UX specification that says
UX requirements, which is kind of a different take on what I said earlier, that the system,
if the users reject the consent request, then the ones that are designing UX for a whole
application, they need to actually have a user journey where the consent is rejected,
and many people always think how people would like to use their system in the accept kind
of scenario, and then they forget that there is also a user journey where consent has been
rejected. And very important also, when you're having the first exchange with the user and
showing we need your consent here, of course it should be visible, what do you do then
if you change your mind. I've also seen UX mock-ups that actually lodge a consent dialogue
in a survey all the way through the survey, so you start by saying yes, I can accept this,
but then as you're asked more and more questions in the survey, you're reminded that now I'm
sharing this data, now I'm sharing this data, so then you can actually reject having your
personal details attached to the answer, or something like that, but have this information
about changing your mind visible, and have first class user interface for it.
So then we had some data models, and now is the time that I can again say that I'm a software
developer, so I kind of want to get to this step, because then I know what to do, and
this was the most simple version we could come up with, to just show what are the general
entities in the system. We have this configuration area, that's where we manage the components
of consent. So then we have the individual models that store the consent of the individuals
to something, and our terminology is that, and this is the core of building this system,
is to understand these data models, because then I think we'll go to a nice place where
consent makes sense, or at least makes more sense, is to model with a data model that
has a data policy, so that's your general policy for data, keep that separate. And then
the consent agreement itself, which is the purpose, what data, and why and for how long,
and so on, there's some properties, we call that a consent agreement. And then we have
a consent record, so a consent record, as you can see with the arrow, that's the link
between an individual and a consent agreement, stating that the individual has consented
to it. And now, of course, I should say that we have a model that's called individual,
but whether or not it's a natural person, that doesn't matter to the system, it can
be any kind of unique, if it's just an email address, maybe it just contains a hash of
the email address, and then that's all the system knows. So we also have the data, we
have a data provider or consumer or processor, they also need to be able to look at consent
in order to determine if the operation that they are doing has consent stored. Then there
is also a procedure, of course, that makes sure that the system can return yes or no,
but not necessarily state whether the user exists or not. It's an API, basically.
Yeah. So I really like this slide. I'm sorry it took so long to get here, but if you have
any questions around it, then be sure to ask them if we have time. Now I'll just make it
a little bit worse, because I thought this was okay simple, and add a little bit. What
I'm adding here is the auditing part, because what we are especially interested in is that
if the user changes their mind, or the consent agreement changes, or the data policy changes,
then we need to track that, otherwise we don't know anything about the past. So in the specification
we have proposed that there is a revisioning system that can track things if it's okay
to track them. And we have signatures, and if there is a way for the individual to actually
sign their consent, of course they should be able to do that, especially if it's the
public sector. They have all sorts of platforms for that. And we've also added the lifecycle,
and preparing the system, the specification, was a way of understanding that consent has
a lifecycle from where it hatches in a legal department, maybe that says we need this,
and then in a place where the whole aspect, legal aspect of it maybe is being prepared,
and then people interact with the system, but it may get used, it may change, that's
why we have the revisioning. And finally we need to be able to establish proofs both,
so that systems that are using it can see that there is consent, and so that auditing
can see that. So this high level view is also turned into an open API, specification
where it's like specific schemas with specific fields, so that's very nice. All of this is
just a specification though, so it's not an actual tool. So I want to go further now,
because what I think we are ready to do is to take this specification, build an open
source tool that is not necessarily for governments, that's probably very heavy, but at least can
work for organisations that we are dealing with in our everyday life that wants to ask
our users simple things like send a newsletter or store some information, because we want
to do a statistic in our organisation about something. Let's have a tool that can do that
the right way. And I thought that since I'm from the Django world, I thought that we can
build it with Django, because it's so nice to write data models in Django, and it's kind
of like a rapid thing, so we can get quickly from prototype to something that we can implement
in a real project. And I hope that this platform will turn into something that can both be
a standalone platform that has an API, so that you don't need to use Django in order
to use the application here, but if you use Django, then you can also do some added things,
so especially I'm thinking about adding a specific Django consent field that data models
can say, I'm a row in a database that's based on consent, and if the consent changes, then
I want to be deleted, or I want to have this particular field anonymised, or whatever.
And people have been playing around with this before, but I found that the older tools were
based on GDPR understandings, and they were kind of abandoned now, so the idea was to
start the project and have these thoughts around the consent definition and specification
from GovStack used as a way to bootstrap the project. So it has a repository. I just added
a matrix channel today, so if you're interested in joining that channel, you can use it to
get updated on how it's going with the project, and you're also very welcome to participate
in it. And then I wanted to add that I'm here, but only today at the event, so I hope you
grab me to talk some more about consent, maybe here, maybe in the back. I will use
your input, I hope that's okay, so if you tell me something about how you think about
consent, I will definitely get inspired and try and use that. And if you want to get involved
in the project, that would be super awesome. And my last recommendation here is that there
is a super nice little episode of All Hail the Algorithm, which is an Al Jazeera series
that some years ago actually took up the concept and really communicates it super well, makes
it exciting and makes it essential for everyday folks. I take questions, if there are any,
and thank you. Do we have any questions for Benjamin?
So we talked about this a bit earlier, but it seems to me the biggest players in the
game of tracking people's PII have a vested interest in not really getting consent from
people and patterns of behavior that indicate that they're not really interested in informed
user consent, they're interested in maintaining their status quo and finding loopholes that
allow them to continue doing that. And I think it's great that we think about how we can
serve our users and how we can respect their data and their privacy, but it feels to me
like the biggest problem is these bigger organizations that aren't going to play ball, no matter
what solutions exist. And I was wondering what you think about that and ways that you
see of affecting a more positive change given those actors like Google, Facebook, other
tech. Yeah, that's a really great question. I think
there is some kind of tactical political game buried here that maybe we should stop even
allowing them the right to use the word consent for these cookie banners. Maybe it's better
to just say cookie banners. And then if we can get as far as building a tool that deals
with real consent, I think we'll discover that the tool is absolutely useless for the
type of data sharing that cookie banners are used for. So we'll just have a great tool
that is great for actual consent and then it's easier to see the differences. If that
can work as a strategy, I would pick that because it's always nice to be able to show
the real consent. And yes, they will not... I mean, I'm pretty sure that at some point
someone is going to make a proposal in the European Parliament because now it's not the
same Parliament that gave us GDPR. It's a different Parliament. And someone is going
to say, look at this. This is absurd. Let's get rid of it and go back to the good old
days where we just shared data without even having the cookie banners. I mean, maybe that
could even be better for actually having consent now that everyone understands what shady stuff
is going on anyways. Kind of weird to have a cookie banner that you just kind of know
that it's being mismanaged and it's not really authentic. So, yeah.
Do you have one more question?
Thank you. I had a similar thought, but I think during the presentation you, without
intending, proposed an approach to dealing with the disservices that don't respect end
user freedoms. You said it's impractical to record every IP address I've used and every
website I've accessed, but actually I don't think so. We could make a browser extension
that does that and automatically request to be forgotten. Would that be a reasonable approach
for dealing with the sort of company that we were just discussing?
Yeah, I didn't think anyone would say that, but I'm glad you say it. Because if someone
can establish what they are doing as a person and giving and not giving consent to and then
use that to inquire into their data in a very precise manner and finding out that things
are happening or not happening as they should be, then we have a case that can be a legal
case, right? Then we can escalate from there. But, I mean, with all those pages in a typical
consent cookie banner, I should say, sorry, it seems like it's a very lot of legal details
going on. So it will be a big thing if we get that. But if we make the first step and
we can see that there is something more buried, then I think it's worth doing, especially
with the do not track header. Maybe that's also a simple way to establish, like, I'm
using a do not track header. Why are you not respecting it? Should you legally respect
that? I'm interested in why you connect government
building blocks to consent. Because from my understanding, most of what we do in government
don't really need any consent. So is government here actually the holder of the consent? Or
why is government involved? So I didn't include anything on the GovStack
project because I was afraid that would take up a lot of time to explain. But GovStack
is essentially not a government owned project, but it does have governments in it that the
German foreign aid ministry is in it, Estonian government is in it, the ITU, the international
telecoms union is in it, and the digital impact alliance is in it. So these organisations,
these organisations, they wanted from the beginning to be able to supply that functionality
from an understanding that it is the right thing to do. But there's many places where
you don't need it. You could just, like, not have this so-called building block in your
set of building blocks because the legal situation would say you can do whatever you want because
you're a government. But I think when the tool is available, at least even though the
government doesn't have to, then they could. And what we found also when we were building
this specification was that there aren't any tools that satisfy our specification. So I
think that was an important discovery in itself, was to work with this, set up the specification
and then discover, hey, we actually need open source tools and Govstack is based on open
source. That makes it also interesting. Digital common goods in this context. And we need
a digital common good that can satisfy this consent specification. Yeah.
Thank you. Sorry, I wasn't for the whole talk, so I apologise in advance if I'm asking something
that you already brought to the topic. But I have two parts, well, two questions. Actually,
the first one, so talking about legal, have you made some approach to some kind of organisation
like, I mean, we have an organisation called Legal Tech Lab, so legal tech is kind of a
buzzword for now. But is there something happening in that and that you can make a case regarding
like, hey, I'm not giving consent or this consent was not acquired in a legal attaining
context, so this is not valid, therefore you are not permitted to keep my data. So that's
the first question that I have. It's unfortunate that I don't personally
go out and do the work of seeing what's going on in that department, but it seems like in
the room there is actually a little spark of energy to also go that direction, so we
could say like, we are building a tool that can actually do the things we want in relation
to consent, but then we also want to expose these practices of fake consent or not respecting
the consent, so I would encourage myself and everyone to look for that, because it could
be something, yeah.
And yeah, the second question that I had is like also considering reaching to the parliament
for having something to pass by, that will require, for instance, taking a look at vulnerable
groups, like let's say Germany is not my first language, so I will just be giving consent
in order to get into a website to search for an apartment, so things of that nature, saying
like, okay, if you are requesting consent from this person, at least have the decency
to put the information on the language that they can understand, or for sites that are
just providing that in a certain language, or also looking at elderly people that for
them would be like, yeah, I mean, I don't know, I just want to see pictures of my nieces,
just get me in there, I will consent to anything, so it feels like kind of taking advantage,
so I was just asking if this is also something that can be considered.
Yeah, it definitely makes me want to say again, like the informed part of consent, it should
be part of the definition. If there is no informed consent, then it's not really consent,
what is it, then I don't know.
The second part was that I forgot to mention accessibility and UX requirements, so of course
UX has to be catering for the user's needs, yeah, super basic stuff, so I think that's
what I should have added to that, thank you.
In my experience, users, so every user, they find it very hard to make that risk assessment
of what is the consequence of me giving, except that you can use my data, so how will this
tool help people do that risk assessment? I know for the site, okay, I can see if I
make a consent, I can do this, I cannot do that, I understand that, but in the broader
picture, how will it help that assessment?
I think that knowing that you can always go back and revoke your consent and from the
beginning knowing how to do that is super critical, because yes, we cannot guarantee
that the user actually reads what they accept, there's no guarantee of that, like they scroll
through the window in two seconds or five seconds or 20 seconds, when have they read
it? These types of functionality doesn't work, but maybe establishing a convention about
consent so that if you have a user interface, then kind of the same way that we are switching
between light, dark mode themes or switching languages, we also know that this icon means
consent, I don't even know if maybe someone uses the check box to say it's about consent,
but yeah, like a well-established convention for consent will mean that people can change
it and then have a system that understands that consent can always change at any time.
Awesome, we are at the hour, let's give a round of applause for Benjamin.