The next speakers we have is the game team that will give us the state of the game.
Let's give them a hand.
Thank you.
We were supposed to be three people presenting today.
One is currently treating a wound, so I will be the first one.
And then we will have Asperon announcing the winner of the game game in the last half.
So yes, the token game has now ended.
You can still attempt to find some tokens if you want, but you can't win anymore.
So we had a lot of different activities.
So the two official ones we have are the Hacker Jeopardy and the token hunter.
But we also have a lot of game-related things created by participants.
So we have some board games, we have a game jam, which is announced in a bit, a Pendleton,
garden games, a Mario Kart tournament.
It sounded like they really had fun in that Mario Kart tournament.
I could hear it all the time.
We have a music quiz, treasure hunt, and a COAD tournament.
So it's very nice to see people enjoying themselves.
And we also have the pixel plot, of course.
So the Hacker Jeopardy.
We had a lot of positive feedback.
So we had this year done a bit of prep work.
I'm not personally the one who does the Hacker Jeopardy, but the team who did it did some
really nice work.
It seemed to have paid off, the preparation, and they were really going a few months in
a while.
So it was really nice to see all the emails we got.
Yes, and we got nine categories during the camp, which were not ourselves.
So one round-up for it is that we need more Hacker Network and cybersecurity-related topics.
We could see that, well, some participants could need a bit of more network knowledge,
but it would also be nice to have some cybersecurity things.
We have previously been focused a lot on software-related stuff, but this is a growing field and we
have a lot of participants working in these fields and an interest in them.
So if you have some ideas, you can write it to the email listed here.
We were very much like so.
You can just write it in this moment or wait a few months.
But we were very much like the categories because they are really hard to make up.
Well, then we have the token game.
So in 2023, we had 60 participants.
This is really nice.
It's actually a few more than in 2021 and 2022.
We had 27 unique tokens.
Well, it's 10 more than the last time.
We did a little more preparation, so I think it's a nice amount.
I would personally like to prepare some more tokens ahead of Bornhack, but it is really
hard to come up with tokens also.
So if participants want to make some, you're most definitely welcome and write us an email
if you want.
So the average tokens found per participant were four.
It's less than 2021.
You were really playing that year.
But it is really nice that people who started playing kept playing a bit more than last
year.
That's really nice to see.
We have eight participants who found more than 10 tokens.
We don't really categorize them, but I would say that's like the players who keep playing
and attempting to find as many as they can.
And then we have two participants who found all 27 tokens.
So you can battle it out with whoever gets the prize, but you have to figure that out.
So what lessons did we learn this time?
We didn't have enough tokens that did not need a computer.
So a lot of the tokens require you to have some computing knowledge and also a computer
in your hand.
It would be nice to have some more tokens that are based on puzzles and color recognition
and similar things.
It has been heavily dependent on the token as a string, as a text string.
So naturally that's the way we went, that somehow you could get a token out of a piece
of string somewhere.
But it would be very nice to have some things where you could use pattern recognition also.
Yes, I have already said it, but we would benefit if we prepare more.
We are very low maintenance when we're in off events.
Most of the content happens actually at the event.
Not even during buildup, it's just when the event starts, this is when token hunt creation
starts.
We did some small things and it really helped out.
We had the space invader, for example, which already included the token before it was set
up.
So yeah, we have received a lot of nice input.
And yeah, we would like to also make tokens more accessible for players.
So this is a thing that we need to work on, is again the thing with the computers.
Not everybody is that good with computers necessarily, or may not be studying a computer
on a university and doing math all the time.
Again it's like we keep enjoying this, but magic just happens when other teams and other
participants just say, hey, I would like to make this token, can I make this token?
And then we say, yes, most definitely.
So it's really nice when the batch team or this year the phone operation center really
just said, yeah, I would like to make this thing, can I make this thing?
That came some really nice things out of it.
So I can show some more details on it.
We have the batch token.
So I'm not the one who created this.
I'm a bit unsure about the details on them, but let's get to it.
So on the batch, there is some letters you can read.
Well, this whole grid refers to a token.
So it is basically encoded, and you can, if you decode it, you can get Frank Miller, 18,
and the year.
So you can, let's see how many we have here, yes, a lot of things.
So that's a lot of references to this one-time pad of the paper from Frank Miller, and I
guess you had to go in and read it.
Or similar, to start finding the tokens, but yes, that was most definitely tokens on the
batch again this year.
Maybe we will have it again.
So the batch had NFC, right?
Yeah, I didn't make these slides, unfortunately, so I'm not sure what all these numbers mean,
but someone says hack the planet, and you could convert it to the token in the end.
I'm sorry, I don't know what the end result gives.
Maybe a participant could explain.
And then we have this one, it's also a bit of evil, that this batch gives you access
to the data needed to gain SSX access to a VM that contains some data that contains more
tokens.
Yeah, again, I have no idea what this means.
Yes, unfortunately, who knows what all these numbers mean, and yeah, you can find him after
this talk if you want, and get some explanations, but I'm sorry, I cannot.
So we also had some Dex phone numbers we could call.
You can call the number that corresponds to token game, and it will read out some nice
letters to you in phonetic alphabet.
You probably have to record it or call it at least three times or four times to get
it on the whole thing, but that's a token there.
You can also call the number token, and well, you will get a conversation from the movie
Hackers, where I crash overwrite the main character, request a number from a person,
and if you call that number, then you activate an omelette where you can then read the numbers.
So yeah, that's also GetLisa's numbers, and that's also one of the numbers mentioned in
the movie, one of the phone numbers, so you can get a little hint.
Thank you to Phone Operations Center, because that little piece of evil was actually very
nice.
I really loved calling in and testing different things.
Oh, yes, of course, that's conversion.
I guess that says token, and that says Lisa, and that says token hunt, or similar.
Apparently, that was an audio, sorry about that.
So we also, well, I also made some artwork together with the bat, and this, but it didn't
start as a token, but we made some artwork, and I thought, yeah, why not include a token?
This would be fun.
So that's a small thing that says Space Invader 1978, and if you mix those letters around,
you will get a token.
Very easy, but you should have to spot it.
Also credits to the nice person who took this picture, because I'm not that good at taking
images.
We also have a token in the sticker exchange.
Maybe you can see the QR code.
So there were two boxes of stickers in sticker exchange at the info desk, and you can scan
both of them.
The hint is ROT in the sticker chain, so that was the hint, and the QR code, one of the
QR codes had some letters, and then it said plus four or minus four, and the other one
did the same.
So you could do a rotation plus four, rotation minus four, and put them together.
I accidentally made one of them a little too long, so it had 33 characters, but yeah, small
correction much that you just removed the last letter of the token, but yeah.
So this was the token hunt.
Do we have any questions about some tokens?
Maybe I can answer some.
Yes.
This was definitely not all tokens, it was just a few selects.
So I saw that one of the tokens is the sequence of lights down the main path, is that right?
Yeah, I think so, yes.
I couldn't figure out any combination of lights that would make up 30 and make sense.
Also one of them is white.
Maybe the participant over here can answer the question.
So I guess the question is how are you supposed to do that one?
So the white one is actually blue, and you can see the film if you look, and there's
two towards the cabin, those count.
The first one here towards the bar doesn't count, and the two towards the food area doesn't
count either.
How can people sign up or help out with the game team?
You didn't really specify?
Well, you can sign up on the Bornhack website for the game team, and then drop us an email
and say, hey, I would very much like to be part of the token hunt.
Right now it's me and Dennis who are making the token hunt, but having an extra person
or two extra people being the, what is the English word for this, but being the caretakers
of the tokens would be very nice.
It would allow us to have more minds on it.
So yes, go to the Bornhack website, really, and sign up.
If I can ask, there was a hex in the slides between the presentations, it looked like
it was a valid token, but was it?
Which one, sorry?
There was a hex value in the slides between the presentations, so it was valid.
That was a hex encoded token in the info beamer, yes.
I couldn't figure out how to, I mean, I decoded it, but I couldn't get to a valid token.
So there's a very nice website called CyberChef, if you search on that.
I used it.
Okay, if you type it in correctly, hopefully you should get the token.
There was not that much else in that token than finding it and typing it and then converting
it over.
Yeah, I've done that, but maybe you can show me later.
And I also make mistakes sometimes, so it could be I also made some mistakes, but try
again and then ask me if it didn't work.
And then I will hop further to the next thing.
Well, we have the winner.
Oh, sorry, beyond the end of the talk.
Sorry about that.
I made mistakes there in the last second since I didn't look at the, yeah, sorry.
We have the pixel flute.
Well, this is a graph that's also showed up in the state of the network talk.
This is a monstrosity made by Asperger.
So it has an 80 gigabits, which I can explain a bit more about it.
But we had some participants pulling their own fibers.
We had Asperger himself making a pixel accelerator, takes a 10 megabit nick, like an old Bornhack
badge, and then do loop magic and apparently turns it up to 10 gigabits.
I don't know, like something with 15 kilometers of fiber.
It took a few days to get this up and running, but it seems like people were enjoying themselves.
So I hope this can keep showing up and more people would like to participate.
We have a little graph here.
Well, you can see it started, okay, the graph at least started Sunday.
I can hop over to this and say, well, the peak at the 95 percentile was at 31 gigabits
per second.
The switch is limited to 80 gigabits, so we'll get to near that, well, I guess we will get
a larger switch or something.
We averaged it, I cannot say that word, our average was 21 gigabits per second, and the
peak is like a weird thing to count, but at 43.
We have some new protocols, I misspelled that apparently, new protocols implemented.
You can find it on the link, it's the same link that hopefully all players saw.
And this year we had multiple 10 gigabit clients, yes, the pixel accelerator thing was great.
We streamed some movies on it, well, not me, but Max streamed some movies on it.
Labyrinth of a village pulls their own fiber and put in some QSFP plus optics.
They were, however, limited to 10 gigabits per machine, so it's not like bringing the
largest machine you can and the largest Nick, because I could just find a 100 gigabit Nick
and put it in if the switch couldn't take it.
So all clients are limited to 10 gigabits, and we were as well, but we just could sit
in our comfy tents instead of going all the way out next door to a machine.
Legacy IP addresses were again punished this year, you had to use IPv6 or else you would
get some transparency on your pixels.
You can see the little pony, perhaps, that was because I didn't update my client and
could not find the V6 version I made somewhere.
So yeah, it was transparent.
I just send enough pixels that it's not immediately, it is still visible.
So there was also a participant who attempted to create a distributed pixel flow client.
The goal was to play Doom on it, like with one controller and then multiple small machines
and stuff, the distributed distribution thing worked, but not playing Doom.
Maybe that will work next time.
So yes, I guess we can go to the game jam, and I will attempt to remember to announce
the winners of the token hunt.
Oh wait, I have to do this talk in English, then you understand.
We did the first ever bornhack game jam and it was a great success.
Thank you for everybody who played.
If you have your laptop out right now, you can go to pyjam.as slash game jam and see
all the submissions.
We had eight very beautiful games made by, I think, something like 15 nice hackers.
All of the games had to fit the theme switch, which was announced last Friday at 1800, and
then we had three days to complete the game.
The deadline was yesterday at 1800.
So since there's eight games, I just want to show you all of them because I couldn't
help myself.
This one, Killswitch by Vair, is really cool, it was made by a child, I think the first
time they ever made a game.
It's a switch, there's also some Nintendo switches and there's some networking switches
and there's a light switch, and you have to press one of three buttons and try and kill
the prisoner instead of the cops.
But it's very cool.
It plays in the web browser and it has a leaderboard.
Moral switch is gamifying the trolley problem.
Norske made a game which you're given a moral dilemma and you have to choose who you want
to kill.
The text was generated, I think, using a large language model and also images that were being
made on the fly so it would make at runtime new scenarios.
That's quite cool.
Somebody made a game called Past Parentheses 2.
I think they uploaded under the same name twice.
But this was Astron 1, Mast, Nielsen, Philip.
This is a game which had several different backend implementations.
So every time you die, you switch to a different backend which had its own complete different
state and different rules for the game.
Think there was backend written in Haskell and Go and Rust, right?
So that's kind of crazy.
So there's several different games.
There's one which is like a pixel art drawing game and this is a snake game.
This one turns out to be a lot of fun because there's an HTML injection in the username
field.
So you can just change the game on the fly.
Yeah, this website was looking really crazy last night because of the HTML injection.
That was cool.
Dowser made a game called Save the Network which is about defending a network switch.
You have all of these different ports.
Some of them, they turn red while they're being hacked.
So you have to be quick and click it.
So it's kind of like a whack-a-mole game.
This is super difficult.
But it has nice audio and stuff also.
Another cool game, Design Nuda, Nicolas made a game called Shield Switch in which it's
sort of like an asteroids type game where there's different types of asteroids.
It's difficult to see right now but these are like the red ones.
And then you switch between being in the red state or the blue state so you can phase through
different kinds of asteroids depending on what color it is.
That's quite cool.
Nicolas, who made this game, also composed an original soundtrack for this game and just
because he had more time and wanted to, he also made an original soundtrack for this
game.
So that's super cool.
This Sliding Snake is a terminal-based game in which you control a snake and you try and
avoid these lines of trees.
I think this was originally made to run on a receipt printer.
That's great.
This was my game.
It's like a physics-based game where you're the snake inside of your network switch because
you know the snake inside the network switch, right?
You pick up packets and you try and drop them in the right place and you try not to switch
the packets wrong.
Samuel made a game called Switch Off the Music.
This is a mobile phone game which is GPS-based, right?
So the plot is that it's late and all the hackers are making a lot of noise and you
have to go and find the parties and then tell them to turn off the music.
This game will get your heart rate up like you're sprinting around the field and trying
to turn off the music before you lose your patience.
That's a lot of fun.
All right.
So those were the games.
We had a rating system so it works like this.
Anybody who submitted a game could rate the other games.
We had a little bit less than 24 hours to play and rate all of them.
These are the categories.
There's an overall score that determines the winner of the game jam totally.
And then these are the aspects of creativity and aesthetics, how well it fit the theme
of Switch and how fun the gameplay was.
So let's do the winner's announcement for each of these categories.
The aesthetic winner is...
Mortal Switch!
The creativity winner is, I'm sure you're not surprised about this, Switch Off the Music!
The gameplay winner is Shield Switch!
And the theme winner is...
Mortal Switch!
Again!
All right can I have a drum roll for the total winner?
The winner of the Born Hack Game Jam 2023 is Shield Switch!
But really so much thanks to everybody who played.
It's been a lot of fun making games with you and we're definitely going to do this again
next year.
So there's a theme for the game jam which was Switch this year.
I'd really like to hear suggestions for a theme for next year.
The game jam Lulu Dare does this thing of submitting a bunch of different themes and then we vote
about it.
I think we should do that next year.
So send an email to the game team or send a message to me or just come find me if you
have a good idea for a theme.
Also I want to make it so that I don't know the theme in advance because that would be
more fun for me.
Yeah, but that's it for game jam.
Thanks for playing!
As you can see he's a bit more energetic than I am.
So yes, now the token hunt winner is...
Well, yeah, you have to play Rock, Paper, Scissors but it's Emilia and Sebastian.
You can decide amongst yourselves what you want to play Rock, Paper, Scissors.
Okay, I guess we can fight for a year about that one.
So yes, thank you so much for visiting this talk.
See you next year!
Are there any questions?
Thank you for the great state of the game.
Let's give him a round of applause.