The next speaker we have is me, who will talk about Funion, a talk client in Alexia.
Let's give him a hand.
Okay.
So, hello and welcome to my talk about Funion.
Since I'm a talk client, I've written in Alexia in order to do, yeah, to learn tour and to
learn Alexia, but I will talk about this very soon.
And I want to ask a few questions to the audience.
Who of you is quite familiar with the tour protocol?
I mean, just the basics in the sense of, you know, what a circuit is, what a connection
is, what a stream is, and like, you know, the EFF graphics, okay, nice.
And who of you has used Erlang or Alexia?
Oh, that's quite a high amount.
I think it gets higher the more north you go in Europe, but yeah, nice.
So yeah, a few things about me.
I'm Emil, I go by any pronouns.
I've graduated high school this summer, and I'm going to study pure mathematics and computer
science beginning in October.
I contribute to open source projects since 2018.
Some of them include curl, Rosenpass, there are some others as well.
And I've been doing tours since October of last year.
And yeah, I'm also available on the Fediverse and GitHub.
So first of all, I have to do some acknowledgments at first.
I would really like to thank Alex.
He was always helping me since day one.
I mean, I've posted this on my Mastodon account, and he immediately supported me there and
was always there to answer questions.
So many thanks to you.
And then also many thanks to the Teller authors.
For those of you who don't know what Teller is, Teller is an implementation of tour done
in Erlang.
And this also helped me a lot because I was required to use the Erlang crypto library.
And it definitely had some weird things in it.
And looking at the Teller source could definitely help me there.
And I also have to thank the people who are in the TourDev IRC channel on OFTC, most notably
Nick Mathiessen, Roger Dingledine, Ian Jackson, Trinity Pointard, and others.
It's in no particular order.
Yeah, so what have I actually done?
I've written a tour client in Elixir.
It's an onion proxy.
It's not a relay.
It's like a thing you actually use to connect to the tour network on your computer.
It implements only the core, only like the bare bones of the tour protocol.
That is the tour spec.txt document and the search spec.txt document found in the tour
specification repository.
And it is more of an educational thing rather than something that people, if you really
depend on privacy, you probably should not use that.
And it still lacks many features such as directory support, hidden services, a SOX proxy, support
to be a relay, and so on.
And it probably also suffers from side channel attacks because I didn't pay that much attention
to it as I was just trying to get a tour client working.
And yeah, but hackers are very welcome.
If you would like to do to implement some of these things or something completely else,
just come to me and I will invite you to a martyr for sure.
Yeah, so what was my motivation behind that?
So as I've said, I've graduated from high school and in Germany it generally works like
that.
School ends in March and the finals are in April.
So you have like a month free in order to prepare yourself for the exams.
But let's be honest, you don't use a month for that, you use like the night before the
exam for that.
So yeah, you could do something productive, party all the time, or learn for the finals.
I have done both of it and this like on the day before.
So yeah, it was a good time, a time killer as well.
Yeah, my background, it's like I've been doing low-level C development and Rust development
for like three years.
So I was more like a low-level guy and had no prior experience with Elixir and functional
programming in general.
And I began contributing to ARTI, which is TOR's re-implementation in Rust in the autumn
of last year.
And it got me hooked.
I was really fascinated by the protocol itself.
But then earlier this year, I saw the computer file video in Erlang and I got really amazed
by that.
It was an eye-opening experience, but I will come to this very, very soon.
And because I had so much free time, I simply decided, okay, I'm going to learn Elixir,
functional programming, and TOR with this project.
And this is what came out in the end.
So yeah, I will talk a little bit about Elixir and Erlang, what those technologies are, and
because they have quite some differences from like the average programming language.
So Elixir and Erlang are functional programming languages that both compile to the same virtual
machine in bytecode.
It's quite similar to Java and Kotlin and to JVM respectively.
Because of that, Erlang libraries can also be used from inside Elixir and vice versa.
And it's an extremely fault-tolerant language.
It has like the slogan, write once, run forever.
And it emphasizes process separation and isolation.
And like as a real open BSD diehard in my youth, this gave me really, really wet dreams.
And I just got amazed by that concept in general.
And Erlang and Elixir, the entire ecosystem around it, it's like the first time IPC is
actually easy and doable.
And I really do not want to use Unix IPC again after I've did Elixir for the first time.
And in my opinion, it's also one of the most underrated technologies that are out there.
So especially in network-facing applications, there's like this traditional approach.
The traditional approach usually works like there's one monolithic process, and it handles
multiple connections through either an event loop or as a chrony.
Both of the solutions have the downsides and pitfalls.
An event loop destroys the linear execution flow of a program, whereas as a chrony, in
my opinion, is like the helpers of programming.
Because once it's inside your project, you can almost never get it out.
I mean, everyone who has done ASIC and Rust probably knows what I'm talking about.
And it adds like lots of craft.
So you might ask, why don't you just use threads for handling multiple connections?
I mean, that's actually what many beginners do, because it sounds like the most intuitive.
But there are definitely some downsides to it.
Most notably, on modern Linux systems, a thread takes up to eight, takes eight megabytes stack
at least.
And this becomes a problem.
It's OK if you handle like 10 connections, but it becomes a real problem if you have
like 10,000 connections, because you quickly run out of memory then.
However, there are some notable exceptions, most notably OpenSSH and Postgres who spawn
a new process for every authenticated connection.
So they are not vulnerable to denial of service attacks that much, because you have to be
authenticated before it forks.
But the Elixir process is quite different.
Actually, Elixir does it one process per connection.
I will tell what the difference about a thread and a process is in a second.
But they are not real OS processors, so they do not take like an eight megabyte stack for
each thing.
They offer isolation, and they make the code, in my opinion, much easier to understand.
And this isolation leads to, in my opinion, a much bigger security benefit.
So you might be wondering, isn't that like Go routines?
I mean, they are also like very cheap and solar.
That's kind of true.
They are very similar.
From an OS perspective, they are very similar implemented.
But the major difference is that Go routines are more conceptualized as threads, whereas
Elixir processes are, like the name suggests, more like processors.
The difference is that a thread can access all resources inside a process, whereas a
process itself is its own isolated unit that exists and run on its own.
This is also the reason why in multi-thread applications, you often have to deal with
things like mutexes and those kind of lock mechanisms.
You do not have that when you use processes, at least.
You sometimes do have that as well, but it's something different then.
And yeah, it has an extreme security benefit because, like, if one process gets taken over
by an attacker, the impact they can do is much less significant.
So yeah, let's look at my project from, like, 10,000 feet.
I've developed it using Elixir 1.15.
It supports the link protocol version 4 of the top protocol only because it's like not...
I was a bit too lazy to implement version 5 because it had, like, a feature.
Yeah, I wasn't yet motivated to do that.
And version 3, well, the difference between version 3 and version 4 is, like, very minimal.
And version 1 and 2 are, like, really, really old, really legacy.
I'm not even sure if Ctor still supports them.
And yeah, the code is pretty good documented, in my opinion.
It has a consistent type spec almost all over the place.
And its design is also very modular.
I got inspired by Arty.
So there are, like, four modules right now, Tor cell, which handles, like, the cells as
Elixir data structures.
Tor cert, which handles the elliptic curve certificates, which is a custom Tor certificate
format.
Then there's Tor crypto, which does, like, the handshakes and other things related to
cryptography.
And then there's also the Tor proto module, which is, like, the heart of the entire thing.
But the most complexity really lies within the Tor cell and the Tor proto module.
So let's take a look at the Tor cell thing.
It implements the cells, which are Tor's basic unit of communication.
All traffic that is sent throughout the Tor socket is done in cells.
And the parsing takes place with pattern matching, which is, like, a really cool thing that's
supported by Erling and Elixir.
It basically allows you to parse a protocol within the language.
And not many languages offer that as well.
A cell has three fields, a Cirque ID, which is like a 32-bit integer, which indicates
to which circuit this thing belongs.
Then there's the command field, which is an atom containing what the cell means, like
the semantic value of it.
And the payload is dependent on the command.
And it contains a decoded payload that is actually, yeah, viable data then.
This module, however, performs no cryptography.
This is done outside of it.
It doesn't even validate the certs and those kind of things.
It just parsed them into plain, boring Elixir data structures to be operated on later on.
So these are the connection cells, but Tor also has relay cells.
They are the actual cells that use the onion routing principle.
That is, they are encrypted, and a layer gets removed at every hop, or a layer gets added
at every hop if it's going backward.
The decrypted relay cells are implemented in the TorCell.RelayCell data structure.
And once they are encrypted, their ciphertext goes into a TorCell.Relay data structure.
And the decrypted one has three fields, command, which is also an atom, the stream ID, which
is a 16-bit integer indicating to which stream this belongs, and then there's the data containing
the decoded data eventually.
It has two public functions, decrypt and encrypt.
Decrypt takes an onion skin, an array of stream cipher keys for the backward direction, and
a digist, and speaking more concrete, the backward digist, which is used to know if
a cell has been fully decrypted, and it returns a tuple containing a Boolean.
If the Boolean is true, the cell has been fully decrypted.
If it's false, there are still onion skins left.
The second item is either the decoded TorCell.RelayCell, or it's an onion skin which is still ciphertext
but with a certain amount of onion skins removed from it.
And the last one is the updated backward digist.
With encrypt, it's quite similar.
You pass in the plaintext RelayCell, then an array of forward symmetric cipher keys,
symmetric stream cipher keys, and the forward digist.
What you get in return is the onion skin of it and the forward digist, and then you can
place the onion skin into the encrypted cell and send it over the wire.
Then there's also the TorCryptoModule, which performs various cryptographic operations
that are simply required by Tor, most notably the Antor handshake, which is used for circuit,
for establishing circuits.
It also offers a small abstraction about the digist implementation, and it also implements
the encryption and decryption of onion skins.
I've called them onion streams because they are stream cipher, and so they have a state.
And it's a pretty small module.
It's like only 150 lines of code or something.
But the real stuff is going on in the TorProtomodule, which implements the actual Tor protocol.
It's implemented using GenServer and a client API.
And it is highly process-oriented.
That is, there is a separation of resource as much as possible, which you can see in
the next slide.
This is an average session using that.
So there are multiple connection processes.
Each connection has a satellite process and also multiple circuits.
And each circuit then also has several streams, and they communicate in a linear fashion.
So it's not that the connection communicates with a stream, but when the connection communicates
with a stream, it passes through the circuit.
So it just talks to the parent in such a kind of fashion.
Yeah, here you can see it in a more smaller version if the previous slide was a bit overwhelming.
And what's a bit notable is that all of these processes, except the stream process, have
a thing called epiphyphos.
The thing is that cells have to be enqueued for processes so they can request them and
obtain them from their parent respectively.
And epiphyphos is effectively just a map where the keys are the process identifiers and the
values are phyphos.
And so we are going to have a look at the first process now, which is the connection
process.
So this is the connection of the top protocol, and it's responsible for spawning the circuit
processes through a call I've called create.
It also spawns a single satellite process that handles the raw TLS circuit.
Why this has to be done, I will explain that in a second.
And it gets pulled by the satellite process every time a new cell arrives.
And those cells are then either processed by the connection if the circuit ID is zero
or are redirected to the appropriate circuits if their circuit ID is not zero respectively.
And if that's the case, it pulls the appropriate circuits and it has like, and that's the state
of it.
So there's the circuits map that is like simply a mapping of the circuit IDs with their accompanying
pits.
Then there's the phyphos, which contain the enqueued not yet fetched cells for all of
the circuits.
Then there's the router field, which just stores the only router we are connected to.
And then there's also the satellite process.
And then there's also the satellite field that contains the pit of the satellite process.
So yeah, and generally the workflow of it works like that.
The satellite process pulls the connection process and the connection process talks to
the satellite process by sending either the queue messages or when it sends a dequeue,
it gets a cell that's in the phyfo.
And if you send cell, it simply sends a cell outside of it.
And with the circuit, it's quite similar.
The connection pulls the circuit and the circuit either dequeues, sends a cell or informs the
parent that it's going to die now.
So yeah, let's talk about the satellite process a bit now.
It creates and manages the raw TLS socket and it works on cell level.
So the serialization and deserialization of cells happens there, process just sends cells
there and they do everything that is left to do then.
It pulls the parent connection process whenever a cell has been decoded and enqueued successfully
and the state consists of the following field.
First and foremost, a buffer because it receives the raw TCP TLS data.
There might be data that cannot be fully passed yet because there's not yet enough data to
construct a full cell from it.
Then there's also the connection, which is the pit of the connection process.
Then there's the FIFOs.
In fact, it could be called just FIFO.
The plural is a bit misleading here and it contains the enqueued cells for the connection.
Then there's the socket field, which just contains the actual TLS socket.
And then there's the virginity boolean.
This has just one purpose.
Usually until a connection until the first version cell has been received, all circuit
ID fields are two byte integers instead of four byte integers because of backward compatibility.
And once the first version cell has arrived from the responder, it will set this thing
to false.
So the circuit ID will then be passed with four byte integers from there on.
And yeah, you might be asking why is there a satellite?
I mean, the idea of a separate process just for handling the TLS connection may sound
a bit unintuitive.
And you may be wondering why not do that in the connection process directly.
But there are several reasons for that.
Most notably, the connection process has to receive data while it's currently already
processing a request.
In other languages, you would simply call a receive thing, which will block until the
data arrives.
Unfortunately, that's not the Elixir way to do it because in Elixir, you do not obtain
the data from the socket by using a receive or something like that.
Instead, the raw data gets delivered to the process mailbox.
And I would have to do a manual receive then, like the Erlang Elixir receive keyword.
And this is, I wouldn't say it's discouraged, but it's discouraged in the way I'm doing
it because I'm using GenServer.
And the entire purpose of GenServer is to get rid of these receive statements.
So that would be a bit counterintuitive.
And beside this, it also offers the great advantage that the TLS socket is in a separate
process, which is very good because the TLS socket also contains cryptographic data, which
is nice if it's separated in its own thing.
So yeah, then there are also the circuit processes.
They obviously manage a circuit of the top protocol.
And what's really cool about it is that they are the only process that have the real cryptographic
keys like the shared secret and the other keys derived from that.
So if the other processes get pawned, it's not as critical as if that one would get pawned
because that's the one holding the keys.
And it spawns the stream processes, which are then the actual TCP streams.
We will talk about that very soon either.
And it gets pulled by the connection process every time a cell for that circuit has arrived.
And if it receives that cell, it does some things with it.
Most notably, if it's a relay cell, it performs a decryption, encryption there.
And if the decrypted relay cell happens to be associated with a stream that's open, it
will do the same that the connection does with the circuit.
It will pull the stream and enqueue that cell for it.
And yeah, the state consists of obviously the circuit ID that was assigned to it by
the connection.
Then it contains the pit of the appropriate connection.
And it also contains the FIFOs field to store the enqueued cells.
Then there's also the hops array, which is an array of all hops the circuit is extended
to, including the cryptographic keys.
They are also stored inside that.
And last but not least, there's also a map of all stream IDs with their appropriate stream
processes.
And here you can see how it works in combination with the connection stream processes.
So the connection process pulls whenever a new cell arrives, the circuit decues it.
And similar, it goes with the stream.
The circuit pulls the stream if new data has arrived.
And the stream then sends these messages, like it either decues a cell from it, it sends
a cell, or it notifies the circuits that the stream is now going to die.
What's quite interesting is that the send cell contains like the plaintext cell, and
the encryption, like I said, takes place here.
So the stream doesn't know anything about the cryptographic keys, which is really nice
in my opinion.
And yeah, it manages a stream.
So yeah, I've talked about the stream processes quite a bit.
So what are they actually?
They manage a stream of the top protocol that is an actual TCP connection.
During the creation, it accepts a closure that handles the received data, which is like
an amazing thing.
My first idea for that design was to simply include a pit rather than a closure.
And the pit would then like handle incoming traffic there.
But that's actually not that good idea, because I would have to define a message format for
it and those kind of things.
But a closure gives you like unlimited power.
It's much cooler because a closure can also lose the local scope and those kind of things.
And it gets pulled by the circuit if an appropriate stream relay cell has arrived.
And like I've said, no encryption and decryption is performed there.
And it accepts data from external processes using the client API.
So yeah, how does the client API actually work in that sense?
I've talked about it quite a bit.
So first and foremost, a connection is created.
Afterwards, a circuit is created on that connection, presumably more circuits as well.
The circuit is extended two times to have like a three hopped circuit because that's
what Tor likes to do.
Then it creates a stream with providing a closure.
I already said that this offers like unlimited power.
Then optionally data can be sent to the TCP stream.
And once it's done, you terminate the stream, you terminate the circuit and you terminate
the connection.
However, this is done recursively.
Like if you forget these things and just terminate the connection, the connection will recursively
terminate the circuits, which will terminate all associated streams.
So what are the upcoming features?
What are my plans for this project?
Like I've said, it was more a thing to learn Elixir and to learn Tor a bit.
I definitely accomplished the first thing.
I feel pretty confident with Elixir now.
But with Tor, it's like, it's a Sisyphus task.
You know, Tor is like, there's so much things you can learn about it and it's still a very
open field of research.
But I hope I can still contribute to Tor and do some stuff there because it's a really
amazing project and it's really interesting as well.
Yeah, currently we have a priority to implement the directory protocol as well as the path
protocol because right now all routers are hard coded when you want to connect to them,
which is not very nice, especially because you like have to redo this like every three
weeks when the keys expire.
Even services would also be nice, but I think that this would be really hard.
But maybe I have the time.
We will see.
And relay support is not planned right now, but I'm not against this, but it's simply
not on my priority list either.
But as I've said, I'm starting to go to university very soon and I do not know how much free
time I will have then.
So I'm not sure how the project will continue.
And the development takes place in our fossil repository.
We also have a GitHub mirror available here.
And pull requests and issues are more than welcome.
So while I've developed this, there were also many pitfalls I've encountered.
And I'm especially talking to you, future implementer of another Tor specification.
I think you owe me a beer, but fortunately those pitfalls I've encountered you should
not encounter them because I've submitted quite a few patches to the specification in
order to fix them, hopefully.
So what were the greatest pitfalls in an ascending order?
First and foremost, circuit IDs need to have a most significant byte of one.
I forgot that because I didn't read the spec specification that carefully, but there was
also I wouldn't call it a mistake in the specification, but the specification wasn't that clear that
this is like a really hard must requirement.
It just said that it's done, but it doesn't say it must be done.
I fixed that because otherwise nothing will work.
And it took me like an afternoon to figure that out.
I could have done that much easier if I had read it properly or if it would have been
a must statement.
Another pitfall was that circuit extensions have to be done in a relay early cell and
not in a relay cell.
This is the design for that or the purpose behind that design decision is that you simply
do not extend the circuits indefinitely with relay early cells.
That's like a hard limit.
I think it's something like eight, so once there are more like eight relay early cells
received from that connection, everything will fail.
And this was also only slightly mentioned in the spec.
If I had read it a bit more carefully, I think I wouldn't have had that problem.
It was a bit frustrating, but it eventually worked out because the creation of a circuit
worked, but the extension didn't work.
And I was like, well, am I doing the hand check wrong?
I was just looking into the hand check because it worked like the first time, but not the
other times.
But in fact, it turned out to be a much different problem than I initially assumed.
So then there's like the number two, which is I definitely thought way too complicated
in the digits verification.
Everyone who has implemented Tor on their own knows what I'm talking about.
The digits verification is something like, if the digits is verified, if it's valid,
a relay cell has reached the end and it's fully decoded now.
And I was thinking way too complicated about it because relay cells contain a field that's
called digits, which is four byte long.
And the digits is like all relay cells that have been sent so far.
However, the digits field has to be set to zero because you cannot include the digits
if it hasn't been computed yet.
And I thought like, okay, the zero digits is like only a temporary thing.
And then like the real digits that was the temporary thing gets sent into the real digits.
I was thinking way too complicated.
You can still see my mistakes in the Git logs.
But I'm very proud that I hopefully fixed that for you because I've written an entire
section on Tor specification providing a pseudo code.
So hopefully this doesn't happen again.
And the last thing, which was like definitely one of the most frustrating experiences in
my life, was realizing that Tor, or not realizing that Tor uses a symmetric stream cipher for
the onion skins.
I assumed that it would use a block cipher for whatever reason.
I'm not quite sure why.
And I mean, thinking about this a bit further, it makes like no sense because the onion skins
are 509 byte long and no sane block cipher would return such an odd value.
But it took me a long time to figure it out.
And when I eventually figured out, I was just like, okay, it's AES 128 CTR, okay, not sure
what the CTR means, just ignore it, just still continue using the block cipher functions,
which eventually resulted in that I didn't kept a state at all.
And this result in the really nasty bug that the first encryption always worked, but all
letter ones failed because I always reinitialized the state for every encryption.
And this was so hard to figure out.
And when I eventually figured it out, I was really, really mad because everyone who has
done functional programming knows that when you have a state, it taints throughout the
code base.
And I didn't design it with that state design in mind at first place.
So I had to redesign quite a bit, although it wasn't that bad because the Erlang crypto
stream cipher module is not functional.
It has side effects, which is a bit ugly, but in that case, I had luck and misfortune
or fortune and misfortune.
Yeah, so thank you, Erlang guys, I'm not sure.
Yeah.
And you are welcome for these things, future tour implementer.
I won't be the last one.
So now I'm going to do a quick presentation of a quick demonstration of what I have done.
Yeah, let me move that terminal window right over there.
I hope this works now.
Oh, no, that's the wrong directory.
So, sorry, I can't mirror the screens right now.
Use TMSL screen and then open the session twice.
That's a good idea.
How do I attach to that session from elsewhere?
Thank you.
My neck is thanking me for that.
What was it?
Tmax space A enter.
Thank you.
What do you mean?
Oh, okay.
Yeah, sure, makes sense.
Okay, so I'm focused.
Oh, I'm just making it a bit.
Okay, now, that should it be.
And now let me get back to the main screen.
So, yeah.
So, dang it, it has no...
Can I open Emacs here?
There was a way to open Emacs without X11.
Thank you.
Okay, so, yeah, this is much better.
So, this is basically a list of three onion routers we are going to connect to now.
They all contain the nickname, the identity, which is like the fingerprint of the RSA identity key,
then it obviously contains the IP, the port on which it's running,
and then it contains some cryptographic keys, most notably the RSA identity key,
the ED25519 identity key, the elliptical signing key, and also the X25519 enter key,
which is used for the handshake.
And I've extracted them manually from the Tor directory just now, like two hours ago.
So, how do we use this thing?
First, we start a connection by doing...
By calling this function, connection-initiator-start-link,
and then provide the guard node, the formation of the guard node.
I will do a short sleep here so you can see that it's working.
If I'm splitting the Emacs...
Okay, you see this as well now? Yeah, nice.
If I run it, you now should see that quite a few debug statements.
So, you see it created a TLS connection, it created a satellite process,
sent a version cell, received a version cell, decided to use that link protocol version,
validated the certificates, sent a net info cell, and in general finished the handshake.
So, we just created the connection, and now we want to create a circuit on it.
How do we do that? Very easy.
We also use a function, tor-proto.connection.initiator.create,
and just provide the connection process.
And now we can see, when we run it again...
Oh, you can't really see that. Oh, you can? You can now.
Yeah, you can see that now, after establishing the connection, it sends a circuit handshake,
it receives a reply, the circuit handshake is valid, there's a cryptographic function inside it to validate it,
and then it's finished, and then it was finally created.
But that's not still that nice because, you know, we just have it with one hop, and we need to extend it quite a bit.
So, let's do that.
We use tor-proto.circuit.initiator.extend, and then we provide the circuit and the hop we are extending to.
I'm doing this with both of them, so it gets directly extended to the exit node, which in that case is vinculum-gate.
And then, when that's done, we should see...
Okay, so it should focus, yeah.
We can see that it now gets extended to Adrian, and last but not least, it gets extended to vinculum-gate,
doing the handshake all over again, but with different cryptographic keys for sure then.
And now we want to create a stream because we actually want to send some data.
And what would be cooler than, like, fetch our IPs through Tor, so I can show you that it actually works.
We do that by also using a function in the circuit module that is connect.
What a surprise.
And in it, we provide...
What was it? It was the circuit.
It was the host name.
Let's do ifconfig.me.
Let's use port 80, and then we need to provide a closure.
We will write that closure now.
It's basically just a function with one parameter.
And here we just do, well, I like to just log it.
Just do an info statement with the data, and yeah.
And when we run that, we should see that we have forgot something.
Yes, this 2 doesn't belong there.
And we see that nothing happens afterwards, except that it connects now to something.
Because, well, we are not sending data right now, so it doesn't receive an HTTP request.
The endpoint, which we will do now.
Then we simply use topproto.dream.initiator.senddata alongside the stream.
And then the data, we simply do an HTTP 1.1 request.
ifconfig.me backslash r backslash n backslash r backslash n.
Long live these MS-DOS line endings.
Everyone loves them.
And now we should see that we get a reply.
And we see that our IP is 776820.2017, which happens to be exactly this IP here.
And I forgot a very important thing to clean it up.
We do that by simply doing, by simply terminating the connection, because the connection, like I said, will then terminate everything else recursively.
This is done by just stopping it, providing the connection.
And when we do it, we should see like some destroy things.
Okay, that shouldn't have happened.
I think maybe it's a bit busy right now, the exit node.
Or it could be an async issue.
Maybe try that.
Yeah, okay, it was an async thing.
And now we can see that it successfully terminates all streams, then destroys the circuit.
Then it says, well, I've terminated all circuits.
The TLS connection gets closed, and finally everything was properly closed.
So yeah, I now have a thank you slide, but I'm too busy, or I do not want to start the presentation all over again.
I'm too lazy for that.
So thank you.
Thank you.
Are there any questions?
So you said you shouldn't use this at this stage.
And I know that ARTI is also designed to be used as a library by other programs.
But of course, your implementation is on the Beam virtual machine.
So do you think eventually the library will be production ready so that programs on the Beam VM can also use the Tor protocol?
Yes and no.
I would really hope that this could work eventually.
I mean, I'm designing it as a library after all.
I'm documenting it.
And if it's all a matter of time, like if I have the time and motivation, it will eventually be that case.
But I can't know that because I do not know the future.
And the no part is because of the following.
Many people often claim that you should only write cryptographic applications in like C or Rust,
because they are like the only commonly used programming languages that allow you to control everything.
Like in C and Rust, if you really want to, you can control each and every CPU instruction.
You have full control over the memory, which is a critical part in avoiding side channel attacks.
Most notably, the probably most famous example is overwriting memory with zeros like private keys once you are done with using them.
And this is, for example, a thing that's impossible or really, really hard to do in Go right now.
And yeah, so I would hope it would be productive ready one day.
But of course, you always have the side channel issue that you simply have because it's a high level language.
Hello.
Hi.
Are there any privacy implications of using a nonstandard client like the version cells?
Do they leak anything?
OK.
I mean, if you use that client, like if that client becomes really widespread in this current stage,
it will become known that you are not using the official tool implementation.
So people will know that you use a different tool implementation, which already reduces the privacy quite a bit because in an anonymity network,
it's important that all peers look similar or even the same.
So this is definitely a privacy implication, but it's not a thing that's it's possible to fix that.
I mean, like I've said, I also I also haven't implemented all things of the tool specs.
So there are quite some differences in features that can be spotted compared to the official tool implementation.
And yeah, and on the other side, you also have like downside.
This is a project done by me.
I'm the only one who has probably reviewed the code yet.
And with tour, you have like thousands of eyes have already seen that.
And it's a thing that I can simply not offer because it hasn't ordered that much yet.
Thank you for being here, Emil.
Let's give him a round of applause.