You can also find information on how an instant exchange operates.
There's some information.
There's a very high level and doesn't really explain too much.
And then there's also the administration of talking to ripe and what objects do you need
and how do you get IP addresses and stuff like that.
That's many policies included.
And yes, I wrote everything as an acronym group because that's pretty much what it is.
So LabX is a community-run instant exchange.
We made this because I like BGP and network routing.
And I would like to play more with it.
So in LaboSat we have a facility called LabiColor.
We will get more into that at some point.
But we offer a service called a route server.
Again, I will get more into it.
What that is, we can assist you in how should you talk to a local internet registry to get
an AS number and IP addresses.
You can actually start looking into real network routing stuff and not just play with it in
a virtual machine.
You can do BGP stuff, security and research and build on what is RPKI and things like
this.
Also, yes, I wrote 9KMTU.
We don't have that currently but we will soon set it up to 9KMTU.
It's currently 1,500 like most.
So what is an internet exchange?
Well, it's a VLAN on a little switch and then some networks are connected to it.
Well, that doesn't really say much.
So let me explain what is the internet.
First, this is how we do internet routing or network routing.
We have some prefixes.
You find a facility that would like to host you.
That includes some power and cooling and stuff like that.
You install your machines.
You set up a routing daemon.
It could be like BERT if you use Linux or other things.
Then you have some peers that are other network operators.
And you will PO them to get their content.
And then you also need a transit uplink, which is how do you, well, now you're in facility
with, and you can connect with the other people in that facility, but how do you connect with
the rest of the world?
We're not Copenhagen, it doesn't contain the whole internet.
So you need a transit that says we will like to transport the traffic from your network
or to the station.
And profit, I guess.
So let's set a scenario.
You are an ISP.
You are currently located in Hygge Damm, coincidentally where we are.
And an eyeball ISP is that we have some customers with eyeballs.
They consume content that could be watching their favorite series or watching the news
or somehow get content.
You don't host servers necessarily.
So for you to be able to have to say, like, when a customer wants to connect to another
provider to get content, you need some IP addresses.
That is, well, hopefully most of you know, some is like an address, like postal address
where do the thing need to go?
You also need that for your servers.
Then you need housing and fiber stuff.
I won't go into the fiber stuff.
I don't dig too much into layer one things, only layer three in this case.
So how does the network connect with other networks?
You probably cannot see my mouse.
So we have in the left, it's called, well, in this case, called ACME.
This is one network provider.
What if ACME is ACME 1 and ACME 2 are not located in the same city and the same facility?
Well, in our lovely picture here, we have two transit providers that need to go through
first.
So there's Comcast and there's GDT, which are some providers in the world that exist.
And then we can go into ACME number two.
That could be where all the nice series are hosted or similar.
It could also be that what if ACME 1 and 2 are located in the same city, they're just
not really connected.
And it would be perhaps too expensive to connect them.
So let's look at what is an autonomous system.
It says AS1 and AS2 here.
Something, something, something.
In other words, so we have a lovely RFC that describes AS as a connected group of one or
more prefixes run by one or more network operators, which has a single and clearly defined routing
policy.
I can explain a tiny bit more on that.
But it is the most clear explanation I have found until now.
So that's why it's here.
So an AS is an organization, as I said.
And we have, we use what we call AS numbers or ASMs to identify an organization that could
be your friends in the other side of the facility.
And they have some, well, you and the other ASs have some prefixes allocated to them so
you know where the content should go or the traffic should go.
So the routing policy, well, it's found in databases, regional internet database like
RAPES database.
These routing policies say something like I have authorized to use these IP prefixes
and they should, so now see IP prefixes at all traffic to these prefixes should be distant
to me.
And it could also be that you have some customers that may be a little bit more fancy with their
networking.
And they would also like to announce through you, so you are that transit.
And that could be some business customers, for example, or in our case, Labitat or me
where Labitat is my optic.
I have included a lot of places, links to things that can be read more on since I found
these useful, I have left them in.
So peering and transit.
Well, first peering is that we agree it's free to both of us.
There is some optics, fibers included and things like cross connect where you have to
like you are looking at a data center and you would like to connect to the other side
of the data center.
And it takes a bit of money for that.
It costs usually some X amount per month.
We only send traffic to each other.
That is totally fine.
As long as we don't tip the balance where I send a lot of traffic to you and you don't
send that much traffic to me.
But it's fine.
We peer with a lot of people.
Then we also have transit.
So transit is where it costs per megabit.
And this I will transport traffic from you to other networks.
As I always said, if you want to go to the other side of the globe, you perhaps don't
have the funds to lay a cable over the Atlantic or something similar.
So someone has done that for you and you would just pay them.
Well, what is the instant exchange then?
We keep local traffic local.
We avoid what we call the trombone effect.
This is an image of the United States, San Francisco, New York and Los Angeles.
So what would be the shortest path between San Francisco and Los Angeles?
Clearly not New York at least.
That can sometimes happen due to some characteristics with our network routing.
You look at the shortest path, for example, in many, many cases, and also other things.
But it could be that your transit just didn't have a direct connection between San Francisco
and Los Angeles.
So you would need to go over New York.
So we have the instant exchange to avoid these kind of things.
It also gives lower latency because, again, we keep local traffic local.
It's easier to interconnect with other networks.
So what if we are two small providers and we don't necessarily have the need to connect
to each other?
Why should we pay transit when we are located in the same facility?
We can't justify paying the fees to have this cross-connect active and similar things.
So when you have the internet exchange, it makes things a bit easier when you're local.
So here is a very simplified quality of an internet exchange point.
Well, there are four providers of some kind.
They all connect with one link into a meet me room, as we call it.
And with this, we now, instead of everybody connecting to each other, with I have one
cable to you, you have one cable to you, I have one cable to you, we just have one cable
in and then we get the traffic via that cable.
That could be like a larger cable, for example.
So what I showed here is, yes, we do have the meet me room, but in an internet exchange,
we also can go from what we call bilateral to multilateral peering.
And it is from many to many to one to many.
As the image also shows, we have the route server.
And again, I'm just explaining this because it was not that easy for me in the first five
hours to understand why the fuck do we need a route server.
It was not really clear.
But now it's more clear for me, at least.
So the control plane traffic is now aggregated to the route server.
Don't necessarily aggregate all the data plane traffic, but at least the control traffic.
It kind of looks like this.
So we need less maintenance, we need less points, like less configurations that you
can screw up with.
If I'm already connected to a route server and we have some new clients that comes to
our IXP and then joins the route server, we can immediately peer with each other without
necessarily agreeing and talk to each other directly.
We can have our peering policy set as yes, I would like to accept everybody who is on
the route server.
We can also have a little more sense on what is going on in our IXP like traffic stats.
So our route server looks like this.
It's a very small machine.
It uses six foot of power.
We chose this because it was free.
And we had it.
I had it in my storage.
It fits really well for our use case.
The LaboSat Internet Exchange is only for very small devices, embedded devices like
APU 2 or Raspberry Pi.
So yeah, it didn't really make sense to have a large machine that could do fancy stuff
and have many more routes and things like that.
So the software is, well, Debian, we use a route server as a config parser to create
our BERT config.
And we use BERT as a BDP speaker.
So a route server does a lot of automation of, like, we have a list of clients and we
have some AS sets and we have some prefixes and similar things.
And then a route server creates all the 300,000 line config files.
So we don't need to maintain that.
Yes, server hosting.
It's located in LaboColo.
Again, there's links all over the place.
And yeah, Oliver and Espeon will go more into details on the LaboColo on a talk on Sunday.
But the very short version is it's intended for things like Raspberry Pi and APU 2.
But at Bornhack, you can connect to a LaboSphere village or you can connect via VLAN, which
I haven't received yet.
So yeah, but you can connect.
So we have made it so since our uplink is very nice that we have transported the VLAN
via Laptop and then over FibreVue, which is then Bornhack's uplink.
That means we can have the whole VLAN transported, the whole peering line transported down to
the camp.
That's a bit weird, but since we could, we did it.
So our switch looks like, our switch and our rack looks like this.
It's a horrible mess.
But again, the switch was a pre-used thing, it's a Cisco switch.
We are already using it.
It can do MagPort filtering and that's fine, it's nice for writing loops.
So yeah, it's a switch, that's not really much to show other than it can do that.
We actually tested out a switch which we found out could not use MagPort filtering.
So yeah, that's why we keep this.
We have a peering policy set up.
So when you join an internet exchange or start peering with other networks, you accept that
peering policy.
So it could be like I only accept traffic that is distant to you and I only send traffic
distant to you and you send traffic distant to me.
In an internet exchange, we have a few more things, not much.
Well we say we can say we will accept IPv4, ARP and IPv6 addresses, Ethernet frames, sorry.
We do not like proxy ARP, we do not like OSPF and other kinds of things.
We will do MagPort filtering again to avoid a lot of loops.
The same with proxy ARP, it creates funny things on the network.
So yes, we will not, well, routes learned through the peering network are not allowed
to be announced by BGP.
And we also would not like to be connected via a tunnel of some kind where the MTU is
lower than 1500.
So this means you have to be directly connected to us and not a remote IX which defeats a
lot of the purposes of internet exchange.
Though I have nothing against remote internet exchanges, but for all purposes it didn't
benefit.
So well, you have to get some IP, also internet resources, I call it here, but yes, IP applications.
So an AS number and an IP address is like, there is a large pool, I usually call it a
So a large cake, IANA owns the cake.
And then RIPE, which is the organization handing out IP addresses in Europe and Russia
and the Middle East, they get a bit smaller piece of the cake which they can then hand
out.
So you have the local internet registry that then they can then have a little smaller piece
of the cake which they can then hand out to you.
So RIPE do not want to talk to you, they have decided that they do not want to talk
to you, sorry, unless you are a local internet registry and that means you are a RIPE member.
I am a private person, so if I want an AS number, I do not necessarily want to pay the
1600 euro fee per year to be able to talk to RIPE.
So you need a sponsoring LIA to be able to get addresses.
You can find some nice people, you can also pay a bit for it, and there are multiple ways
to do it.
So we have found a LIA that we really like, it is a project called free transit project,
and there are some nice people.
So what is the difference between IP addresses when you have an IXP and your network operator
is that you would usually like your IP addresses to be globally routable, that means it is
your IP addresses and the route to them is in everybody's routing table.
So that is reasonable, but when you have an IXP you do not necessarily want to be globally
routable.
There are no reasons for the routers in your network to have a global route, it should
only be the routers on the peering land which should be able to connect to you.
So, yeah.
You have the, well, yeah, when you, well, so how do you, how do I know that you have
some resources allocated?
It is available in the regional internet registries databases, again, like RIPE, that we use in
our case, and so what you need to create an IX or just as a person, you need an organisation
object, you need a maintainer object, you need a person object, and also as a network
operator you need an AS set, this is for other networks to include in their routing policies.
So others can know that they are allowed to announce your prefixes, for example.
And I have again included a course, a small, very nice course in the bottom here.
So I also found out there is some miscellaneous info, I could never have guessed, when talking
to our local internet registry which then forwarded or it all directly to RIPE, well,
the obvious one is that, well, you actually need a name, yeah, I guess, so do you also
like want a route server, you have to think of that, and you probably do, so then it means
you need an AS number, and also you should probably get a 16-bit AS number, because you
never know if some customers bring really old equipment that cannot handle 32-bit AS
numbers.
A little bonus is that also that a 32-bit AS number fits on a Danish number plate, so
so you can get some, you can now find another plate that is valid in Denmark.
So we also need some prefixes, and this is one of the reasons why I said this, but not
global routable and globally routable, because we do have a shortage of IPv4 IP addresses,
so RIPE is not really keen to hand them out unless you really, really need, they have
set aside some addresses, and that's why you say, yes, I swear that I would not use these
two as normal services, and then you would get them, hooray.
You can also get a slash 48 IPv6 or larger if you really need, but you probably need,
you do not need a larger, like we use six addresses out of a lot, so yeah.
So yeah, again, things I had not thought of was get a hold of a seed or contract-confirming
connectivity to IXP ColoSight.
I had to find our bill to our Oblink, I guess it makes sense that our facilities somehow
should have an Oblink.
You also need to say, yes, I do have three customers that are willing to appear at our
IXP, so I'm not just creating an IXP for one, for me, and then I have no customers.
This also matters if you want to go and have the, be present on peeringDB as an IXP, again,
the magic number is at least three, and also with the IXP database.
These are some databases that people, network operators use to find out what IXP should
we go to, and what facilities should we go to, and who is there.
So it's a very nice way of network operators talking to each other.
It's kind of like a social media, but we don't post pictures, we just post where we are.
So yeah, again, facilities, like what is my address, and then you also need at least one
contact person and a phone number.
Just things I didn't know, and then it took five days extra to get all these sorted, so
you can send it at the same time, it would save a few days of talking back and forth.
So yes, the local internet registry, well, we used free transit projects, I have used
it for my own AS number, there are some nice people, also some hackers, so I like this,
but also I have a bias because I know some of them personally.
And if you want to find some local internet registry services, you can search on an Indian
right there service, and someone will gladly take your money to get an AS number and some
prefixes.
It is really expensive as just an organization to get IPv4 addresses, but I won't dwell too
much into that, it's just because we have a shortage and there's a market for that shortage.
So similar projects are, well, sorry, my tech phone is calling, okay, there we go.
So there are many internet exchanges in the world that are community run by network operators,
and it kind of makes sense, like some people got to get an ORB and said, hey, why don't
we do this?
And then they did this.
So yeah, like that's also commercially run, like a lot of them also, but I find it kind
of inspiring that a lot of them are just, hey, let's do this, and then we did this,
and people donated equipment and money and hosting and stuff, and it kind of just worked.
Real nice.
So yeah, there's also some hosting, some projects similar to ours, our HackerSpace, we have
in Amsterdam, we have CaseSpace in Tallinn, we have Communitech in Zurich, and they offer
some hosting of some kind, also to small machines and some larger machines for private persons
or small businesses, and there's also BGP.wtf, they do BGP stuff, similar to us, but they
are just in Warsaw instead.
And we have in Berlin also, which I learned recently also existed.
So if you're interested in finding some of these, I would say thanks to my collaborators,
so I did this as a school project also, so hooray, I got easy test points for this thing.
Olivia and Daniel helped me build this, and we also have Yorui, which is from the free
transfer project, and really nice, and then Ashburn, for having way too much knowledge
about networking, and it's a bit dangerous asking a question, because then you get a
very long answer.
So here are some good resources, like PNGDB, the interconnection database, yes, NUC meetups,
like we have in Denmark, most countries have them, there's a ripe academy, I learned a
lot on IPv6 with the course, that was really nice, and you don't have to take the certificate,
you can take the course, you can also pay to take the certificate if you want, but you
can learn a lot for free.
And yes, the network start meetups, they also helped me in some of the introductions, and
slides they have, that was really nice.
That's also, I didn't go into PNGDB filtering, it's a very important thing of network security,
but there's a small guide that InnoNUC have made collaboratively, and then InnoNUC also
have a thing they call InnoNUC ring, it's a nice way to find out how reachable is my
prefix.
And you can find us in a bornhack, in the Labitat, or Labifair village, there's a Dagnarva,
and in all other days you can find us on Labitat, we have a website for the IX, you can also
find us on PNGDB, so if you already got an AS number, you can join us, we'd really like
to have you, again, VLAN is not decided, we can also, if you bring a machine, we can probably
host it.
And if anyone wants to kind of sponsor this project, because it's been paid out of my
money until now, it wasn't really that expensive, but still, I'm a student, so, money.
All hardware is just things we found, and we're very, very nice with some updated hardware,
and maybe a second uplink, because you never know, some machine may just dig up the road
and kill the whole uplink, or something, something, and we like stickers.
So what is next for this project?
Well, we have all the, we have the RxP running, it's pretty nice, we have the Routserver running,
but we would also like to have some, well, more peers, of course, but Looking Glass,
which we have now set up, I would very much like to set up ARP Sponge to limit ARP requests,
Yeah, more monitoring, more documentation, and set up a RPKI relay I have set up on my
own network, but not for this, it uses a very inefficient way to check if AS number and
prefix match, so, thank you for listening, here's the URL, good talk.