The next speaker we have is the one with the braid that will talk about performing cross-platform
development using Flutter.
Let's give her a hand.
Thanks a lot.
Welcome.
Next 45 minutes I'll entertain you with some code in Dart and with some history about Flutter.
About me, I'm the one with the braid or in order to sum up my Danish skills down with
flattening, that's everything I know to say in Danish and that's everything I need to
know in Danish.
I'm Dart developer, so I mostly do front-end stuff using Dart and I work in healthcare
in Germany even though I'm from France.
What exactly I do there is Matrix, Matrix not as in mathematics but in the communication
protocol for decentralised communication and here apart from what I professionally do
with Flutter and Matrix is some trickling with the BSD, Linuxes and reduced instruction
set architectures.
And how did I come to Flutter?
I started using Flutter back in 2018 when it was first released and since then I'm
pretty convinced of Flutter.
What is Flutter?
Flutter is an entire set of things you can use or which it provides.
First of all, if you use Flutter, it ships the Dart platform.
Dart is a programming language more or less only used in Flutter with Flutter.
Apart from the programming language, Dart which is shipped along with Flutter, you
have the Flutter engine.
The Flutter engine is what's executing on your device, you run an application on in
order to have your Flutter application showing up.
Then you have lots of libraries, for example the foundation library providing some pre-defined
stuff in order to have easy development with Flutter, then you have design specific libraries
and widgets, for example in order to create a particular look and feel like material apps,
Cupertino apps matching IOS users, workflows, so that's what you get in order for development.
And most important, debugging, you get pretty fancy dev tools and pretty fancy analysis
in order to make the developer's lives easier.
So now that we know what Flutter consists of, why do we like it?
Flutter compiles to native binaries which makes it pretty performant.
If you look at the current state of cross-platform development, we often have constructions like
JavaScript being used in web views, in React, buzzword, Electron on desktop, and it's often
pretty inefficient because we simply run a web browser or JavaScript interpreter in order
to run time in development, whereas Flutter compiles to native code, your device is executing.
That makes it super performant because compiling does not mean being performant but the Flutter
compiler is pretty performant.
And of course if we look at our fancy startup building a new application, we have a single
code base, that means you need only one third of developers instead of developing a dedicated
native IOS, Android web application, maybe even still a Linux port, a Windows port, everything
in nature, that means good luck developing this.
With Flutter you have a single code base, well that's nothing new in cross-platform
development but that makes things way easier.
And what I love, and that's the killer feature of Flutter, you write your code once, you
design it, but it somehow adapts.
If I run the same application with the same design, with the same stuff, exactly the same
code on IOS, you will have tiny difference compared to Android because the framework
itself adapts to the platform, it takes care of placing the app bar or the app title and
position the user expects on the platform, so even though the design is completely the
same, there are these tiny differences between the platforms, some positioning, some rendering
in order to create the native look and feel you expect from your platform.
And that's super fancy in both developer and user experience because as developer I only
write it once and as user I get it as I know it from my platform and don't get a completely
IOS branded application on Android, I want something which I'm familiar with.
And there we are already at the last point, it's a fancy developing experience.
Flutter has, all the Flutter developers, which is Google, they have an entire UX team but
not a UX team in the end users, no, a UX team in order about the developer experience,
so they have an entire team taking care of creating a good developer experience and that's
something you feel when developing, it just feels, yeah, developing with Flutter, Flutter
tries to make it as comfortable for you as possible, not comfortable in order to like
simplifying stuff but in order to, yeah, this is how I want to access my stuff, this is
how I want to develop.
That's super developer friendly and yeah, you feel like that they are trying to get
rid of some legacy patterns in development, we will get on to that later, again, that
makes using Flutter and developing in Flutter in front end super comfortable for me at least.
Now short history of Flutter and Dart, so Dart is the programming language we use and
it was initially released in 2011. It aimed to replace JavaScript with a type safe language
which is a bit ridiculous because Dart was not type safe at that point back in time,
so I don't know why they wanted to but they wanted to.
The idea was, I mean, you know the UX nightmare of JavaScript, at least back in these times,
you had to handle five different browsers because four different browsers implemented
in five different ways, your API, just remember how to open an index DB or how to place an
HTTP request in JavaScript back in these times, it was awful, that's why they aimed to replace
JavaScript with Dart which obviously completely failed because no one implemented Dart as
browser site language. Also it's because they only were implementing half of the APIs from
modern browsers, so it simply did not work. It absolutely failed and then they were looking
for a new purpose. What can we do with this language?
What they did with that language is first of all developing a new version of Dart, Dart
2, or parallel developing Dart 2 which fixed many bugs like, yeah, I don't want to have
the JavaScript kind of everything is dynamic, that was fixed, and they made Flutter, and
Flutter turned out as pretty successful, at least if we look at the stats of developers
using it, it's pretty successful nowadays. It started as a tiny framework initially aiming
to support cross platform development on iOS and Android, whereas the first release
was Android only, but already within the first year, the first two years, web support and
iOS support were added. One year later, which was 2020 I think, already first preview of
desktop support on Linux and Mac OS was added, Windows 2, now we even have a runtime for
the universal Windows platform, so kind of the new Windows 11 apps that you have. So
Flutter runs on everything apart from previously, that's a story of pain, if someone is interested
I can explain that further later on. So yeah, from this tiny cross platform framework between
iOS and Android, it developed to a platform running everywhere, and running everywhere
as in we compile it to native binaries and not as in we have a browser rendering it everywhere,
which is a huge difference. I don't know, has anyone of you ever used Flutter? One?
Yay, that's many people. Okay, so I will give you a quick heads up of how Flutter works
and the basics of Flutter and Dart before showing code and going into deeper stuff I
think. Flutter, first of all, is mostly a UI framework meant for UI design of front-end
stuff. That's the first thing. It's not your backend framework for your Rust server, it's
front-end stuff. When we design our user interface, every UI element is to simplify it everywhere.
Every UI element is a widget. So as we have XML tags when doing Android development or
as we have HTML tags when doing web development, we have widgets nested as a tree in Flutter.
So it's the same as everywhere. We have our huge, I know the entire container containing
our entire app and then our sub widgets which might be an app bar, some text we display,
all these are widgets and they are nested in a tree as far as I know pretty everywhere.
Flutter already provides us with many high-level widgets we can use in order to create complex
designs in a fast manner but also provides completely basic widgets. A complex UI widget
might be an account chooser for a sidebar. That's a pretty high-level widget where you
only provide some profile pictures, some action and it does everything for you. That's
the most high-level you can imagine from a simple UI framework to ship whereas a more
basic widget might be a container doing nothing but being a container containing anything
else and getting some properties like a size, a color and such things. Then we have some
of course things in between which might be text which already interacts a bit. It detects
whether we are right or left and stuff. This is a bit more high-level but still pretty
low-level. So Flutter ships everything from I want the very most basic in order to create
the very most custom stuff I can create up to I want the fastest way to get an app working,
please give me high-level widgets. All these we can do.
Now the first code sample. This is a Flutter app. I think it's the shortest Flutter app
we can have. We call our file main.dart, import the Flutter library. I think we lost the connection.
Now we are back again. I don't know why but my web browser here is communicating with
the web browser on the other screen which is also on the device. I don't know who invented
this shit. It usually works. This is an example of a super tiny Flutter app. As you see it
displays nothing but which is more or less a Klingon phrase for hello world. I was not
able to write something in Danish so I chose Klingon here. We can have a look at it. It
looks awful but that should not prevent us from at least having a look at it. Let me
compile. This might take a minute. Here. There we were compiling it. Here we have it. That's
a bit ugly but we see we have a window, a native Linux GTK window appearing with content
and that's it. Since we do not provide any information about what color whatsoever this
should display. It's simply a red text because someone found red as a fancy default color
for text if we do not provide any information. There we are with our first Flutter app. You
can have a Flutter app with one line of code. Since that's not that pretty, let's go a bit
deeper into this thing and I need to figure out how to get back into full screen mode.
I think that's the right button. Are we still connected? No, we are not connected. Now we
are connected again. I was talking about the different widgets we nest and of course there
are different types of widgets. We can reduce the different types of widgets onto two basic
types of widgets which are stateless and still full widget. If you're familiar with
software development you likely can relate what it means. A stateless widget is immutable.
You once create it, it's being rendered and that's it. If you want to change something,
whatsoever method, whatsoever place creating this widget needs to create a new widget with
other properties and it's being rendered again. It's once created, it has no state. If you
want to change it, we need to dispose it and create a new one. The state is managed around
this widget. It does not have anything managing any state. Whereas a state full widget takes
care of logic, you can create interaction with the state full widget. It's mutable hands.
It has a state containing your fancy variables you want to store. It can trigger its own
rebuilds. It can react on listeners on triggers in order to change itself and hence render
again. It's mutable. In short, it can self modify itself. Easy samples. If we display
a text, just a constant text with hello world, that's obviously a stateless widget because
it does not change anything. It will never change. It's just if the screen size changes
and it needs to render again, it's just being rendered again. Whereas if we have a button
listening on being clicked and then changing its color would be a state full widget because
we somehow need to store the state. Have we been clicked? What's our current color? That's
definitely a state full widget in opposite. And usually a state full widget is only everything
around that's finally building stateless widgets. So we have the state, okay, are we currently
red or blue? And in case we are red, we render a stateless button which is, yeah, we have
this button and you're red. And yeah, so a state full widget returns a bunch of stateless
widgets usually if we look at the widget tree. How to keep it performant and beautiful? Keep
a stateless as possible. Try to reduce the amount of places where you manage your state
to the lowest possible because the more state you manage, the more places, the more diffuse
it gets, the more broken it gets. And if we always, for example, have one state full widget
containing an entire tree of other widgets also being state full and always initializing
again when being rebuilt, recreated, that's of course less performant than if we handle
our entire state as top as possible in our widget tree because then we do not reinitialize
states, we do not compute states again. We have this state here, we read it out and render
it correspondingly. So the less state you handle, so the less places you handle it at
is the more performant. Also if you use state full widgets, prevent from recreating them.
Flutter has APIs in order to check whether we actually, if we have, I don't know, we
have our fancy red button thingy and whether we actually need to reinitialize our state
if our surroundings or our parenting widget changed, there's the didUpdateWidget method
with which we can check whether we actually need to react on that state change or just
say hey, I don't care, I keep my state. So this is also how you keep your application
more performant, try to preserve your state as long as possible unless you need to modify
or you need to react on the modified environment. A common pattern is you write your controller
or use some fancy libraries in order to have control logic, like for example block might
be a word you might stumble around where you have a controlling instance and you only build
your widgets against one single controller, you read the state out of it. So kind of you
handle the state as external as possible in order to have one place you keep your current
app's pages state in. And another thing is Flutter has something called keys and if you
provide a key to a widget and the key is equal to the previous key provided at this place,
it won't recompute the state, it's simply in order, for example, if we render a list
view with a thousand elements, we might consider adding keys giving them the index we are building
to so that if we change, for example, the length of the list or scroll by, we do not
have to recompute the state but tell the Flutter engine, you already computed the state of
this one, take that state, connect it to that key. So now we're talking about lots of stuff.
It's really slow and it's misaligned. It's misaligned, it's misaligned, it's misaligned
and it's misaligned. The screen is somehow split, let me try to fix that.
Okay, here we are again without a split screen. Yes, now we were talking about how to handle
state, how to have performant code. Now the question is if you want to have performant
code, how does it actually render because rendering in Rigid of your I-Frameworks is
still the most exhaustive part of our development. Yes, so let's have a look at it. First of
all, what's the architecture of Flutter? Are we going to get to the next slide or not?
That's the question. Who is the Flutter developer?
Who broke the Internet? So next slide. Yes, now it works again. Sorry, it's a bit broken,
all this stuff. I think that's part of chaos. This is the architecture of the Flutter framework
whereas we have the framework we already talked about with all its widgets and everything
related to what we actually ship to the end users and we have the engine. I already mentioned
that component too and the engine is basically the part written in C++, at least if you look
at the IO based platforms, which takes care of all the rendering and which basically executes
the Dart VM, takes care of communicating which text is displayed to your operating system,
something accessibility and screen readers. We should not only render text but also communicate
what text we have there. And building up on this engine, we have this entire framework.
We have the foundation library containing all the basics of Flutter, which is for example
the run app method. That's the most basic stuff we have. It must be contained everywhere.
That's part of the foundation. Up on the foundation, before we come to high level widgets, we have
everything regarding animation. So everything we need in order to rebuild the screen, in
order to trigger new rendering, new frames. We have the painting of widgets. So now we
have the final widget, but how do we layout it? How do we render it? All this is part
of the painting stuff. We have gestures, of course. If we have an application, we need
to handle input, may it be a mouse, may it be a stiller, may it be a keyboard, may it
be anything, may it be touch, or if we look at smartphones nowadays. On that, the rendering
with its widgets, which might be a basic widget like a container, having nothing but the size
and the color, and the high level pre-provided libraries like material, providing you fancy
buttons, your beloved account chooser widget, or a Cupertino library matching iOS patterns
with a fancy context menu as a high level predefined widget. That's the architecture
mentioned here. This is the architecture. If we look at mobile and desktop devices on
web, it's a bit different because some things work different, but we will talk about web
later, at least if you still have the motivation. Now let's look at the rendering. So we have
a GPU. It can build a desired amount of frames per second because our CPU has a particular
performance. Flutter supports rendering up to, I think, 120 frames per second as of now,
which is enough for most cases. If we build a widget, if we render a frame, if we render
our application, the first thing we get is a tick from the GPU, time for a new frame.
Tell me what to render. That's what we call in Flutter vSync. We get that one on stateful
widgets, where as we can hook into the Flutter engine communicating your Dart code, your
write every single time the GPU finished building a frame, please give me the next one. And
yeah, if we render anything, we first check, do we need to animate anything? Do we need
to adjust anything on the layout? For example, do we have, for example, a progress indicator
which should move for two pixels because we have a time offset of these and that many
milliseconds? In case of that, first thing is we animate, we check the new values of
everything that we build, we create a widget tree, we define, okay, this widget should
be placed there and so on. And then the next thing is, yeah, now we have our device. It
has this size, it has this DPI. We need to layout it according to what we get from our
hardware. That's the next part. And once it's being layouted, Flutter computed all the positions
of the widgets, all the hierarchy, what's in front, what's in background, then we come
to the point where the Skia engine is having fun communicating with the GPU and painting
new stuff on your screens, painting your new frame. Then you have your layer and widget
tree painted on your device and we get our new vSync tick and can start over. So this
is pretty much what happens if your GPU is free. She's never free because your GPU always
gets new input. So this is how rendering works and if we know how this rendering is supposed
to work, we can optimize performance for it. Now we are back at stateless and stateful
widgets. A stateless widget is once constructed, we have its constructor, it's constructing
the widget, it's defining everything we need to know with this widget and as soon as the
Flutter engine decides it should be built, it's being built. Often it's just built a
single time because we have our static page, our device size does not change, it's just
being built once. We have cases where it's going to change. For example, if I run it
on my application on the desktop and I just shrink the window size. Of course then we
have a new layouting process. We do not have a new build process where we create the widget
tree again. We only have a new layouting process because we already know the present widget
tree and we need to layout again. So this is the only case where this loop is being
entered and being rebuilt in case our layout is changing and we must adjust anything. A
stateful widget in opposite is creating its state and once this state is created, also
we enter the build loop. If the Flutter engine decides we build it, we build it. But also
this stateful widget can trigger a change of its state on its own and communicate the
other way around back to the Flutter engine, please rebuild me because for example I was
processing an onclick event and I should now change my color. Now I was storing this state,
I have current button color set to green. Now we communicate to the Flutter engine,
set state, the most prominent method in Flutter and the Flutter engine knows next GPU tick
we get, we will rebuild this part of the screen, this widget according to its new properties.
And how that looks is in particular this. That's a pretty long loop. We once create
our widgets, we initialize the state, we have the init state method where for example we
can read out some properties from environment, create our initial state, for example creating
a text field controller in order to process text input or anything. Creating an animation
controller, you often initialize controller classes in the init state. Then we have a
dirty state because we have a present state but it's not rolled out so rendered for the
user yet. If we have a dirty state and the Flutter engine knows about it because we call
this set state or because we were finishing the init state method, it's being built. Then
we have a clean state because what the user sees and what the state of our widget communicates
us to be like, it's same so it's clean. Now we have several options what may happen. The
config change, for example the layout change because the size of the screen was changing
again because I don't know what. In that case we also need to rebuild because things will
rebuild. The other case is we process something whether it may be we were waiting for a random
delay of five seconds in order to change the color or we were listening to an animation
controller animating the color in a fancy gradient or whatsoever or we received a button
click and we adjust the color, we are at the dirty state again. That's why Flutter engine
knows, okay, dirty state, I either got my set state call or I got from the engine itself,
I got the information, layout change or anything I need to rebuild again and at the end of
the life cycle of a stateful widget we dispose of the widget, it's no longer needed for
example because we were navigating to a new page. Also this navigating to a new page isn't
often a problem for example if you want to get back to the previous page but want to
preserve the state. In that case you also can communicate to delay the disposal of the
widget. Also very common bug in order to break your applications. Yeah, now we are
looking, actually we are optimizing performance all the time but let's optimize it a bit further.
Simple hints, simple tips and tricks about performance, I already mentioned keys, keys
you provide them to a widget and it knows we already have computed the state, we already
store the state somewhere, please reuse it as soon as you encounter exactly this key
again. That's pretty useful for animation purpose where you rebuild stuff but parts
of the screen are same even though everything around was messed up because we were moving
stuff around but in order to communicate to the Flutter engine, yeah, this is the same
part again, you can preserve it, keys are useful. Also very useful, similar use case
where you render a lot if you listen to a stream builder building again, again and again,
use keys because it does not force you to rebuild everything again, everything once
a new element is entered into a stream, just use keys everywhere. Yeah, yeah, in Flutter
you often, it's a high level framework, you often listen to streams, to listenables, to
future builders in order to not implement all the logic again and a very common easy
pattern is hey, isn't there this constructor list view dot builder, let's just run it against
our stream because we have a stream for example, a list of your inbox from your mail application,
your inbox from your mail application, you have the list, the stream of the last messages
you were receiving, yeah, let's just build again against it. Better do not do that because
there we have the state, you communicate to Flutter, these 50 items are my current inbox
items, build a list out of it. If we do not communicate the engine, this item was previously
there, this item was previously there and actually only this single new item changed,
we are building everything again. That's what we have an animators list view for in order
to handle this where you simply can say insert an item at position five or delete item at
position three, move item from position one to position five. That's way more efficient
because everything is only rebuilt these tiny parts that changed, also it's way more beautiful
because everything is animated. Flutter is high level, it's animated. Yeah, if you use
raw slivers, slivers is what's doing everything which is sliding in Flutter, the equivalent
is an animated sliver list delegate. But of course you can also use keys if you want to
use a basic list view, then you also prevent from rebuilding everything again. You should
benchmark your applications trying to do that, you will find a huge difference. We were recently
having this trouble in something we were developing at work and it was, yeah it was a different
from 100 to zero. Kind of full GPU blocked because 10,000 items were re-rendering compared
to, yeah it's this tiny item re-rendering, you feel the difference. Animation in my opinion
is very important, in my opinion it's very important. Now it's split again, cursed screen.
Over 10 minutes left, oh wow. Yeah, animations are nice but you should avoid using pixel-based
animations. For example, a video, rendering a video, a GIF, an APNG, an AVIF is always
less efficient than if you use native Flutter shaders. And generally all the performance
is awful on web because Flutter renders in a GL context and rendering your video in a
GL context decreases the performance kind of by 100% if you use it on web. Use, for
example, if you animate stuff, use the animations package which simplifies lots of, yeah, which
provides you many high-level IPIs in order to create efficient animations where you only
give in, hand in the initial thingy, layout thingy, state, whatever it should be, the
initial widget, yeah that's what I want to say, and the outcome, what we should animate
to and it fades or transitions in any way you define there in an efficient way. Yeah,
now I was talking a lot about all this stuff. I would now better go to a practical part.
Let me scroll around here. I think I already moved there. Yeah, I just wrote you a tiny
sample. The screen is still that cursed. Let me disconnect again. I wrote a tiny sample
in the morning today showing pretty everything you need to know about Flutter, which is how
to store stuff on your device, which is how do I do proper routing in my application.
We have some animations we can look at here and that's the sample. You already saw the
run app method in the first sample I was showing, though in the first sample it was only a text
and now we provide some widget. Everything is a widget. You see it here. Everything we
render extends some kind of widget. In that case it's a stateless widget because we only
return some random stuff, some data in order to show a material app. What we do there, we define
titles, some color scheme. Because I like pink, I was setting it to pink and then we define a
router. A router is a pretty relevant part, though the line is not that visible. I stored
a variable called Bonhack router containing all the information about routing, where to find which
page and so on. What is happening? It's always splitting up. That's a cursed connector. Let's
look at that one. It's unfortunately cut again because the beamer is doing cursed stuff. Our
router is a Go router. Go router is currently the way to go to do routing in Flutter. It's a
package developed by the Flutter team itself, providing some fancy APIs for routing, whereas I
just provide some routes containing information about what's the path it should react on. I can
also store variables, for example, colon ID in that case. The router state would contain information
about there was a path parameter provided with the identifier ID and one can access it, but in our
case, we don't need it. It's a simple example. It only has two routes, which is the splash screen
we get to when opening the application at slash and we have the home route where we get to a page
I define, which is called Bonhack page. Let's look at the splash screen. It's already a bit a longer
file, but not that long. What we have, we define a stateful widget. A stateful widget does not have
many contents. It's pretty much nothing. The only relevant part about the stateful widget is the
line create state where we once create the state and everything about this widget is later on
handled in the state. In the state, we have two very important parts in the widget lifecycle,
which is the init state. That's where we start initializing our widget. Often, you start asynchronous
tasks in there where you later on react on further stuff. In our case, we have these two. I will show
later. The second relevant part, which is the build method. In the build method, in our case,
we do nothing but showing a scaffold. Scaffold is the flatter name of I have a material page,
please show it. It's showing a centered progress indicator, which is spinning like, whew, whew,
whew. Why do we show this? This is an asynchronous method. We do not wait for it. We just start it.
Hence, the initial state method is passing before that method completes, so we're building just
instantly. What we build is this progress indicator and while showing this progress indicator in order
to emphasize the stupidity of the code, I was just adding a constant delay of two seconds at this
place, so we wait for two seconds. Maybe you are checking some HTTP stuff, checking whether your
user is logged in or whatsoever, and we initialize a database, Hive. Maybe you've heard of this word
Hive is one of the three pretty popular databases in Flutter. We initialize it and I wrote a tiny
helper class where I store my Hive stuff. We can look at that one. It's also pretty much most
stuff you need to know about Dart code. It's a single term implemented as we have a factory
providing an instance which I just deleted. We have an asynchronous constructor, hence a static
method opening it because we need to wait for the disk. We need to open the data store, wait for it
to be opened, then we store it in our class in order to later on easily access it via this instance
getter. So now we open that one. It takes a few milliseconds and let me go back to my previous page.
I think it was that one. And once we are done also opening our database, everything we need to
initialize is done and we get to our new page, the home page, which is a pretty simple call in
Flutter with a tiny condition in the front. It's if mounted. If mounted is what you always check
before accessing anything which relates to your current context in Flutter. If mounted simply checks
whether your widget is currently active, whether it was deposed before because if you dispose your
widget you can no longer navigate from this widget away. It's not possible. So we check whether our
current widget is still mounted and in case it's still mounted we go to the route home. And home is
the other page I will still quickly show you before I release you into freedom. It's this tiny page.
It already has some more things. I was storing some static strings I used a bit below. I will
also show you how it's being compiled later. We have a page where we have an app bar that the app
bar has some color set. We have some title being set. We have an action we will look at later and
we have a center in which we have some stuff. And now we have a very relevant widget of Flutter which
is a value-listenable builder. Well value-listenable builder itself is not the relevant part but
everything ending on builder in Flutter is super important because in order to have performant
and user-friendly UX you want to react on asynchronous tasks which might be I need to load
something from my web server. I need to wait for this to be stored on the disk and what we have in
this case is a value-listenable builder. The database I chose is high level as most things
in Flutter. I simply can listen onto a database and once it's changed this builder is being
executed and with whatever changes in this database on this store of the database we can rebuild our
widget. In this case it's a counter containing an integer I can change. So if I change this integer
this part of the screen is being rebuilt it's being set to the new amount we get there. We have this
here we listen to the counter and every time the counter box is changing this one is being rebuilt
we get the current value of the counter store. Here we fetch the value of the main counter here
and we display it. That's everything. Down here we still have a button incrementing this counter
but that's no magic. Let's quickly look at it before the talk is going to end.
Navigating across screens.
There you see my fun with display configurations while it's building my Flutter. Here we see our
splash screen for two seconds and everything the application does currently is being ugly because
I did not expect it to run in full screen mode and hence my development tools tell me hey you
were not handling this size of the screen that's why we have this pattern here and my development
tools want me to fix that. So let's go into a better screen size so that we can see it. Here we
have we have nothing in the store we were talking about yet so the database store does not contain
anything so we cannot really read anything out and the fallback is null. Here I have a button with
which I can increment it. The button does nothing but writing something new to the storage and the
value listener builder is doing all the magic so that we finally get the counter here being displayed
again. I can press it as many times as I want and I was mentioning my GPU struggles. I was mentioning
some high level widgets. I added you one. Here you see an image but I wrapped it with a high level
widget with a fancy high level widget with a cupotino context menu. I can just long press it
or right click it and we're getting a fancy context menu as you know it from macOS or iOS.
So this is as more or less the final words an example of a super high level widget which is
one line of code to implement and you get such an animated context menu and this combination of
doing everything low level, listening on streams, but having these fancy high level widgets. That's
why I love Flutter and that's my final word. Questions?
Thanks for the nice talk. So I looked at the code and I think you only showed state full widget
so what are some examples or especially typical examples for stateless widgets in Flutter?
I can show you. I was showing one stateless widget as well.
Here this is a stateless widget. A stateless widget usually has nothing but a build method.
A stateless widget is simply a sum up of widgets we already know how to compose. So in our case
the stateless widget does nothing but returning the material app. So another widget already
provided by the Flutter framework itself with the properties we know we want to have.
So that's what the stateless widget does in this case.
Thank you for being here. Let's give Shia a round of applause.