We have the last presentation today in the speaker's tent is Peter Stucke, who is going
to talk about Simplex Chat, simple messaging with unusually good privacy.
Let's give a round of applause for Peter.
Thank you very much.
So, yes, Simplex Chat, it's a messenger.
I want to talk a little about why it is better than many other, maybe most, maybe all.
I'm going to go into a bit of propaganda about good technology and bad technology.
I feel very strongly about that.
Talk about some good messengers and then compare with this, which I find is an unusually good
messenger.
I'll talk about what client software there is.
I'll talk about the feature set that works already, and then I'll talk about what's on
the roadmap for this project.
Maybe we'll look into the protocol.
It's a little bit complicated with this other computer because of the graphics, and then
thank you and questions.
So, good technology and bad technology, right?
I don't know if you've thought about this before, but why another messenger?
You may be thinking, and I say, well, most of the messengers out there are really bad
technology, and please make an effort to get friends and loved ones away from this bad
technology that a lot of people are using.
Most of new technology is actually really, really bad.
It's not made for us.
It's made to make money off of us in some way or other, right?
I argue that this is why the internet has come to feel so bad lately, right?
Many perhaps were around in the beginnings of the internet, and then it was all fun and
exciting, but now it's really, really not so much fun anymore.
So the thing is, you are valuable, right?
Anybody who's dealing with technology, who's using technology, is really valuable, and
by choosing what you use and what you do not use, which is very important.
I find that we talk way too rarely about not using technology, choosing to reject stuff
that is actually bad, right?
By choosing what you use and what you don't use, you're determining the value of technology,
because technology is worth nothing if nobody uses it.
So there's this reverse network effect.
Maybe you heard of the network effect.
The more people use something, the more powerful it becomes and the more difficult it is to
switch to something else.
Well, if we start to move away from technology and choose not to use technology, then we're
also helping get rid of that technology, which is really what we should do, because it's
not in our interest.
So whenever we use bad technology, we also help increase its value.
We are sort of actively supporting this bad technology.
So don't do that if you can't at all avoid it, right?
It's important to reject bad technology.
Enough propaganda.
Some bad messengers, like WhatsApp is a bad messenger.
It's a centralized system, U.S. jurisdiction.
It's even forced centralized, right?
There's no way to integrate with this system, really.
It's closed.
It also uses strong identifiers, so it's not so privacy-optimized, privacy-friendly.
It's the full name, and it's closed source, so it's also really hard work to find out
what is it actually doing.
Signal is surprisingly similar to WhatsApp.
The main difference is that it's open source.
Meh.
It's especially the way that Signal uses phone numbers as identifiers, I find, is an absolute
disaster and completely rules out using Signal for anything.
Signal is also a centralized closed system because they refuse to federate with anybody
else, right?
Then we have, for example, Telegram is another bad technology.
Nobody knows what that is, where that's based, but it's still centralized and it's closed,
like you can build bots and stuff, but you can't really run your own server, as far as
I know.
The security properties are nonexistent to unclear, is what I wrote.
If you have a group in Telegram, anybody can just connect and download all of everything
that has been said there, and for the direct chats, I'm not so sure what is really going
on there.
It's also closed source, right, and it's the identities and a bad situation, all of these,
and there are more bad examples, right, but the slide is full.
So let's talk about Simplex, and I find that I call it an unusually good messenger because
it does a lot of things really, really right.
I'm not involved in the project in any way.
I found it a couple of months ago, and I looked through it, not the code, but the protocol
and the design.
I was really happily surprised.
It was refreshing, so there are no global user identities, there's no way to recognize
the same user, means there's also no discovery or search, so there's no way to find people
inside the system, which I argue is a really good thing.
That means we have to create connections explicitly when we meet or over some other channel, and
why I think this is a good thing is that we have no spam.
It's impossible to get spam in, or I mean, if you do get spam, it's from somebody you
know because you connected with them, right.
So invitations is what is used to create a connection, and it can be a QR code, or it
can be just a link that you share over some other medium, and once you've connected, you
can also verify if you'll meet later, if you're not connecting in person, when you'll meet
at some later time, you can verify that your connection is really not man in the middle
by anybody.
So invitations, there are two kinds, that's kind of fun, I haven't seen that anywhere
before, they can either be single use, that's sort of the normal case for adding one contact,
adding a new contact, there's only one chance to use it and then it gets locked in, or it
can be multi-use, that's like a public invitation to join a group, or maybe to contact me, if
I want to, I could do that.
And these are both revocable, so at any time I can also stop the invitation and anybody
who tries to use it after that will not be able to connect, and that's really nice properties.
Then there's this incognito option, which is a lot of fun, so because there are no user
identities, right, how do we, what can we do with that?
So we can have the situation where my client uses a different identity in every context,
so it has a different identity for every person I'm communicating with and it has a different
identity in every single group that I'm a member of.
This means that somebody that I'm communicating directly with, they cannot know whether I
am a member of some chat groups, and that may be really useful for me.
Many clients, or I don't know about normally, but clients do have the possibility to probe
group members, so if you join a group you can send a probe to everybody to sort of check
if they are known to you already.
Switching on this incognito option makes that not work, right, then it just, you will have
duplicate contacts perhaps with the same name, and yeah, and be none the wiser.
The server architecture is delightfully simple.
It's a very simple server, it doesn't do much of anything, it's a message queue, just receiving
messages and sending them out, there's crypto and so on, of course, but the server doesn't
know very much or really anything about the contents, and the servers are decentralized.
There's not one single server, you can have your own servers, and there are many servers
already in operation, and it doesn't really matter which server you use, you can also
move servers, like change servers at will.
That's also fun, a nice new concept that I haven't seen in really anywhere before.
The protocol is layered that helps with this, so I wrote like TCPIP, that helps with the
separation that the server doesn't really know, it only takes care of transport, messages
going through, it doesn't know the contents.
Only the clients know what's inside the messages.
Of course the server can see IP addresses, but we can use Tor and maybe other methods
as well in order to not show our real IP address if we want to.
And the way the protocol works, and the way this sort of loose server architecture, or
well, flexible server architecture, works, allows the servers to not really have a lot
of persistence, they don't need to store much information, which I also find is great.
Of course a malicious server could still store everything, but the common case, the happy
path, is that the server doesn't need to store really anything at all, almost, but very very
little, which is also a really good thing, and this is very different from Matrix, for
example, where the server has to store everything about everybody since forever.
Don't use Matrix.
So what about the client software?
What is available right now?
There's the command line software, it's the original implementation of the simplex chat
protocol, it's written in Haskell, runs on at least Linux, Mac OS and Windows, I don't
know that anybody has tried it on BSD, so please do that.
Then there are mobile apps for Android and iOS, it's youngish, the first version was
released in March last year, 2022, and by now the Android version is up to version 5.2,
so there's quite a lot of development going on, and I've been using it for two months,
just about, and I've had two updates so far, so about one update a month with a few new
features in the first one, and one new feature, red acknowledgement, like the second check
mark in the last update.
So download you can from FDroid, it's already available there, you can get the APK file
directly from upstream, but use FDroid, it's better, you get the updates, and it's also
signed and so on, it's even available in the Play Store, get FDroid instead, and the Android
app I feel works really well, I'm happy with it, using it for a couple of months, it's
in Scotland, iOS, I haven't played with that, but I have a couple of friends who are hostage
in iOS, and they are able to communicate with me, and I'm with them, and it's fine, everything's
fine.
Feature set, so it does text messaging, of course, that's the really basic stuff, right,
you can also send links, they are a separate message type, links can contain a preview,
the preview is created on the sender side, but there's an option to disable this, so
you just send the link text and nothing else, like the link address, but if you have the
option on, there's pretty graphics of the web page that the link points to, you can
send also attachments, images, and any other kind of file, but images are then displayed
in the conversation.
So you can quote a previous message, supports forwarding, and if enabled, it allows to delete
messages also in conversations.
Secret chat groups, the chat groups are quite fun because they are not stored anywhere except
on the clients, so the server doesn't know that there is a group, it only sees lots of
connections between people, or like between clients, right, and they are no different
from one to one connections, so a group looks for the server exactly the same as many person
to person connections, that's nice, it works fine to create groups and manage groups, it
also supports audio and video calls, that works as well, uses WebRTC, so the privacy
benefits of the simplex message queue protocol are lost, but well, it works for calling,
and if you enable Tor inside the app, I don't know what happens with the WebRTC, we should
investigate that, that's on my to-do list, but anyway, the calling works fine also.
So these are some to-dos on the roadmap at the project, they want to do this, as I mentioned,
we can change servers, change which server is being used for an established contact,
that can be done manually at the moment, but they want to make that automatic I guess every
now and then, change server and or just replace the queue that is being used.
Then contacting somebody using an invitation, they want to add sort of an introduction message
of some kind, some encryption for local files stored, navigation and search inside the conversation,
larger groups, so I don't know where the cutoff is, but it seems that there is some kind of
scalability limit, right, because there is this everybody to everybody connection or
situation in the groups, I can imagine that if doing really thousands or hundreds of
people in a group that doesn't scale so well, so I'm interested to see what they come up with there.
Ephemeral, like disappearing conversations, sure, sharing location, sure, I don't know,
but this web widget stuff, not so much for me, but okay I guess, programmable automations,
like maybe vacation replies, the classic one, and then there's I think a big one that really,
it doesn't matter so much to me personally, but multi-device support I think is really
valuable for a lot of people, and I look forward to that working as well, and then for those who
want to, they want to help create easier discovery, something based on DNS, and then this message
delivery relay for senders is something I think like what Tor does as well, with you add extra
systems in front to just not show the exact IP address you're using and still get messages
delivered, that's also fine, but yeah I like the general sort of ideas that they have in the
roadmap, I think this is fun, and especially the multi-device support I think will make a big
difference for people being excited about this. So now I was considering just walking through the
protocol descriptions, because they are actually really simple, and I encourage you to read them,
but on this computer I'm not so sure if that will work out.
Yeah, they want help translating, why not? So they talk about privacy here and why it matters,
there was some discussion, some debate about that right, why do we need privacy or how much
this story is amazing, somebody who made a phone call to a relative in Afghanistan and then was
put in Guantanamo for 15 years, it's not a good situation. So Simplex, they talk about what they
do, I mentioned some of this ownership of the data, everything is client-side, I think that's
a really good feature, and we can run our own servers, I talked about signal being centralized
with all the metadata, how's it different from matrix etc., well there is no identity at all,
it's really every connection is a new connection, quick install, platform design,
so not the chat protocol, also not the server implementation here, this is what I want.
So it's 900 lines, that's not really long for a protocol, description markdown,
independent of any transmission system, so it works over TCP on the internet right,
but it can also use anything else but it doesn't really care as long as the message format is the
same, we could also use bridges, build bridges between lots of different transports. The data
model or the communication model has three participants, the recipient, the server and
the sender, this order will make sense in a second, the server has these cues, message cues,
and a cue is created by the recipient, so if I want to invite a contact to reach me,
I prepare a cue for this, and I then provide some information in the QR code or in a link
to the person I want to be reachable for, and they then connect to the other side of the server,
and then we have a one-way channel, they do the same and then over this one-way channel they send
me how I will be able to reach them, and then we have a two-way channel, and this is all transparent,
it happens just that, the app does it, but these two paths they don't need to go over the same
server, they usually don't, and they don't identify us also in any way, that's also nice,
so out of band messages, we need to do this initial contact out of band, simplex cue,
as I said, it sends messages in one direction, can be communicated in a link, it has this syntax,
so when as I said Alice and Bob they want to communicate, Alice wants to receive messages
from Bob, she creates the new cue, creates a random key, creates another random key,
so the first one is for Bob to encrypt the contents of messages, and the second one is
for Alice to communicate with the server, and then another key pair for one extra encryption layer
that the server uses between itself and Alice, so that anything that goes into a server never
comes out the same, the same data never comes out, this is also a nice feature that I don't know
that I've seen anywhere else, this makes correlation really difficult for anybody watching the server,
right, then Alice creates the cue with this new command, the server responds and says here are
the IDs that you and Bob need to use, Alice gives Bob this information, gives him first the public
key for the messages and then where the server is and then his sender ID for this cue, Bob creates
then his key for communicating with the server and prepares confirmation message to Alice,
so he then sends through the server to Alice, okay I'm here, Alice then receives this message
from Bob and locks the cue to only work with Bob, up until that point anybody else who also
guessed the information that Alice sent to Bob out of band could also have tried to connect,
but only one, so the winner, the first one wins and Bob would get an error message and if Alice
and Bob are communicating as they need to be out of band, then they will recognize that somebody
is trying to mess with them, and that's it, now this one-way communication from Bob to Alice
has been established and after that Bob does exactly the same thing to create a channel
for Alice to reach Bob, here's a nice diagram showing exactly this,
and here's how the cue works once it has been established, so the recipient subscribes
and is verified, then the sender subscribes and is verified, sends a message, the recipient fetches
messages from the cue, that's it, it's really simple, and there's end-to-end encryption going
on inside or of the message contents as well, but the server doesn't know and doesn't care,
that's pretty much it, right, multiple servers do not communicate with each other, they don't need
to share any state, they don't need to know anything about each other, the clients decide
everything, servers need to store messages only until they are downloaded by the recipient,
no history or logs need to be stored, again very unlike matrix, and so what was this last point,
yeah simplex cues one-way, crypto it's using a lot of salt, the salt crypto box, it's using
EDD 24519, EDD 448,
yeah servers must not store and send stuff to other servers, sure, there are message delivery
notifications, so for, and that's also a really nice, I think they've solved that nicely,
so for mobile operating systems there are proprietary services for push notifications,
right, and we don't want to send the message contents, and we also don't want to send
the metadata there, here there is a sort of extra subscription possible for a notification helper
that will receive information that there is something to fetch in the cue, but not what it
is and not from who and nothing else, and can send this through the proprietary push notification
infrastructure, that's fun also, and it works really well, even on the, so I heard the command
line client actually also does this kind of notification on macOS, which is fun for macOS
users, here are the details of the block structure, it's quite simple, refreshing, so when I read
through this detailed and slow I had the feeling I'm actually able to implement this, it's going
to take maybe a week, but it's really straightforward, right, that's very nice, I haven't seen
such a simple protocol in a while, some interesting commands that we can take a look at,
acknowledge message delivery, suspend queue, I haven't tried that, yeah, send message,
receive message, okay, so some has some depth, right, to the message structure,
but it's all right, it's not so bad,
and error responses,
we have transport protocol, TCP, whatever port, TLS 1.3, with this particular algorithm,
cha-cha 20, poly 1305, SHA-256, 24519, ED and X, key exchange and signatures,
strict, so a couple of really strict requirements on how the server behaves, the client has a
possibility to reject the server if the server starts behaving strangely,
fixed size communication blocks, so 16 kilobyte communication blocks, that's good to not reveal
how large messages are that are being sent, and 16 kilobyte is not so much overhead, I think that's
okay, yeah, and that's it, that's the end of the protocol specification,
so let's see, page nine, that's all the the protocol fun I want to go into, but I encourage
you to look at the documentation, the documentation is really good, there's a user guide,
and there's also a description of what the message protocol is
for the contents of the messages, I didn't talk all about that, it's a very simple JSON format,
yeah, quite straightforward, so if you want to, you can connect to the bornhack23 simplex group,
there's already like 15 people maybe in it, once you've installed, and thank you to organizers and
volunteers for making this event, and I'll take questions if you have any, we have a question here,
yeah, thanks for the talk, actually very interesting, as a matrix user, I know that
matrix is really optimized for large rooms with large groups, and you said for the servers in
with simplex, they don't know if it's like a one-to-one connection or a connection to a group chat,
and I wonder how well does simplex scale for larger groups, and is that even a design goal
to scale that much? Right, excellent question, so at the moment groups are the same as one-to-one,
so if I'm in a group, I have a connection to everybody else in the group, and everybody
else also has a connection to everybody else in the group, that doesn't scale so great,
I don't know where the limit is, but it will be somewhere, and on the roadmap they have this
large group point, I don't know what the status is, but clearly somebody's thinking about it,
and they want to also have a good solution for that.
Thank you, and someone in the middle of your talk, you mentioned that the server re-incrits
incoming messages into another key, sending it out, and that was good for stopping correlation
attacks, and then at the end you mentioned the 16 kilobyte padding, are those connected? Because
without the padding, I can see that the correlation could be done anyway, is these 16
kilobytes, is that the message size that will help, or what is that? So the 16 kilobyte is a block
size, so it's the smallest amount of data that will go out, anything coming in or out of the
server will be a multiple of 16 kilobytes. Does that answer the question? Yeah. Okay, and
yes, correlation, there is the extra encryption on sending to the recipient, on the server
sending to the recipient of a message, to make sure that what comes in is never what goes out.
Yeah, so thanks for the talk. I think it's also read the protocol, and I thought it was a kind
of nice take to do something really new. However, I also thought that this is very much a privacy
focused, mostly privacy focused application, and for using broad scale communications with
other people, it has some big flaws, I would say, kind of hard to have this as the one
app to use. So, and especially for instance, if I were to have people contact me somehow,
well, should you have email as a fallback as the first point of contact? Or how would you go about
doing it? And what happened if you lose your device? Because if I understood correctly,
you can't really save your link to the persons you have, because then if you would use that
shared link again, then it will be an error. So think like, if you lose your device,
and you have, like, how would you go about doing it? And basically, can you see any problems,
as I will see, having this as the only app in big quotation marks? Thanks.
So let me confirm, I understood two questions. One question was how to use this for
inviting anybody to contact me, anybody I don't know to contact me. And the second one was about
how to handle the situation where I lose my device. Did I understand correctly? Okay,
so let's start with the first one. I mentioned, it was quick, sorry about that. There are two
kinds of invitations. There's a single use invitation, but there's also a multi use invitation.
And this is a multi use invitation. So it's possible to publish a multi use invitation
on a webpage, on a slide, and any number of people can use this to connect to, in this case,
the group. I could also put my own, like, one for me personally there, and I can revoke these
at some later time. I will, after the event, I will revoke this, so make sure to join now.
But I think the multi use invitation is the solution for the first. And the second part,
what do I do if I lose my device? Well, you restore the backup that you had made
on a new device. And personally, so once the multi device feature is available,
I'm really excited about this. I think this can work really for everyone and all use cases,
right? Okay, so there's this broadcast and super large group. That's also an important feature,
but I'm really enthusiastic about how this is going, and it's been around for not very long.
Thank you for the talk. Do you know if there's any progress on making a desktop client that's
not the CLI one they have, or if anybody's working independently on implementations in other languages
besides the Haskell? So I've seen that they have a to do for a desktop client. I don't know what the
status is, because I personally don't care, but a lot of people want that as well. That's true.
And other implementations, well, my fingers are itching to implement this myself. So maybe there
will be one at some point, but I'm not going to promise when. And other than that, I don't know.
You people should also create an implementation. Why not? It's pretty straightforward. And I think
that's a good also call for action to, well, either at a minimum integrate with what is there,
but also look at creating more implementations. Was there one more? Okay. Any other questions?
Is this related to the very similar looking protocols on the surface level from NOSTA and
precision? I don't know. I haven't looked at them.
Any other questions? Let's give a round of applause for Peter then.