Let's give a big hand to the last speaker, we have this here, Tyk with Goodbye World.
Thank you, everybody.
We are nearing the end of what has been an amazing BornHack 2023.
It is always a bit weird.
The week goes by incredibly fast, it feels like, and so much has happened that it can
be difficult to get your head around it.
We had some weather over the last couple of days.
We have reduced the number of pavilions significantly on the site.
I guess we can say that starting teardown early, unplanned teardown, most of the important
things are still standing and we hope that the worst of the weather has passed.
Especially right after this, where we hope to take down the big tent, please stay dry.
I have a lot of fun stats about the week that went by and some practical info.
I want to start out by talking a little bit about Graffen.
As you remember from Hello World, and as most of you know, we lost an organizer this year.
Last year, but between the last BornHack and this BornHack.
We have been struggling to figure out a good way to remember him and we've decided to plant
a tree here at Hylkedom.
It will be placed out here by the radio tower and it is being delivered the day after tomorrow.
Probably there's some logistics involved when you're getting a sizable tree delivered.
We hope it will be here no later than Thursday.
We have put up a mailbox in the bar where everybody is encouraged to write a letter
to Graffen and all the letters will be buried under the tree, put in the hole before we
put in the tree, when we put it in on Thursday or whenever it's going to be.
The mailbox is in the bar and we hope you will take time to write down some thoughts.
You will never read it.
So it's more for you than for anyone else.
The tree is a Silver Linden.
I don't know much about trees, but it's pretty and we hope it will be here for many years.
Okay, let's get on to the more fun stuff.
Statistics, we all love that, right?
The program grew significantly this year.
There was a few talks, but overall it was a more full program than it has ever been
before.
Thank you to everybody who submitted.
We had 23 of the regular talks, which is fewer than last year, 11 lightning talks, which
is quite a bit more than last year, 18 workshops, which is a lot and some of them were way overcrowded
so there could probably have been more.
We had the panel debate, which was, again, a great success, and 12 meetups this year,
which is double what we had last year, a couple of music acts and 19 recreational events,
various things submitted by villages and everything, and it's been so good to see all the activities
going on.
The content team has been working hard putting this together and all the people who submitted.
Thank you all.
Let's give everybody involved a big round of applause.
And, of course, let's not forget the video team, who are tirelessly working to stream
locally and stream online, and also everything is being recorded, so we can go, let's give
it a month.
We have to recover a bit, but pretty soon you'll be able to see it on media.ccc.de once we've
done the post-processing and stuff, and the video team has been handling all that like
So thank you for that.
The NOC team has, as always, delivered an impressive infrastructure out here in the
middle of nowhere.
We had a very fast doubling speed, so I think I saw a speed test from a tent of 8.5 gigabits
or something, and that's out to the outside world.
35 access points were put up by NOC for the Wi-Fi.
300, almost 350 unique connected devices, or no, max, simultaneous, I think it means.
Quite some data was pulled through our connection, 42 terabytes uploaded and 6 terabytes downloaded,
and of the 42 terabytes, a single tent and a single user is responsible for 90% of it,
so well done.
I happen to know it is data going through a really good course, so it is very good to
see.
Bar numbers, as you know, we depend on the bar to stay above water financially, and you
have been very good at using the bar.
We really appreciate it.
There's some impressive stats from down there.
They sold 3,700 things, over 2,600 transactions, 628 cocktails, I may be responsible for quite
a few of those, 619 litres of beer, I am absolutely responsible for zero of those, 445 litres
of mate, same, 17 tsunamis, I may also be involved there, and we had this year four
free cakes bought by participants in the bar and put up for free for everybody to drink,
three of them were weddings and the last one was 40 around birthday.
The bar has been open almost like I've been awake, there hasn't been many times where
I've walked by the bar and it's been closed, and it's down to an amazing bar team, both
constructing it and keeping it alive and involving over the week, and also cleaning
up and doing everything that's needed to keep the bar running.
Let's give them a big round of applause.
So the game team once again organised an amazing token game, it's sort of a treasure hunt for
little text rings all over the venue, they are offline and online and all over the place,
60 people took place in the contest and 27 tokens were found and 242 times a token was
found.
Game team, do we have a winner to announce?
They have been announced.
Oh, I didn't see, sorry.
The winner has been announced and I hope they are happy they got a free ticket for next
year's event.
Let's give them a big round of applause to the game team.
Between the token game and the jeopardy and everything, they are really doing a lot of
work that used to fall on Orga, so we are very, very happy with that and it's working
so well, so thank you.
The shuttle team has also been busy this year, they almost got out of it, we almost didn't
get a shuttle car but we managed to get one last minute thanks to Dennis who helped find
the sponsor.
The shuttle team does the drives back and forth to the station mostly and to the supermarket
occasionally.
47 trips and a lot of communication and coordination in the mailbox and a few jumping runs.
They are still doing shuttle runs, so when you need to leave tomorrow or whenever you
need to leave, you can write an email to the shuttle team and hopefully they can take you.
I don't even see, I hope Floma is here and some of the other shuttle team people because
they really provide a service that for participants at least makes it so much easier to get to
and from the event, so thank you to them.
The power team has again rolled out an impressive amount of copper on the venue, so we could
all get something resembling 230 volts.
It is tricky with the resources we have available and the way the power is wired on the venue,
it is very difficult to provide stable power at the voltages we would like to but they
are again and again proving that it can be done with a few low voltages here and there
and a few fallouts because of water in village equipment and stuff.
It is very hard to avoid completely because with the weather we have been having, it is
tricky keeping water out of everything.
When you do take down your village, please unplug stuff before you start touching the
roof and stuff so we don't get any outages during tear down.
The power team has been very quick to respond when there has been outages.
They go from distribution point to distribution point and try to turn it off and isolate and
eventually find the culprit and get it fixed and everybody has power again.
It is usually a quick process.
Thank you so much to the power team, Flemming and the others.
As you may know, we are about 10 people or 11 people in the organ group and it takes
maybe 50 people to run this event or more.
We would be unable to even begin considering doing this if we didn't get all the help
from all the volunteers, especially this year.
It has been a joy, there has been volunteer meetings every day at 14 in what used to be
the start center across from the info desk until it disappeared and people have been
willing and have been helping out even on their own discovering things and just putting
a message in the signal group, this was off.
I fixed it, you don't need to worry about it.
It is such a huge load of organ specs, which means that we've had excess cycles to do other
stuff that would usually pile up towards the end of the event, stuff like economy, stuff
that's usually lying because that can be pushed forward.
It means a lot to us because when we get home, we, like everybody else, need to wind down
and that's difficult when you know you have a pile of work waiting for you.
A lot of that has already been done from day to day and that's all thanks to all the volunteers.
Can everybody who helped out please stand up and be applauded?
We are preparing tear down right after this talk, we'll take down this tent, I'll talk
more about that after, but tomorrow at noon, the event is officially over and then we'll
start taking down power and network and all the infrastructure until noon tomorrow, there
will be full power and network and everything.
The only thing we are taking down is this tent, but we do need help with tear down so
if you have one or two extra days and you can stick around and help us sort, carry,
stack stuff, return it, get it ready to return to all the suppliers who are showing up Thursday
or Friday to do pickups, the more the merrier, we can always use more hands, Jonathan is
cooking from starting tomorrow evening and it's always, yes.
And it is actually always good fun even though it's of course hard work and you have a full
week of event and maybe even build up in your system already.
The more the merrier, not all of it is hard work and hopefully the weather will treat
us nicely and yeah, maybe some bio leftovers, it's usually a good time, fires every evening
and everything you can want.
All the work you could ask for.
Even a little helps, even half a day or something.
So please consider staying for tear down.
We had the first coordination meeting at 1600 in the bar start tent where we also had the
volunteer meetings during build up.
The tent is disassembling itself as we speak, it knows what's about to happen.
So at 16 tomorrow in the start tent by the bar we will have the first coordination meeting
and at 19 we will have the first official tear down meal and those of you who have tried
it before know after each meal they will be 9, 13 and 19, we have a coordination meeting
and hand out the tasks.
We have the venue until Saturday officially, we are aiming for most things to be fixed
by Friday, barring any violent weather or something can easily delay things but we think
we should be ready around Friday, Saturday.
We would like to know what you thought of the event, sometimes it's easier to sit down
and gather your thoughts and put it in writing and it's easier for us to remember.
For hack.dk slash feedback, please post positive and negative feedback, it's greatly appreciated
and there's also an option on the individual events in the program to give feedback to
the speaker about the event and that is also appreciated by the content team because then
they know what to get more of next year so the program can be even better.
If you lost anything or you found something then please take it to the info desk and we
will try to get it untangled and get the right stuff sent home with the right people so nobody
leaves anything in funeral.
Our food vendor will leave tomorrow around 14 so there's time to get lunch tomorrow and
then there will be a tear down meal in the dinner in the cabin from 19 but we are not
serving volunteer lunch tomorrow so make sure you eat on your own and then we will start
taking care of the meals starting tomorrow evening.
The food area tent will stay up until Thursday and we will start taking it down there so
there's also the option of cooking for yourself over the next couple of days.
The food area team has been keeping and we are talking about a two man army or two person
army has been keeping the food area so nice and tidy so let's give them a big round of
applause.
It's a fun story because we didn't quite understand what happened suddenly the food area started
being really messy and dirty and we had to get cleaners to fix it and everything and
it turned out that these two lovely people just missed a couple of born hacks and wasn't
doing all the cleaning they were usually doing and suddenly the absence of something like
that becomes very obvious when it's not there so they have been doing this.
We just maybe forgot to notice or appreciate it, fantastic work, thank you.
We have a tradition that goes back all the way to the first born hack that the speaker's
chair is built carefully and lovingly and artfully and then when we are done with it
we burn it and that's kind of a weird tradition but it is a tradition nonetheless and tomorrow
evening weather permitting or otherwise Thursday we are probably having a fire anyway but one
of these days the speaker's chair is going it's usually great fun we can get rid of some
hand sanitiser and the same while we are at it.
So post camp blues can be pretty rough being surrounded by so many lovely people and enjoying
the content and the environment and the community and the feeling of togetherness and then returning
to a pretty bleak reality on the outside of these walls can be a little rough and there's
nothing to do, you have to come down when you've been up but there are some suggested
remedies for when you feel the sadness, watch some of the talks you missed, we are getting
them up as soon as we can, you can play with your badge or some of the previous year's
badges, you can organise all your pictures and send the cool ones to us if they are in
a creative commons license so we can use them, we would greatly appreciate that.
Stay in touch online, we have the ISE channel, we have the signal groups, talk to old and
new friends, keep the community going throughout the year, buy a ticket for Born Hack 2024,
they will be for sale as soon as we've recovered from this during the fall at some point and
keep on hacking.
Born Hack 2024 has moved forward slightly, it is scheduled for the 17th to the 24th of
July 2024, it's a Wednesday to Wednesday, we realise moving it is going to be inconvenient
for some people, for other people it will be convenient, there's no way to make everybody
happy with this, the current dates like mid August that we've been doing for some years,
conflict with the big German and Dutch camps in a way that makes it really difficult for
us to get the venue because this venue has to be booked about two years in advance and
when the big Dutch and German events don't decide on that date until eight months before,
then we have, as you can see, an impossible job of picking a date that doesn't conflict
because we are the small camp, if we end up being at the same time as the CCC camp or
the Dutch events, we will lose, even Orga would not show up because we want to go to
the big events too.
So we want to avoid that and moving it ahead of it means that we dodge both the big German
and the big Dutch events, there will be other conflicts, some people might be unable to
attend that have been coming for years, we are very sorry about that, hopefully this
will allow other people to come and at the very least it will make it so we don't have
to ask the venue people to move, other people who rented the venue where we needed, so they
have to cancel other renters at the Hylke Dam so they can fit us in, they did it twice
and we have been here in four years and it's too stressful and too much to ask, we cannot
keep doing this and we cannot demand from CCC or the Dutch events that they put their
dates out several years in advance, that's not going to happen, the only way we can do
this is to kind of roll with the punches and move to a place in the calendar that doesn't
have so many big events.
So Pornhack 2024 will be from the 17th to the 24th of July, we hope very much to see
you all there.
Speaking of avoiding Hacker Blues, another way of doing that is just to keep on talking,
when we are done with Teardown we will repeat our great success from 2019 where the CCC
camp was also right after Pornhack, what we did was basically finish Teardown, pack everything
and then do a big convoy of 10-15 vehicles and just drive down there with radios and
everything, it was amazingly good fun and we arrived at CCC camp, maybe one vehicle
didn't get there until 48 hours later, that's quite a story, you can ask Omni about that,
but mostly it went very well and we are repeating it so as soon as we are done here everybody
gets in their cars and we drive to CCC camp.
You are welcome to, if you need to leave and come back, you can do that, but most people
will probably stay and help with Teardown and then leave when we are done.
It should be good fun and it's a good way to recover from, what better way to recover
from Pornhack than by going to another Hacker camp.
Okay, we have some inventory left in the bar that we don't want to carry around too much,
we would like all of you to take it home, so we are selling boost bottles and infodesk
at reduced prices, you can get a full bottle for 200 Hacks instead of 300 and there's Akhavit
and Vodka and Saber Blurter up there, also Mate and Beer I think.
It should be already ready in the infodesk, I don't think they will open about now and
be open today and also tomorrow, so when you leave or are about to leave, consider going
by there and getting some nice Saber Blurter or Akhavit or Vodka to take home, it is also
a good way to get rid of the Hacker Blues.
Okay, I'm almost done, we would like some help right now with taking down the speakers
tent, this is a massively parallelizable job, we could almost do it with a GPU, but we do
need some help, so it is, once people get up and start running around, it gets a bit
chaotic, so I'm going to go over it slowly and explain what we would like and once we
start, please everybody be careful, nobody hurt themselves, we used to time the taking
down of the speakers tent, we don't do that anymore because people are way too competitive
and will end up hurting themselves and we of course don't want that.
We have a bunch of helmets that we are getting for when the frame has to come down, but before
the very first thing is you get up, take the chair you are sitting on and take it to the
car, park right outside and stack it inside that, I'm guessing two people inside it to
stack and then an anthill of people taking out chairs, after that we take out all the
tables, there is a row of metal frames out here, the tables go on the metal frame, 20
high or so and then they get a ratchet strap, there will be organisers in these black organ
vests at all the stacks and they know, all of them know how to stack it, so there is
nothing worse than having to re-stack a stack of tables that turned out to be stacked wrongly
or a stack of floor plates in two or three days before they pick it up because our arms
are hanging down there at that point, so let's get it right the first time, so it is much
better to do it a little slowly, a little more slowly than to get it wrong and we have
to redo it, and especially the tables and the floor plates have historically been sources
of re-stacking work, so let's get it right and just check with the vests before you leave
anything even though you think you might know how, it's a very, we are all very capable
in our daily work and it's easy to, I know how to do this, I will just get it going,
but please check with somebody in a vest before you place things, the chairs go to the Oscar
van, the tables go on the frames out here and the floors go on the wooden pallets that
have the big wooden plates on top, the floors kind of snap into each other when you stack
them so it's not like a pile, it's a very neat pile when you are done, so they click
into each other so they are completely straight, the sides, so if they are not straight they
have to be re-stacked, so put it down, get it into place so it clicks in and then put
the next one in.
The video team will start taking down all this stuff and they will handle that themselves,
so tables and chairs and when we are done with that we can start taking up the floor
and putting that down and taking down the sides and folding those and putting them on
the pallets.
If you have questions or doubts then stop working and just stand around and look what
others are doing or come ask an Oscar person, much rather get it right than doing it twice.
That is it, we love you all, we will see you next year and thank you for everything.