That's become possible, at least for all my webcam and screen share videos.
So I'm going to share that with you today, how that is helping me, and hopefully you
can get some inspiration from that.
Either to improve your own setup or to see, hey, okay, that's maybe not so difficult.
Maybe I can start putting some videos out there as well.
So that's it.
Why am I doing this?
Well, that's because 11 years ago I quit my daytime job to become a writing instructor.
A year later I figured out that being a self-employed writing instructor with a small kid and a
family you want to see sometimes, that's not super easy.
So I decided I would try to take some of my teaching online.
Back then, ten years ago, we were like two people in Denmark who did online courses on
horse training.
So people were a bit like, oh, that's weird, but also pretty interested because it brought
some knowledge to them that they had a hard time obtaining in other ways without driving
a long while to get there or something like that.
So this is me ten years ago, almost to the date, end of August 2013, doing my first ever
webinar on horse training.
With a grainy webcam, probably the one that was actually built into my laptop and not
very good lightning, not very good sound.
Well, the sound was semi-decent, but everything was pretty blurry and not so super.
Also the internet connection back then was terrible.
But I managed.
It improved a wee bit pretty fast by switching webinar provider.
I've always been sort of both compassionate but also a bit picky about how my teaching
content shall be because I know it makes a difference for people.
I've used to be a teacher and I know it makes a difference to people if you're just providing
them talking slides or if you actually are there on webcam.
If it's a grainy old webcam with a fuzzy image, it makes a difference that people can actually
see you and can feel a connection to you when you're teaching online.
So I upgraded my system to something where I actually felt that they could see me better.
And that worked.
Then I started doing also not just live webinars but also recording videos.
And this here, this is some of the videos that took a long time to produce compared
to the video time because I had to record the slides presentation first or have the
images for that and put into my video editor.
Then I had to sit there and talk about the slides, record that, put them together, put
the logo on, put the text on, and that took usually longer than actually doing the video.
Then the video had to process afterwards before I could upload it.
It was boring.
That is like 2015.
Then in 2018, as I said, I met OBS at my first hack.
I had been looking at it previously because I heard someone talk about it at some marketing
webinar I had attended, but it was like, ah, it's difficult and I don't really know what
to do about it.
But then when I had my hands in it at BornHack, I was like, yeah, okay, oh, so there's something
about scenes and there's something about sources, ah, I get that now.
I can go back and use this.
Still took me six months because as far as I could tell when I was digging through my
archives yesterday, I only started using OBS in January 2019.
So that's like almost four and a half years ago now.
This is one of the first attempts.
Did a video series where I put myself in the corner and I had some background images that
I could switch like slides and that worked really well and it was still like a one-take
video.
Of course, doing one-take videos means that you need to actually know what you're going
to talk about and not make that many mistakes and stuff, but today, I much rather do if
I'm doing like a 10-minute video, I try not to make them longer, but if I'm doing like
a 10-minute video or a five-minute video, if something goes wrong, I just restart.
It's a lot faster than actually having to go back and edit out a cough attack or whatever.
So it really, really helps my flow in content creation.
This is then in May 2019 where I started doing screen share videos.
My business had then moved on from doing, as you can see, this has not much to do with
horses.
I'm now primarily teaching other people how to use the online course and email marketing
system called Simpliro.
I've been doing that since 2015, 2016, where it slowly took over.
So today, my main video production is videos where I'm on screen share and I show something
from inside Simpliro and tell people how to set up a course or create an email series
or do fancy automation stuff.
I started doing these courses also back in some time in 2019.
And this is what it looked like back then.
And this is then what it looks like today.
I've gone to green screen, so now I can just put myself in without sitting in a square
with some sort of background.
That's really nice and that's also built in in OBS.
Also I use this to stream.
This is actually from, I have like a membership club for people who are using Simpliro and
we do monthly themes and they are like live streamed to we have a Facebook group.
So I live stream it to the Facebook group using OBS.
So I get a high quality local recording of the stream because then it's not the stream,
then it's just what's happening on my desktop.
Then I also stream it to Facebook and then afterwards I take the recorded video from
my desktop computer and upload it to the course material in Simpliro.
So I have both this option.
I don't know, you're probably not that much of a Facebook crowd, but in Facebook, if you
do live, you can either do screen share or do webcam.
You can't combine them.
When I use OBS to stream, I can combine totally like I want.
So I have full control and I get the local recording in high quality and I could also
use this to stream to YouTube or any other service where you can stream with a stream
key.
So that's really, really nice and that makes my work so much easier also.
I've also been doing like if you want to teach something about like a creative process or
thought process, then it's not always the best.
People get so much, especially during Corona, people had so much of everything being online
and people just doing talking slide presentations and it kind of gets boring.
If you need to keep people's attention, then you should mix things up.
So what I have on my desk is I have a second webcam mounted on an arm so I can take that
and point it down on my desk and then I can have a writing pad and I can sketch up things
either if I want to design flows or I want to sketch out a thought process or whatever
it is I want to do.
I can actually do that and put that on webcam as well and then I still have myself down
in the corner so I can also look up, put down the pen and sit there and talk to people.
And this is I know from my students that they are like really happy about this way of doing
things.
I could also be standing by a white board or whatever I wanted to do that was like something
else.
I had been looking into, oh, maybe I should get one of those fancy drawing pads for my
computer and because I wanted to do some live drawing stuff and then I was like hmm, I have
an extra webcam, I have pen, I have paper, how does that work?
And that actually works excellent.
So that's a way of mixing things up and that's totally easy to set up several camera sources
in OBS.
And I can switch between the scenes so that I can do this and then I can switch to another
scene where I have screen share or I can switch to another scene where it's just me on webcam
and I can sort of spice my teaching up a bit without having to do all that editing that
For me, I know some people are probably editing faster than me but for me at least it takes
a lot of time and it isn't really worth it.
I could maybe get like two, three, four, five percent fancier videos if I decided to do
after editing but that's really, really not worth it.
So this is how things look today.
This is how it looks from inside OBS and in a second I'm going to switch over so you
can see I'm going to open OBS here on my machine and then we can take a look at how does this
actually work?
How do we set it up?
What do you need to be aware of?
And then there will be some room for questions.
So yeah, I wanted to show you my setup as well.
So this is my desktop at home being unusually tidy.
So I have like two screens because if you're working with OBS you can do that in a one
screen setup but it's really, really, really nice to have like two screens so you can have
whatever you are, if you're doing a screen share, then you have whatever you're working
with on the front screen and then you have OBS or if you have some chat you need to pay
attention to, you have that on the other screen.
That's a really, really big help and I also highly recommend that even if you don't use
OBS, if you're doing any other sort of webinars or anything where you need to be able to both
screen share something or have your slides and also keep an eye on a chat or some other
tech that is running, it's really, really, really a lot easier if you have at least two
screens.
I teach a lot of my clients are like not very techy and when I come and say yeah, you should
probably get an extra screen and they're like but I only have my MacBook and then we'll
have to figure out how to attach an extra screen because it's just so much easier.
I have a microphone and I have an external webcam and that's basically it.
What you maybe can see in the corners of the desk is I have a couple of that's like 20
halogen, not halogen, LED working lights that are pointing away from me because they create
a pretty good ambient light so that's a lot easier than buying some very fancy studio
lights.
If you have some white or whitish walls that you can throw the light up on and then it
comes back, that really makes a big difference.
I tried buying one of them famous ring lights because they're so fancy, right?
But I have glasses and if you have glasses and you're sitting in front of a ring light,
you have ring light in your glasses and that doesn't really look that good on videos.
Actually, you can see it in the, it's also reflected in the eyes of people that have
ring lights, you can see it inside the irises.
So I still have the ring light but now it's mounted under the ceiling and it's also pointing
away from me so it's creating ambient light instead of shining directly in my eyes.
So that's the setup.
I also bought a low noise mouse and keyboard because I found out at some point that when
I was sitting doing things and setting things up and I needed to type, all that typing,
especially with the microphone so close to the keyboard, that was sort of annoying.
But basically, I would say get a decent webcam, get a second monitor so you have at least
two.
And you can see here, this is my green screen setup so this image is looking the other way.
My office is not very big and I have my bag up to what you call a cabinet with glassware.
It's brown, it's not very pretty, it showed on some of my first webinar videos.
Then I got a white roller blind that I mounted in the ceiling so I could roll that down when
I was doing videos and I could pull it up again when I needed to go to the cupboard
behind me and now I've upgraded that so now I have mounted just basically a piece of vibrant
green sheet on the roller blind, fastened with magnets so it's easy to remove, and that's
my green screen.
And that's working really, really well.
So that's like a super cheap setup to get a green screen so you can remove your background,
put yourself in any background you want.
Even when I'm doing, I do a lot of Zoom meetings and Zoom also has all these virtual backgrounds
things, but you can really, really see if people, I'm sure you have had meetings with
people that are using virtual background and are not sitting on like a uniform background
then if they have a headset on, sometimes the headset disappears, sometimes their ears
disappear, sometimes their arms disappear, if you're using a green screen and you tell
Zoom that you actually have a green screen, it is working much, much better.
So you won't be as fussy as the usual virtual background function.
So I really like that.
It has upped my game a lot.
Cheers.
Yeah.
I think that was the last slide.
Yes, it was.
Good.
So, OBS, open broadcaster software.
It's open source, so it's free.
It's running on Windows, Mac, Linux.
I'm on a Linux machine.
And it runs really, really well.
It also has a built-in virtual webcam function.
So like if you're using some program where you need to put in your webcam that, for instance,
the software I use for, I use this really, it's a nice software to do webinars in called
Webinar Jam, but their customer support is like really, really crappy, so I can't really
recommend them.
But I signed up so long ago that I'm like grandfathered into the big plan forever.
So hey, it works.
And I like to use it, but I don't really recommend it.
But they don't have a streaming function.
I can't get a stream key for them and say I just want to stream my OBS feed into Webinar
Jam.
I have to use my webcam.
And can of course do slides and webcam stuff, but now they have sort of a virtual background
function for the webcam, but it's not very good.
So I'm like I would much rather just take my OBS feed, put that into Webinar Jam, or
whatever else service I'm using.
And now there's a virtual webcam function in OBS, so I can just tell Webinar Jam to
use my virtual webcam.
That's not super, there's sometimes a bit of a delay, so it's not necessarily super
good for Zoom meetings.
You can do it.
But those realtime meetings, maybe not always the good solution, but it can be done.
But it works super well for webinars, and that makes it a lot easier.
And I don't have to use all the controls in the webinar program to switch between slides
and webcam, and I just do everything in OBS as I used to do, and I can even make the local
recording in OBS as well to get the high quality recording that I want.
So I love OBS.
It's like one of my absolutely favorite tools.
So what does it look like?
I do run a slightly old version on my laptop for some reason.
So it might look slightly different if you go and install a new version now.
I just only realized a few days ago, and then I didn't want to rock the boat by running
a big upgrade.
But the principles are the same.
What we have here is you can put it in, down here I have studio mode.
This is what we have here where we have like a preview screen and a program screen.
Actually those of you that can see the setup up here where we're using the black magic
box, it has the same principle.
You have program, that is what we are streaming live or showing or recording.
Preview is what we will, if we click the transit button, get instead of what we are recording
or streaming now.
So that's like the main setup that we have these two scenes that we're looking at.
And a scene in OBS is like a combination of sources.
So you can have a number of scenes that you're switching between.
This scene I have right here.
And this is if it's in studio mode.
I can also just say I'm only doing like one scene.
I don't want the studio mode thing.
But I really like that I can have usually what I'm doing is I have one scene that is
just me on webcam, maybe with a background image of like I have a starting slide or something
like that or title slide.
So I have that as the background.
And then I switch to me with screen share and the webcam.
And of course at home I have the green screen.
So what we have here is we put in the scene.
So we have a scene.
And we can rename that to something that makes sense.
So we could call this one.
That didn't really work.
Yes.
Yes, it did work.
Okay.
So we call this webcam and screen.
So that's one scene.
And I can have here I have now I have adjusted some resolution.
So I have to like if I can do this.
I'm moving that one too.
This is a lot easier with a real mouse, you know.
There we go.
And now I move the video capture device somewhere else.
I need to grab that and drag it back in.
There it goes.
There.
So I can put myself in the corner here.
Here it goes.
Yes.
So that is like we have a screen with screen share and the webcam.
That would be a quite usual setup for me.
I could also put in my logo and some text at the bottom if I wanted to do that.
Then if I say, hey, I want to have another screen that is just me on the webcam, maybe,
then I go and say here I can add a scene.
There's a little plus down here.
So I add a scene and then we call that just webcam.
And it's a really good idea.
Tiny piece of advice.
Label your scenes in a sane way.
Because like three years later when you're running still on the same setup and you have
like 20 different scenes and they are all labeled something weird, it makes it a bit
hard to go in and see what is actually the two scenes I need to use today.
That will of course never happen to you, but that happened to me.
So label it.
Then we have to go here and see now it says here we don't have any sources.
Yes, I know.
So I go and add a source.
And I say I want, since this one was supposed to be webcam only, I go and add a video capture
device.
And since I already have an input device for my built-in webcam, I just go and say I want
to add this one.
So I click add existing and then I can take this one and I can say okay.
So now I have the webcam.
Then we can say and it's 4 by 3, it's not 16.9.
So I can go and right click this one.
And we can say settings, properties.
I'm going to show you how to do the green screen as well in a moment.
So I have here, I can see what's the device, it's input one, what's the video format, resolution.
Then I can say hey, can this actually do, it can do 1280 by 720.
So that's at least 16.9, that was what I wanted.
I can change the frame rate.
So it can only do a frame rate of 10 if I set the resolution to 720, so that's maybe
not so impressive.
And there's also something about color range.
This is also where you can experiment with if your color settings are not correct, if
you need it to zoom in or something like that.
You set that here under setting for the camera.
You have all these settings here and set the power line frequency to 50 and stuff like
that.
So you have all the controls for your webcam inside OBS as well.
Now we change the resolution, so now it got way too big.
That was not what I tried to do.
So we just need it to fit here, so that goes fits.
So if this was at home and I was using my green screen, then I would also add the filter,
because green screen, that lives in filters.
So I go down here to the bottom and I pick filters.
And then I can say I want to add an effect filter if I could get to the bottom of this.
My screen is too small.
How do I do that?
Now that's a good question.
There it goes.
So here I have the effect filters and I want to add that.
And I have what's called a chroma key.
And that is the chroma, that's something with color.
So we need to fill that out and call this one green screen.
So I can remember what it is.
And then I can choose what type of screen I'm sitting with.
Do I have a green, blue, magenta or custom color?
Sometimes you need to say custom and then give it a slightly, if your green screen is
a different shade of gray, or not gray green, you might have to tell it exactly what color
green your green screen is.
But otherwise just go with green and then you can experiment with these.
So now there's like nothing green behind me.
So it isn't working.
But what you need to do is you need to experiment a bit with similarities, smoothness and spill
reduction to make it fit your setup with your webcam, your lightning, the exact color of
your green screen.
So that it actually removes the background but it doesn't remove all of you or you don't
get green hair unless you have that already.
If you have green hair already, green screen is a really bad idea.
Also don't wear green clothes.
Don't wear a multicolored scarf with green stuff.
I've had issues when I've been wearing this old born hack or born hack t-shirts with the
green logo on them.
Then you can see it's a minor detail but then you'll suddenly see then you become transparent
where the logo is and you can see the back, what it was behind you in the layers here
on the screen that they will appear through whatever green clothing you have on.
I still haven't, I need to get like a long-sleeved green roller neck sweater to play around with.
I haven't gotten to that but I think that would be fun.
So you could be a talking head as well.
Exactly, then I can become totally a talking head in the middle of the screen and also
need some green gloves.
I had an issue once where I did a webinar where I needed to talk about, that was on
horse training, where I needed to talk about comfort zone or zone of development or zone
of danger.
So where you are, are you comfortable or are you, it's a bit exciting or a bit too interesting
but it's still okay or is it feeling really dangerous?
I had three pieces of paper, a green, a yellow and a red.
And whenever I hold up the green piece of paper it just disappeared and showed the background
and I was like, oh I need to do something else about this.
I had to figure out a way to actually, I think I found a very different shade of green paper
and then it kind of worked but you have to think about what you're doing when you're
using green screen like this because it actually filters out anything green.
So that will give some interesting effects sometimes.
But it is pretty easy to just put this in.
Also if I wanted to have maybe that, okay now I wanted to be used the 16.9 and not the
3 output of my webcam but I want to just cut a wee bit off in the sides.
I could put in another filter as well.
I think, yeah, that's like a crop.
So I could say like, we just call that crop, whatever.
And then I can say, okay, so on the left I want to crop 100 pixels.
And on the right I want to crop 100 pixels, there it goes.
If I for some reason wanted to do that.
So now my input is smaller and then maybe I want to turn it to the side, maybe I want
to put it in the middle, whatever.
But I have put like a bit of cropping on the sides without altering the input format.
So that can also be helpful.
That can also be helpful if you have your webcam put in a position where it, of course,
if you need the entire width of the webcam, that's not a good solution, but if you have
a corner that will always be shown on your webcam where your green screen isn't covering
or something like that, you can just crop that out without actually having to alter
the resolution.
So now if I say I have this, I want to now do my live presentation or something like
that, then I'll have to set up some streaming.
And I do that by going here to tools, I think.
Nope.
Settings.
Here, under file we have settings.
And then I have like, there's like a ton of settings and it's, you basically start with
the default settings and then see where that takes you.
One of the things I really, really also like about using OBS, that is, because it's open
source, it has so many users and there's like a ton of videos on YouTube about using OBS.
So if you find a function and you're a bit like, hmm, how should I do that, go Google,
find a video on YouTube, see what people say, check out a different couple of videos to
see who is saying something sensible.
Because it's usually very easy to find information on whatever it is you need.
That also means if you have some sort of issue, there's someone, probably someone who already
had that, if you have an issue with a specific webcam that isn't working or something like
that, there's a good chance that someone else has already had that problem and have solved
it.
I really like that.
And also because it is a program that is widely used, there's a lot of development going on,
so there's continuously coming new versions.
But what we wanted to look at is, we might look at the output first.
Because if I want to do a recording, I want to make sure that I'm actually recording in
the format that I would like.
So I say, yes, we want the encoder to be 264, that makes sense.
Something about the audio bit rate, that's probably okay.
We can turn on some advanced encoder settings, but usually that's not necessary.
And we can say, what is the recording quality?
Stream a stream, that's usually recommended, because if the computer needs to both create
a stream in one resolution and a video output in another resolution, it has to work harder.
If you have a big computer with a lot of resources, that's not a problem.
If you're working on a laptop, then maybe you need to do that.
Actually it says here, recordings cannot be paused if the recording quality is set to
same stream.
Yeah, that kind of makes sense.
There is now, there wasn't when I started, but now there is a pause function, so if you're
doing something and then you hit a snack and you need to investigate something, that happens
a lot when I do videos.
It's like when you sit with a live piece of software and you demo that, there might be
something weird going on sometimes.
So sometimes if I'm like five minutes into a video and I've been demoing some new feature
and then something unexpected happens, what I do instead of having to start over is I
say just a second, I'll investigate this and then I hit the pause button, that's if I'm
not live, then I hit the pause button and then I can go investigate and figure out have
I misunderstood this feature, do we have a bug, is this doing what it's actually supposed
to do, did I just click something wrong, what happened?
And then I can go back to OBS and my screen share and I can pick up where I left and
I can say okay, so what we need to do is this, this, this, instead of having to restart the
recording and start from the beginning.
So recording format, it defaults to Matroska which usually works really, really well.
There's also audio settings, video settings.
So we have like the canvas resolution and then we have the output resolution.
So the canvas resolution, that's what we are working on in the program or preview and
then we have the output scale resolution and we need to have the, you can see here like
the aspect ratio on the canvas is 1600 to 899, that's like as close to 16.9 as you'll
get, right?
I'm not really sure what happened to the last pixel here since it's not 1600 by 900 but
hey, yeah, we have a question there, can you hand him to me?
Then I'll just grab a bit of water and I need to hurry up.
What's the point of having a canvas bigger than what we are going to actually output
because scaling might get lost?
Yeah, you are absolutely right.
Usually I would also, I'm not quite sure why it has default to the 1600, I would usually
make those the same because it's annoying and I would usually set this to 1080 for output
because then I get like the maximum quality on my videos.
One of the things you need to be aware of if you are screen sharing is that if you are
using like 1080 and people are maybe watching it on their phones or on a smaller screen
size then things will become rather tiny where they are looking like nice and sharp on your
big screen.
Then you can in your browser when you are visiting any page, I have like a really crappy
resolution here, but if you are on a page that you want to screen share and you are
working in a high resolution and you want your audience to have a chance to actually
pick up on what you are doing you can use control and plus and I usually run on 125
percent zoom because that actually makes it a lot easier for my audience to see what's
going on if they are sitting on a smaller screen than me and I can keep the high resolution
quality on the videos, on the webcam, on everything.
I kind of like that.
Yeah, we have another question there.
So this is also regarding the base canvas resolution and the output scaled resolution.
So for example I am doing a broadcast or recording on my computer but my computer has
a 4K screen, here is where I can choose what people see is just 1080p and it does the downscaling.
And I saw there is also a recording option and the recording is also the downscaled version.
Thank you.
And that's a good point and also if you are using background images it's a really good
idea that whatever background image you are using is actually your canvas size.
So if I have a 1600 by 900 canvas size I should make my background images that size because
then I don't have to scale them then I will get a better quality.
So that's good to keep in mind.
The last thing I wanted to show you before we have time for a few questions more that's
like the stream, you just go to the stream here and then you choose whatever service
it is.
They have some predefined sources you can use.
I found out that choosing Facebook live actually doesn't work.
I usually need to say custom, not Twitch, custom, there it goes.
And then from my Facebook it tells me the server and it tells me the stream key.
And in Facebook I can set up so that I have for the same Facebook page I have a recurring
stream key so I don't have to go into OBS every time and change the stream key.
That is of course less secure.
If someone should obtain my stream key they can now stream to my Facebook groups but the
The risk of that happening is not enormous and if it happens I can go and reset my stream
key but you of course need to be aware that that's the risk of reusing stream keys but
it's a lot easier that you don't have to go into OBS every time and paste in the new stream
key when you're going live.
There's also you can program hot keys and there's other settings.
But basically this is OBS, this is my Swiss army knife for video production.
I love working in it.
It saves me, I have no idea over the last now four and a half years how many hours of
editing work this has saved me.
I just love that I can get an idea to a video, I can create the setup, usually it's only
like editing a small piece of text or something like that in the scenes I already have.
I sit down, I click record, I show whatever it is I want to show.
This could also be something to a client if I need to tell them how to set up something
specific in their Simplio account, I go into their Simplio account.
I do a short recording with OBS, I upload it to their account, I send them an email
and say hey here's the video and I don't need to do any after processing the Matroska video
is just ready to use as soon as I hit stop recording on OBS.
I love it, it's fantastic.
Yeah, any questions?
Hello again, so the question I have is I use, I personally use a fork of OBS but I'm considering
using OBS itself because it's well maintained.
The software I use is also an older version and I only have a single screen and you early
showed you have a studio mode and a single mode screen thingy.
Yeah, so studio mode is just switching between showing like two, both the preview and the
program or only having.
So mine looks like this and when you were doing your talk in studio mode I saw when
you were building scenes you can just play around in the scene adding sources and on
the right side for us that is what is live and then the left side is?
The left side is always preview and the right side is always live.
How do you push the preview to the live?
Then I just hit transition and then I switch to the new scene.
Because for example when I do a broadcast or at work I need to present something, sometimes
they ask something I need to pull in a terminal or maybe I need a scene with a terminal in
it.
But I was just wondering with this mode I can check for myself something first and then
push it to live?
And then press it to program.
Thank you.
And you said there were virtual webcams, is that you can designate pretty much the video
output of any app, of any window that is running on your machine.
You can designate that to be a virtual webcam?
Yes, because then whatever is running in program will then be shown on the virtual webcam.
It's a pretty cool feature, for a long while it was like a special plugin on Windows where
they had it on Linux where they had it on Windows and I also think Mac but now it's
built in from the beginning.
Hi, I've heard that the Linux version of OBS is more limited than the Windows version,
is that still the case?
I think so, yes.
One of the specific examples was the virtual webcam where you needed a special plugin that
someone else had created for the Linux version that is now built in.
And there are some other limitations but I've been running this on Linux for four and
a half years and I'm happy, happy.
You can't remember any other limitations?
No, no, I haven't met anything where I've been limited and then what usually happens
is if I find something and I start Googling and then they say hey there's this function
you blah blah and then I see oh okay so that's like a Windows function and then I Google
a bit more and then I find out okay so that's not available on Linux yet but it's so far
the only thing I've seen was the virtual webcam function.
Okay, thank you.
Hello again.
So as I said I do presentations at work, you know, Monday meetings but I'm considering
live streaming.
Yeah.
I'm not sure what I'm going to do yet.
In the settings you were scrolling through like the video and audio and I saw shortcuts.
When you're recording for yourself or doing a presentation, do you use any shortcuts for
like scene changing?
I do that.
If I use more than two or three scenes, I can put shortcuts on specific scenes so that
I know that if I hit F2 or something like that it will in the preview switch to a specific
scene so I don't have to scroll and look for it.
I can just hit a button that was also what we had on the video box set up here way back
when when we used OBS and that works really nicely because that's a big help if you have
many scenes you're switching between.
I'll assume that all the shortcuts are defaulted in the application and you don't need to add
yourself because when I was researching a week ago when I looked on YouTube to some
reviews about OBS, they all most of them suggested to get one of these devices with like multiple
buttons and so on but they're very pricey so I was wondering if everything is just doable
on just a regular keyboard with your computer or on the laptop.
I actually can't remember.
Yeah, see you have here like start streaming, stop streaming.
You have keys for that that you can put in.
I'm guessing then you just put in the key combination you want but there's also a way
to put key shortcuts on your specific scenes.
I just can't remember how.
I can't remember how you do that but there's a way to do it.
You can bind a shortcut to a specific scene.
Yeah, there's a way to do that but I just can't remember right now how you do that.
It's there.
Yeah.
The green screen function, does it have to be green or can you designate pretty much
any color to be black?
You can use other colors and you can tell OBS exactly what color you have.
Some colors work better than others and you also have to consider but like if your brand
colors are green and you're wearing a lot of green, you need to figure out another
color because otherwise everything will be very weird.
So you can do other colors.
Blue is another traditional color for, then it's blue screen instead of green screen.
That also works really well.
So it works better if it's a primary color.
Yeah, so you just need to and you can in the chroma key settings you can specify the color
of your green screen.
Yeah.
Any more questions?
No?
If you get any questions, then you're welcome to stop me on the street here and say hi or
send me an email or anything.
I'll be happy to answer your questions.
Please give a big round of applause to Mariette.
Thank you.