So, welcome to the first real talk at Born Hack 2023.
First of all, I would like to, and then you can clap afterwards.
I would like to announce that there's still slots available for massage today.
If you go to the webshop, if you have some sore muscles that need massaging,
the guy who's doing the massages is really, really good.
So, please go to the webshop on the Born Hack website and book a massage.
There's also slots on Saturday, I think.
So, yeah, I promise to announce that.
Then, let's give a big welcome to Flummer, who's going to talk about this year's batch.
So, welcome.
I know that the batches are not available at the Info Desk yet, but they will be.
They are here.
We need to put some firmware and stuff on them, program them,
and they will be available as soon as we can get them there.
So, this year, we are playing with NFC.
It's a technology that has sort of moved into a lot of everyday things in recent years.
And I'll start by going through a little bit what NFC is and how it works,
and then we'll go into the more details of how the batch is set up.
So, NFC is short for Near Field Communication,
and it's a sort of radio frequency identification and building on top of that.
It uses the 13.56 megahertz band,
which is also known as the high frequency RFID.
It's mostly used for short distances, so places where we can get fairly close.
It doesn't work from like meters away.
In theory, you can get up to meters, but in practice,
that will not happen with anything that resembles a regular antenna.
And it's also designed for very sort of low data rates, low information.
And most often, you see it in little plastic cards like these.
Usually, they have print on them with marketing or whatever,
but it's hidden away in these plastic cards.
There are also other types of RFID just to sort of give a scope.
So, the sub-130 kilohertz stuff.
The older access systems, like for doors getting into buildings,
server rooms, and so on, often use the 125 kilohertz band here in Europe, at least.
And those only had an ID. There was nothing else.
It was just this ID number, and nowadays, they are very easy to crack.
It's copy them is not a problem.
They're still used for like simpler stuff in this frequency range.
It's also used for animal tracking.
So, if you put a little chip in your pet, when your cat runs away,
somebody finds it, they can scan that chip and get the ID out,
and then they can look up who's owner of this pet.
Another use of RFID is the 430 megahertz band in Europe
and the 900 megahertz band in the US for shipping containers
and inside a factory floor, controlling little boxes moving around and so on.
That's also known as UFHF, ultra-high frequency.
And then there's the toll booth systems, the little storebills or whatever,
when you go through these bridges and so on.
They use 2.4 gigahertz.
So, those are the other kinds of RFID stuff.
But for this, we will focus on the NFC that is sort of in the middle here.
They are most commonly, like pretty much anybody,
if you probably have a payment card that has NFC in it,
it's the tab to pay the contactless payment that usually speeds up the processing in the store.
You don't have to enter your PIN if it's low amounts and so on.
They have become very popular.
The stores love them because they can handle more customers in the same time and so on.
And also, they don't break as easily, like the chip might get dirty and the contact doesn't work.
The chip, you can pretty much run it through the washing machine and it will still work.
Also, travel cards. Here in Denmark, we have these Leizakorps things.
They are also NFC-based.
And access control.
Some places you might switch from the older RFID stuff,
the Prox or the EM4100, to NFC to get more security.
But in many cases, it's also because you want functionality.
So, like a hotel updating their system.
They can actually use the data on these cards to prevent having to wire every single lock
in every single room of their building so that you can have some intelligence there
and a little bit of crypto to protect stuff.
And if it's not super high security, that will work okay.
The building where I have an office recently changed to NFC bricks
because they could simply change the lock part of the lock without taking any wires.
There's a little battery in there.
But then they can do functionality where some users can access some doors,
others can't access the others and so on.
But every user only have one little brick or card or something.
Another place where NFC is used, not as common as the other ones,
but it's like at museums where you want to augment the exhibits in different ways.
Where you have a phone, you can get a URL or something similar to QR code being used
where you can scan the QR code.
But here with NFC instead, there can maybe be a little more data in there.
Smart posters and that sort of things.
And then there's also provisioning.
So when you get a little home device of some sort that needs to connect to a Wi-Fi,
you need to have some credentials and so on.
NFC can also be used for that.
So if you have an app for that device,
then you can just touch your phone up to the little NFC antenna on the device,
and then you can communicate and put in the credentials.
So sort of getting a device on your network, little IoT stuff and so on.
That sort of mechanism is actually what the little part on the tag of the badge
is actually meant for that because it has a dual interface.
And the last one I mentioned here is a trigger for tasks.
So many smartphones have these NFC stuff built in nowadays.
And since there's a unique ID in all the tags, well, unique,
then they can be used to trigger things.
So you can have like a little tag next to your bed.
So when you put your phone there, it can sort of read that tag
and then run some commands in your home automation or whatever.
It could possibly be other things.
We can sort of pre-program things where you simply just tap your phone,
maybe as part of another operation where you put it to charge or whatever.
Then you can just trigger things to happen.
So that's another thing that you can use these NFCs for.
So NFCs are sort of radio stuff.
But it's radio is slightly different than, for instance, an antenna like this.
And where Walkie Talkie had the same radio in there,
the NFC stuff is sort of asymmetric where you have an active device,
which is the reader or like a phone.
It could also be the payment terminals.
All these have some sort of power in there.
They have either a battery or they are plugged in,
they're connected to a computer or something where they have permanent power.
They can supply power.
And the little coil, I'll probably use the word antenna or coil,
but I mean the little traces that are on the PCBs or put into these plastic cards.
It's not a traditional antenna.
It's slightly different.
But this coil will generate a powered field
that when you approach one of these passive tags,
they can sort of get energized without having a battery,
without anything in there.
So they use the magnetic field and rectifies the frequency,
the 13.56 megahertz, rectifies it and makes power
that they can use to power up.
In some cases, they can even get so much power out of this field
that they can power other things like a little extra controller and so on.
So that very sort of asymmetric thing is what makes these very doable.
You can't really just break them, but they can take a lot of beating
because they're totally encased in plastic.
There's no battery, there's no contacts, they're nothing.
So that's a design thing about NFC and also all the other RFID stuff usually.
So the communication between the active part and the passive part
is very similar to an old-time transformer where you have a coil
and then usually there'll be a metal thing between and then another coil.
And then via this metal thing that sort of helps the magnetic field
sort of be a shared field.
And again, you can transfer energy between these two coils.
Almost all sort of where you plug something into the wall
will have some sort of that inside it to bring the voltage down.
In modern things, there's a very little one and then a lot of trunks around it.
In the old time, it was just one large brick, a heavy one.
The theory when you have this close to a reader is very close to that kind of transformer.
That's just not this metal thing.
And then the reader, the active part, can modulate the frequency a little
with amplitude shift keying to send data to the reader part.
So it gets little bits, it's fairly slow, it's low data as a one.
But the way that the tag gets commands back to the reader is a little more interesting
where it pretty much just shorts the connection so that it pulls way more power
and then the reader can actually detect that.
So that's sort of a way of sending back without actually sort of being the active transmitter.
It just sort of shorts the coil and then the reader can see,
oh, you're pulling a lot of power and then introducing it very quickly.
It can actually read these things.
So if you look inside these tags, this is a transparent one.
It's actually pretty much the same as this.
It's just transparent plastic instead.
So the little red one going around, that is the coil.
And it goes into a little chip and that chip has all the getting the rectifying the frequency
and getting power and then also having the ID and the flash and the memory.
So there's a unique ID.
I put it in quotes because they're supposed to be unique.
When they come from the factory, like NXP produces them and others also,
they are unique.
They have sort of a first part as the manufacturer and then some unique IDs.
They promise they don't use the same IDs again.
But I think this card specifically is made so that you can actually clone it.
You can change the ID on it.
So there are Chinese manufacturers that produce cards that can be rewritten.
And that's, of course, a security issue if you use it as just the ID as your security stuff.
But some way that the readers, the more advanced ones, try to get around this,
that they just try to change the UID.
And then if the UID can be changed, then OK, that's a fake card.
And then they drop it.
But of course, the people making the fake cards, they try to circumvent that
by you have to do some little hoops to change the ID first.
And it's a little talker.
But the uniqueness, it is possible to fake or clone cards to some degree.
But some of them also have some crypto stuff, something like a little engine
where they sort of have a private key inside and never let go of that.
That can sort of up the security when you're using it for door access and so on.
The one on the batch does not have that sort of fancy stuff.
The memory on these cards, the one on the batch would have 2K of memory.
That can be formatted in different ways.
NDEV is an NFC data exchange format.
And if you want to read an NFC tag with an iPhone, iOS,
then you need to have it in NDEV format because they only support that.
On Android, you can also do a little bit of other things.
And when we get these chips from NXP, they are sort of factory reset
without any format on them.
So they have to be formatted first.
And then we can put little records on them.
It could be records like a URL.
It could be a business card.
It can be just a text string.
There are different sort of standard types.
The trigger thing about the business card thing is that if you scan it with an iPhone,
nothing happens.
It doesn't recognize the business card.
But a URL is easily recognized by both Android and iPhone.
So if you want to share your business card, for instance,
you can put a URL to a business card.
And then it sort of, on the iPhone, is tricked to open the URL.
Then see, oh, that's the business card.
And then it actually sort of triggers and finds a business card.
On Android, it just shows up as a business card.
And you can add it to your contacts.
So the reader part, the active part, is put in quotes here,
because it can also write.
So it's both a reader and a writer.
And it's similar to access points and the gateways and so on.
It's sort of the gateway between this communication and then
some sort of application behind.
Usually it could be a computer.
In the batch case here, it's a little RP2040 microprocessor.
And via this communication channel up to the card,
you can send commands and you can get replies from the tech.
So it's always the reader that initiates all these things.
The tricky thing is that sometimes an active device
can also be a tech.
So for instance, if you use your phone
to pay for stuff in the store, it actually
emulates a credit card and then sort of presents itself
as a credit card and a tech.
And the reader will see it as a tech.
In the credit card case, it's not
a copy of your credit card.
It's a separate credit card with a separate number and set up
so that it is designed a system.
So it's not a cloning system.
It is individual cards.
So the batch that we have here, the active parts
should be able to do this also.
So the batches, we say batches because it's two.
And some of the goals we have is to have something super light,
very similar to what a batch is at all the boring conferences
with cardboard batches.
So have a little light thing.
You can actually wear it.
It's just hanging, no need for a battery or anything.
It could even take a little bit of washing.
And also, we would like to have some sort of functionality
maybe after the event so that you can use it as a tool.
And we hope we can have this fit in that area a little bit.
The design, it's shaped exactly as a credit card size.
And it's one of the tricky things, these antenna coils,
because they have to be very precise for the chips
to actually sort of work with it.
You can do a lot of matching circuit.
And on the reader, it's also required.
On the text, you can actually, if you design the circuit
in the exact right way, you can go directly
into the chip and don't need extra parts.
So there's only two actual parts on the attack batch.
The past few years, it's been a little tricky with parts,
because the world has been a little broken on that front.
This year, I've been looking to the shops in China
and found parts that are available there due to the fact
that we are producing the batches in China
and getting parts into China is sometimes a little difficult.
And having a shortage of stuff is not making it easier.
But I think I managed to find parts that are all sort of
easily available to them.
The main processor that we're using on the reader batch
is, I think, some surplus that has ended up
in the store in China.
So I got them very cheap.
Otherwise, it wouldn't have happened.
And I got some parts first.
I assembled some prototypes.
This is a prototype that I kind of messed a little bit up.
So I had to fix it.
But that's sort of part of the process.
And also the antennas, so making these antennas,
the easier way is finding a calculator online.
And that's what I've done, where you specify
different dimensions, the thickness of the wires,
the distance between the wires, how long they are.
And then you can sort of punch in all these numbers.
And it gives you some indication of what
is the inductance and so on, what frequency resonates it
with.
And then you can say, OK, is this
within the bounds of what the chip can handle?
And what other parts do you need to do that?
And I've just been fiddling back and forth a lot
until I found something that this is actually
doable, fits in this area, and so on.
I tried making little one with rounded corners and so on.
But the performance of all the ones I made
was based on the design that I ended up here with,
very square and following the designs very closely
on these calculators.
So if you want to make your own user calculator,
you get fairly close.
And it works fairly OK.
You might be able to tweak a little bit more
and get a little bit better reading distance.
But these are OK, I think.
So there you have the prototypes for hand assembles.
I'm using a technique with solder paste stencils,
tweezers, and hot plates.
I really like this method.
And if you guys want to try that out,
there's actually a workshop on Friday at 12,
where Theo Baum will be doing a workshop here
with exactly that technique.
And it's a technique where you're not as stressed
because you put paste on it first.
And then you just place the components.
You can take a break anytime.
You can just put them on there.
And when you're sure and you can check that all of them
are perfectly aligned, you can put it on the hot plate
and it'll solder.
And everything will just snap in, actually,
because of the surface tension of the solder.
And you have a board that you don't even
need to clean afterwards, where if you
go in with a soldering iron, you will likely
have to clean something, otherwise it'll look ugly.
So I like that technique if you want to learn it.
I learned it at a Hacker Congress in Germany.
I've been using it since.
So have a look at that.
Also on the design of the PCBs, I'm using KiCad 7.
The files are available on GitHub.
And if you want to learn that, there's
also a workshop on Sunday about how
to use KiCad to design PCBs.
Highly recommend it.
So getting to the two badges, this is the tag badge.
It pretty much has only two components.
It has a little chip with eight legs.
And it has a little capacitor.
That are the only two parts that are needed.
Then it has a coil behind all the text.
That's like a coil with, I think, seven windings or something.
It's just little traces on the PCB going around.
And then it jumps on the backside
to get back to the chip.
There's no battery on it.
It can run just as you can put it up to a reader.
You can put it up to your phone.
They will come with pre-programmed and in-depth
records that has a URL that you can scan with your phone
and goes to the GitHub.
The chip used is called the N-TAC I2C+.
It's a little chip that has this 2K memory in there.
It also has a unique ID.
Unique, can copy it.
And the difference between a card like this
and this TAC is that it has a connector.
So you can connect it to the other batch
or to the last year's batch and also, I think,
the previous year where you can actually
program the same memory via I2C instead,
writing to registers and addresses and reading from it.
Though you should be aware that there are also
some registers that can lock certain parts of the memory,
either from the RF side, the coil,
or from the I2C side.
And you can, in theory, if you lock both sides,
you can't go in and replace it or fix it.
So you can't rig the card in some way.
So please try to be a little careful when
messing with these registers.
And also, if you put the card up to an unknown reader
somewhere, let's hope that those that put up readers
and interactivity don't do nasty things to your batch.
You can lock it off, so you can, but some of the interactivity
might need to be able to write to it.
When it comes to the active device, the reader,
it is powered via USB, so you can either use a computer
or you can have a power bank and something like that.
The main sort of NFC stuff is the PN7150.
It's a chip that is slightly older.
They made a new version that is called 16 in the end,
but it's still a fairly powerful chip.
And it's one that was available at a decent price.
It communicates with something called NCI.
It's a NFC command interface.
It does that via I2C.
So the main controller on the board, which is the RP2040,
it's a Raspberry Pi, same as on the Pico.
It's powerful, has two cores, has USB connection,
and it will have a circuit Python preloaded on it
and a little driver that can sort of communicate
with the chip.
There's also two user buttons and two LEDs.
It's mainly designed if you want to use this batch out
in the field, have a power bank on it.
You can sort of have different operations.
You can have the LEDs blink if you get a read
or something like that.
There are also some pads up in the top for debugging
if you really want to go deep, but you don't need it.
So the RP2040 has a USB bootloader.
You can just hold down boot when you reset it,
and it will go into this USB bootloader,
and you can program it with whatever you want.
It is just a UF2 bootloader.
So the prototypes were assembled by me,
but the final ones were done out in China at PCBWay,
and they sent me this little video of their production line.
So this is the stenciling machine
that puts solder paste on it first
and then runs through a series of pick and place machines.
Some of them, they just run through.
I don't think they use all of them for this one here,
but they have different feeders on each machine that
has some parts, and then it grabs a part here and there
and then puts it on the PCB.
It comes out here and moves into the next one.
There's a little panel that has both the reader and the tag
next to it and little holding tabs.
And then these little robots, they pick off parts
at the feeders and then move them in and place them exactly
on top of the solder paste.
And then when it's done placing the parts,
it runs out again on the conveyor belt,
and usually they have a little manual inspection afterwards
so that they know that no parts has had misaligned.
And then when everything looks good,
they send it through an oven.
It's like this long oven.
We have different zones, so they ramp up the temperature
and so that the chips doesn't break.
And then they end up soaring and cool down,
and then the balls are depanelized
where they remove the extra tabs and so on.
And I think they've done a very nice job
in cleaning up the edges.
So that's very nice.
So programming the batches, primarily the reader,
will have CircuitPython preloaded on it.
It connects via USB, shows up as a match storage device.
There's a code.py file.
When you change that code.py file and save it,
it will reload and run the code you have in there.
If you're having typos or missing libraries or whatnot,
you can connect to a serial terminal
where you can get outputs of errors and so on.
You can also go into this rebel interactive
where you can run Python commands
and interactively scan the I2C bars and so on.
SMEAL is working on a CircuitPython library
for this PN7150.
We have some sort of whole connection to the batch
so we can read something.
We need to finalize the final things,
and then we'll reprogram on the batches.
You can also use the reader with a little wire.
It'll be included also.
So you can connect the two batches together,
and then you can change the content of the intact chip
or read it out again.
So if, for instance, you're using it for a game or something
where somebody writes something to your little tag,
then you can read it out via the reader batch,
or you can just read it with your phone or something.
The little cable and the connections on the batch,
they are SparkFunQuick or AdafruitStemQt compatible,
same as was on the batch last year.
And if you have little extra things for that,
you can of course connect them also.
There's also a library for the PN7150
for the Arduino IDE framework.
It's made by Electronic Cats.
And you can load this library into the Arduino IDE,
and you also need to load a package,
a board package for the RP2040.
But then you can actually program it very easily.
Just press the boot, and then hold boot,
and then press the reset button.
It comes up in the bootloader,
and you can just say program in the Arduino IDE,
and it'll program it.
You can also have a serial terminal there
to monitor activity and so on.
Some of the ideas for projects,
either by you or maybe also the batch team
will look into some of these,
is to make sort of a piece of bridge code
that sits in the Raspberry Pi,
that takes the NCI interface, the NFC controller interface,
that the NXP chip has,
and then converts these commands to URs
that can be done via USB.
The idea here is to actually make it into an NFC reader
that acts as any commercial USB reader,
where you can just plug in,
and there's a libNFC, I think, on Linux,
that you can actually, there's a standout for these things.
So that could be a little project of making this bridge code.
The other thing could be a very simple one
where you have a keyboard emulation.
So over USB, it emulates keyboard.
So every time a tag is scanned,
it will just type out all the ID numbers of the tag.
Could be a very easy one also.
Many commercial readers function very much like that.
Another way to change content on the tag
is to use mobile phones or desktop apps.
So both on Android and iOS, there's a tool called NFC Tools.
It's sort of a little Swiss,
I mean, I have to kind of things for playing with NFC.
You can read tags, you can write tags.
Then they do have a paid version
that can do a little bit more,
but the free version is capable of doing a lot of things,
and it exists both platforms.
There's also NXP Tag Writer.
That's the one we'll be using to format the cards.
It's made by NXP, who also makes the chips.
On iOS, you can't sort of format the card
because you can't read it afterwards.
It has to be in-depth formatted.
On Android, you can.
You can even both format them and make them factory reset.
On desktop, if you have like a USB reader,
there's also NFC Tools for that.
And then I'll just sort of mention a few other tools
that are sort of related in this.
The Proxmark 3, I saw one of you earlier
that also had a similar thing.
That is a tool similar,
so that I can read and write a lot of NFC stuff,
also RFID.
This one needs to be connected to a computer.
It's sort of a device that has a part of the software
running on the computer.
Another one is the Flipper Serial,
someone who might know it.
It's also a little toy tool.
Very fun, self-contained, has NFC reading, emulating.
It's a little bit more, at least the standard firmware,
it's a little bit more sort of commercial
where they don't allow you to change UIDs and so on,
but maybe you can convince it to do that anyway.
There's also a little thing, something called the Chameleon.
This can actually emulate NFC tags,
and you can have multiple on there
so you can switch which tag you want to emulate.
It has a little battery so it can run without a computer.
And then if you're doing sort of pen testing
or red team stuff,
this card is a little sort of tricky thing
that I didn't design it.
It's a guy, Corey Harding, that designed this one.
It has two coils on there,
and when you hold it up to a reader on a door
or something, it will light up either a LED in one side
or the other side, depending on which type of reader it is.
So if it's low frequency, one of them will light up.
If it's high frequency, it will be the other one.
And it's using the whole sort of power system
in these RFID setups.
So you can use that to sort of check
which kind of attack you need to do on a reader.
There's also cards like this.
This is a commercial for Molex,
but it's actually an RFID blocker card.
So if I have this in the stack of my credit cards and so on,
the cards can't be read
because this here will suck all the energy.
So that's also, they exist.
I haven't been able to find them at the trade show,
but they do exist.
You can also, of course,
put it into like a metal container, your cards.
I use a little thing like this normally.
You can read the card through this,
but simply having metal on one side
is usually not enough if you have a good reader.
So you have to protect them either with an active
or with some electronics in it,
or with like fully containing them.
We are also trying to integrate the badge
a little bit more into the game team.
We have had like tokens on the badge before,
but this time we have been making a little box.
It looks like this.
It's powered.
Inside it has a Raspberry Pi and the power supply,
and it has a little NFC reader.
And during the camp here,
the game team will try to sort of make a little sort of
extra hunts, little challenges
where you can use the primarily the tech part of the badge
and hold it up to these.
In the bottom section of this,
there's a reader on the backside.
So watch out for these.
They'll be spread out in the field for some game stuff.
If you wanna make your own station,
I have a bunch of these.
I think I have 10 or something.
They're in the hardware hacking area.
It's fairly easy just connecting I think eight wires
to a Raspberry Pi,
and then you can communicate with Python,
and you can read and write IDs,
but you can also read and write some data on them.
So you can use to make some sort of, I don't know,
blinky blinky thing in your village,
or I think I heard some ideas about maybe
provisioning servers by holding up your tech
with the private key or put the public key on or something.
I don't know.
Go at it, have fun.
They're free, you can just grab them
in the hardware hacking area.
There'll be along with a bunch of other parts.
There are also some cards if you want to play with that.
I think game team also has a bunch of NFC stuff
to play on.
So yeah, hardware and codes is on GitHub.
More code will go on GitHub,
and if you make some awesome hacks,
I would love to see pull requests.
We use a slightly different model for our branches,
so if you have something and don't want to put them
on your own GitHub,
you can just do a pull request to a separate branch
on this repo and we can put it in there.
We already have one branch that is the hardware,
one branch that is CircuitPython,
one branch that is the initial code and so on.
You can also just do a pull request to the readme file
with a link to whatever you have made.
Yeah, the hardware design is in KiCad 7.
You won't be able to open it in KiCad 6 or older.
It will complain a bit.
Maybe if you force it, you can do it,
but much easier in KiCad 7.
So that was pretty much it.
If there are questions,
I'll be happy to answer as good as I can.
Thank you.
Any questions?
And questions?
Can the reader talk to other readers?
If it's in card emulation mode, it's supposed to do that, yes.
So one of them needs to be in reader mode or active device mode, and the other one needs
to be in card emulation.
But code for the card emulation, you need to fiddle a little with that.
And what is the maximum load you can pull from the tag, basically?
Sorry, once again.
What is the maximum current you can pull from the tag?
It's very little.
So there are two little pins, like pads, next to the chip.
One of them is V out, and the other one is FD, FD stands for field detection.
So that will go higher, I think, when an active field is there.
The V out has to be activated by a register reading in there to actually make anything,
It's not, you have to maybe normalize it a little bit, and it's very little.
It's tiny little things, but it's enough to run a tiny microcontroller.
I can't remember the exact, and also it all depends on the distance to the reader and
how the reader reads and so on.
Any more questions?
Hello.
The card emulation mode of it, can that be used to spoof other unique IDs?
So could you clone a card and say, yes, I'm this unique ID instead?
I believe so, and I really hope so.
That should be possible, yes.
Maybe Esme has some extra info on that.
No, I just want to say that all this, of course, depends on how well the software is working.
So if anyone likes reading data sheets and writing a bit of Python to continue the driver
I started for the NFC chip, then please contact me and I'll get you set up so you can work
on it.
Awesome.
So the Arduino library has an example of using the reader to detect an other reader.
I think that is a good example to start out with if you want to do the Arduino side of it.
Yeah, anything else?
No, let's give Flummer an extra hand.
Thank you.