Welcome back in our speaker stand after a lot of lightning talks.
We have now Juergen Jakobsen, and he will talk about open source chip design.
Give him a warm welcome.
Thanks.
So I just took some hardware with it.
It's down on the board there.
If you please pass it around.
So it's a good example of how many chips we use on various stuff.
And this is about 20 years old design.
And you can see how big and clumsy these microchips on this board is.
All of these have been done with commercial software.
And it's been a hell of a job to do something like this.
So fortunately, we have moved into open source domain for doing chip design.
And that's a reality possible right now.
So I'll give you a brief introduction to what's possible today, what kind of ecosystem is
out there, what's the option to try to do that.
So I was here two years ago doing the same speech here.
At that point, I had just left my job, and I wondered that there might be a future for
me to work with open source tools all the way.
And it actually succeeded.
So during the last two years, I've been trying to push political levels, interest organization,
to move into this space, because there's actually a possibility to enable more chip designers
to get back to that, because we actually need that.
I've done a lot of talks around on various places.
I've been around to the universities.
I've been on podcasts, webcasts.
I've been attending the Free Silicon Conference in Paris twice as well.
So it's a three-day conference where all people from the area, the environment meets with
each other and show the latest progress, what have been done.
And over the three years that I've been working in this area, there's been a lot of improvement
on the tools that's available.
So to support myself, I've done some normal IoT, FPGA architecture consultancies, and
I got the funding from Enelnet to do an open source tool as well for design management,
where I tend to merge analog and digital design, because these two species, they don't really
work very good together.
There's a reason why you go and do digital design, and there's a reason why you go and
do analog design.
But you can't do a chip without combining these two things, and that's what I try to
solve with that piece of software.
And now I have clients that I cannot tell you about.
I only work in open source tools and PDKs for that.
So consider that succeeded.
And the reason why I'm doing this is that we are lacking chip designers, because it's
so hard.
It's black magic for a lot of people.
The universities are falling off of educating people in this area.
It used to be something that you take electrical engineer and turn them into a good analog
chip designer.
And what happens at the university is that we see less and less electrical engineers.
We see more computer science people, but the computer science people don't tend to
do chips design, at least not in the areas of Denmark where we are.
So I went to the Technical Museum of Denmark, and they really would like to see what we're
doing here.
And I hope that we are not ending the Danish chip design up there.
That would be a big shame.
So what you see here is actually a good example of a custom mixed mode analog digital chip.
It's only 3 x 4 millimeter.
It has a big digital core in the middle.
It has a lot of analog stuff.
It's very powerful.
It's actually a 2 x 80 watt power amplifier.
It's done in 20 years old technology, so that was bleeding edge 20 years ago.
But today, that's a very, very good platform for doing both analog, digital, high power
on the same platform, very cheap.
So things like this cost, as you see, $5 if you buy it from Infineon through your broker
in one piece size.
But if you have large quantity, you get them as low as $2.
And customers from us buy these chips, put them into soundbox, Marshall speakers, et
cetera, and things like this goes in millions a year with these devices here.
So when we do this, we have like 30 volts coupled into this very small little piece
of electronics.
We have very advanced I.O. structures here.
They can handle up to 200 volts when you take it with your fingers because you need to make
sure that it discharges there.
We have tens of amps running in and out of the transistor stacks that you see on the
sides here.
And we still have very, very low noise amps in the signal pass.
And here we need to have something around 100 dB suppression from what goes out outside
to what comes in as the audio signal here.
So it's a lot of technologies, processes that you need to do when you want to do a product
like this.
This one has been done by a group of seven people.
It took us five years to take it to the market.
We got acquired by Finion and we also made a second generation of this platform here
that hosts DSP as well.
Because when we do chip design, it is something that takes an awful lot of time.
You use a lot of time for your initial specification, what you want to do.
to ship it off to a photomask place where they can do masks so that you can do a full
wafer of that.
And then in the fab, you typically spend two months for the processing time and then you
get chipped back.
You need to put them into plastic houses and you need to test that.
And in a process, in a development process like this, you see a lot of smoke coming out
of this because there's something you didn't manage to do correctly.
You have all these faultless domains interchanging with each other and that's what happens.
And again, on the front side over here, we have the analog and the digital disciplines
of design.
So one thing is circuit design, the other is hardware description language to get to
that point.
And as the chip gets bigger, you need to put more and more efforts into that area here.
And again, all of this is black magic because you don't have access to the tools that we
use for this because there are some industry standards for that.
Cadence is used for the analog domain, Synopsys is used for the digital domain, and then we
have Mentor Graphics, now Siemens.
They are used for the backend LVS DRC, so design rule check and schematic versus layout.
And all of these tools are extremely expensive because they're priced from the leading edge
technologies.
And the leading edge technologies is what you know with this sub 5 nanometer race that
we're doing here.
So that's what's very expensive out there.
That's what goes into the CPU, the GPUs and the GPUs that you typically have in your phones
or your mobile computers today.
There's a lot of money going on out there, and there's only maybe two or three fabs around
the world that can do that.
So they can set the price point for that outrageous high.
On the more general thing, you have 19 nanometers, 45 nanometer, these are considered cheap because
you can do the design there and you can scale them up in millions.
And that way you can keep the cost of one single device very low.
Still taping out in this area is expensive.
And that's why we stay in the dirt cheap old legacy technologies that we have here.
Because we've seen for the last 50 years, we have Moore's Law here.
And Moore's Law have been driving down costs for a single transistor that you put on to
a piece of silicon.
The process speed has been increasing and the power has been scaled down.
So in this way we were able to do exponential development.
But the problem is that Moore's Law died out 10 years ago because at that point we were
not able to increase the speed of the processing anymore.
So we flat it out around four gigahertz on normal processor technology.
And that was even what was scaled down in size.
And you see that around 48 nanometer, it became more and more expensive to put a new transistor
onto the die.
And as you want processing power in the leading edge, you also need to add a lot of transistors
there.
And the cost goes exponential high.
And the cost of putting that extra transistor there stay flat or actually increase for the
products.
So there's no more innovation we can do there.
We are pretty stuck there.
What you can do in this area would be to add more cores into a single chip so that you
can get more processing power done.
And that's what you would like to do there.
So in our world, we actually have a crisis here.
So there's lack of innovation because everything is just like running for making things smaller
and smaller.
There's no reinvention there.
The tools has a monopole there.
So they have no interest to put new features in there.
They just concentrate on the leading edge and let the lagging edge pay too much for
the thing.
We don't have the EE engineers anymore.
We have monopole on the tools.
And again, the access to the PDKs and the PDKs here are the manufacturing manuals for
the processing has been locked down with the NDAs.
So I can have access to a PDK, but I can't share it with anybody.
So every time I start on a new project, I need to reset all I've done, all I learned
and restart with a new technology, cannot reuse anything.
So Google, they experienced that three years ago.
And they said, OK, we're pretty screwed because we know that the amount of servers processing
power we need in that segment are going to increase exponentially as well.
But the guys who do the chips for our servers, they are not catching up.
So there's a big void between these two graphs.
And we need to find out what to do there.
So they said, let's try to understand how these chip designers work.
And can we actually do anything here?
And they did a very formal evaluation of this and came back and said, OK, these are morons.
They don't even share what they're doing.
They distribute these PDKs that they don't allow anybody to share anyway in PDF documents.
So everybody had to open that PDF document and try to read out the design rules, how
the parameters for the transistors work.
And they fully understood that that was not the future for anything.
So they found a FAP in US.
And that FAP is an old memory FAP from Cypress.
And they convinced them that if they wanted to open source their PDK, then Google would
help.
They would sponsor tapeouts on that platform.
And then we will see a lot of new innovation in this area.
That was what happened.
So the green thing down here is what you see was the Google Skywater PDK that when that
was released, everybody has been waiting for that for a very long time.
So it has been installed on a lot of computers now.
And again, you can install that on your own computer.
You can install the tools.
And you can start to do chip design that way.
So they did this realization program.
So you can submit your chip design to eFAPless.
And then Google will pay for the shuttle service.
And then you'll get that chip designed, manufactured, put on a PCB, shipped back to you.
And then you have done your chip.
And you can start to get experience with that.
So over the last three years, we have had more than 500 individual chip designed this
way.
So on each of these MPWs, you have around 40 designs that are combined into one single
rectangle.
It looks like this.
So each of these little squares are being diced out and being put on a PCB.
And then you get that back.
So this setup is what we today call the Google lottery because they get more submission than
they actually have slots.
And we are around tape out number eight right now.
So you submit something, but you're not sure that it will get manufactured for you.
There are some other ways you can try to get your chip on one of these vehicles.
We have other PDKs that will offer that service, but I'll get back to that.
So what's on one of these chips?
You get a harness where a lot of things are done for you.
So the pad ring, that is a complicated thing to do.
There's a tile over here that assemble a RISC-V processor and the infrastructure that
you see up here.
And then in the user area, you just fill your digital stuff in here.
Or over here, you see some small analog structures.
This is again some digital.
This is more blocks put into the same ICS here.
In the structure you see over here, you have some memory, more memory, and various digital
design again that is the RISC-V processor that you see there.
And again, somebody looked at that chip and said, okay, that's an awful lot of wasted
silicon here.
Couldn't we do something about that?
And that's what I'll get back to in a minute.
And again, the whole community did a lot on how to make it more easy, more approachable
to work with these open source tools so that you could learn more people to start to do
their chip design this way.
And we have done a lot on packaging so that you can install the tools in the cloud somewhere
and you can start to chip design this way.
We have some educational program going on so you can use your Jupyter notebook.
And from there we have Python interfaces into all the tools that we use.
And from there we don't need to use obscure old scripting languages as we do in the commercial
tools to automate what we're doing.
And again, now we have free license for these tools.
Why don't we deploy them in massive amount out in the cloud so that we can do a lot of
number crunching to make sure that we pick the best solution out there.
So that's what has been done a lot.
There's one guy who actually looked into how to do adders and tried to elaborate on
how that could be done.
And he actually found out, let me see, it's not here.
Yeah, I'll get back to that later.
But again, people start to do innovation in the area to make sure that what we are doing
is actually being developed, pushed back to the community.
And you know that from open source that can go really fast when you have a lot of people
crunching on the same problem.
Again, here in the digital domain we have some process of doing placement, the initial
placement of all standard cells on a digital thing.
You can do thousands of runs on that in the cloud.
You're not limited by the licenses.
And then you just take the best outcome from that because you will get a graph down here
that you can actually find where you want to be performance or power wise.
And again, we had the enlightenment that other companies didn't want to let Skywater run
alone with this setup.
So Global Foundry released 180 nanometer technology as well.
Skywater, they are releasing a 90 nanometer fully depleted SOI process as well.
And all of that has been funded by EU CHIP Act money or US CHIP Act money.
So a lot of things are being put in there and is getting back to the community.
There's another offering that you don't see here, but we have a FAP in Germany.
It's a research FAP.
It's a BiSIMOS high speed for radar thing.
It's a 130 nanometer technology.
And they will start to do offerings just as we see with this setup here as well.
So I guess that we will look into a situation where we will have like 40 CHIP designed on
that platform every third month for the next coming two years.
And that's a lot of space for design exploration as well.
The solid state community, IEEE, has done a lot of things as well.
We have a CHIP hackathon where university professors are teaming up with people from
all around the world.
And they do their educational first CHIP taped out on these platforms as well so that they
can get experience and understand what's possible with this.
Because it is really a lot of handcraft that goes into doing this on top of all your electronic
or computer science theory that you need to do as well.
They have travel grants to the major conferences around if you can do a Jupyter notebook educational
part that actually is useful for the community.
And again, we see that the big players in the open source community as the Linus Foundation
goes in and start to take ownership of some of the projects going on here.
So what we have here is CHIP Alliance that's part of the Linus Foundation.
They have adopted the flows for FPGAs.
So now we are supporting fully open source flows for FPGAs.
So that's the mid-range FPGAs.
We have Lattice that is fully supported.
We have parts of the Sightings thing and we have new people on the block.
We have a Chinese company called Goodwin that also produces FPGA that is fully supported
here.
And again, I said open source chip design in Denmark is not a big thing.
I really had to go to my old professors at the university and get them started again
showing that there was these offerings that we could do something in this field.
And whenever we do this, we get a lot of students because they love to do this.
They can see that the potential in this area, the crowd around machine learning, AI is so
big that it's hard to do something different there.
And people recognize that if you can do something with microchips or maybe do application from
these domains into here, there's an opportunity to do something that is interesting.
And again, these young people, they also understand the model on open source and that's what we
need to actually bootstrap what we're doing here.
This is a guy from southern Denmark.
He works in one of the big power companies down there.
But in his spare time, he did chip design.
So he taped out like a SAR IDC for like three versions of it, experiment with how to do
that.
You're running simulation and running all of these tools to do that on his own PCs.
I don't need to tell you a lot about open source software because you all know that
that's an actually very, very big technology engine.
But it hadn't really happened in hardware and that's what we all try to do right now.
But open source software is only like around 20 years old, at least from when it was rebranded
from free to open source instead.
And it has been adopted from the top management around the world and nobody doubts that that's
a model that actually works.
Even Windows use it and want to be a part of the party as well.
This was what we saw with the adders that has been put into the digital tool flow.
So when you translate your high level description of your digital code, you can add an adder.
But if you can say something about the adder, how fast you want to have it, if it needs
to be parallelized, then you can have various performance points out of that.
And what you see in the red thing here is what has happened with the progress in development
for the commercial tools.
And what you see in the green is what happened in the open source domain.
Because here you just add that as a module, release it to Yoast and Yoast, they are the
guys who do the synthesis tool and then everybody has it out here.
And that's the kind of speed that we see that things are involved with.
You've seen that one.
But again, here we have an example of a German company, they were used to do FIS for ISDN
wires and I guess that you understand that that's not a big market anymore.
So they decided to use their brain power to do FPGAs instead.
And when you do FPGAs, you also need to do a lot of software because people need to be
able to work with your technology.
But they said, okay, let's just adopt the full open source tool suite.
Then we just need to do something that can place a route because we know the internals
of the thing.
We release that and then we have a full flow that's actually reusable for everybody out
there.
So that's a model that we see now that didn't exist a couple of years ago and that's really
nice to see.
When we do digital design, we have the digital front-end thing where we work in high-level
description language, so that's VSTL or Verilog.
These are very low-level, so you define a register and you assign values to that and
you clock it and you describe the next state.
But we are trying to abstract that with more capable languages.
We have XLS from Google.
We have Schissel as an open source project.
It runs on Scala, so it's a functional language.
So we have a subset of that that can convert your functional code down to Verilog that
can be taken into the full flow and from there you can do your normal chip design this way.
But again, on the front-end here, you do the functional implementation.
Then you need to take it to the digital back-end where you have flows that can convert that
gate net list of standard cells into placed thing.
You put the power IOs and then you make sure that your clock gets distributed around to
that.
But it's a very easy process to do and it can be automated.
Now we actually have some very, very good tools in the open source domain to handle
that path.
So it's called the open lane flow.
That's where we see, that's where we use all of us in this area.
So you have your design entry files there.
You take it through Eurosis ABC that maps it into standard cells.
You run static timing analysis to make sure that it will do the required amount of job
within the limited time you have before your clock flips into the next flip flop.
And then you have the open road application that actually is a database where you can
interact and place your standard cells.
You can do your routing.
You can synthesize the clock tree in there and you can size cells up and down to make
sure that you read the timing that you would like to have.
And then there's a lot of things that you need to put in for manufacturing things.
So that's antenna diodes so that your small gates doesn't blow up when you try to produce
them.
You could do verification with logic, equivalent logic.
And you need to extract your RNC from the circuit that you do there to make sure that
now you suddenly have a delay in your signal from one place of the chip to the other one
that these doesn't ruin the way that you expect the thing to do.
And then on the other side over there, you stream out your GDS file and you can send
it for manufacturing at the FAPT.
This is how a standard cells look like.
So it's actually just like a pizza stack of very low level structures.
In the low level structures, you have your n-mold, your diffusion.
And if you put a poly layer above that, you get a transistor.
And by controlling the doping and the layers of these, you can have PMOS, you can have
NMOS, and you can have field poly and you use that for resistors.
And then you can interconnect them with your terrible bad conducting material called interlayer
wiring.
And then you have metal 1, 2, 3, 4, and 5.
And you can see as you grow up in the stack, these get higher and higher.
And that's to be able to conduct more current in the upper layers here.
That's not necessary at the base level down here.
You also see that between metal 3 and 4, you have something with a via down to a cap.
So that is metal caps and that's very precise caps that can actually be used for storage,
decoupling or precision circuit where you have ratio between caps.
Look into that later.
And getting back to the void you saw on one of the early tape outs there.
So Matt Wayne here that I met in Paris and a couple of other conferences has created
a set up.
He announced it one year ago and already now there have been four tape outs on that platform.
And that platform is called Tiny Tape Out.
So here Tiny Tape Out allows you to gather hundreds of designs into one single slot in
an MPW.
And this way you can get the cost down.
But I think we should get the words from the man himself and try to listen to that.
Tiny Tape Out makes it easier, quicker and cheaper than ever before to get your designs
onto a real chip.
Open source tools, excellent documentation and a vibrant community helps to make it much
easier to get started and avoid common mistakes.
Tiny Tape Out is for students, for makers, hackers, universities and anyone who is interested
in learning more or getting their designs made into a chip.
All our learning resources and tools are free to use and they are online to avoid download
and installation problems.
If you're a total beginner, you can try Wokwi, our digital design and simulator tool.
Or if you know what you're doing, you can use a hardware description language like Verilog,
VHDL or Amaranth.
Then use our github action based system to build the files you need for the ASIC.
This also lets you explore your design with this really cool 3D viewer.
Once your design is finished, you can make an order.
The minimum size is 160x100 microns and that's just $100 including a PCB.
If you need more space, you can buy extra tiles for $50 each.
We also have special deals for group workshops and universities.
You might be asking, how is it possible to get the price so low?
The trick is that we combine all the little projects into one big design using our fast
multiplexer.
160x100 microns doesn't sound like a lot, but in our three previous runs we've seen
a load of interesting designs made, including RISC-V CPUs, FPGAs and lots more.
One of my favourite things about this project is that not only are you going to get your
design, but you're going to get everybody else's design as well.
You'll be able to look through the chip's datasheet and try out someone else's design.
Our previous three runs all used a slower scan chain, so this is a really big upgrade.
We're now expecting around 50 MHz bandwidth on the I.O.
Another upgrade is that we've now got more I.O.
We have clock, reset, 8 inputs, 8 outputs and 8 bi-directional pins.
Once the design is ready, we send it to eFABLUS, and they'll manufacture it on the open source
Skywater 130nm process.
I want to say a really big thanks to eFABLUS for sponsoring this project and making it
possible.
Once we get the silicon back, we save you the trouble of soldering by mounting it onto
a PCB.
You select which design you want to be active with these switches, and then the multiplexer
connects the design to the inputs and the outputs.
To get started, follow the video tutorials.
Expect it to take between a few hours and a few weeks, depending on how complex your
design is.
If you get stuck, join our Discord chat server.
Make sure you sign up to the mailing list so that you know when submissions open.
So have fun, get involved, and I'm really looking forward to seeing what you make on
your first ASIC.
So there's a tape-out deadline for this one here on the 7th of September, and yesterday
or the day before we had a workshop.
I never tried it before, but I managed to do what you see here.
So it's a SPDIF to I2S converter.
So it takes a blinking flashing light from my DVD or sound card, and I convert that into
the four-wire, three-wire bus that interface to the chip you saw previously.
So that's the power amplifier that I made in my previous company.
So putting this together, I will submit this, and we will get it back, and we can try it
out next year on BodyHack.
So look forward for that.
The thing is, I had this code lying around.
I need to adapt it to the user interface of this harness that you see that he described
with all the tiles.
I need to adjust the size of the tile.
I use one single tile there, so that's the cheap $100 tape-out option, and I guess that
around there, there's space for around 100, 150 flip-flops in that scenario.
So what you can do in 100, 150 flip-flops will fit into a system like this.
Then when you submit it, you run some GitHub actions in the background, and these GitHub
actions are the one you see down here.
So when they're green, it means that the sign has been compiled, it takes a five-minute
job on these servers here, and you end up with the layout that you see up there.
I jumped the very important thing, and the thing that takes most of the time, and that's
the testing.
So I need to do a test bench where I actually try to put in a reasonable signal from audio
source and check that what comes out is actually a real playable thing on an amplifier as well.
But I'll probably do that a bit later, where I will use the same code, but I'll throw it
down to an FPGA, use the open source toolchain to make sure that the sign is actually also
producing audio, and that's pretty easy to do on FPGA technologies.
Using this platform has enabled a lot of new designers into the area.
People who have backgrounds with computer science or embedded electronics, they suddenly
are able to do chip design instead.
So now we take the black magic out of what we're doing here, and they understand what's
going on here, and that's a really exciting moment for a lot of people.
We also have this SillyVis, and SillyVis is like a childish simulator where you can start
to draw your substrate, your diffusion, your tapping into this diffusion, build up a transistor,
try to play with the length of the width with these, and there's a simulation mode
so that you can actually see what happens if you try to do that.
And in the TinyTap outside, there's a good description all the way around that describe
what is parasitic capacitance on things like this, how did we do transistors when we only
had in-must transistors with resistors low instead.
All of that is very good learning material in that side as well.
And you can also, if you want to go full on, install the OpenROAD tools and the OpenROAD
flow scripts, and from there be able to produce your own digital parts there.
It's not that hard, and there's a lot of good description on how to do it out there, and
that's what was not possible to find previously, because once you're knitting, you will never
find tutorials for the cadence environment or the synopsis thing.
These are well hidden behind paywalls, but out here, there's a lot of people who actually
have done it and write good tutorials on how to do that and how to use it yourself.
So in the analog world, we are working terrible slow, because we do transistor by transistor
circuit simulation, and from there, when we have a system that works, we take it to layout,
we lay out the structures that we did in the schematic, and we do a check that the schematic
versus the layout is correct, and from there, you have a block that you could combine together
with some digital stuff, or you can take it out alone as an analog function block there.
But that is even more black magic for a lot of people, and these are the analog guys.
Problem is that we need the analog guys to step up from this doing one transistor at
a time, so we need to learn them how to program, abstract what they're doing, make generators
so that the structures that they do is actually current mirrors, op amps, you can put it together
as a bigger system, and because you have Python to glue together, you can also do layout of
what you're doing, and then automate the process of doing analog design.
There's a lot of effort going into that, but it's really hard when the resources at the
university is as low as it is.
Because this is the old-fashioned way to do, we put in transistors, and we put a lot of
them in there because they're cheap and they're easy to put in there, and because these transistors
and resistors that we put there are terribly shitty components, they spread around 20 to
40%, so we need to have ways to trim, compensate, use structures where we don't rely on the
absolute value of components, but the relative values, and then we can make circuits this
way.
When we do that part of it, we need a simulator, and a simulator is like a circuit simulator.
You probably know PSpice, so you can put various components in there.
You can apply some input signal, and you can see what comes out on the other side.
That's what we do in these two versions of the tools that we have.
Size is something from the Sanity Labs in the US.
It's very powerful, and it's highly parallel, so it can solve very big matrixes.
RNGspice is the very simple, easy-to-use tool here.
When we do that, we also validate the circuit design that we do, that it actually works
over corner, so that's in the fab where the operator had a good day or a bad day, so we
need to make sure that the design that we did can do within that.
Also the voltage, and also the temperature is put into these matrix, and then we decide
that as corners, and then we make sure that the design works for all these corners.
That's just a hell of a lot of simulation that we put through there.
But luckily, as things are parallel here, and we are not limited by the amount of licenses
we have, then it's just to throw these China jobs into your big-ass server in the basement,
and then they solve it in very little time.
For the analog layout, we have K-Layout, and K-Layout is a more modern version of that,
and there's a good cell generator in there, so that you can automate that process.
And also here, we have Python interfaces for that, so I can actually open up a Jupyter
notebook, and I can start to use the engine from K-Layout to run some of the tasks for
me there.
We also have Magic, and Magic is like a 40-year-old tool, but it's still used for a lot of things
in the flow today.
But a lot of improvements, or room for improvement here.
So I've done, with universities, a lot of special courses, trying to get people to use
the open source tool, evaluate if it's possible.
It's very hard for me to convince the professors, because they don't really understand how something
that is cheap can be better than something that you pay a lot of money for.
And at the university, they get great discounts for the tools, so for them, it's not a big
thing to have them.
The only problem is, they have forgotten how to operate them or install them, so it's actually
easier to go the open source way anyway.
Where we're going is that we would like to see a lot of chip design being done in these
open source tools and processors, so that when I meet a customer who says, I need a
chip, I need a microprocessor, and a CIDC or something like that, then I can just grab
what was done by the community, put it on my chip, because these are open source, these
have been validated by other people on the process, and I can put together something
that is actually compatible in the market for a full custom chip.
And that's what I see happens now.
I have people coming to me saying, ah, putting that chip on the circuit board that we're
doing here is terribly expensive.
In some cases, I can't get this chip anymore.
Is there a way that we can start to do our own versions of these chips?
And that's what's happening right now, so I'm happy.
Here's a good example, not even is it a good example of a SAR ADC here, but he also made
a description in a master thesis there, very well described, and the objective of what
they were doing here was to do something this advanced, but only using open source tools
and PDKs, and they managed to do that.
So Harold Pretz, he's a professor at the University of Linz.
He also has a distribution where all the tools have been assembled into one single repo.
So it's just to clone that, and then you have what is needed to do chip design here.
And from Berkeley, we see that they have started to go back into the mode that I was taught
25 years ago at the university, where they group people into doing various parts of a
chip, shipping it off of one of these platforms.
Not really, because they're Berkeley and they work with Apple and Intel, so they have other
processes to do that, but they still use all the open source tools to do that as an educational
part of it.
And they are highly advanced.
They use protocol buffers to interface between various tools to actually have an open source
way of describing schematic.
They use Python Rust to do that, and they have generators to do the analog stuff.
Very advanced things.
So my last shout here is a bit outdated, but when I started here three years ago, I took
some online courses in India.
They are very well priced, and the quality is good.
It's the same open source tools that we use.
You can find the Sky 130 PDK out there.
Tim Edwards maintains open PDKs, so here you can have five different PDKs installed in
one single structure and work with them within the various tools.
And you can again take a look at the MPW that has been taped out here to actually get inspired
and see what can be done.
There's an open source Slack channel where everybody meets in the community, and they're
very friendly, open, and you can ask the stupid questions there and also the advanced.
And then again, if you're interested in this area, hook up with me.
I'm very happy to try to see if there's a spot for you in the place or something that
needs to be done.
Thanks.
That was what I had.
Any questions?
There is one.
Thanks for the talk.
I have many questions.
So you mentioned the funding by the CHIPS Act, and I understand you've been around in the
community for a good while.
Is there any talk in the community about how both Google's community building slash marketing
effort and all of this tooling development is part of the DARPA ERI, so electronics
resurgence initiative, in order to ensure that defense technology is, well, to ensure
the U.S. doesn't forget how to manufacture defense technology?
Is there awareness that that is the origin of this project?
So the DARPA thing is going on.
They support development on the 19 nanometer technology node.
They fund the size simulator.
The size simulator is more or less covered by some restriction.
So you can't take it to China, for instance, because it's highly classified in this way.
I don't know how they make sure that it doesn't happen, but at least that is the thing.
In Europe, we're a bit slow, so not a lot is going on.
We had the EU CHIPS Act, and that has been ratified.
But from there, you need to put that into action between the various member countries.
Some countries have been active.
That happens a lot in Germany.
That happens nothing in Denmark.
But it's different from place to place.
So again, it's the larger companies who actually now can get funding from the government to
put a FAP in EU soil or in U.S. soil.
So you see a bit of competition there, where they would like to have the next generation
big FAPs placed locally in this way.
Yeah, fortunately, everybody has understood how this is important.
You didn't answer my question, though, whether there is awareness in the community that the
origin of this project, and also E-FABLUS, the American company, that they come from
this DARPA initiative to protect military technology in the U.S.?
I think we know that, but we see it as the greater good for us to be able to do chip
design open source.
I agree that it's good that there's more open tooling, right?
So another question.
How do you feel about the terms of service of E-FABLUS, where they require that you promise
that your design isn't covered by any export regulations?
I don't know, but E-FABLUS is an entity in Egypt.
I believe it's an American company.
No, it's in Egypt.
But they are still using Skywater as a foundry service this way.
But they have offerings for everybody.
If you come and you put US dollars, then they can produce an MPW for you, and they don't
ask questions in this way.
Regarding export regulation, I'm not an expert.
I don't know anything about that.
All right, I recommend reading their terms of service really carefully.
And another question, I'll make that the last one.
Were you aware that the Skywater fab is one of the few that is certified to manufacture
military equipment in the US?
No, but I guess that a lot of fabs would have that authority as well, because that's what
been driving that industry for the last 20 years.
So as far as I've been able to find, when I've done a bit of scratching behind all of
this, that's the only one.
OK, but now I'm not aware of that.
All right, so please be considerate where you upload your chip designs, right?
And if there is finally a European fab, I think that's fantastic.
I just hope there is a route that does not involve E-FABLUS.
I think that the work we have with ISP in Berlin is actually being very fruitful, and
I hope that we see a lot of things being tabled out this way from Europe at least.
That sounds good.
I want to hear more about that.
Thanks.
Any other questions for Jan?
Yeah.
Oh, sorry.
Hey, so this is, of course, quite specialized skills, and I'm just wondering, could you
talk a little bit about maybe how do you, you say you work with professors sometimes
and universities here?
Just talk a little bit more about that, because, for example, I did a computer science degree.
We didn't scratch anywhere near this.
Now, of course, other universities will, but yeah, how do you even get, you know, young
people, or not necessarily young, but, you know, just new entrants into computer science
in general to be able to understand all of this?
But that's a hard part.
At DGU, where we did a lot of chip designers over the last 30 years, all of them went out
to the hearing aid industry, to the mobile phone communication thing, network technology,
et cetera.
So we had a good outcome from there to that area.
But even though there was no direct study line that was called chip design in there,
so you entered the university, you took computer science or EE, and then from there you tried
to specialize taking the courses that actually enabled you as a chip designer.
So chip design is centered on a few universities around the world, but now also in the open
source community.
So if you have normal skill set within EE electronics, then you can also upgrade that
to chip design.
You can even find a lot of these courses online as well.
I know in Sweden there's a good set of courses for that.
Today at DGU University we have started a bachelor education as chip designer, computer
science, engineering.
So that's the way it should go.
I also have communication with SGU, so that's the Southern University of Denmark, and they
will start to produce chip designers as well.
And right now the biggest group in Denmark is located in Aarhus, and it's Farshad, one
professor.
He attracts a lot of research money.
He tapes out twice a month, every second month, with the various projects.
And compared to Copenhagen, there's not been a tape out for the last two years.
So you need to find these center of gravities, and they're probably not in Denmark, they're
probably all over Europe this way.
We have one more question.
How can you ensure that malicious code is not inserted in your chip?
I can ensure that because when I do the validation of the chip, I see all the things that I put
there validates to the schematic or the HTML that I put there.
The other thing you say, then you send some blueprints to a FAP, they might be able to
put something in there.
But I'm not a big fan of doing chips where I don't have 100 control of what I put on
it.
And the way you do chips today might be that you have black boxes from other companies
in there because you use their IP, and then there's no guarantee that they haven't had
the malicious code in there.
So yeah, that's a good question.
But what we can do in the open source community at least is that we know what we put in there.
That was the last question.
Let's give a round of applause for Jrgen.
Thanks a lot.