The next speakers we have is Karen Melchior, a member of the European Parliament, and Jesper
Lund, the chair of the IT poll.
They will speak about chat control.
The next month will be critical.
Let's give them a hand.
Thank you very much and thanks for coming to this, I think, one of several presentations
about chat control, a surveillance proposal from the EU Commission.
And there was a talk yesterday by Jan and today we will focus on what is happening at
the political institutions in the EU and why the next couple of months will be critical
for fundamental rights in the years to come.
This is a quick outline.
We will do a very quick outline of what chat control is about and what is the real name
of chat control.
And then we will, without hopefully making it too boring, explain how the EU lawmaking
process works, because some understanding of that is very useful to, first of all, influence
the process, but also understand why does it matter that Council did this and that and
so forth.
And in the end we will suggest how you or others listening to this online or seeing
it afterwards can try to influence the process so that this mass surveillance proposal doesn't
become a reality.
And then this is really the crux of the issue when we're looking at the proposals.
Every time we have a presentation of the Commission's proposal, the proponents of the proposal will
start out with spending 10 minutes, 20 minutes out of an hour explaining how terrible sexual
abuse of children is and how it's grown online in the last couple of years and sort of really
explaining what has happened to the children and how difficult it is for the police to
prosecute the criminals that have committed this without actually going into sort of,
OK, there are criminal networks that are behind this and there are things going on in the
physical space.
They just jump to, OK, we need to do something about this online because we need to save
the children.
And look at these two cute young girls.
Who would be able to say no to save them from being abused?
Who would say no to actually help children from experiencing horrible things and being
subject to criminals and criminal networks and having the pictures and images shared
across the world?
That makes it very difficult to say the Children's Safety Online proposal, child sexual abuse
material handling is something that we don't want to do anything about.
And that is really the political environment and the discussion and the debate that we're
going into when we're talking about this.
So we need to remember to think about the feelings of the people that we're talking
to and not only think about the sort of technicalities because we all want to save children from
abuse but we actually want to do it in a way that works and what we have on the table doesn't
We want to let the politicians know that, I'm one of them, that we want to have legislation
that can save the kids in a way that works.
And as I was mentioning with the Kids' Online Safety Act, it's not only in the EU.
We are having proposals being made across the world.
We have in the US where they're also mixing it up with a little bit of some of the content
that we had in the DSA in the EU.
The UK also has an online safety bill that is proposing some of the same things on client
scanning.
So this is a sort of global phenomenon and therefore we need to help each other across
the different countries and regions to fight this and try and find strategies that work.
Because just saying no to saving the kids is not going to appeal to sort of the masses
And we need to make sure that we have technology that works, technical arguments for why the
proposals that they have don't work, but at the same time saying we're actually doing
this to help the kids as well.
So the next couple of minutes will be a quick outline of what Check Control is about and
also revealing the real name.
So Check Control is just what it's called on social media.
I think a phrase coined by Patrick Breyer of the German Pirate Party.
So the full name is Regulation Laying Down Rules to Prevent and Combat Sexual Abuse.
At IDRI, Isipol is a member of IDRI and I participated in IDRI's work on this file.
We call it the CSA Regulation or CSAR.
And that is, obviously we don't have time to go through everything and that would be
incredibly boring, so I'll just focus on the most interesting parts or the most troublesome
parts of the CSA Regulation.
And clearly the most, the absolutely most troublesome part is the Article 7-11 on Detection
Orders which is sort of basically why it's called Check Control.
These can apply to messenger services or interpersonal communication services, as they
are officially called, and hosting services.
And so messenger services are always private communication services, hosting services can
be public services like social media, but it can also be really private services like
cloud storage on Google Drive, Microsoft OneDrive and whatever it's called.
And if a service provider is issued a so-called Detection Order, that will be an obligation
to scan all users' content for three different things depending on which type of order is
given.
Known child sexual abuse material, which will be done using some hashing matching algorithm
or perceptual hashing typically.
But there are also possibilities for detection orders for unknown child sexual abuse material
and grooming, and the latter two will be done through some form of AI classifiers that
come with extremely high error rates.
These orders, the detection orders cannot be issued to all services, there's a requirement
of significant risk of child sexual abuse after the so-called mitigation measures that
I'll talk about in a minute.
But the way that significant risk is defined in the regulation itself will very likely
in practice mean that a lot of services will have a significant risk that they can be used
or abused for something bad involving children, especially as the very purpose of messenger
services is that people can communicate privately without the service provider monitoring what
people are talking about, and that means it will actually be very difficult for the
service provider to say that there is not a significant risk of the service being used
for child sexual abuse.
One interesting thing is to say, well, what about encrypted services, which are specifically
designed so that it's impossible to scan the content of people's communication?
Well, encryption is barely mentioned in the proposal itself, but it is presented as technologically
neutral, which means that it will simply be up to the service provider to figure out how
to do the impossible of scanning communications content that is end-to-end encrypted.
This is not explained particularly well in the proposal itself, but there was a Q&A published
by the Commission along with the proposal where it is spelled out that detection orders
will be technologically neutral, and it is an obligation of results, not of means.
So unlike sort of previous crypto wars where a specific circumvention of encryption was
proposed, this time it will be left to the service provider to backdoor their own services
essentially.
I'm skipping some of this for reasons of time because we want to get to the interesting
stuff what can be done about these bad things, and we will distribute the slides afterwards,
so don't worry about that.
I also want to talk a bit about risk assessment and risk mitigation, which is something that
is supposed to come before detection orders can be issued.
This is sort of a mixed bag of something that is, some is good, some is bad.
So taking the positive hat on is about making services platforms safe for children, which
is an admirable objective and a good idea, and if this is something that service providers
haven't done already, then having an obligation in EU law to do it is a good idea.
The problem with this is that it's done in a way that presents the internet as inherently
dangerous, and if something is inherently dangerous, we should keep children away from
it.
So just to walk you through what will happen, service providers will first be required to
assess the risk of their services being used for child sexual abuse, which is a difficult
exercise, and then they should take mitigation measures.
The problem with this is that it's rather vaguely defined, except the notion that the
internet is a dangerous place, and the only thing that is really concrete is that online
age verification is a good idea in the eyes of the Commission.
But some incentives are created to make services safer, which, so maybe having less sharing
of personal data by default, especially for accounts belonging to children, that would
be a great idea, but that is actually not in the Commission proposal, but in some of
the amendments that are coming out.
And then the heavily contested idea of age verification that is also coming up in national
politics in Denmark, Germany, the UK, with the online safety bill, and France, and maybe
potentially other countries, that is a not so good idea.
And by the way, there's also, I don't really have time to go into that, there's also an
age verification requirement for app stores, which will apply to all app stores, whether
they are large, like Apple's app store, or Google Play app store, or small, such as FDroid,
the alternative app store for Android devices.
And since these alternative app stores don't really know their users, they have no way
of enforcing age verification.
So the problem with online age verification, which I don't really have time to go into,
is that there's no good way to do it.
But it is being proposed, and typically it involves bad solutions, such as uploading
copies of ID documents, which sort of invites identity theft, doing some form of biometric
facial analysis, a company called Yoti is heavily invested in doing that, which is at
best an estimation of your age, not a verification of your age, checks your payment cards, and
then maybe 10, 15 years from now some really fancy solutions where you can prove your age
anonymously without revealing anything, but this is nowhere ready for deployment.
Irrespective of what comes out of this, there's a risk of digital exclusion.
Users that will not be able to comply with these age verification requirements, whether
they are children or adults, will be locked out of online services that they want to use,
potentially even including Digipedia.
We thought we'd give you a quick outline of how legislation in the European Union works.
If you study political science or law, you will spend years of classes and 10 or 20 ECTS
points on this, so we're going to do it very briefly in basically one slide.
The Commission comes with a proposal, then both the Member States and the Council and
us in the European Parliament, we look at it together.
The Commission came with a proposal last year in May and already at last year's Born Hack
there was a group of us that got together and said, this looks really bad, let's try
and do something about it.
That's why we have, together with Jorn, who talked yesterday, we have set up a website
called chatcontrol.dk and .eu and we also have a mailing list, so please support us
on working on that so that we can influence both Member States and the Parliamentarians.
We are in the Parliament in the process of making our amendments to the Commission proposal
and we'll probably have a vote here in the fall on this and the Member States are also
making their amendments and trying to have a joint position and that's where the advocating
for National Parliaments come in and then after both the Member States and the Parliament
have come with their positions, then you go into what's called a trilogue negotiations
where we sit down together with the Commission, the Presidency of the European Council, so
that's going to be Belgium.
That was Belgium this spring and then now it's Spain and then you'll have Hungary and
Poland in the next coming six-month periods and that's when they sit in a closed room
and try to hash things out and figure out how the legislation will look like.
As Jesper has written down, it's typically somewhere between the Parliament and the Council position.
Jesper is going to talk us through the way it looks in the Council between all of the
Member States.
I'll do the bad guys and Karen will do the good guys.
That's how we divided the EU legislature on this file.
No, just kidding, actually a couple of months ago I was more optimistic about Council than
Parliament, but there was a bombshell event in April that changed a lot in Parliament
but not in Council.
So a working group, the Law Enforcement Working Party, and don't be confused by the word,
it has nothing to do with parties, it's sort of a working group that is always called
working parties.
The Law Enforcement Working Party has worked on this proposal since June last year and
they are, the plan they have announced is that on 28 September they will adopt their
position.
This has to be done at a meeting where the Ministers are present, the Interior and Justice
Ministers, so they have a Justice and Home Affairs Council which will be held on the
28th September where their plan is to adopt the Council position which becomes the negotiating
position for the EU Member States when they get together with the European Parliament
in the trilogues that Karen talked about.
And looking at the most recent Council text, it has a lot of amendments, but it has very
few amendments to detection orders.
They still apply general and indiscriminately to all users irrespective of whether they
are suspected of actual involvement in child sexual abuse or not.
So the only thing that Council saw a need to exclude was real-time voice calls.
Everything else including encrypted services are still included in this group of the proposal.
There was a couple of weeks ago under the former Swedish Presidency a proposal to exclude
or not necessarily exclude encrypted services from the proposal, but to protect them from
detection orders and at least make sure that encryption is not undermined, and this was
framed in a way that clients are scanning that I'm sure Jan talked about yesterday,
planting the spyware on your mobile phone, would be prohibited.
But there was no support for this proposal even though Germany and a couple of other
member states have advocated quite heavily for it, so that was dropped again.
There are also fairly modest changes on risk assessment and risk mitigation, meaning age
verification is still de facto mandatory in certain cases, and then Council made a lot
of changes to some of the more boring aspects of the CSA regulation that I'll not talk about.
One interesting thing is that they decided to completely ignore a legal opinion that
the member states themselves requested from the Council Legal Service, the specialist
lawyers employed to advise member states on whether a proposal complies with EU primary
law including the Charter of Fundamental Rights.
They don't usually ask for such an opinion because there's a presumption that new laws
are consistent with the constitution of the EU, but in this case they did, and they got
a very unusual opinion back at the end of April which clearly said, no, this is not
consistent, this does not comply with the Charter of Fundamental Rights.
And I must say at ITERI we have done our own Fundamental Rights Assessment and that was
actually quite lacking, or at least not quite lacking, that was sort of less complete than
the one that the Council Legal Service did and was supposed to be the radicals on fundamental
rights, but in this case we were not.
So just to sort of quickly summarize, they used the data retention case law, we did that
as well and concluded that general indiscriminate detection orders are not limited to what is
strictly necessary, which is sort of the yardstick for doing something in compliance with fundamental
rights at the EU level.
They also, and this is where it gets really unusual, said that the proposal is likely
to violate the essence of the right to privacy, and that is the generalized scanning of content
of communications for everybody, goes back to the first SRAMS judgment in 2015 where
they were referring to the National Security Agency, the Court of Justice, and basically
they pointed out that this would create a state of sort of a permanent surveillance
society where all interpersonal communications are monitored.
And the lawyers, the clever lawyers, pointed out that detection orders must be targeted
against individuals where there's actual suspicion of involvement in child sexual abuse, not
the general population.
Very interesting, they also pointed out that doing this on end-to-end encrypted services
where they use the word backdoor, although it doesn't really have a legal meaning, creates
an additional interference with a right to data security, which is very interesting.
To make a long story short, the Commission response to all this was that, well, the content
is the crime, so we need to monitor everybody's communication, which is a completely untested
legal argument, so it will be interesting if this ever gets to the Court of Justice,
what the justice will say to the Commission.
But member states are seemingly set to ignore this altogether, so what can possibly stop
a disaster with the CSA regulation in Council?
A better negotiating position for member states that does not include mass surveillance?
Well, if there is a blocking minority for member states representing at least 35% of
the EU population, it's not enough to have a majority in Council that needs to be a super
majority of 65% of the EU population, but if there's a blocking minority, they can,
in principle, stop the position in its current form going forward.
And we know there's substantial disagreement in the law enforcement working party about
detection orders in the child sexual abuse regulation.
That is why they requested the legal opinion from the Council legal service.
It is also why they sort of escalated their disagreement to the ambassador level in the
Corp here, I'm not pronouncing this correctly, in the end of May, but the ambassadors basically
reaffirmed we want to monitor everybody, potentially even including all your communication.
Some of the good guys, the good member states include Germany, Austria, the Netherlands,
possibly Poland and Estonia, who have all in various forms voiced criticism of this,
and then there's a like-minded group of other countries, Belgium, Bulgaria, and so forth,
that want the proposal in its current form.
If you're wondering what does Denmark think about all this, well, Denmark has the most
absurd position.
Denmark wants end-to-end encrypted services to be included in the proposal, but they do
not want, Denmark does not want to weaken encryption in any way, and it's a bit hard
to sort of monitor and get access to encrypted communication without weakening encryption
in some way, because the whole point of encryption is to prevent this monitoring.
So the big question now going forward is will the majority among the member states be able
to pressure the minority to give up its opposition so that council reads it as a compromise?
That is often how it's played out, because sort of the way council works is seeking compromises.
But this really needs to be seen, and now I'll hand over to Karen, because we also have
the good guys in the European Parliament.
Well, sort of the good guys.
We have, in the European Parliament, we have a lot of different committees.
The main committee is our Fundamental Rights Committee, which is called LIBE.
They are the ones sort of writing the main opinion from the Parliament regarding the proposal.
And we have a bunch of other committees, including the FAM Committee, which is for equality,
and also the Cult and the Budget opinion.
We write opinions and let the LIBE committee know what we think that they should include.
They can usually just disregard what we're saying and just continue on with what they're thinking.
We've had a draft report from the LIBE rapporteur in April, where they do have protection of
message content for end-to-end encryption, but this is a little bit like, I don't know
if you recall, the copyright directive debate, where they said, well, we're not going to
have upload filters, but we're going to ask you as a service provider, as a platform,
to do something that you can only do with an upload filter.
We're not asking you to have it, but we're asking you to provide us with an end result
that requires you to have an upload filter.
And this is a little bit what the problem is with the debate in this Crypto War 4.0,
which is going to be the next debate as well here in the Bonhac, is that they're not actually
saying precisely what it is that they want the service providers to be doing, because
they know that's going to be unpopular.
So they just sort of fudge it and say, we're going to ask you to provide us with this end
result, but we're not going to tell you where it is.
And we've had also in the draft report from the LIBE committee voluntary detection orders,
which is sort of trying to improve the position, the proposal that we came from the commission,
so instead of having it mandatory, then it's just voluntary.
And also we're going to have supporting age verification.
We're hoping that it's going to have not last 10, 15 years before we have something, but
we have sort of EU wallet where you'll be able to have age verification without sharing
your identity.
And also different mitigation measures so that you don't need to have detection orders.
In the FAM committee where I was what's called the shadow rapporteur from the renew group,
we actually had a lot of proposals on how to improve the proposal, so amendments, but
unfortunately they said that this was too technical for the Equality Committee to look
at, so they said that they were out of scope for the FAM opinion.
So this was also we have a Swedish rapporteur in the committee, and the commissioner that
has put the proposal forward is also a Swedish commissioner.
And this is like her pièce de résistance, her big thing that she wants to achieve in
this mandate of her being a commissioner.
So there's a lot of personal pride and ego in this.
So the Swedish rapporteur in the FAM committee managed to get all of our amendments taken
off the table, so they weren't included in the FAM opinion.
Nespar already mentioned the Council's legal service, and that they had an opinion saying
basically you can't do this and respect our Charter of Fundamental Rights, so basically
you're going against the sort of fundamental laws of the European Union if you want to
go forward with this proposal.
We in the Parliament asked our lawyers, the Parliament legal service, to look at the proposal,
and they came up with the same conclusion that this proposal is garbage and you shouldn't
adopt it, and it should actually be taken away and looked at again.
Unfortunately, the people who've invested a lot of private pride and commitment to this
are actually still going ahead.
So we have, this is the complementary impact assessments, where we're also saying, okay,
you cannot technically have detection orders.
You can only do that for known CSAM, and even then, if you're doing it with hash, you can
circumvent that, and it doesn't actually work.
The problem with the proposal from the Commission, in my opinion, is that you're trying to use
technology to protect kids that is not actually going to protect them because it can be circumvented,
whether we're talking about hashing for known CSAM, but also if you're looking at age verification,
for example, in app stores, then you can find the apps somewhere outside of the app store
and then upload it to your device.
We have amendments from LIBE that are actually looking quite good with protection of end-to-end
encryption and also that the targeted detection orders are actually going against persons
that are suspected in involvement of child sexual abuse, where we're saying, okay, you
can actually detect stuff, but only if you have a court order looking at it, if there
is an investigation going on, because I usually say if you want to find a needle in a haystack,
you shouldn't make the haystack bigger, but you should actually find a magnet.
If you are going to have detection orders and scanning of all of our communication,
you're going to be making the haystack bigger.
And then also, I mean, we are a parliament that's quite split on this, so there are also
some bad amendments on, for example, voluntary detection.
And the situation in the parliament is that we are very split on this proposal, and unfortunately
a lot of the people that are the rapporteurs or the shadows are quite pro the proposal,
a little bit the situation that I was talking about in the FAM Committee, where the person
is writing the opinion like the proposal and is not listening to the criticism.
So therefore, it's really important not only to influence the people that are the rapporteurs
or the shadows of the proposal, but also their wider group.
So the next steps are going to be that there are compromise amendments for the Liebe report,
and that works as the rapporteur that we looked at here from Spain and the conservative groups,
my Spanish is not good enough to pronounce that.
He will negotiate with the other political groups about what the amendments that have
been put forward and trying to find out if they can reach a compromise on the amendments.
Once they have those, they are going to be put to a vote in the Liebe Committee, and
then after that they are going to be put to a vote in the plenary where all 705 of us,
or a little bit less, and people don't care to show up, are going to vote on the proposal
as a whole.
Liebe has been postponed until October, and then after that there will be a vote in the
plenary.
So if that's going to be in October, possibly later, it will probably be in the spring just
before the election of the next European Parliament.
That means that there is a lot of personal interest of the different parliamentarians
in the result coming out, because they need to go out and defend it only weeks later in
the general public, and I think that is a real big opportunity for us to actually influence
the people in parliament, to say, are you able to go out and meet your voters and defend
what you voted through?
But that means that we need to actually try and influence not just the people in the specific
committee, but more widely.
In Renew, for example, we have a couple of members from the FDP in Germany, and Germany,
even the government, is against the proposal, as Jesper was saying, and the debates that
we've been having internally in the group has actually shifted the position of our rapporteur,
who is a Belgian lady, who is very pro the proposal.
And there has been a lot of lobbying from companies that can provide technology for
doing client-signed scanning and scanning in general, and also Ashton Krishna, who will
be appearing later in the slides as well.
And the S&D is also split.
They have a large German fraction in the political group, and they are trying to then also shift
the position of the S&D there, but there they have the problem that the commissioner, she
is a Swedish social democrat, and then how do you then balance supporting your political
family commissioner and having good legislation?
So I will very quickly sort of outline who is trying to influence the legislative process,
what is sometimes called lobbying.
We have sort of free groups of, free advocacy groups, civil society organizations like IDRI,
Electronic Frontier Foundation, CGT, and others, it's not an exhaustive list.
They tend to sort of oppose the main elements of the child sexual abuse regulation, decision
orders, and age identification that I've talked about, and at IDRI we have also called for
the entire proposal to be rejected because children deserve better.
So if you take detection orders out of her proposal that is basically all about mass
surveillance, there's very little depth doing something for children online.
So opposing us are mainly the child protection organization, or I should say some of them
are, some of them are critical, but a majority of child protection organizations throughout
Europe support the proposal, and they are sort of the most, STON supporters are really
an organization called STON led by Aston Kuster who pushes for technological solutions and
goes to the European Parliament and gives movie star explanations of how technology
works.
For instance, that Aston Kuster's scanning technology cannot be used for anything else
than child sexual abuse material, so there's absolutely no risk of mission creep.
We're talking about matching hash values, and these hash values can be anything, but
that is sort of forgotten.
Big tech service providers, Google, Meta, Apple, and so forth are also involved.
They tend to oppose mandatory measures, but they like voluntary measures when nobody tells
them what to do.
And sort of the most principled opposition that has come out is an opposition to weakening
encryption just because a law in the United Kingdom or in the European Union requires
it because this will have global effects.
So WhatsApp, Signal, and Apple, I forgot to add that to the slide, have said that in principle
they will refuse to comply with such demands.
Then maybe one day Signal will be blocked in the European Union, just like Signal is
blocked in Iran, and we'll have to use it for proxies, who knows.
That could be what we're looking at.
This is just a dude, where is my car?
This is Maurice Koerner, one of Karen's colleagues in the Renew Group, making jokes about who
is advising the Commission.
It's actually more tragic than it's funny.
And this is just to give you an example of sort of how this lobbying activity works,
sending briefing papers to parliamentarians or rather to their assistants because they
don't have time to read them themselves.
So there was a fact check of top nine claims, blah, blah, blah, from one of the child protection
organizations, which was immediately followed by a fact checking of the fact checking done
by Idrie actually by myself because Ella Jakubowsky was on holiday.
I will, in view of time, I'll skip our Idrie advocacy efforts and just mention that the
Commission really has no response to the criticism from the tech community and criticism of
technical issues in general.
There was an open letter from the scientific community signed by more than 500 at present
scientists saying that detection technologies are deeply flawed and vulnerable to attack
and that undermining end-to-end encrypted services, backdooring them, will have severe
technical implications.
Well, what was the response from the Commission?
Well, she gave a speech a week later where she sort of compared that letter to a report
from a victim of child sexual abuse to be not happening online, but that's beside the
point.
So on one hand we have this report from that individual, on the other we have an article
that is the scientific letter that only speaks about technical hypotheticals and she's sort
of basically calling it conspiracy theories, which is totally insane because it's a well-founded
critique of the proposal.
And now Karen will tell you how you can stop this or help stopping this.
I think the last slide is quite evocative of the problem.
They're proposing a technical solution where the technology that they're pointing to simply
isn't going to be working.
At the same time you have sort of front organisations saying that they're working to protect children
against sexual abuse online, saying that this is going to help and it's the only way of
helping children against sexual abuse.
And therefore we need to say, OK, we want to actually help children against sexual abuse.
We need to get some of the other children's rights organisations on board on this and
get them to speak out about the problems that this proposal is going to have on protecting
kids.
Because I think if we just look at the very real technical criticism, then we're going
to lose a lot of people because they don't actually care about the technology and the
solutions that could be proposed or not.
Because it's like, oh, there is a debate on one side and the other side and then we'll
just ignore both of them.
There is the EDRIK campaign teams, both at a European level.
There is a working group, a campaign industry working group on a slide that just was skipped.
And then there are the national organisations.
I think one of the most important things you should do if you're a Dane sitting here
is go and actually become a member of IT politics funding.
It costs you 100 hacks a year and will help to sort of reinforce the organisation and
then also join the communication campaign on this.
At the national level, the current government and members of the parliament in a lot of
countries need to approve the decision made by the government when they go into the council.
So in Denmark, EU will have to approve the mandate for negotiations and the final vote
of the Danish government when they go to the vote on the 28th of September.
So therefore it's really important that you target, for example, the EU spokesperson in
the different political parties and also the person dealing with technology.
And in Denmark we even have a digitalisation minister now.
And try and explain to them in easy, tangible ways of how this proposal is not going to
be working.
In the European parliament, you could go in and then contact the individual MEPs, both
in Liebe, ahead of the vote in Liebe.
You can go in on the committee website and see who the members are.
Emails are already available.
You can contact us and try and provide us with arguments that we can then also bring
forward in our groups.
Individual emails are, of course, better than the sort of mass emailing systems where we
just put up a filter and put that in a folder or delete it.
Because we're not that technically smart, but we can work around Outlook, which is what
we're using.
Technical input is, of course, very important.
Let us know what doesn't work.
And then also I think it's really important to try and use personal, tangible and national
arguments.
We were discussing a little bit about whether we should actually use, mention the Rasmus
Pelluden and the sort of debate that we have in Denmark and Sweden about the Quran burnings.
But I mean, try and use the political debates that are in each member state and try and
get the journalists and the politicians involved.
Communicate about this.
There's a lot of people communicating about why they think it's a good proposal.
You need to help communicate the problems that are there with the proposal.
I think it's taking what Jesper is writing, for example, in IT police screening, and repeating
it on your own websites or wherever is going to be useful.
And use the platforms that are there that you know how to use to get people's attention.
We know that this is not working.
Google has had an automated tool to detect abusive images of children, but the system
is getting it wrong.
We need to make sure that people actually understand how amazing the internet is, what
it can be used for good things.
And also that it allows young persons and children to actually engage with communities
that they are a part of but might not be present where they're living geographically.
And also that we need to make sure that the technology that we use encourage children
to actually think for themselves.
We can use technology in a good way, but the proposal from the commission is not the way
to use technology.
We're trying to hide away things, we're trying to filter things, we're breaking encryption.
And instead of using technology to actually empower kids to be able to identify danger
and seek help when they need it, and also to have the privacy that they also deserve.
So we need to actually use technology to empower children and to help them, rather than to
take away their freedom and their rights.
We have a couple of minutes left, one or two, for questions, and I don't think we have like
a thank you slide, we're not very polite, we're Danish.
So I think there is a roaming mic if you have a question or two, and otherwise we'll go
out of the tent and we'll be happy to take questions.
You started out by saying that your way into this was going to tell these people that we're
also trying to protect the children, but you didn't really come up with very much in terms
of alternatives.
What are the alternatives?
The alternatives are actually spending money on having police enforcement looking at investigations
and looking at the criminal networks that are distributing and creating child sexual
abuse material.
It is also having more responsible social media platforms, for example, and also having
like use of, for example, pop-up functions if they detect you're being asked to share
your address or meet with somebody online, that you have like a pop-up that's saying,
well, do you know this person?
Is this somebody that you trust that you want to meet with?
Do you really want to share your address with the person?
Do you want to share your phone number with them?
Help kids also to, if they want to share nude images, to think about it before they do so
they make conscious choices.
And also to make sure that we don't spend a lot of money on technology that's not going
to be working, but actually spend it on supporting kids and the children's rights organizations
rather than just spending it on technology.
But it's not been written up as a formal proposal or amendment?
I have written it up as formal amendments that were then taken out of the Equality Committee.
The problem as well is that we have, for example, Edry that's saying we should take the proposal
completely off the table and say it's so bad that we shouldn't even be discussing it and
therefore don't want to engage with the proposal and trying to see how we can improve it.
And then we have the people that just love it.
And I've been trying to strike a middle ground saying, if this is going to go through, we
need to improve it a lot so that it's acceptable what's being put into law at the end.
But it's easier to say, let's keep out of it and ask the commission to take it off the
table completely.
And that's why there's not a lot of us trying to engage with the proposal in terms of trying
to improve it rather than just getting it off the table or saying that it's wonderful.
I think it's also the case that the commission spent typically years preparing a proposal,
doing multiple rounds of consultation, writing hundreds of pages of impact assessments, considering
policy options.
And for a civil society organization like Edry to sort of do that, well, we've thought
about it, but which I know we can't do that in a credible way.
So the right thing to do is call for the proposal to be rejected so that the commission, the
next commission, without Ylva Johansson, can come up with a better proposal to protect
prison online.
Maybe we should move it outside for, so yes, by all means.
Further questions is outside.
Thank you for being here, Karen and Jesper.
Let's give them a round of applause.