Okay, this is ClausMail, I found a little vulnerability in it which I wanted to present
to you.
So this is one of the settings in ClausMail where you can configure basically what happens
when you click on a link in an HTML mail.
So it doesn't really support HTML mails, but it has some very limited HTML email rendering.
So and I saw this and I thought, okay, this looks suspicious.
Like if you're kind of security minded, then if you see something like this, this looks
like there could be some form of injection.
So yeah, so how does this work?
Like okay, it's calling Firefox and it's passing some variable which is probably what's in
the link.
So maybe we can do something like, okay, we do a link and then we close this quote, like
the single quote and then we add something that we inject and hope that this will be
executed.
The first thing I tried was something like doing a subshell or just adding another command
with this, yeah.
But this doesn't work because it's not executed as a file.
This is a shell and these are kind of shell features.
But what did work is like adding some command line option which then would be appended, then
would be passed to Firefox as a command line option.
Now you're wondering, okay, I can pass a command line option to Firefox.
Can I use that for some form of attack?
And so I looked into the command line options of Firefox.
I tried quite a few things.
I thought, okay, maybe there's some logging.
I could have a command line option somewhere and then we could write a log file somewhere,
but that, there is something like that, but you cannot really control the full file name
so that doesn't really help you.
But then I found, okay, Firefox has this option display which you can use to run Firefox on
a remote X11 server.
So basically you have, I'm not sure many people are not really aware of that, but like the
Linux.
is has some kind of client server mode
where you can have a application running on one system
and have the X server on another.
And yeah, there's the command line parameter for Firefox
where you can say, okay, run this thing,
but I want to have the basically the window shown
on a remote server.
So, okay, so putting that all together as an attacker,
you can send a link to someone that would open Firefox
and then, but then it would run Firefox actually
on the server that the attacker controls.
And then on the attacker server,
the attacker can then basically save a file
anywhere in the home there of the user.
And then he could, for example,
save it into the autostart directory,
and then it would be executed on the next login
or put it in the bash RC,
then it would be executed next time
the user opens a command line.
Yeah, so that gives you a remote code
execution vulnerability.
Yeah, this, it got a CVE,
it's fixed in the latest ClausMail version.
ClausMail is a fork of another application called Zilfeed,
but that's no longer developed, so it's not fixed there.
I tried to report it to them, but I didn't get an answer.
Yeah, and I have a demo video that's showing this.
Can you see this?
Yeah.
So, okay, so, I mean, this shows the option again.
Then, at first I'm showing, like,
just opening the DevTools console,
which basically just shows that this injection works.
And now I'm doing this with running the Firefox
on the remote server, then on the,
on the victim, nothing happens,
but then on the server from the attacker,
at some point the browser opens,
and I did this, like, right away,
I opened a URL, which contains a,
which contains this file for the attacker
that he can then put into the autostart directory.
Yeah.
So, this is just a standard for Linux desktops
in this autostart directory.
What you have in there gets executed on the next login.
Yeah, back to the victim server.
Victim logs out and logs in again,
and the, it got executed.
Yeah.
So, that was.