Hi, I'm Celta Field from the Update Computer Club and I want to tell you a little bit about
the problem we have with our collection of historic computers.
Unfortunately I could not be here today or otherwise I would have loved to talk to you
vintage computing fans at the vintage computing meetup this evening in the bar area.
So what is Update?
Update was founded as a student club.
Now my neighbor started drilling, I'm very sorry for the background noise.
It was founded at Uppsala University in Sweden already in the 1980s.
And its aim is to promote interest in and broaden knowledge about the field of computing.
It is located in the basement of the IT department and at the moment has about 80 to 90 members.
Most of the members are students, but there are also a lot of alumni that are students.
So I'm still in touch with Update.
What does Update do?
We have several rooms.
Some of them are used for students for working on their homework and exchanging knowledge.
And we have a library there as well.
And we use our space to organize lectures, conferences, workshops, and our computers
are also shown to the public in action.
And we have a library there as well.
And of course we also have social activities.
We have a server hall where we run both modern and historic hardware.
Here you can see our rooms.
This is the terminal hall where we sit and hang out and talk about computer stuff.
And there is also one of our very special collection items, Elsa, the PDP-12, which
What you can see here is the server room, it is about 32 square meters big.
Not all of the computers there are running 24-7, some of the old computers are online
only sometimes.
And here in the hallway we have an exhibition about some of the computers, but we also have
exhibitions in other rooms of the university and also sometimes in completely different
locations.
And then back here we have several storage rooms.
Our computer collection contains basically everything from microcomputers to entry-level
supercomputers and it also spans a very long time frame.
The earliest items are from the 60s.
And we even got one IBM 026 keypunch from 1949 recently.
We don't just have the computers, but we also have software, documentation, peripherals,
everything you need to actually use the computers.
And we try to keep them running.
So we sometimes replace modules or solder things that broke.
So, yes.
We actively use them.
We have a lot of them.
We use these things.
We don't just put them there to collect dust.
And we would like to run a small computer museum in the future, where we can present
running computers.
Some of our computers.
I don't want to go through all of them in detail, but you can find all of them and some
background information on them in our wiki.
It's in Swedish, but just use Google Translate or something.
And then you have all the information on them in our wiki.
All the information is there.
And if you want to have a look at them, you can.
So what's the problem?
Well the IT department is going to move to a new building at the end of this year and
we will lose our current rooms.
They have so far been very generously providing rooms, electricity and internet for us.
But in the future we will ourselves need to finance them and we need at least 60 square
meters, better 150 square meters so we can make use of the computers, because of course
they take up a lot of space and if you want to run them and work on them even more.
And on top of the rent of course we have to finance the electricity and everything that
comes with running a hackerspace basically.
But so far unfortunately there was no real interest from the university or from the municipality
to further...
support us.
So we're asking you for help.
Please support us by becoming a member.
For approximately 1000 crowns per year or 725 Danish crowns or 97 euros we can get about
a square meter per year, but the membership fee is flexible, you can pay what you want
or donate or help us find sponsors or just tell others about us.
Thanks, I hope you were interested in this, please get in touch if you have questions
and thanks for coming.