Yes, and I would like to welcome you all to our next talk,
which is Lasers in Space by Henrik Ehler.
Here you go, Henrik.
Yeah? Okay.
Not that used to microphones.
Yeah. Thanks for the invitation.
I haven't been here before, and it's...
Well, I've been here a few hours now.
It is quite a big experience.
It really seems like an amazing place.
I even tried this...
I can't describe it, but...
Yeah. Maybe you'll get used to it. I don't know.
So, yeah, I was invited to talk about
one of my side projects,
and I work a little bit here and there
on all sorts of different things.
But one of my projects is about sending stuff into space on purpose.
And, yeah, I have a small creation to the title
because it's more like it's not lasers in general,
but my laser.
Well, our laser.
So...
Um...
I'm doing the project together with a company in Aalborg.
It's not GOM Space, but something called Space Inventor.
It was founded by one of the founders of GOM Space.
And we're doing it together with ESA and...
It's not called Højteknologi Fund.
It's called the Innovation Fund.
So...
I will...
And also, if you have any questions,
during the presentation, just let me know.
And we can also take them afterwards.
Just a small disclaimer.
We are involved in a proposal for a new project
where parts of this system will be integrated into.
And the proposal has been...
The deadline for the proposal has been postponed,
meaning that I have had last night
to cut out quite a bit of my presentation
because there's just some things that I have to do.
Just some things I can't discuss yet.
Not because it's, like, government secrets,
but it's in terms of IP rights.
We have competition...
There's competition for dark...
We have competitors and...
Well, so we're keeping our cards a little bit closed
on some of the things.
But still, I mean, I have 40 slides.
So it'll be fun.
I hope.
So, yeah, we need...
I just want to go a little bit back in time
just to let you know where I'm coming from
and where the project is coming from.
So we need to go back to the...
Yeah, let's make some suspense.
The year that brought us the DAP,
BB-8,
burning hoverboards,
and, of course, Katy Perry's left shark.
Of course, I'm talking about...
I'm talking about 2015.
It's not that long ago.
But it was a time where I was a little bit
in between projects and jobs.
And a aforementioned friend of mine
who founded Space Inventors,
he approached me because he wanted to...
Well, probably a word at that time was disruption,
but he wanted to disrupt the small satellite industry.
He also knew that I was involved in DTU-SAT-2.
That was like...
At that time, it was 10 years ago,
so, yeah, I'm getting old, I guess.
And I also apologize that I don't have
higher-resolution pictures than this,
but the incident was just, I don't know,
720p at that time,
so it's the best I got.
That project was...
It was about tracking birds.
At my time on DTU, it never launched.
I think it only launched like five years ago.
But nevertheless,
there was...
It was just a few courses I had at DTU,
but it was my...
It was the starting point for this project
because I knew a little bit about space technology.
Not much, but I've touched it.
And as I said, we wanted to take a different approach
to producing and designing microsatellites.
It's been...
There are like two ways into this industry.
There are the big competitors that make huge satellites,
like governments and private entities,
and then there are the universities.
And it's two very different approaches.
So our philosophy was to take the way the big companies did it
and try to miniaturize some of these things.
And this was 2015.
About seven months later,
we attended a conference in Malta called the 4S Symposium.
It's...
It's a small conference for companies that produce
both complete satellites but also subsystems for these microsatellites.
So you won't see if the big companies,
but all sorts of startups and independent young companies
attend these symposiums.
Of course, there's also a lot of talks like here,
but also...
But...
But in this case, we had our booth where we presented our products.
Just take a sip here.
Yeah, I'm...
Okay.
So...
One of the things we did was to pack all our subsystems
into individual smaller pages or encasings, which is, again,
is the way to...
The big boys do it.
And we got...
Thanks.
It's not that bad, actually.
Just...
Just new.
Yeah.
So, anyway.
Yeah, we took this approach to design things to be very...
very robust and small, independent modules that could be stacked together.
This meant that we could...
From our Lego bricks, we could build a whole satellites in a matter of days
from off-the-shelf items we've made or not off-the-shelf,
but independent systems we've made compared to a normal microsatellite
that would take like months just to put together.
So yeah.
We got a lot of stuff in the end, but...
Okay.
So, yeah, we got a lot of stuff in the end, but...
We got a lot of attention also from Acer.
One of the products we presented was our LaserLink, or Laser Downlink Terminal, as we call it.
This was another almost coincidence, because besides my involvement with the DTU set,
I spent quite a lot of time at the photonics department at DTU.
So I also knew a little bit about lasers.
And just in a second, I will come to why we want lasers in space.
But this little thing got a lot of attention, and it was just a prototype.
We weren't really sure if it would work or how it would work.
We also met people that have been trying to do this for plus 10 years,
and they were like, how did you make this?
It's so small.
And I was like, I didn't know what to say, because it's just a prototype.
So now let's get into the reason for the product.
So why do we, yeah, that was our backstory, but why would we want to put lasers into space?
Well, it can solve quite a big problem.
A problem that is...
It's relevant both for big and small satellites, but especially for small satellites.
And it's a matter of communication.
I guess you probably guessed that by now.
But if we take a look at the traditional approach to data downlink from satellites,
again, this is not to scale.
The satellite is, in fact, quite a bit smaller.
I don't know if you can see it on this.
Yeah, sorry.
And there's no banana, but, you know.
But again, this is just a representation.
So this satellite is in what's called low Earth orbit,
which is about anywhere from 400 to 800 kilometers above sea level.
The speed is between 7.5 to 9 kilometers per second, depending on the orbit.
And that means the round time is roughly 100 minutes for rotation of the Earth.
So this means that when you want to communicate with your satellite,
this is completely different to geostationary satellites.
Of course, they have a fixed position.
That's a whole different story.
But these low Earth orbit satellites, you only have a few minutes, maybe two, three times a day,
where you can talk with...
talk with your product or your project.
And due to budget and frequency allocations,
most small satellites, they need to use the ISM bands.
So, yeah, anywhere from 400 megahertz to a few gigahertz.
And the reason for this is that they...
even though...
you try to make a very directional antenna,
you'll usually cover a circle about 3,000 kilometers,
even from this low altitude.
It means that when you try to send data,
I mean, you take up the frequency space for whole continents.
And this means that you can send with a very high power,
which again means that you can't really send very much data.
you can get a frequency allocation saying that you can use a specific frequency
and say you have a lot higher power, but it's very, very expensive
because it covers so many countries or whole continents.
So it means that the effective data rate of these small satellites
are in the kilobits range,
which is fine for housekeeping data
and just to get a beacon from your satellite.
But one of the things that people really want to do is to take pictures.
And it's not that difficult to put a nice camera on a satellite,
even the small ones, the small satellites.
But with this data rate, it takes days just to get a single image.
And if you have hyperspectral cameras
or if you have hyperspectral cameras,
or other scientific equipment that produce even more data,
you have a bottleneck there.
So that's where our laser comes into play.
First of all, the affected circle is, depending on the altitude,
it's about 100 meters compared to 3,000 kilometers.
So we only hit a very small area of the Earth,
and just due to the nature of optical transmission,
I mean, it's not picked up by all sorts of things
and garage door openers.
And it means that we can achieve speeds,
even with these small systems,
easily one gigabit per second.
But in theory, with our current system,
10 gigabits per second.
That's including overhead for error creations and so on.
So that's sort of the back story
and why the product is relevant.
I need to also say that this is not a,
an original idea.
NASA has been working on this for quite some time.
This is just a render,
but it's from a project called OPLES,
which was tested on the ISS.
So, yeah, putting lasers into space is not new,
but doing it at that small scale,
that's the,
that's also the hard part,
but that's our core business.
You could never fit this to a CubeSat.
It's,
I can't remember the exact size,
but a few meters on each direction,
as far as I remember.
So,
for those of you who are not,
don't know this,
this is a 1U CubeSat.
It's also called a U-class,
a U-class spacecraft.
It's, it was developed for use with,
especially universities to get,
just get a chance to send something into space
without being part of a huge million,
multi-billion project.
So this one liter cube is the,
it's like the minimal dimensions.
I, so,
I brought one.
This is a 2U satellite.
There's nothing in it.
It's just the mechanics.
But in principle,
you can build these up to 24 units,
not in length,
but you can go in all three dimensions.
So two by two by two or whatever you want.
But it's a nice form factor.
And it also means that many of the launch providers,
they, these are not sent up.
Usually just as the,
as the primary payload,
but they piggyback on different,
on bigger missions.
So when,
when a company paid for launch of a communication satellite,
there's also,
this gets stowed away in that glove box,
so to speak.
More precisely,
it's in a small,
in a small tube,
and it'll get ejected into,
into space after the satellite,
after the satellite has been released from the,
from the launch vehicle.
Another great thing about this philosophy
is to use a lot of what's called off-the-shelf,
no, commercial off-the-shelf equipment,
means that we,
you don't have to develop everything yourself.
You can use,
is my computer making a noise?
Oh, never mind.
I just didn't know what was going on.
But you can use,
like off-the-shelf camera modules and so on,
because it's not,
it's not a critical thing if it doesn't work,
but at least you learn something.
So the,
also the technology level,
witness level requirements for sending a CubeSat
into space is a lot less than for,
for real spacecraft.
Anyway, what did I,
so as,
as you can see in the picture of January of this year,
about 1,300 CubeSats are in orbit,
or they have been launched.
1,200 successfully,
and 90 has been destroyed in launch failures,
or are just not operational,
or was never operational.
Since these are built by primarily students,
so, yeah, mistakes happen.
Both the first,
the first few CubeSats from Denmark wasn't functional,
not for long as I remember.
And, yeah.
This is just a,
this is a render of one new CubeSat made
with a space inventor.
The, yeah, the kind of price,
these are quite inexpensive.
A guy like this with solar panels and some payload
will run you just about 200, 300,000 euros.
So it's, it's affordable.
So,
I'll go into a little bit details about the laser project.
And some of the drawings I'll show you
are of a little bit older date,
because as I said, we,
we ran into some issues.
So, yeah.
Last night, we got in what we can show them,
but we can't.
So,
this is way too small to see, right?
Okay.
So I have, let's see.
Yeah.
This just simplified diagram of the system.
I just, now it's upside or on the side,
but at least a little bit bigger.
Just to show you the main components of the laser terminal.
We have the OBC, which is onboard computer.
It communicates with something called a space wire,
which is a derivative of a fire wire.
No, it's not a joke.
It's, it's real.
It sounds way cooler.
I mean, fire wire was already a cool name, but you know.
And then we have the optical subsystem.
It consists of two parts.
It consists of a seed laser.
We're running at 1260, 1064 nanometers.
And the seed laser is what we modulate with our data signal.
It goes into a fiber amplifier,
which amplifies the signal from a few milliwatts
to about one watt optical output power.
It's not, I mean, it's not that much.
You can get laser pointers.
You shouldn't, but you can.
They're way more powerful than this.
But our beam is much nicer.
I assure you that.
And then we have some mechanics for fine steering.
And I'll come back to why we need that.
One of the big issues with a system like this is,
remember we only hit 100 meters per second.
That's the size of the target.
It's not 100 meters.
Well, not target, but our beam is just 100 meters
from four to six hundred kilometers away.
So it's quite difficult to hit the right, hit the target.
Small satellites like this one, they, when they're in orbit,
they are not, they, I mean, they rotate like crazy.
They are not, this is very hard to see.
It's not that easy to see.
they're not stationary and that's why we have something called attitude control system but
even with with a system like this they are very very unstable I mean we are talking things like
plus minus a whole degree of movement which is which is fine for everything else but almost
trying to hit the earth with a laser so it's quite fine and to control system is consist of
two major components reaction wheels which just imagine a skateboard wheel with a motor and you
can spin it up and we have this whole thing about a reaction and action and reaction mean then we
spin something in one direction the whole spacecraft spins in the other direction we
have four of those so we can
orient or we can turn in all directions and then we have something called magnet augers and that's
because when these wheels they hit a certain speed they can't go any faster so at certain intervals
we need to dump our the energy in the wheels so we lock with these magnetic or with these calls
we can sort of lock on to the earth make earth's magnetic field
mean that we by sending um power to the course we can keep the spacecraft stationary right we
spin down the wheels and when we're done with that we can start spinning up the wheels and
getting into position again that's also a whole science that's that's also a product for space
inventor so just let me know if you want to buy one um anyway with this system we can get the
pointing accuracy of about plus minus one degree which is nowhere near
good enough for for our laser but we are getting there um but that's just that's not the only
problem because we the spacecraft sort of knows where it is but not precisely when you launch a
spacecraft you you'll get your um the orbit parameters back from the launch providers and
you can kind of predict where where the
spacecraft will be at a given time and you can relay this data to a spacecraft
and it will kind of know where to point the laser
um but again it's not precise enough so we need a beacon from Earth uh which we send into space
it could look like this but it doesn't um it's just it's just a small five watt laser and it
goes out of a telescope so it's a quite big beam
so it's I mean we it's it's kind of boring actually uh but we we we point the the lasers
to the area in the sky where we expect the satellite to be when we want to communicate with
um we don't know exactly where it is so on the first orbits will go in some special patterns
uh actually just circle going upwards just in hopes to to get a log on
uh other people that have tried this if you need to use multiple uh orbits just to to get the first
light uh hitting the satellite so we're very not concerned but yeah let's see how it goes
um and actually we we just to correct myself we don't point at the salary we have some pointer
hit so because uh a little bit of uh travel time so we point to the other and then we do the same thing
to where we expect the spacecraft to be when the beam hits it.
Let's go back to this slide again.
On the far top right, you can see that's where the beacon laser hits the spacecraft,
and it goes through some optics,
and then the beacon laser is focused down just to a commercial machine vision camera.
We use that to track the dot around on the chip.
One thing I can tell you, on this image,
you probably can't see it,
but the whole right box, at that time we designed this,
we wanted to move both the receiver and all the optics.
We changed that a little bit, so now we have some mirrors that will take care of all the pointing.
But nevertheless, we received the beacon laser in this camera,
and we didn't know how the satellite is aligned to the ground station.
So we decided to use a telescope to see how it works on Earth.
And just to stay in the whole realm of commercial products,
this is our ground station.
It's a big telescope.
Well, it's 10 or 12 inches, so it's for the serious amateur, I guess.
But it is off the shelf.
So it's a telescope.
We, of course, we modified it a bit, but that's the basis of our ground station.
Now you'll get another drawing that you probably can't see,
but I did the same trick again, so I don't know if it's better,
but this is the whole ground segment.
We have the telescope that will both send out the beacon laser towards the spacecraft,
but also receive that downlink laser.
So, this is the telescope that will both send out the beacon laser towards the spacecraft, but also receive that downlink laser.
And the laser goes into something called, well, it's just a very sensitive photodiode,
which we use to demodulate the signal.
And then a whole lot of stuff going on,
but again, it's built up around this commercial telescope and then just a small box.
And this, now I'll just shortly cover the fine steering.
That means the way we steer the beam from the spacecraft,
and that's one of the areas where we run into quite some issues.
This is a MEMS mirror.
I don't know if you are familiar with MEMS devices,
but they are in gyroscopes and all other things.
And they, I mean, this is a perfect mirror for some applications at least.
Just to go back to this image again,
the mirror replaces the whole right box.
So, we don't, it doesn't move the optics,
it just moves the beam, just to.
But, so, this is one of the areas where you,
need to remember that we are in space.
The beam is just about one watt, the downlink beam.
It's not that much.
But due to the way that MEMS devices work,
this small mirror, it's about eight millimeters in diameter.
It needs to have a very, very low mass,
because these MEMS motors, at least not,
these types are not very powerful.
So.
And we need to move it quite rapidly.
Not like we are scanning,
but we need to keep up with different things.
So.
We have one watt laser hitting a very, very light mirror.
And we don't have any air.
So, this mirror is extremely shiny,
or reflective, as you probably see.
But there is a small loss.
And this small loss is converted into heat,
and the mass is almost nothing.
So, if we try to do this,
we will end up with a burning mirror very quickly.
And now we go into the part of the presentation
I can't go into.
But we did solve this.
I can tell you a bit about some of the things we tried
and failed miserably.
We tried to encase the mirror in a small box
with a window in it,
and fill it with an atmosphere of helium, I think.
Can you remember?
No, nitrogen, of course.
Trying to make use of convection.
And, yeah.
That wasn't a success.
We also tried to get piezo actuators.
They are very powerful,
and they can easily move a big mirror,
and a heat sink,
and the whole desk.
But the way they work,
they only move, like,
almost at the nanometer scale.
Meaning that,
and they have an expected lifetime of,
a certain amount of millions of movements they can do.
So, if you try to use a project like this,
in our case,
it will stop,
it will be at the end of life
in about 15 minutes.
Because it's sort of a technology
that's used for more stationary objects.
So, yeah.
A little bit about the future.
We hope to fly this prototype next year.
We have passed something called
a critical design review,
actually last year.
Then due to COVID and other stuff,
we have not been working that much
as of lately,
but now it's picking up again.
We have some,
we're working right now on the flight model.
So, now we have everything lined up
at a breadboard level.
Both the electronics and the optical systems.
And now we're integrating the whole,
yeah, this square meter of stuff
into a small box.
With some luck,
this work will be done around Christmas.
And then if we pass all the reviews and tests,
then we just have to wait
for a launch opportunity.
It could be with a rocket,
it could also be tossed out of the window of the ISS.
It's up to ESA to give us this opportunity.
So, yeah.
And this was about 10 minutes less than expected.
But again, I'm sorry I couldn't tell you much
about everything.
But if there's any questions,
let me know.
Any questions?
Yeah, we can start up here.
How do you deal with atmospheric refractions?
Because you don't have a kind of reference laser
that tells you about the state of the atmosphere
to compensate for that.
Disturbances?
Yeah.
So, we,
for the first tests and so on,
we are going to see how it goes.
But you can do like doing the big telescopes
with adaptive optics
and having a laser pointing towards the sky
and measuring the surface.
So, it's not going to be a big disturbance.
So, it will probably be needed in a commercial setting.
We chose 1064 nanometers.
We could also use a 1550 like you use in telecom.
Both of those frequencies are almost not dampened
by the atmosphere.
It will still be disturbed,
but there's not much absorption.
You told us there's like a 100 meter spot.
You have following and tracking.
But what's the window of time you can communicate
before you get out of reach
because there's a 7.5 kilometer per second going by?
It depends on the orbit.
Also, if we're standing here
and the satellite goes above us,
it can be way out on the horizon
and we only have a horizon.
And we only have a very limited time
or it can go right above us.
And it also depends on the height of the orbit.
But we designed the system
to get about four or five minutes window.
If we get very low into the horizon,
even though I said it's 1064 nanometers,
it doesn't get absorbed that much by the atmosphere.
Just like when you have the sunset,
when the light has to go through a lot more air,
it gets dampened a lot more.
Just a few minutes.
Any more questions?
No?
Thank you very much.
Thanks for having me.