I would like to welcome Flummer, who is going to speak about this year's batch.
You go ahead.
Thank you very much.
So yeah, this year we actually managed to have batches ready for check-in.
So I guess most of you already have the batch.
In the next little time, we'll go through some of the thoughts behind the decisions
that we made about batches this year, and then explain a little on what's on the batch,
and what can be added to the batch, and also how to add stuff to the batch.
Little ideas, and finish off with ways of integrating with existing batches if you
have one from a previous year.
And then the last thing is a little competition, so to get people started and sort of motivate.
So do a little thing and see if you can manage to hack something.
We have a little competition.
So the past year and a half, especially last year, electronics sort of supply chain has
had some issues.
Some companies thought that when Corona hit, they wouldn't sell anything, so they canceled
their pre-orders.
But people still wanted cars because people didn't want to sit in buses.
So when the car industry figured out and then found out that people still want to buy cars,
they kind of want their parts back.
But the whole supply chain had said, yeah, we already sold that slot to somebody else,
because the whole graphic card system.
Yeah.
And obviously, the parts business and Bitcoin mining and people working from home need the
extra graphic card.
They needed the extra capacity.
So stuff didn't sort of work out as the auto industry had hoped.
And that has sort of trickled out.
And right now, we are in a state where some parts you can easily get, you can just buy
them as you normally could, but other parts, especially ones are sort of silicon and some
more advanced stuff.
some simple like voltage regulators that everybody needs them but but they still
need to be manufactured a little bit more sort of advanced than the very
simple parts those parts are sort of just not able to you can't get them
especially parts that are little sort of have a very specific feature they they
are like the screenshot here that's I took it like earlier today this is not
that bad it's only half a year out you can get the parts but normally they had
like 47 like 47 weekly time that means when you order them that it'll be 47
weeks until you get them for large-scale production where you plan ahead might be
okay normally it's in the five maybe 20 weeks but for a little batch project
that we do we usually sort of rely on the distributors just having stock that
we can get them like that and then we can get the parts that we need to get
like day to day almost um so with this little sort of uncertainty uh we decided
this spring uh that's making a patch that had a bunch of these parts that are somewhat
difficult to get um would be a challenge where it's not fun to have a badge like two weeks after
born hack um so so we ended up even though I had more or less a design for a batch and making one
from parts in the way in my little workshop that I can do that but if we need like several hundred
of them um this whole production setup is it needs to be sort of used and and if that is somewhat
flaky the risk of not having a badge is very high the previous years this has been just like the
first or second day of born hack they are done um if we're pushing that just a few days it breaks down
um years batch is something very different um it's a batch that focuses much more on the
electronic side than the previous year's patches um it's simple um but what you want to make of
it you can sort of choose yourself a little bit um the batch has a bunch of prototyping area
that's little holes and the little pads that that sits on the on the front of the badge the holes
are spaced in a distance that is very common for many little sort of through hole parts where you
put the pins through the holes and then you sort of them on the back side where the the pads without
the holes little square ones those are for the surface mount components and the spacing are also
useful for the for for the slightly larger parts um so it though the the shape of the pads and the
placing will help
in soldering them um you don't have to solder SMD parts but having a little practice I think it's
a good thing if you want to fix uh your electronics stuff does break down and often you can fix it and
every type of electronics you have today will be SMD surface mounted devices um so the badge also
has the connector um it's a similar collector connector as the um connect the footprint similar
to the previous years
uh but for this patch you can actually decide whether you want the batch as
uh a batch that has maybe power and then you can power other add-ons or you can use this batch as
an add-on by putting the connector on the back side instead um and then you can have it as add-on
to previous years batches if you want for instance to to get started coding and that's sort of what
you want then you can make this into an add-on and then make some LEDs or temp sensor or something on
this and then you can do the coding on the
batch from the previous year the little uh that's a little connector called uh quick or stem acuity
that's a standard that uh spark fun and uh Adafruit has made it uses similar connectivity as the add-on
connector so that's also there'll be a slide also a little later also the I2C pins are sort
of broken out so it's easier if you want to add something from functionality both on the throughhole area
and markings on the back and then on the SMD area if you want to add a little temp sensor or something
you can also write your name on it if it's uh I guess that's the bare minimum of hacking your
batch it's just a writing name on with a sharpie the batch is open source so for us like the previous
years you can download the files their KiCad files there's also a schematic um the URLs on the batch
is PCB way so we got them to to make them and a nice glossy gold finish
so since these are very sort of hardware focused uh and people usually don't bring a lot of parts
uh I made a bunch of boxes with little containers in them with a lot of different parts it's not
everything because millions of parts exist but they are parts that are
Meats for higherد
fairly easy to sort of get going with.
It's resistors, capacitors, some transistors
so you can make very simple circuits.
And there's a bunch of LEDs.
I have colored LEDs in, I think I have six,
seven different types, some of them with multiple colors
in the same one.
There's even LEDs that blink themselves
and you just need to power and then they
will do little flashy things.
So depending on what sort of type of hacking
you are interested in, you can start
get going with very simple things,
just add some sort of battery holder.
I have three different types.
Then maybe a little bit of wire and then an LED
and then you have something that will blink in the bar.
We have a hardware hacking area.
It's the big white tent in the middle of the general camping.
Up there, there are sawing irons,
there are extra lights for detail work.
There are these boxes with parts and you're welcome
to grab parts and add to your batch.
It's of course not meant to grab the whole box
but taking it out.
But if you're taking individual parts and hanging them on
and putting it on and making something,
that's what they're for.
So feel free.
There are also some microcontroller stuff.
It's mostly MSP430s.
They are very easy to get going, three volts, no problem.
I also have some programmers for the different types
of microcontrollers that are there.
Come get me and we can figure out how to program these chips.
The whole microcontroller thing is for people
who maybe have a little experience
because they are very, it's just the chip
and some capacitors and then you have
to do everything yourself.
But if you want to do that, that's definitely an option.
There are even some with Wi-Fi on the little breakout board.
Some ideas like blinking LEDs,
definitely have some flashy for the bar.
There are also a little buzzer or some jacks for headphones
if you want to make some audio thing maybe playing with that.
With a few transistors, two capacitors, and some resistors,
you can actually make audio.
You can make sounds in different frequencies.
So playing with that could be an interesting idea for.
Also, we have some vibration sensors,
maybe like an alarm system where if you touch the badge,
then it'll trigger a little LED and you
can see somebody has touched your badge.
You can put it on top of your laptop, have an alarm there.
Also, of course, there's a lot of stuff
that you can do.
So a vibration motor, maybe some identifier or alert stuff,
maybe combining with another badge.
And then, of course, the microcontrollers.
I also have some temp sensors.
These are, the temp sensors are surface mounts
and they require a little practice maybe.
But we will hang out in the hardware hacking area
and be able to help.
So if people want to learn to solder for the first time,
I'll be happy to help.
And there are also a bunch of other,
team members that will hang out there
and know how to solder and can teach people.
A little on the little, there's a connector on the edge
that, well, on the badge it's empty,
but you can add this little connector.
I also have these connectors.
It's for a standard.
I don't have the modules, but this standard
seems to be fairly popular.
Both SparkFun and Adafruit are using them
for a lot of different ports they have.
And I've seen people.
I've used these for getting prototypes very quickly.
And if you make the badge into an add-on for another badge,
the I2C signals are passed through out to this connector
so you can add sensors or buttons or whatever
in this sort of series of add-ons via this badge
on to other badges.
And also, yeah, I have all the connectors.
This is a little indication of how it will look
when you add the badge as an add-on.
Last year's badge didn't have the connector populated,
but there was a spot for it.
The connectors you can use for last year's badge,
those will also be in the hardware hacking area,
so if you want to add that to your badge.
And then to get people,
you can add a lot of different things to the badge.
So that's how it's going.
We have a bit of little merge things.
And I think for the first five people
who have something blinking on the badge,
the kids, for the kids it's okay to use the little LEDs
that blink themselves.
I think for everybody else,
something else should be controlling the LEDs.
How you do it, I'm open to pretty much anything.
You can use another badge,
but it should be a self-containing thing
that can hang around your neck and have batteries on there.
And if you use another badge,
you should use the connector.
You can't just do random wires.
But I think it's not that difficult.
It should be possible.
And for the first five that come and show a badge blinking,
that'll be a little gift,
one of the little badges that we got
from the sponsor, all these little rulers.
They're very handy.
They have all the little measurements
and the hole sizes and component sizes.
Very, very nifty.
So I would say, happy hacking.
And if there are questions, I'd love to answer.
Yeah, in the back.
That'll be a microphone, also for the stream.
We need the microphone.
In the central connector,
the six pin connector in the middle,
there is a pin called ground,
and ground is clearly connected
to the row of the breadboard called ground.
But there are only three wires going to the corner
that connects to the...
if I remember correctly, all the area in between the little holes are actually ground.
So there's like a flood of copper all the way around, and that is connected to ground.
I have a microscope up in the hardware hacking area, and we can go in and look.
So usually when you look very close to the little path, the round path,
there will be a little extra going out.
So the flood fill on the PCB, we can also open it up in KiCad,
and I can show you how the copper layers are on the batch.
All right.
Other questions?
Yeah, do you have any proximity sensors?
I have a few of these, yeah, Echo.
It's like little modules, but I have a few of those, actually, yeah.
Okay.
Other?
You said you didn't have any Stamak-QT modules, but do you have the wires for the Stamak-QT?
I think I can find one of two if you want to test stuff out.
I have a little collection of my own stuff.
Yeah.
Any other questions?
No?
Then let's give Flummer a hand, both for the talk and the work with the batch.
Thank you.