Okay, welcome everybody, and welcome to Saneva Book, Sandbooks, and you will talk about peerhood
and privatization of money.
Yes.
Thanks a lot for coming on this very early morning.
My name is Saneva, and I've just finished my PhD degree at the IT University, and I'm
now continuing there as a postdoctoral researcher at the Center for Digital Welfare, and I'm
going to be talking a bit today about research for my PhD on how, hold on, the dynamics of
Indonesian ride-hailing apps affect how money circulates through integrated payment platforms.
And if that's a lot of very long words, don't worry, there'll be more.
We'll go through them slowly.
And before I start, I just want to give a big shout-out to the illustrator, Nadia Rizki,
who's Indonesian and who made a lot of the drawings that are in this presentation.
So, would you like a top-up?
So, throughout my fieldwork in Indonesia, I encountered many variations of this particular
question from drivers of the ride-hailing platforms called Gojek and Grab, which are
equivalent to, like, Uber or Volt in Indonesia.
And what they wanted to know was, would I be interested in purchasing some digital money
for my own digital account?
So, in practice, it works like this.
The driver and I agree on a sum of money.
The driver...
Then uses the integrated payment mechanism of the app platform, so imagine Uber, but
with a separate money system, to make a digital transfer to my account.
And then I give the driver cash of the equivalent amount of money.
I can now use my newly topped-up balance to pay the next driver digitally, rather than
paying cash.
And for those familiar with the more seamless digital transactions of similar ride-hailing
and food delivery apps...
...this moment of experience...
...this moment of exchange between the driver and the passenger may seem peculiar or cumbersome,
so why not just pay the next driver with cash in the same way that I am de facto paying
this driver cash to have a digital balance?
The fact is that most people in Indonesia do not use credit or debit cards to make digital
payments.
And so this way, storing money as a digital credit and using a smartphone application
is becoming an increasingly popular way to have digital money.
Such mobile-based transactions are sometimes referred to as peer-to-peer, a concept I'm
sure a lot of you are familiar with from the tech sector.
And what they do in this context is allow users to transfer money digitally, directly,
without using a bank.
In Indonesia, the ride-hailing apps benefit from having a fleet of what's called on-demand
drivers who operate as exchange agents, like in this top-up moment, and therefore they
also operate as an extension.
So today, we're going to talk about four things.
First, we're going to examine the concept of peer-to-peer payment.
We're going to understand what digital money means in an Indonesian context, and we're
going to talk about how hassle-free digital payment is experienced at the interface level.
And finally, we're going to talk about how these apps configure consumers and drivers
to very specific transactional constellations.
Before we do that, I'm just going to quickly give you some context.
My research is based on six months of fieldwork in Jogja, a city in Indonesia, which took place
between 2018 and 2019, just as digital payments were becoming really popular.
And so I did a lot of what's called participant observation, as well as interviews with drivers,
customers, the companies, and several stakeholders.
But I also started to collect screenshots.
So I did a lot of what's called participant observation, as well as interviews with drivers, customers, the companies, and several stakeholders.
So I did a lot of what's called participant observation, as well as interviews with drivers,
especially when drivers that I was interviewing started sharing me their screens to try and
explain how they experienced the digital economy.
And so I started to begin paying attention to these app interfaces to examine how the
app's design was affecting my engagement, not just with drivers, but with money itself.
For example, in this screenshot, which was when this app had given me a little token
to spin because I had made a transaction.
And the app goes.
It landed.
it, and it landed on six points. And the app was like, hey, you know, you could have had
175 points if only you had used GoPay instead of cash. So the design of these apps is not
neutral. It affects your experiences and shapes your behaviors, specifically into channeling
more money through the system. At the core of my work were two of the most prominent
Indonesian digital payment apps at the time, GoPay and Ovo. Both gained traction as integrated
payment mechanism of the respective ride-hailing platforms, Gojek and Grab. GoPay only exists
as a digital wallet inside the Gojek app, so not like mobile pay here. You can only
use it inside this platform. Ovo operates as a standalone discount platform for an Indonesian
mall franchise originally, and it also exists across multiple e-commerce platforms today,
so it's kind of like a white-label wallet, except they keep their wallet, or their label.
So the GoPay app is a digital wallet, and it's a digital wallet, and it's a digital
wallet. So through the fleets of their drivers, they have managed to convert customers of
existing transport services into customers of financial services. And that's really,
really critical. So let's examine the concept of a peer-to-peer transaction in more detail.
And to begin, let me describe an advertisement that Gojek released for Ramadan in 2016. These
are some stills from this advertisement. You see a young girl. She's wearing a white
shirt. She's asking her mother if she'll be home in time to break the fast for Ramadan.
As she dons her distinctly green Gojek helmet, the mother gives her a small package, telling
her to open it when she breaks the fast. We see clips of the mother driving passengers
to and fro. It's hot. She's tired. All these customers are cranky and rude. Her final passenger
is taking food to an orphanage for Ramadan, of course. And as she watches all these happy
children, the mother smiles, despite everything.
Meanwhile, her daughter opens the gift alone. It's a box of dates and it contains a card
from her mother apologising because they can't be together. The reason, she explains in the
note, is that mom needs to make sure that everyone else gets home in time to celebrate.
Finally, alone on her motorcycle and having her first drink of water, the mother receives
messages as customers send grateful thanks and positive ratings through the app platform.
So firstly, this advertisement presents the imagined participants in the exchange as two
overarching categories of user for the platform, the service provider and the service customer.
Secondly, besides the green helmet, the company itself is hardly present.
The app's role as an intermediator of the exchange only becomes apparent towards the
end when the phone makes its first appearance.
Instead, the advertisement emphasizes how these users are social equals, helping each
other out in an important social, cultural and religious event.
What it does not emphasize is the precarity of the single mother who cannot be home since
she must work long hours.
Instead, it almost seems as if she's doing this work out of a sense of social responsibility
towards her peers.
Notably, money is never seen nor mentioned.
The word peer itself, of course, has a very specific social meaning.
And instead, it generally refers to a person or object of equal status or rank to someone
or something else.
And I am particularly interested in how the phrase peer-to-peer, which we know as a term
from computing, came to describe an economic transaction, and how the retention of the
term peer in this context imbues the expression P2P payments with certain social meaning.
Firstly, various definitions of the word peer.
The word peer are all characterized by the critical underlying trait that being a peer
is something that can only be defined in relation to something else.
Secondly, all uses imply a sense of equality within the peer relation, whether it's socioeconomic
or computational.
Originally used to describe a non-hierarchical network topology, the phrase peer-to-peer
or P2P is now being more commonly used outside of tech communities to describe diverse types
of digital value transactions.
The term peer-to-peer is a term that is used to describe the ability of a person to transfer
money to another person without the use of a bank, a practice greatly valorized by the
first generation of the world's most advanced technology companies, such as Apple and Google.
The term peer-to-peer is a term that is used to describe the ability of a person to transfer
money to another person without the use of a bank, a practice greatly valorized by the
Solintec industry for creating access to important financial services normally considered
inaccessible to the poor or socio-economically marginalized people.
I am particularly interested in how this phrase came to describe this economic transaction,
and how the retention of the term peer to peer retains these social meanings, and I
would love to talk more about this with you, both today and later.
So a peer-to-peer transaction, where one person
transfers a form of as Neurodenamics to seconds and another person rose to
experience it, È that one person transfers the financial benefits from financial benefits
that all of their businesses do to that person climb up to that person, and then he comes
And in such a job this more clearly means that people need to meted to på me by the 보 y μια
digital value to another.
But the language of peer-to-peer is prominence
within the use of commercial digital wallets
and perpetuates the idea of mutual exchange
in accordance with the P2P ideal of a flat, symmetrical,
or egalitarian relationship without an intermediary.
But this transaction to someone has to happen
through something, through hardware, services, networks,
app interfaces, agents, third parties,
the intermediaries of the transaction.
Thus, rather than interpreting the two
as a numerical representation of the direction
of the transaction, it might serve an analytical purpose
to consider it a placeholder for the intermediaries
through which the transaction travels.
The apps.
The simplistic representation of the directional transaction
implied by the P2P acronym provides a superficial rendering
of the complex exchange relationship it actually contains.
It might instead be useful
to understand this term as a relational acronym,
where the so-called peers on either side of the exchange
have their own relationship, as well as relationships
to the intermediaries.
The use of the phrase peer-to-peer,
rather than, for instance, user-to-user,
undeniably also introduces all of these implicit social meaning
to the exchange relationship.
In the context of P2P and network nodes,
peer is used as an alternative to the hierarchical arrangement
of a client and server, right?
But what is the equality implied in the P2P
of payments?
Are they peers of equal social status?
Is it that they are accessing the same resource
or are presumed to have the same capacity
for operating the technology?
Is it within the configurations of the technology
that they're defined as equal parties?
Or is this peerhood one that emerges
when all other aspects of their social context are removed,
leaving only equality because everything
but the fact of the exchange itself has been stripped away?
The term P2P confuses not only the context of the exchange, but also the user.
these complex relational dynamics, but also obscures the power that the intermediaries
thus exert in configuring the conditions of the exchange relationship of the alleged peers.
In science and technology studies, we talk a lot about how the emergence of a technology
must also entail the emergence of the user.
So rather than being a specific person, the user is a composite character, a caricature
of what kinds of actions those designing the technology imagine its future users to make.
A peer is, of course, also a user of the technology, but the term peer, as we've discussed, introduces
additional dimensions to the person and perhaps also requirements from the technology.
If you're going to call your user a peer, what does that mean for your technology?
What is it you're going to have to put into that code to make sure that there's some sort
of equality in that relationship?
After all, how would you configure for peerhood?
So by thinking about peerhood, you're going to have to think about how do you configure
for peerhood, you're going to have to think about how do you configure for peerhood, you're going to have to think about how do you configure
these self-declared neutral platform companies and the configuration of users into exchange
relationships, we can really begin to unpack the effect of the technology on the many P's
and the many 2's within digital payments in Indonesia.
Which is what we'll do now.
So to understand how the apps work and how they're experienced in practice, we need first
to understand a few things about the existence of digital money in Indonesia.
Firstly, it's important to address the fact that Indonesia has
been going through massive economic growth since political and economic instability
in the late 90s.
But though the poverty rate has fallen, income and wealth inequality has also been growing
rapidly.
Presently, the richest four men share a combined wealth of more than the poorest million.
Thus, despite economic developments, many people still do not have or use a bank account.
The government has initiated multiple projects to increase what they call financial inclusion.
And in 2019, they declared that the government would be able to increase the amount of money
that the government would be able to invest in the country.
The government also declared that over 75% of the population now had access to a bank
account.
A critical step, one might argue, in an overarching public policy to become what they call a less-cash
society.
For most Indonesians, digital payment has generally meant using a debit card to make
a payment at a shop or an ATM card, which, aside from making withdrawals at an ATM machine,
also allows users to access their bank accounts or make transfers directly at the machine.
For most people that I spoke with?
The emphasis was therefore not on digital money itself, but on the ability of the ATM
to transition money between being digital and tangible, as they needed it to be.
Within the population that has access to a bank account, only a minority own a credit
card.
In fact, according to the Global Findex database, only 2.4% of the adult Indonesian population
had a credit card in 2017.
And for those who can pay by card?
This is the type of you that might meet you in a supermarket.
This is the type of you that might meet you in a store or cafe.
This thing that the machines are standing on is called the terminal tree.
It's a little structure.
So despite increasing interoperability between banks and payment providers, customers using
these infrastructures from banks other than their own can still face substantial fees.
And so for the people who are receiving payments, it becomes critical to be able to provide
for all of your customers, which is also quite expensive, and which means that those who
can afford to have all of the relevant terminals can.
And those who cannot, cannot.
Therefore, each bank needs its own EDC terminal, as can be seen in these pictures.
So whereas digital money stored in your bank can be mobilized using a plastic card, electronic
money, or e-money, was given a distinct legal definition in 2009 as a type of digital credit
balance issued and stored by a private actor.
E-money.
E-money is issued based on the equivalent value of state-issued money deposited by a
holder to the issuer, the holder being the customer, the issuer being the companies.
It is stored electronically in a media such as a server or a chip.
It is used as a means of payment to a merchant, which could be a shop, cafe, or of course,
drivers.
E-money is what apps like Gojek and GoPay and OVO provide access to.
It's a type of debt that Gojek or OVO issue to you and which they repay you when you use
the app to pay one of their affiliated merchants, effectively by transferring your credit record
to the record of the merchant, after which it can be withdrawn again as cash.
While the use of e-money has been rapidly increasing these past years, as can be seen
to the left, it's worth noting that despite all of the hype of, like, mobile-based transactions,
the amount of money being transacted in this way pales in comparison to the more conventional
uses of ATM or debit transactions.
Just so we really manifest, hype is hype.
So, when the discourse surrounding digital payments emphasizes the phrase cashless or
less cash, as advocated by the Indonesian government, we obscure what it is that these
cash transactions are being replaced by.
As digitalization draws attention to the importance of cash, it's also important to note that
the use of e-money is not necessarily the same as cash transactions.
In addition to the underlying infrastructures of money, particularly the concept of payments
has received renewed academic attention.
When you make a digital payment, what you're doing is requesting the entity which keeps
your record of accounts to alter that record and the record of the person that you are
making the payment to.
This generally takes place through banks and various third-party payment processors.
Thus, what happens in a cashless or less cash society is essentialization.
It's the centralization of control over payment infrastructure.
Where cash can be considered a public, state-issued social infrastructure, digital payments are
generally the domain of private entities.
Though the money transacted through the Gojek app may be denominated in the state-issued
Indonesian rupiah, the tokens are contained within and transported through their private
infrastructure.
Thus, these apps not only determine the price to be paid for their services, but also determine
the price to be paid for their services.
But the price of payment itself, as we will see shortly.
For the intermediaries processing these digital payments, the value in providing payment infrastructure
shifted with digitalization.
From imposing fees or rent in exchange for the service of physically moving money, to
the value of the transactional metadata itself.
So when I purchase things through the Gojek app, I let the app and its owners know where
I like to shop, what I like to buy, what my transport routes are, and what I want to buy.
Where cash is anonymous and usable only by whoever is holding it, digital money becomes
hyper-personalized.
The digitalization of money has facilitated this unprecedented aggregation of transactional
metadata.
Thus, to quote economic anthropologist Bell Maurer, for intermediaries, the dream is for
a system where value enters a network, circulates endlessly, never leaving as material cash.
The goal of the Gojek app is to create a system where value enters a network, circulates endlessly,
never leaving as material cash.
For Gojek, the self-declared goal is to become a super app.
An app that provides for all of a customer's wants and needs by hosting other apps within
the overarching umbrella of a single platform.
As the head of the Gojek data engineering team writes on the company blog, the biggest
moat Gojek ever built is payments.
Once you're handling money for a user, you can build a castle of services within it.
The moat...
This is not his quote.
This is me now.
The moat is comprised of the digital credits issued privately through the GoPay wallet.
Purchased using Indonesian rupiah, these GoPay credits can be used exclusively for services
within the Gojek platform.
Thus, it is Gojek that controls the metaphorical drawbridge which both gives access to and
confines money, services, and people within the moat boundaries.
So, it's this expansion.
Expansion from a ride-hailing app into the center of our social economic exchange practices
and the subsequent dynamics that these platforms introduce to the circulation of value that
deserves increased scrutiny.
Where cash can be exchanged from one hand to another, digital money requires a little
more infrastructural support, such as QR codes or the EDC terminals we saw earlier.
And much of this infrastructure is rendered invisible by design.
Thus, allowing users to, famously, pay without hassle, the underlying infrastructures become
concealed within these frictionless aesthetics.
So, let's go for a little walk inside this friction- and hassle-free castle.
When you open either the Gojek or Grab app, this is the home screen that greets you.
In both apps, the digital wallet appears as a menu bar at the top of the screen, which
shows you your balance, denominated in rupiah.
The menu allows you to top up or make payments.
And lures you to the top of the screen.
And lures you in with the promise of more features.
Only to reveal that you have to be a premium user to access features like withdrawing your
money or sending money to other people.
Thus, for regular users, money stored in the app can only exit again in the form of payment.
Only through consumerism can you use this money for anything.
If you want to top up your balance, the app specifically asks you to make a payment using
a debit card.
In other words, you are buying GoPay credits.
Not unlike how you would buy a gift card for a very favorite shop.
And for those without a debit card or a bank account, remember, not everyone has those,
the app provides very detailed instructions for a variety of alternative top-up methods.
First and foremost, suggesting that you ask your driver for a top-up, which is also the
only free way to do so.
As a customer, the main way to interact with this digital wallet is when the app asks you
to select a payment method for in-app purchases.
So in these images, we see me selecting a payment method for a car booking I made in
the Grab app.
To the left is the price if I chose OVO, the digital credit.
As I don't have enough OVO, I have to select the cash option.
Noticeably, the price changes from 4 to 20,000 rupiah.
The interface design also deploys color, using green to show how good and cheap the digital
payment option is.
Even worse, having selected cash, a red notification bar appears at the top of the screen, reminding
me that I'll be missing out on an 80% discount for not choosing OVO.
Thus, the presence of the digital payment option is not presented as a convenient or
neutral alternative to making a cash payment.
And this is just one example of how both of these apps aggressively encourage users to
pay digitally.
There's a point that one almost comes to feel punished for choosing cash.
And this affects how people use the apps.
So by 2019, I was constantly comparing discounts across apps.
I found myself taking every opportunity to ensure that my accounts were topped up to
avoid feeling as though I was missing out on a cheaper trip and thus wasting my money.
And similarly, for most of the people I interviewed, the real value proposition of e-money was
not the fact that it's digital.
It's the actual value proposition.
It's the ability of this particular form of money to give access to cheaper services
and products.
What the apps primarily give is an access point for the type of purchases that are associated
with a middle class life.
Personal drivers, discounted food delivery, cashbacks when shopping at the mall, like
this restaurant, where three different apps are encouraging you to use their particular
form of payment with absolutely wild cashbacks.
So how do drivers fit into this whole digital money ecosystem?
So let me begin by describing one of my absolutely earliest encounters with some unexpected transactional
frictions in 2018.
I had just downloaded the Gojek app and I had topped up my GoPay wallet and was trying
to use the money to pay for a cappuccino in a neighborhood coffee shop.
A barista told me when I asked if I could pay for my order with GoPay, you can't yet.
I had selected this coffee shop from my neighborhood.
Because I had seen it listed in the GoFood section of the Gojek app, and so I had assumed
that the digital wallet would be an acceptable form of payment.
The coffee shop only accepted cash, the barista explained.
But if I wanted to use GoPay, there was a way of doing so.
I could make an order for my coffee using the GoFood tab in the Gojek app and select
the digital payment option rather than cash upon checkout.
A driver would receive my order.
Drive to the cafe, place the order, wait for it to be prepared, and then pay for it
using their own cash.
The driver would then bring me the coffee and be paid for the cost of the coffee and
his time using my GoPay balance.
This was my first encounter with the entanglements of online drivers and digital money in Indonesia,
and my very first confounding experience of the peculiar limitations and opportunities
for transaction that had materialized just through the interfaces of these apps.
When I started using these apps in 2018, I assumed that drivers and customers shared
if not the same, at least a similar type of digital wallet infrastructure.
After all, I was paying with my GoPay wallet, it seemed natural to assume that they were
receiving it in their GoPay wallet.
In practice, drivers use a separate app entirely, and it contains three digital wallets, as
can be seen in this image.
There is a credit wallet, from which the company extracts their 20% cut of income on trips paid with GoPay.
And finally, there's a consumer wallet, GoPay for Gojek drivers and Ovo for Grab drivers,
to which they can then transfer their earnings directly and then use it through the consumer
version of the apps, which some drivers do, meaning they can literally just put the money
they've earned directly into the consumer wallet and also spend it on things.
Very convenient infrastructure.
For income to be useful for drivers, they have to make a request to the app to cash out their balance.
The company then debits their account and transfers money to the driver's bank account.
And only then can the drivers withdraw the money as cash at an ATM.
Notably, this means that contrary to customers, all drivers must have a bank account to use these apps.
And if they don't have one, Gojek provides them with one through their partnership with Bank Sentral Asia, the largest privately owned bank in Indonesia.
Truly, banking the unbanked in order for the customer to experience hassle-free and heavily discounted cashless payments.
When a driver tops up a customer balance, they're selling their own digital balance and receiving cash in exchange.
The apps incentivize drivers to do this either by awarding them points,
which count towards their daily bonus targets, or by giving them a digital cashback of up to 20% of what they sold.
As you can see here, where the driver has received 4,000 as a bonus for completing a top-up.
One driver proudly shared that he would nudge customers to buy a top-up,
securing himself cashbacks of up to 100,000 to 150,000 per day just for selling his balance,
implying sales of between 500,000 to 750,000 each day.
Curious.
I asked the driver what his strategy was for maintaining such high liquidity in his digital account.
He argued that for the most part, it wasn't a problem since customers were constantly replenishing his account by paying through OVO just as I had done for this trip.
Incidentally, I had just asked him for a top-up equivalent exactly to the cost of the trip itself,
because as described earlier, I too was concerned with maintaining a digital balance.
I had made a 20,000 cashless payment using OVO
and I was able to use the same amount of cash to replenish my digital account in preparation for my next trip.
As a reward for selling his OVO balance to me, the driver later receives 4,000 as a cashback to his digital wallet.
From the driver's point of view, he had received my digital payment and then sold me the exact same amount back,
receiving 20,000 cash in exchange, but also receiving this digital 4,000 from the company.
In total, the driver earned 24,000 rupiah.
But in the process, he also managed to convert 20,000 of his existing balance into the more useful form of cash.
The irony of this cash-filled cashless transaction was not lost on the driver.
He laughed.
Money goes around.
It wasn't an atypical exchange, he explained.
Like me, many passengers chose to top up on each booking, opting for smaller and more frequent top-ups,
rather than maintaining a large digital balance.
So, for drivers, selling balance to customers represents a really important alternative way to cash out
because accessing an ATM can be quite inconvenient.
By selling their balance, drivers instantly convert digital assets into cash
without having to wait for the transfer to be processed by the system.
Meanwhile, the e-money tokens continue circulating within the system,
company doesn't have to make any bank transfers at all. So operating on the front lines of
the digital economy, these drivers are doing all of the persuasive work of bringing new
customers into the digital payment ecosystem of these apps on behalf of the companies they're
working for. Drivers are converted into on-the-go digital ATMs for customers, but they also
use customers as an on-the-go cash ATM for themselves. Because drivers need cash. And
therefore, it is they who incur the hassle of having to rematerialize digital money into
cash. Thus, in this system, drivers are the ones who take on the frictions, the risks,
and the transaction costs of facilitating a hassle-free digital payment ecosystem. And
this becomes particularly clear if we examine the moment of topping up and
in more detail. So these screenshots show a top-up transaction that I had with a Grab
driver. Once my booking is accepted by the driver, the app covers most of the map with
an unclosable splash screen with a dominating green button encouraging me to top up my balance
with the driver. Fine. After clicking the button, the next screen informs me that I
can request between 10 to 320,000 rupiah from the driver, and it gives me the option to
enter a figure. The app now shows me this comforting image with a sparkling green check
mark. My request has been successfully submitted. In the car, the driver reaches for his phone,
and almost instantly, a new splash screen appears on my screen, telling me that the
top-up has been successful, and I hand the cash to the driver. But there are a few things
that the customer does not see in this transaction. Firstly, when the app tells me how much money
I can request, the number it's showing me is the entire contents of the driver's digital
cash wallet. Secondly, the app's request is not always complete. The app simply knows
the total amount of cash on the driver's digital cash wallet. The image that the app lends to the quoting is the same as
The driver does not actually have the option to decline this transaction.
In the driver version of the app, the splash screen that appears gives him simply the option to click a similar green button that reads, collect money.
The button doesn't even say confirm transaction.
Once requested by the customer, the transaction is inevitable.
There's no meaningful agency here for the driver.
And such design may not have any malicious intent.
But it reflects neglect, revealing that the contents of a digital wallet do not truly belong to the driver until they've been withdrawn as cash.
Instead, the wallet is there to enable customers to access and make use of company-issued digital credit.
So, having examined how payments and digital money work in practice, let's shift our focus finally to how the apps arrange the customers and drivers,
configuring them.
into these roles of consumer cyborg and driver partner.
To begin, let's zoom out from this particular castle for a moment with its moats and examine some of the arguments perpetuated by the financial technology industry in the promotion of these products.
Let me summarize these quotes that are about or from the Indonesian fintech industry.
Publicly, these companies perpetually make the argument that their financial technologies will lead to financial problems.
But what about the financial inclusion of those who are unbanked, by bringing millions of people into the digital economy as members of a cashless society?
And globally, this is a really dominating narrative surrounding the type of P2P payments we're talking about.
And it's an outcome of a global paradigm shift that led to perceiving the world's poor as a new and exciting market opportunity.
And these arguments are frequently mobilized in favor of expanding private money services.
Often with support from national governments, as is the case of Gojek and the Indonesian state, which the founder of Gojek is now a member of, because he's become the minister of culture and education.
It's presumed that by giving a poor person access to financial services or to selling their products and services on such a platform, that they will be able to generate income and thus lift themselves out of poverty.
But this ignores the complex structural dynamics that lead to socioeconomic equality.
Such as the increasing income and wealth disparities in Indonesia.
And a similar logic casts ascendance to the middle class as a personal responsibility, which in turn construes being afflicted by poverty as a personal failing.
And these are stigmatizing moral judgments, which lead to the legitimization of exploitation of those deemed less financially responsible or less diligent.
A critical thing to remember is that participation in a cashless economy is not a universal experience.
A technology that makes life more convenient for some can greatly complicate the lives of others.
In practice, these Indonesian apps reproduce specific ideas about consumption that are at odds with the visions of the marginalized and unbanked populations that these same actors argue that their apps will benefit.
They reveal a certain positionality of the consumer.
They reveal a certain positionality of both their developers, their investors, and their imagined consumers.
Particularly, these visions reproduce ideas about the modern Indonesian middle class lifestyle.
And the type of aspirational consumerism that can demarcate you as having these forms of social capital.
And as illustrated in this wonderful Gojek advertisement for their new Pay Later service.
It's worth noting that a central component of how the middle class constitutes itself is through the employment of others.
publicly demonstrating the forms of affluence
that allow them to pay others to do things for them.
Driver partners, notably, are not employed by these apps.
They're mobilized in service of the customers
and, by extension, the digital economy.
And as I point out in my research,
the loosely organized drivers were previously known as OJEC
and simply existed long before there was ever GOJEC.
What these companies have done
is impose themselves on an existing social infrastructure
and provided customers with an easily interpretable interface for engagement.
And in doing so, their platforms create momentary stabilizing parameters for exchange,
thus controlling the conditions of transaction
that were already taking place before they arrived.
Proponents of the gig economy and those forms of digital capitalism
often argue that this is a type of labor that makes workers more flexible,
more able to exert control
over their lives.
But in practice, with GOJEC and GRAB,
anyone can easily and flexibly employ a temporary servant,
perpetuating what scholars like Ray and Kayum conceptualize
as cultures of servitude,
social relations of domination and subordination,
through which subsequent dependency and inequality
are normalized and reproduced
through these everyday social interactions.
And this division in who is being served
and who is doing the serving is most eloquently expressed
by GOJEC.
GOJEC's founder, Nadiem Makarim, himself.
During a 2019 fireside chat at an industry event in Bali,
Makarim makes a really interesting observation
about the app he helped create,
calling GOJEC the
operating system of the real world.
Makarim elaborates,
you're creating a cyborg in our consumers
that are able to not have to do the things they don't want to do
and therefore have more time to get stuff done in life.
Implicit here is the logic of automation,
which reduces time being spent on a process.
Through this automation,
the app, the phone, and the driver
who's tasked with doing those things for you
all become part of your extended cyborg self.
It's interesting that the emphasis here
is on how the app can serve those similar to Makarim himself.
His emphasis on productivity, efficiency,
on not having to waste your time
when someone else can waste theirs for you,
feels remarkably revealing of his world view
and his orientation as one of the app's consumer cyborgs.
And characterizing what problem he feels GOJEC has
is the fact that he's not just a consumer cyborg,
he's also a consumer cyborg.
And characterizing what problem he feels GOJEC has,
what GOJEC is trying to solve in the world, Makarim says.
It was simply a problem of mobility, right?
How do you get a human, an object,
like food, or money, or value,
to move in the fastest possible,
cheapest, most convenient way,
using one tool?
His answer is the app.
But the app does not result
in the rapid, cheap, and convenient circulation
of people, objects, and value.
That circulation is facilitated
by the human labor performed
by the driver partners.
So when Makarim uses language,
such as cyborg or operating system of the world,
he foregrounds the technological innovation
and reinforces the idea
of seamless automated processes
by which this circulation takes place
almost magically.
And GOJEC and GRAB are not the only companies
that refer to their fleets of drivers
as driver partner,
a title that demarcates a different type of relationship
than someone employed to work for the company.
It was not uncommon for drivers
to express their discontent with these conditions
of the alleged partnership.
They were partners with the app company
who relied on each other for income,
yet they were not equal parties.
When drivers sign up,
they accept the terms and conditions
that come with working as an online driver.
However, as many have pointed out,
those conditions frequently change
without warning or consultation with the drivers.
There is no two-way negotiation.
They experience that the apps define them
as on-demand robots,
their labor mobilized and channeled
through the app infrastructure
to serve the need of the consumer cyborgs.
The financial interests of the companies.
So as one driver responded
when I asked him what word he would use
instead of driver partner,
servant, probably.
In practice, the social relationships,
the alleged transactional peerhood
of these apps,
is heavily mediated by algorithms
which lead to the formation of new transactional hierarchies.
In the final chapter of my thesis,
I go into great detail
to document how drivers experience
being mobilized as on-demand servants
through these platforms.
First, driver income is calculated
by a set kilometer tariff
which does not include
distance to the customer
or time spent in traffic.
This is supplemented by a daily bonus
from the companies.
Drivers earn points for each completed trip,
hoping to reach the highest of three tiers
to reach the maximum bonus.
Critically,
drivers do not receive this bonus
if they cancel more than 25% of trips.
Though they may have good reasons
for doing so,
falling below the euphemistically titled
productivity rating
means that they incur what's called a debt trip,
meaning that they must complete
more orders in order to bring
the productivity rating up
while the company holds their bonus hostage.
Meanwhile,
customers are encouraged
to rate their experience after each trip.
So for the customer point of view,
rating a driver between one to five stars
is a question of a few millimeters
and a thumbswipe.
For drivers, this transaction is a source of constant anxiety
because less than five stars
will ruin their algorithmic ranking.
And many offer customers drinks or snacks
or engage in other forms of relational work
as a way to ensure these good ratings.
In a worst-case scenario,
a customer might give a driver
a one-star rating, leading to automatic suspension.
For drivers,
this can be a temporary or permanent loss of income.
But critically,
some drivers also pointed out
how it affects their access to the digital wallets
and their savings,
and how the app employs them.
And access to digital wallets of the app
is further complicated for those drivers
who rely on third-party account vendors
to register outside of the formal Go-Jek system.
I first became aware of vendors
when drivers would decline
selling me their balance,
saying there was no money
because they were with a vendor.
And what I came to realize
is that vendors manage fleets of drivers
with using an app infrastructure
provided by Go-Jek.
And digital earnings made by the drivers
have to be manually transferred
to the driver's bank account each day
by the vendor.
According to two employees of a vendor that I interviewed,
Go-Jek provides them with a window for transfers
through Monday and Friday
between 10 a.m. and 3 p.m.
With an estimated 250 active drivers
requiring daily transfers within a five-hour window,
the two employees only have
about 2.5 minutes each per driver.
So mistakes are pretty frequent.
And as they transfer these daily earnings,
they make sure to withdraw
their own 5% cut of these earnings, of course.
So there's this hierarchical difference
not just in income,
but also access to and control over earnings
between those drivers
who are registered directly with Go-Jek
and those who rely on the additional
intermediation of vendors.
More critically,
in March 2019,
Go-Jek codified a system of unequal pay
as go-car drivers woke up
to an in-app notification
of a change to the incentive-bonus system
which radically worsened their conditions for labor.
Go-Jek replaced the standard
three-tier bonus scale
with a system using four different scales
known as schemas A, B, C, and D.
Briefly, schema A
required fewer points
and therefore fewer completed trips
per tier, but also reduced
the maximum bonus they could earn.
Whereas schema D required more points
but gave the highest maximum bonus.
Which schema each driver is assigned
was determined by how many trips
they had completed in the past two weeks.
Meaning, taking days away
from driving could affect your income
for several weeks in the future.
Some drivers speculated that other
performance indicators such as customer ratings,
order cancellation, or even how much they turned
apps on or off might also affect these algorithms.
The result is that
drivers' experience of the value of their labor
fluctuates depending on what schema
they've been assigned.
Even if two drivers both complete
20 trips, driver A will only receive
the reward for 10 points.
They will not be compensated equally
for the same work.
These changes to the schema
were a really prominent part of my discussions
with drivers in 2019.
And notably, some drivers, despite their own
exasperations and frustrations with the system,
would differentiate schema A as being
for lazy drivers, and schema D
for drivers who were diligent.
Thus, they were also reproducing
these moral judgments that legitimized
the exploitation of the poor in service
of the middle class.
So to summarize,
the idea of P2P payments
leverages the social meaning and
positive connotations of social equality
associated with the word peer,
obscuring underlying power
asymmetries between the exchanging
parties, as well as the power
that these companies exert as they
define the conditions for exchange
within the digital infrastructure.
Furthermore,
this socially acceptable concept of
peer-to-peer ultimately conceals the
fact that this constellation
is a transactional arrangement
that is valuable to the corporation.
Users of the apps
no matter if they're drivers or customers
are tools for the platforms,
because their transactions lead to the circulation
of both money and data,
which is where profits are derived.
Thus, for the companies,
the emphasis is not on creating equal conditions
for exchange, but on securing
continued customer engagement.
And this is done by providing cheap and
convenient services through the platform,
which depends upon the exploitation of labor
and the displacement of transaction costs
of the digital payment onto drivers.
And this exploitation
and extraction of value
from transactional metadata
are what is camouflaged in the language of
peer-to-peer and financial inclusion.
Companies such as Gojek and Grab
continue to receive a lot of attention
for how they are revolutionizing
the economy through digital
technology, and how they are
automating existing systems and empowering
drivers by formalizing their service.
Meanwhile, they're growing into
super-apps, hoping to be the main gateway
for accessing and paying for services in Indonesia
and neighboring countries in Southeast Asia
They have attracted a massive amount
of international venture capital
from those wanting to be a part of
or beneficiary of this digital transition
as the companies extend
their monopolization of customers
and transactional metadata.
A few months ago,
Gojek announced a merger
with another Indonesian e-commerce company
called Tokopedia.
They formed the rather on-the-nose consortium
called Go2.
Their stated goal is to be publicly listed
on the stock exchanges in both Indonesia
and the U.S., with an estimated value
of up to 40 billion U.S. dollars.
Meanwhile, in Jogja,
drivers are chasing points
late into the night, stressing about
managing their digital balances
and worrying that customers might report them
for driving a borrowed account.
So Gojek and Grab may argue
that their digital technologies will
alleviate these problems and provide the poor
and disadvantaged with alternatives
to conventional financial services.
In practice, however, as the companies
chase profits and market monopolization
the structure of this money system
reinforces socio-economic hierarchies
and attempts to further enclose people
within the moat of digital payments.
Thank you.
Thank you to Sunima.
Any questions?
Hi.
It seems there's a lot of value
within these companies, and we've seen
a lot of other hacks around the world
of Bitcoin exchanges, which this is
a bit of similarity to, and it seems
to be easier to break into their systems
and perhaps inflate it or give all
the drivers a little bonus.
Has that happened, or...?
No.
Not yet.
OK.
So, is it possible to imagine a digital
payment system that does not have this
kind of exploitation, or are we doomed
to forever have exploitation be an intrinsic
part of digital payments, and should we
just all go back to cash and never
use technology again?
Are we doomed?
Maybe.
No.
I mean, I don't know.
I don't know.
I don't think that there's, like,
a deterministic outcome here.
Like, digital payments doesn't have to be negative.
I think what's really important is to focus
on what the people are saying as well, right?
That the emphasis here is not on something
being digital or being cash.
It's about the ability to flexibly transition
according to what suits your needs.
And so, from a designer point of view,
the purpose is to serve those needs, right?
To create that flexible system that enables
people to have the type of money form
that they actually need.
What's the issue with these kind of apps
that decidedly are not neutral in the way
that they, like, don't just model existing
transactions, but actually engineer
forms of transactions, right?
So of course you could design something different.
Whether or not you can change what has already
been made, I think is more complicated.
Thank you so much. It was wonderful
to hear such a brilliant talk.
I would like to ask if you're
seeing in the Danish context
something that resembles this
peer-to-peer philosophy.
Anyway.
That's a great question.
I mean, I think a lot
of the narratives around financial inclusion,
those kind of things, that's a type of hype
that also exists in Danish companies, for sure.
A lot of the advocacy about how these
kind of payment systems will make our lives
easier and more convenient also obscure
the fundamental fact that we're
opting into a private transactional
infrastructure, and the way
that those things are often being promoted
as being a better alternative to cash,
which I think is
almost malignant, to be honest.
I also think
something that hasn't quite happened here,
because in Indonesia you don't have credit cards.
You can't have a system like mobile pay.
But that doesn't mean that companies like
Vault or Uber and these kind of things
are not going to start introducing similar systems.
And it would be super interesting to know more about
how money actually exists within a system
like Vault. For example, if you get
you pay for something and they can't deliver,
so they kind of give you money to store
in that system. I would love to find out more
about how that actually works in practice.
Have the government interfered in any way?
Or any larger...
Yeah, the national
bank has a national
less-cash movement.
So the interference is definitely in favor
of these companies. Absolutely.
I mean, originally when Gojek
started, there was a massive
movement in the government.
The government actually tried to shut them down.
But there was such a mobilization,
like a million drivers protested.
And so they simply had to allow it to exist.
And the reality is that there are really close
ties politically between these CEOs
and the political class.
Like I said, the founder is a minister now.
And so are a lot of other...
The new president...
The president who was re-elected in 2019
brought in a bunch of young tech people,
like start-up people, to come and be a part
of it.
They're really gonna do it.
It's gonna be a digital country, for sure.
It's great.
Okay.
Thank you very much.
Thank you. Thank you so much for coming.