Welcome to the afternoon talk.
Let's hope our picture stays with us.
And Holger Leveson will talk about reproducible booster, bullseye, bookworm.
Yeah. Enjoy.
Holger Leveson Hello, everybody.
For those who don't know, Buster, Bullseye,
and Bookworm are these lovely Debian release names.
I will not only talk about Debian today.
So this is about the last mile and other light years ahead
because this last mile has been very long.
So this talk is a dual talk to be streamed later today
at DEBCONF 21 taking place
on the Debian server.
And I will also give the talk in person at Bornhek in Denmark.
So thank you all for being here.
It's great.
And hi to the people at DEBCONF.
I miss Debian people and DEBCONF.
And the world is not fine.
It's all wrong.
But it is what it is.
So anyway, and this is not my work.
This is the work of many people.
Who have contributed to this in Debian and elsewhere.
And we used to do this talk at DEBCONF with like four
or five people on stage.
And now it's the second time in a row that I'm doing this alone.
So this talk misses many, many updates.
Like Diffoscope, our main tool, has seen over 50 releases
in the last two years.
And I will just mention it in here.
So about me, I'm a Debian user since almost 20,
since more than 25 years.
I'm contributing to Debian since some time.
Located in Hamburg.
And since the last release, I'm also, I have uploaded more
than 10% of the Debian archive.
Which is like completely insane.
I will explain later why I did this
and how I didn't really do much about that.
So, reproducible builds.
Who of you is not familiar with reproducible builds?
Who? So, I'll anyway explain the problem briefly.
So, there's source code of free software available,
which is pretty cool.
But most people install pre-compiled binaries.
And nobody really knows.
So, I'm going to explain this.
But most people install pre-compiled binaries.
And nobody really knows whether they really correspond.
Because there's, they are built on some machine.
There's binary artifact included.
And so, there's various classes of supply chain attacks,
which have become more and more popular.
Like when you, PyPy has been back-doored so that
when you download binaries from there, you get them.
Or other archives.
And this is becoming more and more widespread.
And our solution for that is to end reproducible builds.
And we define this, enable anyone to independently verify
that a given source produces bit-by-bit identical results.
And as a side effect, then you can be sure
that the binary is free software.
Because you can be sure it comes from the binary.
And that's really the only way to be sure the binary comes
from the source.
So, you can only know if it's free software.
If it's reproducible.
And of course, reproducible builds are just one building block
for secure distribution of binaries.
There's other stuff needed as well.
But it's an important step there.
So, when is a build reproducible?
What the definition here says, the build is reproducible
if given the same source code, build environment,
and build instructions, any party can recreate bit-by-bit
identical copies of all specified artifacts.
And we have written that down.
It's readable in our documentation.
That's the definition.
And it's pretty clear to me what it is.
I hope it's clear to everybody else.
So, I mostly ignore why and how to do such builds now.
And I just mentioned that this has widely been understood
as a problem.
Biden.
Biden has done a statement, a cyber defense something act
about supply chains.
And there was a White House briefing and they spent to,
they plan to spend billions in fixing these kinds of problems.
But I will just focus on how and why today.
So, first, some other projects than Debian.
And this is how I understand it.
I'm a Debian developer and I'm not an expert
on all these projects mentioning now.
So, Tails has reproducible builds.
And I wrote easy because Tails only produces one ISO.
So, you rebuild the Tails ISO and either it matches or it doesn't.
While Debian consists of 30,000 packages and you need
to confirm them all and that's more complicated.
And I only also wrote pragmatically.
Europe didn't produce that.
We don't really do that, exactly.
First, we do this called, however,
because now, basically, you have trials,
you have, remember when you were just typing your code,
you know, the code you already use,
you're like okay that world is for you.
So, you'll have people about everybody else.
If they didn't ask about it,
then I think that translations are very likely going to solve
but not systematically because when Tails has a release now,
they, you do the release
and they announce the checksum of the ISO.
And then, you can reproduce the ISO and you don't.
But there's no systematic effort in like whatever,
different countries produce different projects,
different ISOs for Tails, that's not being done yet.
Arch Linux has, in a way, overtaken Debian a bit
because Arch Linux has real rebuilders now.
They check their results.
But there's also not really user tools
or integration or documentation.
It works on a technical level, and that's great.
Zuza has also active development.
One person mostly, Bernard Wiedemann,
who also does the QA efforts.
He's doing a lot of there.
And Zuza could be reproducible in theory,
but they don't set some bits for RPMs,
so Zuza is not reproducible in practice.
Then there's NixOS, which recently,
very recently on this r13yreproducibility.com,
they also show the minimal installation image.
And their installation image is 94% reproducible,
so again, the whole image is not reproducible,
but cool nonetheless.
And there's GNU Geeks,
also reproducible by design like NixOS,
but their design also allows unreproducible software
because some software is still unreproducible.
And they have this Geeks challenge thing
so you can check whether one specific software
is reproducible.
Yocto, which is an embedded build environment,
also has reproducible images,
and they also have a little bit of information, you know,
that's still not reproducible, but it's still reproducible.
Of course, the softwares are still reproducible.
For some of their software, but the tool chain and everything supported
Doctor is quite becoming quite big in some embedded words, and that's really cool
but
That's all I know and all they've been doing you can create images which are reproducible
but all the user tools are again lacking and
asteroid also support after all this this up store for Android phones after it also supports reproducible builds they have some
Applications which do we produce will bits, but it's really arcane to find out
There's a web page with all the AP case and if there's a file
Installed I think then it's reproducible and if there's a file different scope that HTML it shows the differences
So you as a human can call that and find out if your application is reproducible or not
But that's not a UI and there's also no promises for further ups whether one up which stays and is in the
Upstore reproducible today whether it will only be there if it continues to be reproducible
Alpine also has basic support basic bit like your core
Free BSD net BSD open BSD. I don't know about open BSD, but I know the base image of free and that BSD
Can be built reproducible we have not looked at to the ports and as far as I know no BSD person
definitely
can
him
Contentment continue suspense time on this
And feed or red had we going to seem not to be interested
So many projects support reproducible bills
And a kind of different approach is something KPCYRD,
which is his nick, started last week, I think.
He made a project on GitHub,
I probably didn't backdoor this,
which is Justifying Manual,
where he describes a simple hello world program
written in Rust, how to review the source code,
the compiler, and then he reproduces the elf binary,
reproduces a Docker image, and an Arch Linux package.
And he says he didn't backdoor them,
and you can check whether it's true.
It's a nice effort, and it shows that it's not enough
to have just the binary reproducible,
but also the whole package, the system,
you install the image.
Yeah, and then there's another project
from Bernard Wiedemann,
The Unreproducible,
which contains some examples
how a package is made unreproducible.
So what pitfalls you can introduce,
which you should not do,
because it's much easier to show problems
than to show the absence of problems.
So now to Debian,
which I'll start with my wishes or goals for DepCon 12.0.1.2.2.
So Debian is a very good example of a package
that can be reproducible.
And it's a very good example of a package
So we had the problem of CI builds versus rebuilds.
CI builds is just where we take the source code
and do many variations, as many as possible,
and hope that the package is still reproducible.
That's nice to find problems,
but we don't test whether we can actually rebuild
what Debian distributes on the FTP servers.
Then we had some issues with build info files.
Build info files contain the instructions,
the hashes of the source code,
the depends which are needed to build depends,
and the resulting artifacts.
And I'll come to that in this moment.
And then we also had thousands of packages in Debian
without build info files.
That was why I did those 3,000 uploads.
And we had a script,
or have a script, deb rebuild,
which had some problems, and we had other issues.
And back then I said how to use reproducible builds
and user interfaces are not even on my radar anymore.
That was the status last year,
and I'll now explain where we got there.
So the status of these wishes today,
there's some progress with the rebuilders.
Debian build info files got better.
This thousands uploads, thousands uploads has happened.
Deep rebuild was mostly or partly addressed,
but we made huge infrastructure progress.
And there's always other issues.
But then first I want to repeat my frustration with 2019,
or actually 2019 or the previous years.
Because I have given many times the warning,
the next Debian release will not be reproducible.
So last year I committed a big mistake, I say no, and then I got a solution.
So last year I said Stretch could have been reproducible but wasn't in practice.
Buster we missed it and Bullseye we'll probably also miss it again.
And so this year, yeah, Bullseye we almost made it.
And for Bookworm, the next release in two years,
I hope we'll have some meaningful reproducibility.
Because we can reproduce like many packages,
but if there's always some, it doesn't really help.
So what first about the CI versus rebuild issue?
So not Debian is wrong, but most people who see this number
are wrong because it's a lie because these are CI results.
And so what happens is that the blockers are not reproducible.
There's some good ones to use, but not how Debian is really
reproducible, what we distribute.
So we only have builders but not rebuilders and we need
to rebuild Debian and compare this to get the number.
This is what Arch Linux is already doing and Debian is not doing yet.
And up until very recently, we had two main blockers for this,
and I fixed this by uploading them all,
which I just did a source-only upload
where I did not note no changes
except increasing the version number and change log
and upload it so that then a built-in profile is generated.
And to my surprise, that worked hardly,
mostly without complaints.
Some complaints were there.
And then we have Snapshot Debian org,
which is a Debian server which has all packages
since 2005, all ever uploaded for all architectures,
and that doesn't scale.
It's fine to download one package,
but if you really need to download 500 of them
in very specific versions,
and you want to do this 24 hours for weeks,
then you would get connection issues and stuff.
And so Frederic, Pierre, and Josh fixed this by writing
and Snapshot clone and different RP.
They'll give a talk about this on Thursday at DEBCONF
where they explain what they do much better than I could do this.
And so we have now a partial Snapshot mirror for AMD64 only,
not for the other architectures,
and only going back until January 2017.
So that includes all packages from the Buster cycle, I think,
or maybe Bullseye, I think it's Bullseye.
But there's their talk on Thursday, the 26th at 21 UTC.
So this 93 number was wrong.
Actually, today we are at 95.5% reproducibility.
And now this is more showing how to lie with statistic.
So we improved 2% from 93.9 to 95.
But this is not true.
We also increased 3,000 more reproducible packages.
3,000 new reproducible packages sounds way better than 2% more.
Or we solved one-third of the remaining 6%.
Anyhow.
This build info files, I will not get too much into details what it is.
We have this build info Stebian net service,
which is kind of proof of fact.
It's kind of proof of concept, but it works.
But it should be on Debian infrastructure.
It's a hack I wrote on this unrelated service.
And it's still running, but it should be done better.
This problem has been solved with 3,000 packages.
And this also has been worked around that the Debian infrastructure needs
to update the build info files.
And this is basically the same.
This are solved with Band-Aid.
But we still have to do this.
We still have some problem with build info files.
Namely, that for security updates,
these build info files are not published the way other.
That's because how the way Debian archive works.
This is mostly not for the people in the Bonhack room,
but you at devconf21, hello, you can address this issue.
Which means when there's a new security update,
we cannot rebuild it reproducibly.
We need to wait for the point release
when it's put into the main archive.
And similar for Debian LTS, there's the same problem.
But until Bookworm, no, Bullseye will become LTS,
it will be three years.
So we have three years to fix this bug.
And then maybe there can be reproducible LTS updates.
And another problem with rebuilding is DPG keys expire.
And the archive keys, so you cannot create a base Debian setup,
build environment.
In some years to come.
And maybe it would be better not to expire the keys.
I'm not sure.
Yeah, about the rebuilders, what I said last year,
we had this dev rebuild script, which has some problem.
And most of them have been addressed.
But rebuilding needs a working snapshot service.
And snapshot doesn't scale.
So that's what I said, Frederick and Josh have solved this
with this partial mirror.
So that's good.
And you should really see the talks.
There's an API how to use this.
And we also plan to increase this, not only have AMD64,
but also soon ARM64 and probably ARMHF.
But we don't have the resources yet for all 11 Debian architectures.
So what we really want is to make snapshot Debian org scale
or work.
But as long as this doesn't happen,
and because that's a much bigger problem,
we kind of are happy that we have this workaround for AMD64.
So Frederick hosts his mirror at his private machine
at his place, which is this Debian not set France URL.
We'll soon have a mirror of that mirror
at Toasted at the Oregon State University open source labs.
And then we can set up rebuilders and hammer this service.
And you can use it already.
And then we'll have rebuilders for both Bullseye and Bookworm,
because previous releases are really not interesting to reproduce anymore.
And Frederick also has a proof of concept for a rebuilder.
So I'm looking forward to integrating this.
I'm looking forward to integrate this into the coming weeks or months
and then finally have results for Debian rebuilders for real.
And the last part is the meaningful reproducibility of Debian.
Finally, since a week or something,
all 21 essential source packages are reproducible.
Yay.
This is really something new and something small.
But then if you go to the required set, it's only 26 of 29.
And the two unreproducible packages are GCC10, Upt, and GCC9, I think.
And everybody needs them.
So unless we don't fix this, there will be always something,
and quite important part of this something, which is not reproducible.
Of the most installed packages, there's 50 which are not reproducible.
Out of the GNOME package set, it's only 28.
So it's a bit better, but you need to have, it's still not enough.
And then also the Debian installer images are not reproducible.
I think we have patches for all problems,
and now that the Bookworm, Bullseye, Bookworm,
Bookworm, these names,
the Bookworm development cycle has started,
we can hopefully get these patches integrated.
And the last bit is Debian live images are not reproducible.
We also need to work on this,
so there's also the problem that Debian live images need a new maintainer.
That's a problem with the Debian live images.
But I think that's a good goal to have for Bookworm,
to have those images reproducible.
Because we will not get these 95 or 96,
but we can hopefully make a minimal Debian live image
which is reproducible.
Eventually.
Oh yeah, and eventually we also want up to warm
when there's a non-reproducible package to be installed.
I think this bug has a patch even,
so that could be done today.
I just wanted to remove.
It's still true.
We have last release cycle,
the testing team,
release team introduced that the package can only migrate to testing
if there was a,
if the build happened on the Debian build,
these are not at the maintainers.
And we were happy,
very happy that they implemented this blocking.
And at the same time,
they brought up the idea of making migration to testing faster
if the package is reproducible.
We would like that,
but this is just a development process detail.
That's it.
Thank you for being here,
for working on reproducible builds.
Thank you very much for your talk.
I think it's a great achievement,
given that I still remember a few years ago
when people were talking about having maybe Tor browser
and Tails reproducible.
And so that we now have the first OS's
which are close to it is very good, I think.
Are there questions to the talk?
So, do you have,
is it the same problems we have in the packages
that makes them unreducible?
Or are there a million different ways
of making them unreproducible?
There are many ways to make a package unreproducible.
Like hundreds.
Like it's also,
there's different classes of problems,
and then there's also toolkits which have problems.
So there's whatever,
the most documentation toolkits embed the build,
or used to embed the build time in the build product.
And then there's like 50 tools creating documentation
from HTML, from XML, from PDF, whatever,
and they all have these kind of problems.
So when you say that rebuilding them is,
it's a scaling issue also,
it will require, well, basically a lot of extra infrastructure.
Could you have a system where you would be sampling the packages
in order to learn what kind of common pitfalls there are
instead of reproducing everything blindly?
What was the suggestion?
So when you have thousands and thousands and thousands of packages,
it's going to cost a lot of resources
in order to rebuild them in a nice way again and again.
So if you had a strategy for sampling these
so you could document what kind of unreproducibility problems you had
in order to cluster them, if you like.
Well, first the resource problem is really not a problem
because it doesn't need that much CPU power or bandwidth to rebuild.
That is basically fine.
The problem is rather looking at the results,
which we are sampling or automatic categorization could help.
And also you want to always want to retest new software
because if even though you have a software which is reproducible now,
like to a browser, at any moment for the fire,
upstream Firefox can introduce changes which make the build unreproducible again.
So you need to retest every new release.
And every new release of dependent binaries as libraries as well.
You mentioned that the kind of key packages missing are apt and gcc.
I was a bit surprised about apt,
but can you say why these two packages are not reproducible?
No.
Okay.
I can...
I mean apt is...
It's all your responsibility, right?
So...
Yeah.
Mine.
No, I don't know what...
I could...
Does build ID...
gcc, that is not relevant for us.
We have gcc captures build pass.
That is something...
This is something where...
gcc embeds the build pass,
and we solve this by rebuilding in the same pass.
We still track this issue because we want to support rebuilding in a different pass,
but this is not the apt problem.
Ah, it's non-deterministic.
To do end of fires in documentation generated by doxygen, probably.
Um...
What is this?
Oh, this is unstable.
Yeah, it's doxygen.
If you look at the...
Yeah.
It's the doxygen issues in apt.
Hi.
You mentioned there was a problem with the snapshot server,
where you couldn't fetch a large quantity of packages that you needed.
Is that problem simply a hardware?
Lack of...
No.
Lack of hosting?
It's a huge database with...
I forgot...
15 terabytes files and...
10...
15 terabytes size and 10 million files and...
It's not hardware.
It's scaling.
Yeah.
Scaling.
I understand.
And some of the bugs have been addressed,
and the others...
We are working around and trying to fix them, really.
But it's...
It's complicated.
Is it possible to have maybe Debian ports
that doesn't support all the unsupported architectures?
Would there be any effort to have reproducible builds there as well?
Or is that the responsibility of Debian ports,
that is not official?
Well, they...
They gain most of the stuff we did.
Like the build info files,
they are produced by their builds.
So that's...
Should be fine.
Yeah.
It's the same with Ubuntu.
Ubuntu could also take our work,
and it's...
It just takes some work.
Are there further questions?
No.
I don't see it.
Then let's thanks the speaker again.