Welcome to second day with presentations here at BornHack. I would like to welcome Mark-Jan Bastian and your talk about power supply, stability and risks.
Yes, thank you. Well, welcome everybody. This talk, my name is Mark-Jan Bastian and the presentation is called Power Supply, Stability and Risks.
For a very quick thing, which I will discuss in this presentation is always verify the operational life of your electrolytic capacitors, perform stability tests for load step up and step down.
You can do that for example with electronic load.
Repeat that for every new battery.
Use a lot of hardware because you never know which kind of chips end up in your supply chain, especially in these days where there is a lot of scarcity of chips.
And the design time, well there are a few things which you can do.
The power supply of the control signals in your power source, feedback loops, well that is a very academic topic, but I will just do it very practically which things in practice can go wrong.
And then you can do a lot of other things. You can do a lot of other things, but I will just do it very practically which things in practice can go wrong.
And then you can do a lot of other things, but I will just do a lot of other things, but I will just do a lot of other things, but I will just do a lot of other things, but I will just do a lot of other things, but I will just do a lot of other things, but I will just do a lot of other things, but I will just do a lot of other things, but I will just do a lot of other things, but I will just do a lot of other things, but I will just do a lot of other things, but I will just do a lot of other things, but I will just do a lot of other things, but I will just do a lot of other things, but I will just do a lot of other things, but I will just do a lot of other things, but I will just do a lot of other things, but I will just do a lot of other things, but I will just do a lot of other things, but I will just do a lot of other things, but
so yeah this should be reasonable for any power supply like uh audio amplifier and that kind of
stuff so uh yeah it was a pretty good deal i got a bit weird things when i was ordering it because
somebody mentioned uh that there could be a back door into in this power supply i mean well that
was very interesting and i definitely want that so i bought two of them i mean well how can you
have a back door in an electronic load that's what's uh well i'll definitely want to check that
out um there's a there's rs2d3d2 port uh actually serial port on the back which you can use to
control it uh but well i mean yeah that was a very weird story but well you can just use it with the
buttons and just verify all the results with your scope uh all the time domains are not uh
interconnected and the only way they talk to each other is via the line they share so
yeah i don't see any way
to make a back door in an electronic load but you could maybe make a back door in a in a power
supply to actually have it fail at some point so and that's where this talk is about
and well maybe one of the things that you might be familiar with in 2015 was a user
on the raspberry pi forum that actually found out that he made if he made a xenon flash
of his raspberry pi board the power supply crashed and he actually fixed it by putting a piece of
blue text on the back of the power supply and he actually fixed it by putting a piece of blue text
uh on his raspberry pi
and well that's uh that was actually uh very interesting of course well that's that looks like
a an attack on the power supply and that was actually due to uh the the power supply the
power controller itself it was kind of transparent for the wavelength of xenon
and actually uh well caused a glitch which caused a power outage in the raspberry pi
and then caused a reset so that was quite interesting but well relatively easy to fix
well then well we'll go into the several uh power
power supply circuits that you can find on any board or if you design your own board
most common already since the 70s or maybe even earlier is a linear regulator which
basically transistor which controls the current from v into v out and all power
all the voltage difference is actually dissipated in that transistor so it's not very efficient so
you actually if you would do this on a battery power thing and you have a very big difference
between your battery voltage and the usable voltage then you waste a lot of power and that
is of course not uh not good for your better for your battery life so the idea is to always use a
way to do dcd's conversion with a high high efficiency and well the efficiency should be above
70 percent or uh in some cases even up 79 to 98 percent uh those are uh well those direct
c regulators which are capable of doing that on reasonably high power levels um well the most
common uh conversion you will find in mobile phones and battery powered stuff is buck converters
and this is basically the cdc converter where you're having an inductor and the capacitor
the inductor is usually around one to ten micro hundred so it's relatively small and it should
having uh should have a decent dc carrying capability like a few amps and output capacitor
is usually a ceramic capacitor because while they're having a low very low esr so a series
resistance and that's make also makes well it's both a storage and you can also see it as an lc
filter that filters out all the switching noise because the the the the the the the the the the
the the the the the the the the the the the the the the the the the the the the the the the the the
the power will be generated by using two switches there's a high side switch and a low side switch
and while the high side switch is used to actually
put a jolt of current into the inductor the inductor will get the triangular
voltage over it and then the v out itself will be will be stable and depends on the duty cycle
you apply to the top switch there's also a switch here on the bottom
that's not strictly needed for all converters but you can use that to actually
make the converter a little bit more efficient because there's a voltage drop over here and
dissipation and if you use a mosfet here then you have less voltage drop there and while you
can having a little bit better regulation so for all the high power server scenarios usually it's
using both switches well this is then a picture from wikipedia about how a lot of the power is
being produced so it's a big converter works so you see a relatively short on time a relatively
long off time you see here the input voltage and the voltage over the inductor here it's this yellow
area which is both positive and negative if you measure it over the inductor and the output voltage
is relatively constant and that's in continuous mode and if you don't do not have too much load
then you might be in this continuous mode and then it looks a little bit different and you see it's
there's no voltage drop over the inductor this all ideal but inductors
are not ideal but yeah it's just a concept well then if you implement this
in a chip then you want to achieve put all the semiconductors in one chip then
so if you put all the transistors and the diode and everything in one chip and
only have the external components of inductor and capacitor on the output
then yeah it's relatively simple you can do then use a p-channel a MOSFET on the
top and you put a negative yeah you have to pull the signal down to turn the
switch on and it will do that with a certain P with PWM and it will be
control circuits also integrated in the chip which takes the feedback output and
then but this is relatively simple and cheap but if you want to make a little
bit more higher power
scenario then using n-channel MOSFETs and the reason why you want to use
n-channel MOSFETs is because well they are relatively they have usually better
specifications than p-channel MOSFETs for a lower RDS on higher current
capability and you can also sometimes use them as external components so if
you have a separate n-channel MOSFETs external to your regulator you can then
draw much more power because you can optimize control logic to which you just
be engaged
and you can also use a p-channel MOSFETs for external MOSFETs and external MOSFETs
put on the board and even put heat sinks on them to make it even more simple yeah
but there's then there's a difference because n-channel MOSFETs you need the
positive voltage to turn them on and that creates a problem on the bottom
side that's usually not a problem because your VIN is probably higher than
three volts and three volts is usually you kind of threshold for high power
MOSFETs
if this MOSFET needs to be turned on then you also need more than a three
volts over here but if your input voltage is when this thing is on
there will be almost no voltage drop between a drain and the source so you
need gate voltage needs to be above VIN so that's interesting problem and
well you have to solve the problem somehow well it is and you could do that
by actually making
a
internal using a charge pump or something like that in your chip but although those charge
pump needs capacitors the capacitors are very expensive in the chip you cannot get more than
a few picofarads in the chip so or even less so then usually what the chip designers do they give
you a boost input and then you have to put an external capacitor which is connected to the
switching node and this you will be basically at a kind of square wave on this node you do
those things switching initially the gates might be not be very good conducting but as soon as you
got a few cycles you actually use power to charge them here inside the chip and then your power
gets more stable and sometimes you can also help that the charge pump by actually providing external
diode and that's that sometimes very handy so also some power supply manufacturers
provide application nodes how to do that and that's yeah that's you should really always
check if there are application nodes for the chip that you you picked because well if you do if you
forget that there might be some issues if you do not provide the power here quick enough
well what's more yeah this this is the most important part i think for this part
oh yeah but you also see
there's always body diodes inside all MOSFETs.
I always put them in my schematics
because it makes a swapping drain
and source on the MOSFET in the schematic
is very disastrous, you don't want to do that.
And it's also a bit more logical
because if you reverse power anything
or you have some back EMF,
well you have to, you can just trace the path
the current goes.
Then there's another thing about the feedback loop stability.
There's a voltage divider usually on the output
and then, so if you're out to say 3 volts
or 3.3 volts, then there's a voltage divider
which well maybe a few hundred kiloamps
drawing a few microamps or less.
And then you're having a output
voltage which is typically around 1.2
or 0.8 or 0.6 volts or something like that.
And then there's a feedback input
on the controller of your power supply
and there will be comparator which
compares that output voltage and uses
that to adjust the PWM rate of both MOSFETs
just to make sure the
UXC gain the output voltage.
There's also some, yeah there's also
filter response, there's a delay in there
and then there's a filter response
which will tell you how to calculate it.
Usually the data sheet will tell you how to calculate it.
Well, you have to very carefully always check
if you're doing that right.
But might be also some issues with the speed
of which this feedback loop works.
Because if you're for example having outputs
and you put a very quick load step on it,
well you can for example generate that
with an electronic load.
And you actually go from 10% of your current
to say 90% of your current then there might be some oscillations into the
control loop which actually eventually crash your power supply and well if you
just run normal software on it and it seems to work then yeah you think well
everything is fine yeah well let's just ship it but well it's important to
actually just do the extra step use an electronic load to do this step
response from 10% to 90% but also from 90% to 10% because that creates
additional capacitance and then creates more delay times and well that could
also cause issues it's a very practical thing very simple to do and and it works
irrespective of your data sheet so if you bought a component and you see well
yeah it should work because it's pin compatible and you found the data sheet
and well everything seems to work
we've just performed this practical test it's very easy to verify whether you
actually made the right choice but also there might be issues with the current
through this feedback resistor there's some data sheets of some regulators they
also say that you have to add an additional capacitor so you see the
green capacitor over there and that actually creates actually enhances the
performance of the output to the feedback
and so if there's additional capacitance here or some input loads then that's
capacitor could be only a few hundred picofarads actually improves the
response of the feedback loop so yeah if you just if you see issues just
experiment with those capacitor values to see if your step response improves so
well this is basically all the most important parts
so it's very roughly simple and the quick thing so these are the all the
things verified operational operational life for electrical capacitors well
that's because the if you're a capacitor capacitor dry out they usually the ESR
actually goes goes up and it means that the capacitor is doing its work less it
will dissipate more and more power so they get a hotter and hotter and hotter
they will evaporate directly electrolytes much faster so if you
have old consumer hardware the easiest way to repair it is just verify reduce
all of the electric testers verify their impedance using LCR meter and then see
if that's still within spec and otherwise find other capacitors to
replace them with what is the load step up and step down so there's 10% to 80
90%
of your current yeah and if you have new batches of hardware well you could there
could be new chips in your thing your hardware supply chain so always just
check well if you have new new new new new new rule of components coming in
just verify a hardware and also the power supplies well the driving for
electronics power source basically what is the bootstrap capacitor story that I
just told
the feedback loop that's the small capacitor on the voltage divider yeah
they're ringing itself that's yeah you can see just what about looks best I
mean if you go if it goes up and then there's a lot of things ringing before
it becomes come stable yeah that might be getting problematic if the transient
becomes even sharper so yeah it's best to just make it fast and smooth oh yeah and the softness of the power supply is also important
time so if you have a residential product and then you haveoff start function疫al
update you worked out in this I'm
and that now you might won't wanna we have a
我就
so if you just do it in sequence all the power supplies and making sure it's fast
and reliable that saves a lot of debugging for the electronic part so
well this is my this all file this was my talk so hopefully well maybe there
are some questions or other things you can do some more experiments any
questions no but thank you