you
They did it in the ADA programming language
because
first of all, they like that language, but second because Ada was mainly used by organizations with a lot of money and
they did and
Found out that existing computers were too slow to execute it
the best computers for Ada at the time with the data general eclipse computers and it was too slow even if you had the
Biggest eclipse as a personal workstation. It was still not satisfactory
So they gather the team they built a computer
Then they upgraded the IO processor some years later from a PDP 11
to a
68,000 processor and then they did so to a
6820 processor later on but still the same main CPU and
eventually other hardware caught up specifically the RS 6000 computers and
Then they sold the business to IBM for a couple of billions in 2003
The customer base was Department of Defense people
In Denmark, it was Tamar one of the larger European customers apparently
the list price for the machine was 1 million dollars and
You could run between four and eight terminals on it
That's probably built something around a thousand nobody who knows will tell
yet, but we'll get that number and they had absolutely
five-star customer service
What you see on the right side is from the field engineering handbook how to get to Tamar from Copenhagen Airport
All these computers were used for classified work
That's where the money was for that kind of luxury which means there's two ways of get rid of them
The easy one is to run them for a shredder or the other one is to do a hell of a lot of paperwork
so of the
1,000 or whatever many produced
almost all have been destroyed as
Declassification
At this point in time I know of four surviving rational thousand computers in the entire world
Glenn Beck who worked at rational has one in his basement in New Zealand. It doesn't have a power supply and it doesn't have an IO processor
Probably because they were sent to Denmark to Tamar
So we may actually have those
There's one in computer history museum that Intel has IBM has donated
It probably has all the usual failures according to people in the know and has no software
There was one under the University of hot Alsace in Strasbourg
That's Pierre alarm
Miller's machine it had the usual IOC failure and
Then the one in data museum that we got from Tamar because I did the paperwork
It has no software we got high
Discs, but they had never been in that machine
And it had the usual IOC failure the board on the right is the IOC board. This is the IO controller. It's a 68k system
I think it has one megabyte of RAM
Running full speed on the CPU and then it interfaces to the main CPU, which it does disk and terminal access for
The rest of the CPU takes up five boards of the same size
filled a little
little more chips on them than this one
The only known surviving software were in the basement under the University of hot Alsace in Strasbourg
Various tapes some disks in the machine was what Caroline told us
so the long story is that when we got this machine we decided we wanted to get this running again and
We had to fix those RAM errors on the IOC and for various reasons that took us seven years to do
The main part of the reason was to power up the board. We needed a 5-volt 40 amp power supply and we didn't have one
And Peter fixed the power supply trouble the power supply is a 5 volt
250 ampere power supply the cables look like two garden hoses
And
We have some mailing addresses for some of the old rational people
So I sent an email saying well we got further now then we can power it on and yada yada
Then we got an email from France saying I'm popping around next week
Okay
and next week PLM popped up round with his truck and
a rational thousand
some spare boards
some manuals and stuff and
the story was when he received our
Email he thought his cat he used to teach computer science and in the meantime he'd become
Vice president of innovation and now he's president of the entire thing down there
But he thought I'll go and see what I have in the basement
So he goes over to the CS department and goes into the basement and the caretaker said oh good thing
you came because we're cleaning out that room in two weeks and
The way he told it we got the impression that the vice president innovation had
not
Taken that kindly
But he decided having slept on it to load all of it up in his truck and drive it up to us
So now we have two rational thousands that can potentially be brought alive and one of them is still running right now
We made mirror copies of his disks and gently put them into our machine
Turned it on
waited
45 minutes while it actually more like an hour while it did garbage collection
And then it come came up and says username colon
And yeah, that's had PAM and then it's a password and then it went oh
But he could remember the name of a former girlfriend
So we have a running rational thousand
And it's quite an interesting machine
You can go into
some Ada module in a huge project and say I need to change that line and then you change that line and it
recompiles that line and
nothing else
Because it knows semantically that this line is inside the private part of this class. So all the rest will be fine
You don't recompile your entire project because that's not a fast thing that can take a week
So it works what's the problem?
Having the last and very likely
Only rational thousand that will ever run again is a responsibility
We can keep this machine running
2040 yeah, we'll do that 2050 me
2100 nah, then the plastic will start to disintegrate and
You cannot get 45
75 F chips anymore and stuff like that
so
We're probably also the only people who can write the software emulator for it because we have a machine that works we can compare with
And then the Covid 19 lock down happen and some idiot says, ah, how hot can that be?
So normally when you write a software emulation of a computer you simulate the instruction set, right
Move instruction, okay. We move these bytes
Well, there is no instruction set
on this computer.
There's no technical reference manual.
There's no assembler programmer's manual.
According to them, there's never been written,
handwritten assembler on this computer.
What we have is the guru course,
chapter one, or day one.
Apparently, when Rational went out
of the hardware business,
they toured the remaining customers,
gave them a one-week,
really heavy-duty course,
and said, good luck.
We have an Ada description
of the instruction set,
which is nice.
But if you look carefully at this source code,
there's no numbers.
It says what the instructions are,
tells the Ada compiler to put them into
some kind of data structure
that fits in 16 bits,
and the Ada compiler does that,
however Ada compilers do that.
We don't know where the fields are,
how long they are, whatever.
But the data compiler does that.
But there's also two or three pages
about the debugger that's actually there,
which can clearly disassemble instructions,
and there we have numbers.
All right?
We've reverse-engineered the instruction set.
We had a backup tape.
We could take that apart,
find objects where we had the binary object,
where we had the source code,
by looking at the strings.
We found one that did some very rudimentary,
I think, third-order polygons,
and we found one that did some very rudimentary,
very polynomial approximations of sine and cosine
and stuff like that.
So we could start reversing during the instruction set.
Then we had a breakthrough,
because we found an object that looked like the disassembler
from they have used in the,
and that had a list of all the instruction names,
and it did all the usual and with seven bits here
and what does this do.
So Alan pretty much brute-forced the entire instruction set,
using that.
So now we have the instruction set,
ready to simulate, right?
So we have instructions like execute heap access
adaptive balanced tree lookup.
And we don't know what it does.
Well, it probably looks up in an active adaptive balanced tree
somewhere in the heap,
but the closer details, eh.
So what's going on here?
Well, transpires the instruction set,
the instruction set is a private contract
between the guys from the compiler group's
code generation department and the microcode guys.
There's been 15 versions of the instruction set.
We have the latest one, version 15.
It's never been documented,
because only these people need to know it.
So software emulation at instructions level, nope.
Okay.
But we have the schematics.
They're not very good.
They've been copied down and photocopied
and photocopied and so on.
It's really hard to see the difference
between a zero and an eight, for instance.
Or B and D are hard too.
And we even have some documentation of the microcode.
The layout of the microcode instructions.
And we have the IO processor which downloads the microcode,
so we also have the microcode.
So, okay.
Here we go.
But yeah, that's that footnote.
When you turn it on, the IO processor runs and says,
I've downloaded the microcode.
And then it says,
R1000 CPU running now owns the console.
And then nothing happens for 45 minutes
when it runs off a SSD disk.
It takes more time on a hard disk.
While it garbage collects its image,
and we have no idea what that means,
what it does, what goes on.
That's not a very good debugging environment.
So the final thing we can do is to go down
and simulate the circuits.
The hardware.
Here's a NAND gate.
Here's a register.
Here's a...
And if we do a microcode simulation,
we can probably get it to run at regular speed,
which is megahertz.
The top clock rate is 20 megahertz,
but really most of it runs at around 10 or 5.
We'll have to figure out what the microcode does
from the schematics and from the documentation we have.
And we cannot use the diagnostic facilities
of the computer.
Unless we do the circuit thing.
Then we can use the diagnostic facilities of the computer.
The bad news is that it probably runs at kilohertz speeds.
So...
Yeah.
Not good.
Either way, we need to do something with the schematics.
So about the diagnostics.
The 68k CPU talks to 8052 mask ROM microcontrollers.
There's one on each board.
And these 8052s do what is essentially JTAG,
except JTAG is from 1985.
But the I.O. processor can download a byte stream
to the 8052 and say, do this.
And it would interpret these bytes
as an instruction set.
And go out and poke this register
and load this in here
and see what happened over here and so on.
And there's tons of these diagnostic programs.
Um...
The stuff out is one of the diagnostic files.
So they define the parameters first
and then come to the bytes,
which are downloaded to the 8052.
It's not like it's high-level language.
So, yeah, we did a simple reversion
in that instruction set too.
It's kind of getting a thing with this machine.
Um...
It's all built on what they call experiments.
And experiments are written in a high-level macro language
that says, load this here and load that there
and pull these bytes out and take these bytes and do stuff.
And there's more than 1,000 of these
on the hard disk of the I.O. processor.
So that's a lot of help getting things to work,
um...
that we can really use in this effort.
And once you start looking at this computer at that level,
you realize that's some really bright people
who've made this computer.
It has a 20-megahertz crystal.
It also has a 21-megahertz crystal.
So they can test it out running 5% faster
when the field engineer is there.
They can also raise the power supply
and lower the power supply by a quarter of a volt.
And if it runs at plus-minus 250 millivolts,
and plus 5% clock,
it probably runs okay and is stable at normal conditions.
Um...
It's really people who were not going to have any goff happen
on these computers.
This is actually the circuit.
It's very hard to read,
but the top crystal is 21 megahertz.
The bottom one is 20 megahertz.
Um...
And a little state machine to make sure
the handover is smooth and so on.
So the plan right now
is to implement the schematics in System C.
System C is C++ classes for simulating hardware.
It's used a lot for people who create system on chips
to test that all the bits talk together the right way and so on.
It's going to be horribly slow.
It will probably take a month
for the machine to do the garbage collect.
But if we can make it work,
we can optimize it afterwards.
For instance, we don't need to simulate
all the individual RAM chips.
We can just say we have this magic RAM chip
which is one megabyte by 175 bits.
And stuff like that.
There's a lot of places where optimizations can be done.
So we hope that getting it run as a first step
and then optimize it to get it to a usable speed.
Even if we cannot get it to run at a usable speed,
having a software emulation is historically
preservation.
Then we'll have to figure out what to do later.
Maybe synthesize it to an FPGA or something.
System C, as I said, is C++ classes for hardware.
They add some syntactic sugar with macros.
So once it's SC module, this and that and so on.
But basically, this is a 138, 328 decoder.
And you go in and you say, well, if the enabled bits
are not set, then all go high.
And then we have to set this one high and so on.
And the kernel of system C then goes out and says,
okay, this signal changed.
I have to call this one over here.
And I have to call this one.
And keeps track of the clock delta update stuff and so on.
It's pretty brilliant.
It's also rather tedious as all hardware ends up being.
But we can use it.
It works.
So schematics.
We have 470 pages.
And as you can see on the top left corner there,
they have suffered through copying and so on.
The originals seem to have been 24 by 16 inches.
That's something like 80 by 40 something-ish centimeters.
There's a thick margin, a thin margin.
And they have these inch marks along the edges.
Along the border.
And we can use those to correct all the disturbances,
distortions that have happened.
So there is a correspondence between the original inch
coordinates and the pixel coordinates we have.
And it's non-trivial.
It's bent and twisted and shaped and so on.
So when you try to OGR read something like this,
which is geometric, it's a lot easier to do so if you get the
straight lines to be straight.
Before you start.
So that's the first thing we do.
We're going to find the thick exterior border.
And then we're going to recenter the page.
There's a big white margin with three holes in it on top of all
the pages.
We don't need that.
Stuff like that.
So we crop the page around the thick margin.
There's also a page that's slipped in the outer feeders
that will lack one-third of it.
We'll shift that into space and so on.
And then we find the thick border and the thin border and the arrows.
And that gives us an inch-pixel relationship all the way around
the drawing.
We can use that to reconstruct the geometry.
So a bit about some of these slides may be confusing because
real inch coordinates are first quadrant.
But image quadrants in computers are almost always fourth
quadrant where the eye axis goes down.
And we use NumPy in Python, which has Fortran context so you
have the Y coordinate before the X coordinate in your indexes.
And the dots per inch of the original images is 265-ish.
It's not constant.
And black is minus one and white is plus one.
I'll get to that in a moment.
So the first thing we have to do is find the thick exterior border.
And if you never tried to do any kind of image processing,
you'll think, how hard can that be?
And then you'll realize that's actually a surprisingly hard problem.
Because any vertical line will confuse your code.
The diagram might have a thick bus running right inside the border.
So which one do you pick?
But we have the advantage we're looking for a thick and a thin border.
We're looking for two lines 53 pixels apart.
So we simply go searching and say, find the places where we have a pixel
here and 53 pixels further down, which are both black.
And then you get a histogram.
And then you get a histogram like this with a totally unmistakable peak.
A lot of image processing like that is very counterintuitive
because our vision system is brilliant.
It does things like recognize a truck with traffic lights on it,
which Teslas can't do, for instance.
And Tesla has some of the most advanced vision software right now.
But a lot of these things are counterintuitive,
so one has to think about them to get it to work.
Similar, to find the corners, how hard can that be?
So the way you do it is you build a histogram of the longest stretch
of black pixels you can find.
And then you find the median of that and you use a threshold
to find out where you have your corners.
Just saying find corners is not a thing in pixel-based image processing.
And similar, when you find something that looks like a corner,
it may not be a corner.
It may be a T-intersection.
So you need an algorithm that can say,
how many legs does this corner actually have?
So you make, you count pixels in the four directions
and you should only have in two of them.
And they should be at 90 degrees angles to each other.
It's fortunately pretty easy to do in Python these days,
this kind of stuff.
Similarly, finding the center of the arrow.
Do not look for the average.
Because the average, a single pixel can throw your average off.
Look for the median.
In image processing, always look for the median.
So we simply build a list of all the X coordinates
and then we take the middle of that list.
That's where the center of the arrow is.
So having established these points, we need to do a projection
from the pixel-based coordinate system to the inch-based coordinate system.
And we need two projections.
We need one that goes from pixel this and that
to the X coordinate in inches and the Y coordinate in inches.
And it's actually also very useful to have them going the other way
because the things are drawn in inches.
So being able to say, I have this pixel.
Find me the pixel that's drawn half an inch further down.
You convert to inches, you go, and then you convert back to pixels.
And even if the paper is angled at some degrees,
you'll find the right spot that way.
So the way one does that is to connect all the control points by triangles,
find out which triangle you're in,
then interpolate into that triangle with a triangular coordinate system.
But that's also not quite easy.
So if you have one or two points,
there are many ways you can draw triangles between them.
And you want as round triangles as possible.
Ideally, you would want 60-degree,
equal-sided triangles, if you could.
Long, thin triangles mean to come out
basically in tangent mathematics,
which gives you some very abrupt changes
and distortions in the output.
So somebody, Russian,
published a paper which was translated to French,
and therefore his name is pronounced Delaunay,
but he's Russian.
Anyway, his rule is that,
when you circumscribe your triangle,
so you draw a circle that goes through the three points of the triangle,
no other triangle has a point inside that circle.
And it's horrible to construct.
You start out by defining three or four points outside all your points,
and then make a triangle there,
and then you add your points one by one,
and find out, and flip, and so on.
I've written it once, it's not fun,
but fortunately these days,
import Skypey,
I want one of these,
and you're done.
So you can use pretty heavy-duty algorithms
without reading all of numerical algorithms again.
That's a nice thing.
It's still tricky.
It's not a free lunch, but it works.
The top one is a page where
I've used the inch marks as control points,
the top left corner of the drawing box,
down in the corner where all the text is.
The bottom one, I've taken all the tilde characters,
because that's a nice symmetric character,
and they're easy to find,
and used those as control points too.
But you can see I get these very thin, long triangles
if I have too many control points to close together.
For instance,
here I have five control points right next to each other,
so I get these long, thin triangles.
That's not a good idea.
It's better to just have two points there, for instance.
But the other thing is,
this shows the x-coordinate.
Notice the very clear blue-red-blue pattern.
That is very typical when you run paper
through any kind of paper feeder.
You start out with the first drive rollers,
the blue part.
Then you come to the second drive rollers.
Then it runs faster.
Then the first rollers leave it again,
and then it runs slower again.
So that's a very typical pattern.
If you go down,
and you can do this kind of calibration
on anything that's scanned or printed,
you will find this pattern on pretty much everything,
and it will tell you what way
the paper went through the copier,
if that's useful for you.
So moving on,
two of these Delaunay projectors,
we can project things.
But since many image processing apps
and algorithms scale with
the square of the number of pixels,
which means they scale with the
fourth power of the resolution,
we want a low-resolution image to work on.
So we take the projection backwards
and make a 50 DPI image.
That's very crude,
but it's good enough to find things.
And having found them in the 50 DPI image,
we can go back to the other one
and work on the full resolution
to find the precise coordinates.
So for instance,
on this schematic,
chips are drawn,
most of them are drawn as boxes.
Boxes have four corners.
So we're going to find all the potential corners,
all the potential top left,
bottom left,
top right,
bottom right,
and then we're going to say,
okay, what do we have
that corresponds to this top left image?
Find these two.
Is there a fourth one that fits?
And then we have all the rectangles.
So the way we do this
is with 2D correlation.
We built what's called a kernel,
except it's with an A,
which is basically a picture
of an idealized corner.
So we have ones corresponding to white over here,
we have minus ones corresponding to black,
and we have zeros corresponding to gray.
And then we take this one
and multiply it with the image
at every single pixel.
And remember I said black pixels are minus one
and white pixels are plus one?
So we multiply minus one with minus one.
We expect to find black,
we have black,
we get plus one out.
If we come in and multiply one by one,
we expect white,
we find white,
we get a one out.
But the other way around,
we expect black,
we find white,
we get a minus one.
Wrong color.
And if we multiply by zero,
we don't care what color it is.
It doesn't add up.
So you sum up all these,
and then the better the match,
the higher the number you get.
It's really simple.
The only problem is
you multiply all pixels by all pixels.
It's called 2D image correlation
or 2D convolution.
And it calculates
how alike two images are.
Typically a large one and a small one.
And again, scales with a quadruple
of the resolution you scanned in.
So don't do this on a 600 DPI.
Certainly not in Python.
The problem is a lot of people
look at the output and say,
meh, that doesn't look very useful.
And the point is the output
is actually not an image.
It looks like one,
but it is not an image.
It's a probability map
if we want to get serious about it.
But if you look in the four circles,
you can see there is a bright white spot
in each of them.
It's brighter than anything else in the image.
And those are the four corners we're looking for.
So you simply take,
you run through all these multiplications
and additions,
then you find the maximum value.
That's your most likely corner.
And then you can proceed down the list
until you've found everything you think
might be relevant.
So we find all the chips.
We also find a lot of other crap
because a rectangle is a rectangle.
So usually after a 2D correlation step,
you need some kind of sanity check
or geometric check
or other way to get the confusion out of it.
In this case,
there's only a finite number of chips
used in these schematics,
and they only have a finite number of sizes.
So I can simply make a positive list
and say these sizes are legal.
Anything else is junk.
Similar, we have AND gates
and NAND gates
and NOR gates
and stuff like that.
So I hand-built a kernel
which I've run over the 50 DPI image.
And then when that gives a hit,
we go down on the high resolution one
and use a machine build.
First time I went through and sorted,
you know, hits, misses,
took them apart.
So 90% of the hits have white
in the areas that's white on this one.
90% of the hits
have black here.
And the rest of the pixels,
I say, they don't care.
Now I have a high resolution kernel
I can run around just the small area
where the 50 DPI image says
there's one there.
I can run it on plus minus 20 pixels
on that area.
So that's very fast
even though I run it at 600 DPI.
Oh.
The problem again is,
it's looking for one of those,
and that one in the middle
actually looks pretty close
when you look at it pixel by pixel.
So you need to add a layer
of geometric understanding.
So what I do in this case is,
I say all the lines
have to have black pixels
because I know it has to be
a closed figure.
So all the lines,
horizontal and vertical,
there must be a black pixel
in all those lines.
And the middle one fails
on the horizontal lines
in the middle.
They have no black pixels.
So that one gets filtered out.
And I don't know if you can see
it at that distance,
but this is a bestiarium
over trivial gates
in the rational thousand computer.
And it's actually kind of,
I kind of like it.
I'm thinking about having
a poster made with it.
Sort of like, you know,
butterflies of the Northern Europe
kind of thing.
So yeah, we can take a schematic,
we can find all the flags
that link to different schematics.
We can find the ones that link
single signals instead of buses.
We can find all the backplane connections
as 4,200, 2,100 backplane connections
and 2,100 frontplane connections
in this computer.
We can find those two.
We can find the NOR gates.
We can find the AND, NAND gates.
We can find the INVERTERs,
and we can find the CHIPs.
Now we have the coordinates of them
in the inch-based coordinate system
they were drawn.
So we can construct a KiCad schematic
pre-filled with those components.
And then we can take a grayscale image
of the original schematic
as a background.
And then simply draw by numbers,
to connect up and reconstruct
the schematics in KiCad.
I'm looking at trying to see,
can I also recognize the buses and lines?
But I'm running into a problem
where the connectivity model
of the CAD software they used
have three levels,
where KiCad only has two levels.
It has inside the schematic and global.
And they had three levels to play with.
And I'm not sure
how I could map that
and do it automatically.
So I think we'll have to do
the draw by numbers thing
to get it in.
And also, the letters are very,
very hard to recognize.
I have some progress on it,
but then comes the question,
is this a comment,
or is this actually a circuit label,
and so on.
So it may not be faster
to do recognition on the letters.
Time will tell.
But then when you start looking
at these schematics,
it's like,
take a look at those resistors.
They look odd, don't they?
Long, thin boxes at the top,
and the one at the bottom,
major zigzagging compared to
how Americans normally draw
their schematics.
That's weird.
And then if you look at the number,
digit two,
it's smeared,
symmetrically.
The bottom curve of the digit two
looks pretty unharmed,
but the front curve
is almost filled in.
So how many people here
have ever used
a VersaTech electrostatic plotter?
Oh, you're lucky.
We
I had a test last evening and
I had ankle commercials
about an
In Hell A-Pot
together.
And, it was absolutely
all working.
Yeah,
that's it,
because that was the
first step.
Insonge was more intense.
That test was all supposed
to be done
by you and
were only
two people.
immersed in the liquid and if that sounds messy you are absolutely correct. So they
bought a company called Versatech which used to make penplotters and said we have this
pattern do something with it and Versatech did. They make Versatech matrixplotters and
I think one of these, if my computer can deal with this one. There is a drawing here that
shows the principle. Yeah that one. So basically you have the paper specially coated a little
bit like the thermo paper in shop receipts and so on. And then you have a bunch of needle
pins.
And you fire a high voltage pulse on those which puts a small charge at the coating of
the paper. And then you move it over to a small fountain of very dirty water. And the
dirt will stick to the electrical charge and then you quickly dry it and get the color
particles to melt into the sort of waxen layer on top of the paper. It's absolutely disgusting.
You get and idea of when something went wrong when they are very proud of their air tight
paper chamber. Uh...but they made these uplotters and um they made them in
1975 and if you do the math on a utlnotter like this, so its only 20 inch wide about 0.5mm.
It prints at 100 dpi, that means it needs 2,000 dots per line, and it prints 3 inches
a second, so it does 300 lines a second.
That means you have to feed it 73 kilobytes per second in 1975.
There was a lot of computers that couldn't do that.
So it was very used, almost typical, you'd have the plotter sitting on specialized hardware
for driving it, and you'd come with a Mac tape, and the specialized, whatever it was,
would then drive the plotter.
And one of the things Versatech had to do was very fast character generators, so that
if you just wanted to print something where you had, if you could split your drawing into
a bunch of symbols, you could just send symbol 7, 9, 10, like we do with the printer, and
then you could feed it at full speed.
And the CAD program they used...
I'm sorry.
It was originally set up for driving a Versatech printer.
Everything is drawn in a 0.1 times 0.1 inch grid.
All the letters are spaced exactly 0.245 millimeters apart.
There's no letters that's raised half a line or anything like that.
It has to fit in the grid because that's what the character generator can do.
That's actually incredibly useful.
Because now I know everything is...
It's on a grid.
That means I can draw my chips in ASCII art, because that's basically what they did.
And then I can use that to generate a key card symbol, which, as you can see, overlays
pretty nicely on the original schematic.
And then the next thing I can do when I have my ASCII art, I can build a chip signature.
Right?
We have pins here, here, here, here, here.
We have pins here, here, here, here.
So I can build a signature that says, on the left side, pin, space, space, space, pin,
space, space, pin, space.
Right side, pin, pin, space, and so on.
And I can recognize that on the schematic.
When I find the box, the rectangle on the schematic, I can say, where do I have pins?
Oh, this signature.
So that's got to be in 74F244.
Okay.
So, status right now is that I have 407 schematics and I've found 10,772 components on them.
And most of them I know what chip it is.
I didn't think that was possible when I started.
I thought this was something I would use a couple of days on and then I would give it
up, go away, start a crowd project to get all these schematics digitized.
I'm really surprised this was possible.
There's still things outstanding, signals, labels, bosses, all that stuff.
But a lot of that seems to be a problem with mapping it into KiCad.
I don't know if, I'm not quite concluded where I am yet.
Recognizing the letters and digits is going to be tough because they've really suffered
the copying process hard.
Telling a zero and an eight apart just by looking at them, forget it.
But many of them are in the context.
For instance, this one, we know what the pin numbers are.
So, we know that is a 10.
We know that is a one, zero.
Okay.
Whenever we have a schematic with that chip on it, we know that's a zero.
So, that gives us a reference for that piece of paper with the copings, that have been through.
But, I'm still not sure it's enough to actually be able to decode it.
But, I'm going to continue working on this a bit.
There's also other sources of text.
Very often you have a buzz of eight signals.
That's you know, blah, blah, blah, seven, blah, blah, blah, six, blah, blah, blah, five.
that kind of context you can also figure out that yeah they probably didn't swap 18 and
10 didn't and so on but it may be faster simply to draw it by hand in keycat so that was my
little summer vacation product this year I tried to simulate the the clock circuit
what's the name of it
so
so when you run the um the system
system
c simulation you can get it to produce very log compatible wave files and you can pull those up
in a gtk wave and look at them and what you have here is actually here it's running 20 megahertz
here's running 21 and here's running 20 megahertz and that's by taking the keycat schematic exporting
a netlist running that through some python code that generates system c files and then compiling
those and running that
and saving the the wave file um because there's 407 files i'm i'm thinking a lot about the workflow
of this i don't want to have to do something manually 407 times if i can automate it
so the structure of the system c code how to get that to work differently and and i have these five
major boards of the computer that's connected with a backplane and a front plane and how to get
system c to understand that these
are sort of connectors and so on but it's it's looking promising and if nothing else i can use
this to look at specific sub circuits and say what does this do um and then try to get things working
so maybe we will get a software emulation of the rational thousand it's still not impossible
so yeah questions
yes no i don't know what to do about a leaky roof
you were using this system to see instead of doing vhdl or something why um portability um
vhdl if i wanted to to do an fpga version i would go vhdl in particular i would do vhdl because it's
originally ada based
um but the goal here is to make a accessible
emulation of the uh of the rational thousand so would really prefer if we could avoid
that um that that people have to buy special hardware to run it
and system c is literally just c plus plus classes so i figured we can probably find out how to run c++
code a hundred years from now also oh yeah well actually that's a good
question a lot more effort has gone into optimizing VHDL because a lot more
people do it but simulating VHDL at speed is a very expensive hobby
simulating system C at speed is a slightly more expensive hobby I talked
to some of the people from the system C world and one advantage of not calling
people on the phone but doing a video conference is you can see the eyes go
this guy thought what but but when I explain to them what a situation is
there yeah yeah that's probably the way to do it I hope you're a patient man but
but I only I'm
mainly
see the system see as a way to to get something working enough that we can
start optimizing without risking it stop working but yeah waiting one month for
it to boot not optimal but the good thing about system C is that you can
actually synthesize that to VHDL if you write it for it so so that option is
still open I mean basically this is about
getting a net list for the computer and if you have that you can transform it to
anything that you want to just in this eye so if we want to do a rational
thousand on a chip as a souvenir in our future data museum yeah we could do that
any more questions thank you very much
you're welcome