So, we are ready for the next talk, it's Nils Christensen telling us about Netbox.
Go ahead, Nils.
Thank you.
More specifically, it's the integration for Netbox and I'm working at a company called
QuickPay.
We are a payment service provider but we used to be a hosting provider as well until recently.
And we are a pretty small team of system administrators, we used to be three but now we are two people.
So we kind of didn't want to have a lot of different systems for managing QuickPay and
the hosting business.
Obviously the hardware is in the same location so it makes sense to use the same system.
And we used to have this homemade configuration management called Pepsi and it looks something
like this.
You have config files in the config directory and that's not really something that's handled
by Netbox but we use Ansible for that part now.
Okay.
And then we have ETC that specifies which devices we have, like switches, hosts, VLANs
and that's how that is.
This is an example of one of the hosts, so you can see some different data that we have,
the IP address, data centre, packages.
We can see the IP address.
That was just to say that that is something that we have in NetBox now.
If I go to devices, you can see it's both data centre infrastructure management, so
you have the physical hardware, but you also have IP addresses, so it's also IP address
management.
But we have these hosts and different devices, chassis C137, with some devices in, and if
I go on to one of those, you can see here that we have a production platform and a cluster,
so that is to...
In Ansible, you can specify variables for a cluster, for example.
Usually we don't specify variables for a single host, because it's usually something that
you would either have a setting for a cluster or for a data centre or a region or something
like that.
And...
Yes.
You can specify those in a config context, so this is the hard drives and memory in this
machine, and we can use all of these things in Ansible with the integration.
There is this integration, but we had some problems with that.
And I'm going to show you.
Now we are in the Ansible inventory.
We have a few things.
Sorry.
And if you have some secret in all that is passed first, so you might want to overwrite
that secret for a specific cluster or platform or region, but in the way that this is structured,
you would have the secret in all, and then it would be overwritten by the cluster, so
it would be overwritten alphabetically, and that's not something that you want, because
a cluster is a small subset of a host in a region or site, so you would want another
structure, more like this.
So what we did here was just put some numbers in front.
And we did that by monkey patching the...
I'm sorry.
We did that by monkey patching the inventory with this mapping, so, yeah, we just have
these hard coded numbers to get the right order, load order.
And another problem that we had was that by default, I don't know why, but the guys that
made this integration threw away the subnetting information.
Do I still have...
Sorry.
I have that somewhere.
Yeah.
You can see here that there is actually subnetting information, but they just threw that away
for some reason, so we had to patch that back in.
Yeah.
This was just to show some variables that you can put into the config context, like
such secret.
And you can use that in Ansible.
But, yeah.
If you want to learn more about the integration or get the patch that we applied to it, it's...
I don't think it's good enough to upstream, so I just have it locally.
You can just talk to me after this.
And that's it.
Yeah.
Thank you.