Karina Haupt will talk about how to properly open source source code.
Give her an applause.
Yes, hello and thanks. As already was mentioned, my name is Karina Haupt.
I'm not a lawyer, I'm a software engineer or computer scientist by trade.
So this is all I will tell you is to my best knowledge.
But yeah, I'm not just a developer or software engineer.
I'm a head of a sustainable software engineering group and this is what I deal with.
So I make software more usable for others.
And this is exactly why I'm here.
I'm also a big fan of open source and I'm an open source enthusiast.
And this is why I'm giving this talk today.
I work for the German Aerospace Center.
Yeah, where I'm supporting scientists to develop software in a sustainable way.
And also, I'm there part of a team which consults people regarding open source licenses and open source publishing.
And so this talk is something I talk a lot about during my work also in my free time.
Because yeah, open source.
I'm an open source fan.
So as the title says, I want to tell you about how you open source your code properly.
Because most of the code out there isn't open source properly.
But it's really helpful.
So the idea is that you get away from the right side where you have your closed source which looks like a mess.
And you don't want to share with people.
And this is also an argument I hear the most if I say you should share your code.
Oh, it's a mess.
I don't want to show it to others.
I don't want to show it to you.
So I'm going to show you the behavior on the left where you say, yeah, clear.
It's there on GitHub.
Use it for free.
And it's not only about the idea that you're happy to share your code.
It's also about the other person being able to use your code in a properly and safe way.
And this is the one I want to talk about.
How you can achieve this.
So let's first talk really quickly about free software.
What is free or open source software?
So first it was called free software.
But this didn't really went well with industry because it sounded like it's free like in free beer.
So they introduced the term open source.
But the thing is free is like not in free beer.
It's in freedom.
So the idea of free software is that the user has all the freedoms.
This means to run the software, to copy, to modify it.
To distribute it.
To use it.
To share it.
To share it with others.
And so on and so on.
So this is the idea.
I think most of you know about that.
But I always include it to make sure.
And there's a lot of cases where you can what you can do with open source.
So you can use it, obviously.
Nearly all software on this planet you have the feeling is run using open source software if it's not open source itself.
I mean, the Internet wouldn't exist in a way.
But it's also about how you make external contributions or get external contributions to your open source project where you have to think about a lot of things about open source as well if you contribute to open source.
So all of these use cases where you deal with open source sound totally basic, but all of them require you to think about certain things and ensure certain things.
Because open source is not just an idea or a mentality.
It has a legal basis.
So since I'm from Germany, this is a little bit put on German law.
But it's quite similar in most of Europe.
So in Germany we have the so-called .
Normally you call it copyright.
Which means that you can protect something.
But you can't protect ideas and principles.
So normally you have to do, like, source code and object code and stuff.
You can't do something.
Yeah.
So the copyright is a very important thing.
The important thing is that...
The copyright says first that if you write something, you own it.
So you have some rights on it.
But on the same time, if you work for somebody...
They get the rights to...
To work with it.
So it's like the...
In German it's called .
So it means you have the right to...
Great.
I'm missing a word in English.
You have the rights to do...
Yeah.
You have all the rights to sell it, to open source it, or whatever.
So you have the rights to decide what happens with it.
But you don't get the right, at least in Germany, that you can say you wrote it.
So whenever you write a code, even if you work for somebody else or if you get paid to do it,
you're still allowed to say it's yours.
And they are not allowed to say they did it instead of you.
So this is a small differentiation which is really important.
What is important is that it's based on laws.
And open source licenses are contracts.
Meaning if you don't follow them, if you just use something in a way you're not allowed
to, then you break a contract and you can get in trouble.
So there's civil law and criminal law which protects the open source developer or the
one who writes the code, as well as can, yeah, be used against you if you don't use open
source software in the right way.
This sounds a bit strange.
It's scary.
But in reality, the open source community is really nice.
So normally you get a pointer, like you did something wrong, you have to update something,
you have to do something to follow certain rules.
And then you're fine.
So most times when lawyers and stuff gets included in the process is normally when big
companies don't agree to that their stuff is protected by an open source license or
they are using stuff which is protected under an open source license.
They didn't want to comply.
So they get in trouble.
This, so before I start with open source licenses, details and stuff, I want to present you a
process, you could say, for publishing software, which we introduced at my work.
So it's a German Aerospace Center and which counts for nearly all companies.
So where you work when you want to publish something or even most of the stuff you have
to check also when you do it on your own.
It doesn't matter if you're part of a company.
It's just one or two things which are a little bit special then.
For example, the first thing is just when you don't publish your own code, or it's your
own code, but one which you wrote while you're employed somewhere or something or where you
get paid for it.
So the first thing is you have to ask your organization if you're allowed to publish
it.
It sounds really, really default, but in research, a lot of people just publish code
without asking their bosses or something.
And on the one hand, I love it that there's more open source code out there.
But in the end, the problem is that it's not really theirs to decide because while they
have the right to be named as an author, they don't have the right to commercialize or whatever
to distribute the software further because all of this kind of rights are with the employee.
Normally.
So this is normally stated in your contract that everything you do while you work is owned
by your employee.
So ask him first.
Second, and that's where it gets tricky, is to determine all legal requirements and resulting
tasks out of those, meaning you have to check, am I allowed to publish my code as open source
software?
And if so, do I have perhaps something I have to do?
Do I have something I have to care about?
Or am I perhaps restricted in the type of licenses I'm allowed to use?
And so on.
So there's different things you have to think about.
The first one is who are your contributors?
Is it just you?
Did other people help?
If so, they have to agree that you publish it.
So as soon as you gather an external contributor or your colleague or friend or whoever who
works on the same code too, they have to agree too.
So you have to make sure that it gets published, except if it's all owned by the same employee,
then they can decide.
So you first have to identify everybody so that they on the one hand agree if they have
the rights or that you name them at least as an author because everybody who participated
has the right to be called as an author.
So you normally write an author txt or something like that so that you can say, okay, this
is the people who helped.
This is the people who worked on that because they have the right to be named.
Then something nearly nobody thinks about is something called export restrictions.
And I would be interested if anybody with a show of hands, if anybody knows what export
restrictions are.
I've heard about that.
Okay.
We have like four here or five people know about that.
How many have thought about checking those when you publish software as open source?
Show of hands.
Nobody.
Yeah.
That's normally the typical amount of writing.
Okay.
So I'm going to show you a few examples of what I've got here.
So normally export restrictions are known for stuff like weapons and things, but it's
also the same for software.
In Europe, it's quite easy to estimate if something can use or is used in a military
way, you have export restrictions.
In the US, it's a little bit more complicated because they have this dual use thing, meaning
stuff can be used in a military context.
So you can use it in a military context as well in a civilian context.
And nearly everything is dual use.
For example, Microsoft Excel is dual use because you can use it in a military way to do something,
to calculate whatever.
So you have to check if it's under the export restrictions, but luckily with stuff like
Microsoft Excel or whatever, they are under restrictions, but they don't have any restrictions.
So as they are listed somewhere or fits the description of certain categories, they are
under the export restrictions.
But you don't get any restrictions.
But there's other stuff which is restricted.
So specific cryptography or something, especially if you go to all these things, then you get
in trouble if you want to export it somewhere.
And if you publish it as open source, this normally means you export it to the whole
world.
And as I said, in the European law, it's not a big issue, but the US law is important for
us because it's valid as soon as possible.
So if you have a code which is in a whole car or something, one screw which is from
the US, one tiny screw, you have to follow the US export laws.
And same is for software.
And you can perhaps imagine that might be if you use some libraries or stuff, there
might be some code which came from the US.
So suddenly it's under US export law.
So you have to check.
As a private person writing your small game or whatever, this might be a bit of a challenge
for you.
As a research facility, we have to check this regularly, especially that you don't
get in trouble because the US has some crazy ideas who are evil people, and so you're
not allowed to publish it as open source, so you can get in trouble with them.
Then, again, this is perhaps a little bit specific for research facilities, but it might
be depending on where you work or how you perhaps get some funding for your open source
project.
So that's one thing.
If you're part of a bigger open source project, if you're part of a bigger project, you have
to check if there's some conditions with the funding.
So for example, in Europe, there's a research program called Horizon 2020.
Perhaps some of you have heard of that.
I don't know if you're close to research.
And they say sometimes you're allowed to or you have to publish it as open source, which
is amazing if they do this.
But sometimes they say it has to be under a permissive license or a copyleft license.
And what does this exactly mean?
I'll come to a little bit later.
But so you have to check what they say.
And also it can be that you signed a contract with a company where you wrote something or
a part of what you did there gets into your other project.
And somewhere in the small letters on page, I don't know, 130, it says everything which
results out of this project is not allowed to be published as open source, which is for
us, for example, the case with some bigger companies who write this in all their contracts.
So everything we produce or get the ideas from in this project, we're not allowed to
open source.
The best solution is if you have something before which you put in, open source it before.
So it's already open source, so they can't do anything about it.
But you should always check if you signed some funding contracts because there can be
stuff written somewhere down there regarding the rights or yeah.
And suddenly you have this big, big project or something and there was this one tiny part
and now you're not allowed to publish it.
Again, something.
A lot of people don't think about and check.
And I don't know.
Is here some people from research?
Show of hands.
Oh, yeah.
One, three.
So perhaps those of you know, the history of research project is that you get funding
and the next funding and the next funding and it's over years and years and decades.
And in the end, it's really hard to figure out like where did the funding come from?
Do we have some restrictions?
So you have to note all the stuff down early when you get the money.
There's no restrictions.
There's no regulations or something.
Note it somewhere close to your project.
This is really helpful later.
And now comes this part which everybody needs to do.
And this is as soon as, at least as soon as you use code which is not yours.
Especially libraries, which is completely normal today, I think, to have some code from
others which you use.
So you have to check for the third party code regarding the licenses.
And we'll talk about this a lot in the next part.
But before I come to one more part which is if you have done all of this, you will have
a set of things which you need to do.
So this will be the second part also or third part.
It depends on the kind of talk.
And you have to evaluate a little bit.
Is it worth doing it?
In my opinion, nearly all cases, yes.
Do your stuff open source.
Do it properly.
Work on the project from the beginning that you can do it easily.
But sometimes you have to check.
Sometimes you have to check if the effort is worth it.
And especially who would benefit from it.
Is there somebody else who would use it?
And in some cases, it's true to say, yeah, it doesn't make sense a lot.
It would be a lot of work.
Or we would have to rewrite big parts because of some funding restrictions.
Or we can't give everything out because of some export restriction or something.
And so it doesn't make sense to publish it then.
Sadly, that's sometimes the case.
But you should always think about, okay, what do I need to do?
Is it worth it?
So I stepped quite quickly about this analyze license terms of third party code.
And this is kind of what open source is a lot about.
It's like open source licenses.
And that's why we now do an excourse to the world of open source software licenses.
And in general, it's really fun to talk for me, at least, to talk about software licenses.
Not everybody.
It's a kind of dry topic.
But I'm happy a lot of people or some people showed up to be interested in this.
And so in general, you can say there's all these software licenses.
And there's three types.
The free and open source software licenses, which we talk about today the most.
Then there's public domain, where a lot of people think this is open source, but it isn't.
As well as proprietary.
And a lot of people think proprietary means commercial.
But this is not the case.
Proprietary means everything which is not free and open source or public domain.
It can be commercial, but it doesn't have to be.
So there's like shareware stuff in the early days or stuff which is proprietary.
But it might be free to use.
You might even have access to the code.
But it means it doesn't give you all the rights I mentioned in the beginning.
So free and open source licenses always give you the right to use, to modify, to distribute, and so on and so on.
So you have certain rights you get.
And if you get those, it's a free and open source software license.
Important to know is that the term open source software license or something is not protected.
So there's licenses out there who claim to be open source but aren't.
For example, a quite common one is one which states something like,
you're allowed to do all these things for open source, but you're not allowed to use it for something evil.
It sounds really good.
It sounds like a great idea.
But the problem is who says what is evil and what isn't.
To draw certain lines really, really hard.
And again, free and open source software, it's about non-discrimination.
So it doesn't matter what you use it for, who you are, where you're from or something.
You're allowed to do all the same things.
And this is important.
So even if it feels like a good idea to exclude military use or whatever,
it's not matching the idea of open source software.
In the world of free and open source software licenses,
there's two types of licenses.
Most perhaps know this.
One is copyleft.
So this was a copyleft.
The most well-known is the one with GPL.
And these licenses are effective.
Meaning they come with the moral idea that everything which is free,
should stay free, even if you modified it.
And everything which is building on something which is free also should be free.
This means as soon as you get a little bit software which is licensed under copyleft into your code,
it all has to be, the whole software in the total, has to be free.
Often it even says it has to be published under the same or compatible license.
Then on the other hand,
there's another idea.
That's the permissive licenses.
Well-known examples there are MIT, Apache, BSD.
They come from the idea that you should have the freedom to do really everything.
So even put it in a commercial product.
Or change something and bring it onto your own license.
So the idea is really freedom until the end.
So everything should stay free.
And on the other hand,
the freedom to do really everything.
I prefer the permissive licenses myself.
Because I think it's important that we can also use it in parts which might be sold or commercially in some parts.
Because this can help getting funding.
And there's a lot of mixtures and possibilities.
Copyleft sounds like a great idea.
But can happen that people don't use it because they can't use it to all the stuffs.
Although,
because of this type of different licenses,
we can get into the field of license incompatibilities.
The easiest example is if you have two copyleft licenses,
which both say you have to publish the result or the result has to be,
the whole software has to be under their own license.
The problem is you can't do both at the same time.
So if I put two libraries under two different licenses,
a copyleft license,
into my code,
I have the problem that the software,
the one license says the software has to be under this license A,
and the other one says it has to be under license B.
And while there's something like dual licensing,
then each product would still be breaching the other license.
So it can't be under the same executable or one you can create can be just under one license.
So this results in something I always call like impossible software
because you can build it,
you can use it for yourself,
but you can't distribute it because in that moment you breached one of the licenses.
And this is a big problem with copyleft licenses especially.
So this is about if you have a single license.
Picking one is really easy,
but if you reuse and combine stuff,
it can be really complicated.
So what I want to show you now is really at first a little bit like frightening graphic,
which is about combining modules under different licenses.
And I want to give you a quick overview about what this means
because this is normally where it gets complicated really quickly for a lot of people.
So in the orange thingy on the corner,
we have your own software component,
which you wrote, whatever.
And now you combine it with a copyleft component.
Here there's even a differentiation between copyleft or the components with copyleft
or license with a copyleft with strong copyleft
or here strongly reciprocal and a standard reciprocal.
I hope I pronounced that right.
So normally it's called strong and weak copyleft.
With a strong copyleft,
GPL, most famous example,
it means you combine your stuff.
So if you use it as a normal library
or if you change something on that code,
on this component,
it's a derivative work
and it has to be under the license like the GPL.
It has to stay under that.
This is the right case like so.
So it means it keeps the same rights and laws you have to fulfill.
On the left,
you see there's another possibility,
which is called combined work with strong separation.
This is a tricky one.
So it means there is a way to kind of get a bit around about the GPL.
But as soon as you try to get around it,
it don't be used in a proper way,
you're kind of already screwed up and you can't use this way.
So it normally means a good example how you can do is,
imagine you have a tool which do some data analysis
and it will create a nice PDF with some graphs on it.
And so you include into your project,
into your small analysis and graph writing thingy,
PDF viewer.
And use one which is under GPL.
You put it in and you kind of already created the PDF
and you call it via a command line comment from in your code
like run this tool,
open it up in a separate window or something and show this PDF.
This you would call a combined work with strong separation.
This would be fine.
Then the PDF viewer would be GPL
and you can do with your code whatever you want.
You can do it commercially,
also another copyleft or permissive license.
So why is this possible?
Because you're using officially interfaces.
So if you interact with this program in an interface
which was created by the developers,
by the rights owners,
and you say,
okay, I'm using this like a command line interface or something,
this is fine
because this is a normal intended use
by the developer who owns the rights.
What's not possible is to write a command line interface
for a tool,
push it there,
and then use this on the other side
or as soon as you share objects or whatever internally,
you're screwed anyway.
So this is really something which is more the idea
you combine tools which are already existing
or already running
and you just kind of put it in one installation thing
or you put it together in one interface in a way,
but you use it in a way like you would use the tools normally
if they would be standalone as well.
And your code has to be working standalone
and their code still has to be working standalone.
So then you can work with GPL in your stuff
and a common example is you have your,
if you have a distribution or something for Linux,
okay, that's a special thing,
but even if you have Windows or something
and it could be shipped with GPL applications
because those applications are standalone or something,
it's totally fine
and they are not influencing like all of Windows.
Okay, now this is like the hard copyleft,
so in general you can say you use copyleft,
you get under the license,
just if you have it really, really loosely coupled,
there's a possibility,
but as soon as you try to reach a state
by creating this barrier on your own,
you're screwed because here it's about intention.
If your intention is to get around to GPL,
you don't have any chance with the lawyers.
Because this is really strict,
something like weak copyleft was introduced.
The most well-known is the LGPL,
it's a lesser GPL.
They wanted to show that this is not as good as the real GPL,
but a lot of people prefer it
and it was introduced because there was a need for it,
but as I said, a lot of people prefer it
because you give the people a little bit more freedom,
to decide what they want to do.
So the idea is if you combine it
and you don't change the LGPL code or something
and you just use it in the library,
you have your work which you can put under your license
and you have the LGPL library which is under LGPL.
If somebody would ask you for your code,
you would have to give them the LGPL code,
but not your own.
If you change something, you might have to do this as well.
But it's not as simple as it sounds.
So you have to do it first,
because there still has to be a separation,
meaning the user has to be able to exchange the library.
So he has to be able to take this piece out
and take another LGPL library,
or whatever, another library in there.
So you perhaps have to publish some parts of your code
so that they are able or create a solution
in a way with your software architecture
that you can simply say,
okay, I'm not using this version of the library,
but I changed something,
I improved something to make it faster, whatever,
and I can include it in your code.
This has to be possible.
Obviously, for different programming languages,
this means different approaches.
For some, this works really well,
because it depends on your type of linkage and stuff.
Sometimes it just,
anyway, say you have to install it somewhere,
so they just install another version on their system
and it's fine.
Sometimes you have to provide a bit of your code,
of your APIs, of your interfaces, or whatever,
and especially create a specific architecture before.
So LGPL you can include,
but it might depend on how your software is.
If you can't fulfill this requirement,
then it's again a derivative work,
meaning the result has to be under LGPL.
And last, we come to the permissive components.
Yeah, BSD, MIT, Apache,
with this, the nice thing is you can do whatever.
If you mix it up,
you can put everything under your license in the end.
If you don't change it or something,
you normally say it's a combined work.
This is, say, stay under the license,
your code's done under your license,
and you can do whatever.
So with the right part,
you can do also proprietary software,
and you can do kind of whatever you want.
With GPL,
it's a little bit more complicated.
Commercialization is still possible,
but perhaps not in the way
like with proprietary software.
Okay, so I hope you could kind of follow me through this,
because this is kind of important
if you want to clean up your code.
So if you use GPL,
if you use third-party code,
to put this a little bit in a nutshell,
is you have to check the license,
and you have to check how you integrate it.
So is it a loose coupling?
Is this linking?
Is it source code, your copy?
And it depends also, again,
lastly, like how you distribute your code.
And this all has influence
on which license you can choose for your software.
If you use something with copyleft,
you might have to use exactly this copyleft license.
If you use something with weak copyleft,
it has influence on how you create your structure
from your code.
And if you have something permissive,
you normally are totally easily unhappy.
And the distribution is also kind of important,
because all these licenses
always become really active,
you could say,
when you distribute.
Meaning,
while you get all these permissions
to do whatever you want,
you have certain rights to have,
we have all these rights, sorry,
and these permissions,
you also have certain things you have to follow.
So there's some stuff you have to do.
The one thing we already heard is
it can be for copyleft to put it under the same license
or something.
This is really, really strict.
But there's also further small stuff,
which can be important depending
if you ship it really as an executor,
if you ship it as an executable,
or just put it somewhere and say,
okay, you can get it on your own.
And same is for third-party code.
If you just give instructions,
get yourself all these list of requirements,
install it on your computer or something,
you have to check that the result
is still on a compatible license,
and this works out,
but you don't have to fulfill
everything this license says.
Because licenses say stuff like
you have to provide the license text,
you have to provide, yeah,
sometimes for the other nodes,
like for GPL, if you have a GUI,
like an interface,
you have to have a hint somewhere there
and stuff like that.
It always depends on the license
and often on the distribution type
what you have to fulfill yourself
or which you can kind of outsource
to the user who's building the software themselves.
So this is kind of important.
Think about these things.
And I can't list it for all the licenses.
But most of them require
that you send the license text
or give the license text
and stuff like that.
Okay.
Let's get back to our process.
So now we have a little bit of knowledge
about analyzing the license term
of our third-party code.
So we might have checked what we used.
If it's just permissive stuff,
normally you can just go ahead
and say, okay, this is easy,
this is not much to do.
And if you have copies,
or you have something left or something,
you should check,
do you want to perhaps replace it
depending on what license you want to pick
and what goal you want to have.
So do you want it,
a lot of people use it freely
even in commercial use
because you perhaps get
some pull requests back or something,
get some code optimations or whatever.
Or do you say, okay, it should stay open
and it has to be,
it's a mentality thing.
So when you decide this,
this you are really really good so when you checked all this stuff like export
control and whatever you're now in a good position to say okay is it versus
can I publish it or do I perhaps have stuff from different copyleft licenses
in my thing then I have to change things first and is it worse for me to do this
if it's a really tiny script and you have screwed up with the copyleft
licenses perhaps it's too much effort but perhaps you say okay I want to do
this I want to do it clean so now you have to determine the details of your
publication and implement everything all the tasks you thought about the first
thing is define which license term you take and put it all in your code which
form of publication do you want to create executables with your ship or
will you just provide your code and perhaps a list of instructions how to
set it up and which kind of support strategy do you want to go
so I'm going to show you how to do that so I'm going to show you how to do that
so when it's just perhaps a small script you throw out there you perhaps
have the readme in there perhaps you have a email address which people can
contact or you have a nice issue tracker from github you're using to interact
with people if it's a big project you should think about something else like
do you have a forum or FAQs or how-to tutorials and whatever to support people
using your code and then you have to prepare your software for publication
and this will be a little bit what we'll talk about a little bit later what this
means
because throwing your code out there might seem helpful but often isn't
because I mean how many people have perhaps found some code but there was no
documentation no so you had no clue how to run it or how to install it or you
got in problems so short show of hands who tried to use code from other people
because it sounded great at the beginning but then stopped doing because
yeah you couldn't you just couldn't
okay that's a lot more people so this is important factor and I want to talk
about this too not just about the license part and last checks the
requirements for your publication and release the software means have you done
everything which the license says and stuff like that and last publish the
software put it somewhere so
Oh I screwed something up
I screwed something up
now we talked about I mentioned you need to prepare your code and I brought
a list of minimal generic recommendations because in the end it
always depends on your your project what you need to do but this is like what I
think is kind of the minimum you should do for your project even if it's just a
small thing
this is based on something my colleagues and I wrote which is called a dealer
software engineering guidelines where you find a checklist
of things to do but this is like a generic wrap-up so the first thing
sounds really stupid but put your code under version control system and do this
from the start so people can understand what you did and put in good commit
codes use tax use release or stuff like that yeah it gives us talk to
researchers and they don't do this so this is why this is in there it sounds
like totally yeah that's the first thing all of us might do as a computer science
but researchers who write code and they sent her out tar files and stuff like
that then apply a basic coding style also something a lot of people think
they do but they don't probably do so use a linter get some help to get your
code clean up because it helps a lot to for reading and why go with the modular
design don't do over engineering this is a lot of computer scientists tend to do
they try to
create a solution which is extendable extendable extendable for everything you
could imagine and then nobody can use it
automation great thing to include especially to get a usable versions is
really helpful for your user if they can have one sorry and provides a sexual
documentation this is something which sounds also again like a really really
boring easy thing and everybody should do this
but
we checked on github and a lot of projects don't have a read me or read me
which is not really helpful and what a helpful read me looks like I'll show you
in a sec then again test your software assign a proper release number things
again basics not happening for a lot of projects and if you do public releases
oh here's something I wanted to take out it's sexy open source guidelines this is
kind of what I talked about do this
this whole process what you have to check for if you want to do a public
release and don't just use it internally but if we give it to others do this if
your code is probably and so others can use it in a legal way without getting in
trouble because a lot of code I want to reuse it's not properly licensed or they
didn't check their third-party licenses probably or they don't make it obvious
for me that they do it so I have a problem with that
so
then you have to go back to the
and I'll go back to the demo when I gave you the dependence and check all the
And then you have to pre-code in a way
that you add the license file to your repository,
that you add the license and copyright
hint to all your files.
A lot of people don't do that.
And document the third party dependencies.
So how does this look like?
You add a license file.
This is from the MIT license.
And yeah, again, I give this talk normally to researchers,
and they have really stupid ideas.
For example, they change the license text.
When you use something like MIT, you can't do that.
Then it's not MIT license anymore.
And you should keep the license as it is,
because people know how to deal with it, what it means.
If you change something, they have to read it.
So this is also a reason not to use your own license.
A lot of people love to use their own licenses.
I hate it, because I read the name.
I don't know what it is.
It means I have to read the license.
I have to understand it.
And I have to understand it correctly.
So please use an existence license.
Everybody knows.
It's about.
And the only thing you're allowed to adopt
is the copyright hint.
Again, this is a lot of people.
So they are really happy with, yeah, yeah, I know.
I'm not allowed to change anything.
And they don't change the copyright hint.
So this is something you have to adapt.
You really find a lot of licenses
where there's just a hashtag, like copyright holder.
And then it's like, great, close, nearly.
Please, this tiny thing do.
And then you can add the copyright hint license
into the source file.
And what do you see?
And a lot of code is that they copy the whole license
text, which is legally completely correct.
But it's really, really annoying,
because sometimes you have a really short file.
And three times the file content is the whole license.
And with MIT, we saw the whole license.
It's just OK.
But with GPL, it's pages and pages.
So this doesn't make sense.
So there's a new nice way to do this, which is called SPDX.
It's a copyright hint.
It's readable automatically, so machine-readable.
And you just put in your copyright text and a license
identifier.
And this is this.
And the license has to, so you put the whole license
test still in your project.
It's just stored in the licenses folder.
And it has exactly the tag you use here.
It's an MIT.txt file.
And so it matches automatically the tag to the file name.
So this is really nice.
It's something which was defined by the reuse software
initiative.
And they even have a small tool, which
will put all of this where you can enter, like,
I want this license, and for all of these file types, and so on.
And it will put it in all your code.
And if you have files which are not code files,
but for example, images or something,
you can also say, OK, do this.
And they will put a nice small file next to it, which it has
exactly the same file name.
Like the other one, like logo.png and then .license.
And in this is nothing except this copyright and license
hint.
And you can also use it for stuff like Creative Commons
or whatever to have everything perfectly labeled, which
is great, because everything which is not code
shouldn't be under open source licenses,
but use stuff like the Creative Commons licenses instead.
Because if you want to reuse stuff,
this is the only thing which makes really sense.
And this really helps you do this.
So they have a great site where they explain everything.
And there's this tool, which is really helpful.
And getting improved a lot.
Also important for your license stuff
is to document your dependencies.
You have to do it, you can, on the one hand,
you have often, like for a Python requirement,
TXT where you can write your license.
Important is the dependencies you have.
Important is that you list also which version you're using, as
well as under which license they use.
Here's the license information are in the readme file itself.
So it's written in brackets.
It's like BSD3 clause and something.
And because you don't provide it in this project where
we have this from, we don't provide the libraries
ourselves.
We say you get it via pip or something.
We don't have to ship their license files.
If you create an executable and ship it,
you have to get all these license files from them.
And my suggestion is, or if you're going to do this,
it's quite important to really copy it from their project
and not reuse, even if there's like you have 10 libraries
who are all on a MIT, copy of all of them
because they have different copyright hints
and they might have further information or whatever
in these files and say you have to take their files.
Also, it's not enough to make a link or something.
So yeah, and regarding the version, licenses may change
from one version to another.
PySite was such an example.
And they went to a commercial license from an open source
license, so it's important that you state which version
you are using so it's clear you're using the license
of this version and not of a later version where they perhaps
changed it.
Yeah, this is just example.
Everything is cleaned up, stuff, stuff, stuff, stuff, stuff.
Sorry, I just have one minute, so I have to go quickly through it.
But I kind of explained that already,
that you should clean up your code and stuff.
This can look like this.
Use releases, use tags, especially with GitLab,
it's nice, quite easily.
Have a good documentation.
A README is great.
A README should create or have the following sections.
A software purpose, again, sounds really basic.
It's missing off nearly all readments I stumble across,
like what is it, for whom, and why have you written it?
For example, this is just a small proof of concept.
It's important information for somebody who's using it
or this is a project we're using live in a big production
facility or whatever.
Talk about the main features.
Talk about restraints, like this is just
tested with Python 3.4 and Windows or something.
And make sure that you explain how to install it,
how to use it, and also perhaps give a rough idea
about future plans and ideas, that people know where you're
going with this, so if it makes sense for them to get included
or is this going perhaps in the direction they don't plan
or didn't expect.
If you're interested to get more information about this,
you can click on the link in the chat box.
And if you're interested to get a little bit more detail
how this looks like, I will perhaps later provide this slide
so there's a workshop we give which is just
about make your code ready for publication.
So in the end, the list of recommendations I want
to give you is to know who has exploitation rights.
Ah, that's a word I was missing in the beginning,
the exploitation rights.
Great. On my last slide, I have it.
So you have the ownership rights.
You might have the exploitation rights if it's your code,
if you worked it, created it while you worked for a company,
they have it, talk to those people.
If you accept external contributions, either be aware
that you have then other people who have exploitation rights.
You can create a contributor license agreement
where they handed their exploitation rights to you,
or you ensure you select the right license
on the very beginning because changing the license is
really hard if you don't have all the rights
because you have to ask everybody and they might disappear
and then you have to check like in and try to find them.
And we once had to find somebody who went somewhere
to South America to live in the jungle and we failed.
So we couldn't relicense.
When using third party code, check the license early.
If you want to have the possibility to go commercial
or use a permissive license, avoid GPL or be careful
when you introduce it.
Think about license compatibility.
Don't get different code which then doesn't work together.
And for the love of God, use a standard OS license.
I can understand quickly and I don't want to read your license
because, yeah, it's not fun.
And make your code usable for others, make it clean,
make it understandable, documented,
given instructions, all of this,
so others don't get frustrated by using it.
And while all of this makes,
sound publishing something as open source software
perhaps a little bit scary and a lot of effort,
it doesn't get better when you do it in a proprietary license
because you have to do all the same things.
But you have to think about your own license
and that nobody else is going with your stuff
and how you give support and stuff like this
because then people expect a little bit more.
So it's all of this and more work.
And with this, I'm on the end.
Thank you very much.
And if you have, perhaps you have some time
for questions, I...
We got five minutes for questions.
Yes.
Dr. Totsit.
Oh, thank you.
So I have one question about public domain licensing
and then one about dual licensing.
So I read an article at some point a while ago
that said that public domain sounds
like the most liberal thing,
but it's not,
it's just a part of the world.
And I was wondering if that's the same in all other places.
Exactly, public domain,
so perhaps, because the mic was a bit off,
I'll repeat really quick, public domain,
if it's really the most freedom thing
or it's not really acknowledged everywhere
and that's exactly the problem in Germany, for example,
it doesn't work because you have the ,
which means, so public domains means
you give away all your rights.
So you say here, this is the community,
I don't have anything to do.
You kind of cut yourself off of it.
In Germany, that doesn't work
because you have the Urheberrecht.
You always have the ownership.
You can't do this.
So legally, in the US, this works.
In Germany, not.
So you could say it's not valuable.
So it's kind of no license.
But before, if you talk with a lawyer
or a judge or whatever, they would say
it shows that the intention was given
that it's public domain, that you can do whatever.
So if somebody then would say,
so you use public domain in Germany or whatever.
And so then the owner comes and says,
oh, I still have the ownership in Germany,
so I can sue you because you used it in a way.
And because public domain is not
a legal construct in Germany,
the lawyer, the judge might perhaps say,
yeah, but you really made clear your intention.
So it's a bit tricky.
Also, for example, with public domain,
you don't have to state that it's public domain
or something because you don't have
to give any contribution.
I always, if I use public domain,
write in that it's public domain and where I got it,
so I'm still giving contribution
because I want to make it visible
for others that I took care of that.
So I think you can use it.
Because, yeah, normally in the end,
legally it's not really clean, but it should work out.
And now I forgot your second question.
Oh, dual licenses.
So dual licensing is normally something you do,
like you use one copyleft license
and you use a commercial, that's the normal combination.
This means, for example, you put something under GPL
and somebody can, so everybody can use it
who's happy with using GPL,
but if you want to put it in your commercial project,
you have to go and pay.
So that's the idea behind it.
So you pay then for a commercial license
and this is allowed to do because the owner can decide that,
like, this version, I don't know, I don't know, I don't know,
I don't know.
So I can take this version I built like this executable
because I have all the rights.
If I have all the rights, I can say, this is GPL
and I can take this other one and say,
this is a commercial one.
I can do this.
They are like two entities.
Yeah, so as an owner, I can do this.
I don't recommend it really a lot,
but it's done by some companies to get,
yeah, like a big community to use it
and perhaps even give code back and improve it and stuff
and on the other hand, still do a commercialization.
a question or oh okay yeah this exists to like several the audience so for
example if you have GPL and BSD and MIT simply to just say I don't really know
what the sum of this is I just want to make it the most easy for everyone to
adapt on their terms is that an option and is that possibly like what you're
aiming for with the public domain but more digestible for anyone who cares
about licenses yes so there's some licenses who do stuff like this so
there's like GPL 3 and newer or whatever so you have all this family you don't
have to relicense but there's also some who you can say oh this is MIT and BSD
or whatever to give people the prob as a possibility to not run into license
compatibility issues so this exists people do is this then it's really
important that you
state in your project when you use it under which license you're using it
because for the next user and stuff can this can be relevant this is done by
some people but it get can get complicated regarding third-party you
use and also because of the staff which is sometimes written in the licenses so
it depends some you can combine really well some you can't because some say you
have to do this and that and yeah so it's a bit
it depends because they have what's the licenses say some you can combine and
you can do this as it your licensing or parallel licensing with others you can't
but it means a lot of effort because for all of those you have to have a special
like then CI build or something which provides for example the license tag in
each file and normally you should have in git or something a lot of this
licenses say you have to have it in the file already not just when you create
the executable
you would have to have yeah your own license which include all these possibilities or whatever and so
it gets complicated really quickly again because yeah you have to have one copy of your code you
would say with different license tags for every separate license that's why not a lot of people
do it because it's a lot of effort to stay all of this in sync one quick last question yeah do you
know any sanity check in either gitlab or github that will verify if you're using gpl when you're
trying to do mit so if you track something as mit and you have everything including libraries that
is gpl would is there anything in either gitlab or github that will warn you you're doing something
that's not compatible or is there an open source project that will check your open source project
so um there's tools which check this and
i
open source the really good ones so there's one open source which is okay it's the really good
ones which will do all those legal things they will check and they will create the lists and
everything they cost around six figures so the good tools are really expensive because
this is a lot of effort and there's a lot of manual effort behind it um so not really
there's some tools who will at least check like who are all the licenses you have
um other fights which don't have a license header so you have to check for that
why can't somebody verify for that and this is the list of licenses you have in there and you
can have a first glance over it and they will try to give you some info and warnings and stuff but
it's not that they do everything for you um i forgot to be honest which the name was from the
one open source tool it looks like really from the 90s or something i can look it up um if you if you
find me later what the name was and yeah part of it no in gitlab github there's nothing yet really
would be great.
Thank you very much.