Yes, so welcome to today's lightning talk.
We are going to start with a talk about cactus comment.
So you have five minutes. Go ahead.
Thank you.
Uh-huh. Does this work? Good.
Okay. So this is not cactus comments.
This is a traditional comment system.
You have a bunch of users that all use the same client
to access comments that are only hosted in one place.
This is what it looks like in Matrix.
You have users that can use different clients
to interact with different servers
and still have the same conversation.
So you have sort of the email reminiscent structure
of having IDs on different servers,
but they can still be in a room that's shared between servers.
So cactus comments is just a Matrix client.
It runs in the browser. It's written in Elm.
And you have a login button.
And in that login button, you can put in the login field,
you can put in the URL of your own home server,
and then you just connect to your own server.
So the browser, from that point on,
doesn't need to talk to anything that's hosted by the website owner.
You just log in through your own Matrix server.
There's also another component that runs on the server side,
which is Matrix application service.
This part isn't strictly necessary
to actually use cactus comments,
but it adds some nice quality-of-life features.
So this means that you don't...
you don't have to manually go and create rooms.
The application service can do that for you.
And it also does some nice moderation stuff.
If you make somebody an admin in one room,
they will have admin privileges in the other rooms.
Yeah, and it's all a chatbot interface,
so you talk to and configure the application service through Matrix.
So why did we build this?
Why would we want to have comments on Matrix?
Does it give us any advantages,
or is it just more complexity?
This could probably be five slides,
but it's one slide.
One reason is identity defragmentation.
Right now, in order to comment on blogA.com,
you have one identity there,
and then in order to comment on blogB.com,
you have a different identity there.
In Matrix, we can sort of unify that,
and have the same identity across different platforms.
We have more comedian follow ups.
I can install the Element app on my phone,
and I'll get notifications
when somebody puts a comment on my blog post.
That's really nice.
There's a resilience point.
If the conversation can outlast
the infrastructure of the website
that the comment section is on.
that the infrastructure of the website
the website that uses cactus comments and maybe by default people can log in
you on my matrix server and then two wonderful nerds meet and have a
conversation there and then I kill my blog someday as long as those two
different nerds are on two different matrix home servers the comment section
still exists so the conversation can outlive the website infrastructure which is
really cool it's resistant to third-party censorship because you can
run your own matrix server so you don't have to do the Facebook comments or
Disqus thing of relying on a big company that could go and remove your
stuff and then you have more interaction options maybe some people would like to
keep a conversation going in the comments or get notifications but don't
want to log into the web browser and get the thing you can choose which clients
you're participating in the conversation from so there's many different clients
and you choose the one that works for you if you're a terminal geek you boot up
WeChat if you like simple clients you boot up
PluffyChat if you like simple clients you boot up PluffyChat if you like
Or you can use element.
Cool. That's Cactus comments.
What now? How do you participate?
We have a room on matrix.
It's cactus colon cactus dot chat.
We are on GitLab.
It's all open source.
It's GPL licensed.
Going to be moving to LGPL soon.
That's a different thing.
But go and contribute or have a look at the code if you want.
We have a website which has documentation and how to use it.
Should be pretty straightforward.
And then, of course, come catch me if you want to talk about it.
I'll be in the bar or I'll be down in Noisy.
And we have stickers.
All right. That's it.