Tijana Mihajlović Reviewer Reviewer's Name
Well, thank you very much.
So, this is the title of my book,
and you are going to be the test audience for the synopsis of my book.
So, what I've done now is I've taken the subjects in the order
I'm going to talk about them and put them into a slide.
I'm not going to read you the entire book,
but I'm going to tell you the story in a lecture form,
so in a shorter way.
And I would really much like for you afterwards to tell me
if this order is good for the book or if you think I should change anything.
But you will also be getting a really nice story,
so I hope you enjoy it.
So, first of all, this machine is arguably
the first serial series-produced Danish microcomputer,
but the predecessor to it, the Pearl Stripe,
is undoubtedly the first Danish microcomputer ever.
So, there was a bit about who did what first,
and if you announce the computer before you produce it,
who wins and stuff like that.
So, I choose to call this the first Danish microcomputer,
and I have like 50 kilos of arguments for that back in my office
because I have collected a lot of material.
This is most likely the...
most well-prepared talk you'll hear this year.
I have been studying for this for almost four years.
So, and when I started researching about this computer,
I was expecting it to be an article, a really short thing,
maybe a Wikipedia thing.
And then I started digging, and suddenly it all blew up in my head,
and I was taken back to 1972
where this Danish dude by the name Boe,
I'm so sorry.
He died before we could take a good picture of him.
But Boe Rosgaard Christensen, nice last name,
was an associate professor in Tønder College of Education.
That is a Danish school where they train teachers
for like the rest of the country.
It's not the only of its kind, but it's one of them.
He was an eager and insisting advocate
for proper computer science.
Proper computer science teaching in Denmark.
So he's famous for saying that basics should be illegal.
And he was an extremely productive author.
I have 12 books by his name,
and that's only the 12 I succeeded to get my hands on.
Yeah, and then he was a language geek.
I don't know if you know about the language Interlingua.
You most likely know about Esperanto.
Interlingua is...
Don't quote me on this, but...
More or less the same.
So they're trying to make an international language
without any exceptions.
So if you know the grammar rules,
those will always apply.
And he spent 20 years of his life as a board member
for the committee developing this language.
So it's safe to say that A, that dude likes rules,
and B, that dude likes languages.
So that's a bit about him.
Back in 72, no, 71,
his institution got a data general computer
called Nova 1200.
This was a machine sold by Reines & Thalen
under a different name,
but in essence, this was a data general machine.
He started teaching on it,
and he started teaching his students BASIC.
And if any of you know how to program BASIC,
you know that it's fine,
as long as all the languages,
as long as all the lines of code can be on the screen.
As soon as you reach line number 25,
it starts becoming chaos.
So he complained a lot about this,
and around the spring of 72,
he met this computer scientist in Aarhus
called Benedikt Lyfstedt,
and together with him,
they started formulating this new language,
which should be a combination of Pascal and BASIC.
And this Bero dude is very talkative
and very convincing,
and has like the energy of a nuclear bomb.
So I'm sure he just overwhelmed Reines & Thalen
with good intentions and with questions
and with interest,
because sometime during the first half of 1972,
they actually gave him the source code for the BASIC
they used on their systems.
He hired some student workers
and got those student workers
to change this BASIC into a COMAL.
So one of the main differences is that
COMAL in COMAL GoTo is like prohibited.
It's not, but in essence,
you shouldn't use it.
So you have function calls and procedure calls,
and it's a more structured language.
So they turned this old BASIC
into a more structured BASIC,
and in the beginning,
they actually called it RCE BASIC,
Reines & Thalen BASIC,
but soon they changed the name to COMAL,
which is short for COMAL.
I should have written this down.
Common...
Did I write...?
Yeah, of course I did write that.
Common Algorithmic Language.
I did write it down.
Thank you.
And then he used his position
as a teacher-teacher.
So he teaches the teachers
to influence the teachers
that they should use COMAL,
which is super awesome,
because during the last part of the 70s,
suddenly it became
a standard demand from schools.
Oh, by the way,
your computer doesn't run COMAL.
We don't want it.
But it's better and cheaper.
It doesn't run COMAL.
So he kind of forced everybody
to implement COMAL
in order to get
systems to the Danish schools.
We got a story from the head
of the data department
on Odense College of Education
where he called the guy,
the 26th of December,
and said,
oh, can I come by?
I need to show you something.
Ah, we're really busy.
We have this family thing, you know.
Okay, tomorrow then?
So during the Christmas holiday,
he influenced his colleague
at the next over college of education
to start using COMAL as well,
and he succeeded in just one day.
He gave some guest lectures
in Germany, West Germany,
and he got it spread
to most of Europe
just by being really energetic
and talking about it.
And down the road,
he actually managed to sell
this idea to Commodore.
And during the 80s,
Commodore made a version,
the best ever,
and they sold it in the entire world.
And actually, it has been taught
that the biggest user group
of COMAL in general is American.
And we have like 2,400 pages
of their user magazine,
which is a huge source of information.
And finally, he used
the university center
of Southern Jutland
to fund lots of his work.
So this is not a real university.
It was like,
so in Southern Jutland,
they asked the government
for a university,
and during,
I don't remember it exactly,
but around 1773,
the government said,
yes, you can have a university
in two years.
So the local municipality said,
cool, we'll just get started,
and they funded the startup
of it themselves.
And after two years,
the government was just like,
nah, we're good.
And so they just kept
funding it themselves.
So it's not a real university,
but for all practical purposes,
it is.
They had some money,
which they could use
for research,
and Berg Christensen
got paid some money
to develop Comal.
And later on,
he got this crazy idea
that I'll talk more about
in a little bit,
because we need to travel
back in time again.
Now we're back in 1777,
where this dude
called Mons Pele,
he finished his degree
of Electrical Engineering
in 1773,
and has been writing
technical instructions,
you know,
build guides for,
back then when you were a geek,
you didn't have the internet,
so you bought these things
out of paper
called magazines,
and there was basically
a large block,
and he wrote guides
on to build different stuff
for this block.
Well, mostly he read guides
from international magazines,
translated them to Danish,
and republished them.
And that is so many years ago
that it's probably not,
I don't know,
it's probably still illegal,
but it was a bit sketchy.
Anyway,
that was what he did,
and he used this platform
to,
when he got access
to a Zilog Z80 processor,
as one of the first in Denmark,
he used the platform
from this magazine
to start publishing schematics
for a computer that he designed,
and started a movement
of data machine amateurs,
he called them.
They were in several
global Danish medias,
and he got really a lot
of press on that,
so he founded a company
down here,
Metanic APS,
and started selling PCBs,
and in the beginning
he only wanted to sell PCBs,
but then suddenly a guy
from this Southern University Center
wrote him and said,
I read your article
about that computer,
I want to buy one.
And he was just like,
we don't sell them,
but I want to buy one,
you can build one.
I don't want to buy one,
I want to buy one.
So he built one,
and sold to that guy,
and that guy was
Bero Christensen.
So that escalated,
but yeah,
before we get to that,
I just want to mention,
the users that started
building this machine
also founded the user group,
and they actually produced
the NPS 2000 user group magazine
for about a year,
which is also one of the great
sources we have for these stories.
And I might,
I might have forgot to mention
in the beginning,
but all this information
is something I have dug out
from either interviews,
or old magazines,
or like,
there's no history book about this,
this is what I'm writing.
So I have been through
old archives,
through old reading,
30 year old newspapers,
and accountings,
and it's been a really like
investigative journalism
with 40 years of delay.
Anyway,
let's go to the
Southern University Center.
So in 72,
they decided that
we need some of this,
in Danish we said
EDB,
which stands for
Electronical Data
Behandling,
Processing,
which is,
you can translate it today
with IT,
information technology,
but they founded
the EDB Council,
and the idea with the EDB Council
was that they should build
a data center in Esbjerg,
which is one of the most,
so well,
if you leave towards Jutland now
and just keep driving west,
you'll end up in Esbjerg,
that's one of the most,
I don't know if they still do fishing,
but it's a big harbor city,
and the,
well,
they were promised
that by 75,
they would get funding
for both the university
and for the data center,
and as you might already have spotted,
there was a lot of money
spread ahead,
that was denied,
so this is transformed
into a general coordination council,
which would coordinate
the educational institutions
in the municipality,
and help them avoid wasting money
on this computer stuff,
and then in 77,
Mons Pelle discovered,
no,
Berg Christensen discovered Mons Pelle,
and bought this computer from him,
and then the Southern University Center
more or less took over the project,
so if you read Børsen,
Børsen is a Danish newspaper
for business interested people,
or Jyllands Posten,
which is,
yeah,
all the major newspapers,
they talked about this machine,
and they called it the SUC computer,
and it was called the people's computer,
because it was built to be cheap,
and was built,
you could freely build it yourself,
and the idea was that you wanted
to provide ordinary people,
with computers,
which is something,
yeah,
well,
that was an idea
that got very popular
like 10,
15 years later,
mainly by,
pushed by a guy named Bill Gates,
so they were a bit ahead,
but,
yeah,
so the idea was that
the SUC funded this prototype,
which Berg Christensen
then bought from Mons Pelle,
and then he was like,
I need some software for it,
so he also got some money
to develop some software,
and if you read in 1979,
when this machine was about
to be published,
everybody said that this was supposed
to be sold under the name
of SUC Data Maiden,
it didn't happen like that,
but,
and then,
and I'm going to jump a bit again,
because I need some more,
what do you call that,
prehistory,
what's that,
history,
background history,
so,
I mentioned that this
thing got that popular,
that school just said,
we need this,
and then,
like,
one and a half month ago,
a dude in Jutland died,
and one of his friends called me,
because he knew that I might be interested
in some of his old computers,
I'm really sad he didn't call me
half a year ago before he died,
but,
yeah,
you can't win every time,
however,
I worked in
Ribe County,
or Ribe Amt,
department for purchasing
educational materials,
and in,
so,
back in 78,
they founded this committee,
and said,
Ribe Amt needs to buy some computers
for education,
so they requested
which is the Danish version of ICL,
and they requested ICL,
which is the British version of Reinecentral,
Data General,
and some other large manufacturers,
and also they visited some of them,
so they flew to Copenhagen,
and to Great Britain,
and saw some of these machines
in use,
and at this point,
we were talking about,
yeah,
so the committee said,
we want Kummel,
and we want microcomputers.
Do I need to tell you?
Probably I do,
so back in the,
back before the PCs,
when we talked about computers,
a computer would typically be a system
that would require its own building,
and a minicomputer would be a computer
that you could fit inside
one or two small closets,
and a microcomputer would be something like,
like this,
that you could have,
okay,
this one,
that you could have on your own disk,
so this was a microcomputer.
What you would probably call a computer back then,
we would most likely call that a data center,
because that is,
that is five or six,
at least five or six racks of equipment,
and readers,
and really,
really huge,
and we,
some of the offers they got were for one and a half million
crores,
divided by seven for euros.
Yeah,
so said,
well,
we hear you,
you want Kummel,
you want to buy a computer,
well,
you can have a mainframe.
ECL was like,
well,
Kummel,
no,
we have this obscure thing we made ourselves
that nobody likes,
and a mainframe.
So,
I say,
said,
oh,
well,
by the way,
we found this guy called Mons Pelle and Bero Christensen,
and they have built this computer,
and now we are selling that for them.
They said that in the,
in the fall of 1979,
and only two weeks later,
Reiner Strahlen went back and said,
no,
we don't want to sell that anyway,
but we are going to build our own microcomputer,
which will cost the same as a mainframe,
but can only be used by one person.
That was a really good offer.
Surprisingly,
surprisingly,
like 14 days,
no,
actually,
I got the two messages from so-called Telex,
which was the email of the day,
and,
and there are hours in difference from when,
when they received the message from Reiner Strahlen
and the message from ICL.
So it was,
either it was the same day or the day after.
So very,
very close.
ICL comes back and say,
now we sell the computer that Mons Pelle and,
and Bero Christensen is selling.
So that,
that's a bit back and forth,
but all in all,
it ended up that ICL would be the computer,
be the manufacturing company who sold this machine.
So we started with this company called,
called Metanic.
And if you,
it's right here.
And if you notice,
it's probably now I need to mention that Bero Christensen is not on this picture.
Bero Christensen really did not want to be a part of the public story because he was just like this,
a bit of a hippie type and a commercial,
commercial companies were a bit yucky.
And actually Bersen wrote that Bero Christensen was part of that.
And I think one or two days later,
there was a message in Bersen saying,
oh,
we didn't mean that.
It was a mistake.
And I mean,
they don't do that by themselves.
Some,
somebody called them and yelled at them for saying it.
So,
so I'm sure he was very eager by not getting commercially associated with this project
because he wanted to use his contacts in academia without him being accused of wanting to make a buck on it.
That's my theory.
I can't prove it because the guy is dead,
but I have,
I have a lot of,
uh,
indicia for that.
What is that called?
So,
you know,
not circumstantial evidence that points to that.
Yeah.
Okay.
So,
um,
I put Reinenstrahlen in there because,
yeah,
a lot of people mistake this and thinks that Reinenstrahlen made this computer and that is wrong,
but it could have been true.
And that's fun.
That's a fun,
uh,
fun fact,
I think.
So,
um,
in Horsens,
and I'm probably going to make a whole chapter about this in the book alone.
In Horsens,
back in the,
um,
in the 70s,
there was this huge television factory.
Actually,
it started out like a bicycle factory.
They also did chemicals and lots of other stuff,
but they had a department for building televisions and radios,
which burned down in the late 60s,
like,
69,
I think,
70,
around there.
All these details will,
of course,
be in the book,
by the books.
There's a link in the,
in the bottom of the screen slides.
Um,
and,
um,
a Dutch or British,
uh,
company,
a,
a trans-European company,
uh,
decided to,
to,
to enter this,
um,
this,
factory and fund the rebuilding of it.
And,
um,
they went bankrupt in 1975.
Uh,
and then they had like,
I think,
400 workers,
uh,
in this,
um,
part of the company.
And they were just like,
well,
if this international company can do this,
sure,
we can do it ourselves.
So,
uh,
the,
the estate,
can you say that about a company?
I'm not sure.
Um,
anyway,
so,
so they took over the company.
This was a huge story.
They got the municipality to pay some of it.
Uh,
uh,
lot of it.
They made,
uh,
like stocks you could sell to,
or,
it's called the people stocks,
.
So,
so it was a huge deal,
uh,
with publicity and,
and,
the,
uh,
most people who released a few hundred shares by the time,
bought,
uh,
the majority of the shares in the company,
and kept it afloat for,
uh,
until,
1979.
Um,
but,
the,
the vibe of the people's television factory was still there,
and they tried to use that to market the computer as the people's computer.
But,
it didn't go,
3F went,
uh,
bankrupt.
And they went bankrupt,
like months before they had promised to deliver these machines.
Um,
and there are a couple of machines which had,
uh,
a couple of machines that were built at this point, but we don't know who built them.
I have talked to Mons Pele and he doesn't remember what he had for breakfast last day.
So that's, by the way, that's his own words, I'm not mugging him anyway.
He really has a bad memory.
So we're trying to jolt his memory by showing him, yeah, everything I come up with I send
to him and he says, oh, yeah, I remember that.
And then slowly we get the memories back from him.
But he doesn't recall where these machines were built.
The best I got from him was like that, oh, yeah, I might have built them myself.
Which is possible because we are talking about somewhere between 30 and 50 machines.
You can build that in a couple of months, maybe hire a couple of young ones to help
you.
So we have another example of a young guy who built 400 machines with his wife at the
kitchen table and sold them to institutions in all of Finland.
So it has happened before, so it could have happened.
So they shipped these machines off to another factory they found in northern Zeeland, which
started the production.
And that ended up being what was called the ICL, Comet MPS 2000.
And just to put Komal back in there, then the same company who built the machine actually
started developing the first version of Komal for the Z80-based machines.
So we still have Komal tagging in here.
And Metanic was designed.
He was designing the hardware but not building it.
But he was also designing the software.
So this Mons Pelle dude was trying to be the intellectual master without having to do the
actual work, which in theory was a good idea, only in theory.
So the machine, we think there were made about 200 of them, running with a Zilac Z80 CPU of
1 megahertz and 4 kilobytes of memory.
And they used a tape.
Do you remember?
Do you remember these small tapes from we used in the 90s for voice answering machines?
Or for those, you know, the doctor would speak into a thing to make notes, the dictaphone?
Do you remember those?
They used those for data.
They could cram 128 kilobytes of data into one of these machines.
Impressive.
And they lived happily ever after.
Of course they didn't.
Because this is IT.
You have to have people not lagging each other.
So I'm going to talk a bit about HH Electronic, which was the company who took over the production
of the machines.
This company was founded in 1976.
And it didn't stop in 1980, but that's where I'm stopping for this chapter.
So the company was founded by a young engineer.
Actually they sprung out of a company who made gas engines.
And this was the first company to do that.
And he was like, can you buy gas systems?
So, like, regulators and stuff like that.
And the boss of that company asked him to say, can you buy, can you, now, sorry, can
you develop a process control system for us?
And he was just like, yeah, I can do that.
So he also got his hand on a Z80 processor and built a Z80 based process control platform.
And in 1978, he announced in Børsen, again, the same magazine as we talked about before,
that he had developed a version of BASIC, which were more structured than BASIC, and
called it HH BASIC.
And news like that, you can publish that in a local, in a global, what is it called?
In a countrywide Danish paper without Børs Kristensen noticing.
So in 1978, Børs Kristensen called AHS Electronic and got to talk with them about their BASIC.
So that was how the connection was made.
Oh, and I'm sorry.
Sorry.
Actually, it was in 1979.
It says here.
So probably right.
Yeah.
So this machine wasn't really usable, mainly because it took 20 minutes to load the tape
with 128 kilobytes of memory, of program.
So imagine you're having a class, and you need to teach them COMAL.
And you've got four machines.
And each machine, there are four students around each machine.
And they start at 8 o'clock.
And they start with loading the tape, and they wait 20 minutes.
And then two of the machines breaks down and needs to be restarted.
So now the class is over.
That wasn't...
Yeah, they didn't like that.
So Jørgen Høgh went to ICL and said, you know what?
I like this idea with these computers, but I don't like this most .
So either I'm leaving, and you can keep your system, or we are going to make a new computer,
and you can keep your system, and you can keep your system, and you can keep your system,
or we are going to make a new computer.
And we are going to make a new computer based on our process control system, and is leaving.
And ICL had, at this point, been fighting for almost two years to find a factory that
could produce these machines.
So ICL was just like, well, are we going with the guy who had all these crazy ideas and
couldn't put them into life?
Or with this guy who actually put these crazy ideas into reality, but now want to scale
a little bit back?
So they, of course, went with HH-Electronic.
And they developed the MPS3000.
And the MPS2000 was dropped, or phased out slowly.
A funny story about this was that nobody remembered to tell Mons Pelle that.
So he didn't know until around 1980, the spring 1980, when he went to this factory and wanted
to pick up his check.
So how many computers have you made?
And can I please have my check?
And he was just like, we didn't make it.
And he was like, we didn't make it.
Any computers, you can't have any check.
We are doing it ourselves now.
So that's not a good way to...
Well, it could have been done smarter.
More about that during the next slide.
We made this machine, and this is what most of...
Ah, okay.
Most Danish guys in my dad's age
would probably have seen in the school.
That would be this orange case
made out of 1.5 millimeter steel plate.
And, well, today you would probably not be allowed
to move this by the government
because health and safety risks.
It's really, really heavy.
And its power supply is...
Yeah, well, you don't touch the cabinet on the back
when it's turned on.
You'll burn because it's...
Really, really, really hot.
Anyway, the machines became very popular,
and overall, they were produced
about 3,000 units of these machines.
Nothing much to say about that.
It's...
Yeah, it was a new beginning.
But Mons Pelle was just like,
no, hell no, I don't want to be part of this,
and they're not going to screw me over.
So he made a new computer.
He made the MPS 2001.
So now you see what's happening
is we have this first computer,
and now it's...
It's a new computer.
It's forking out into two different machines.
Which one is the following?
Which one is number two, if any?
If you take this machine apart,
on the motherboard, you will actually see
it's called MPS 2001.
However, that's the only place you will see that
because he partnered up with a bunch of young salesmen
from the mid-Utlands,
and those guys could sell.
So he built this machine.
Don't know where, don't know how.
As he said,
I might have done it myself.
I really would like to have interviewed this guy
for 20 years ago, but...
So, and this machine was built during the same time,
and if you look at the specs,
this is a hell of a lot of a faster machine.
It's four times faster.
I know four megahertz doesn't have much today,
but if you're used to one megahertz,
this is four times as much.
And if you're used to a system with 48 kilobytes of memory,
this one goes up to 128 kilobytes of memory.
The ROM is not included in that.
We have ROM,
and on top of that it's all built into one machine
that would be eight more years
until ICL would catch up to this.
So he got it right the second time at least.
So I'm probably going to go into a bit
about Bokeh Datasystemer.
That means Bokeh doesn't mean anything, data systems.
That was the young guys who sold it,
and that's a story as well,
but I'm not going to get into that yet
because I collected a lot of materials about it,
but I haven't read it yet.
I'm not kidding.
I have an entire shelf,
one entire IKEA shelf filled with binders and books
and photocopies and hardware.
Actually, I have a room full of hardware,
but I have a lot of material,
and I haven't gone through it all yet.
Anyway, this machine was being traded,
and it was being sold for the next eight years,
more or less without modifications,
and it could keep up with ICL,
which at this point in time was like this huge international,
it was the IBM of Europe.
ICL had to improve, so HH Electronics and ICL
kept on developing.
As you see now, they got up to four megahertz as well
and 64 kilobytes of memory.
They also managed to put in up to one megabyte of memory
in this machine.
If you were very rich, one application,
one computer, one computer, one computer, one computer,
you could get up to one gigabyte of memory
in the same machine.
So the reason of this was that it was used for drawing,
for CAD diagrams, and you could add up to one megabyte
of memory into it, and they had a requirement
that it should be able to contain the entire drawings
of the Concorde plane, and that took up one megabyte
of memory, and I think it was about 120,000 Danish krones
for that megabyte of memory.
That was insane, and by the way, my dad did that software,
so he had memory for 120,000 krones in his computer.
I don't know if we had an insurance for that, but yeah.
That was when I connected with these computers
because when I was like, like, like, yay big,
my dad worked on one of these machines.
And it has intrigued me ever since.
I never really get to play with it until I got, like, what's older?
Well, that's not true.
When I was yay big, I get to like,
eh, I'm working on the computer
because this keyboard was made of, again, sheet metal.
Well, if something would break by me using that,
it would be me breaking.
The computer would not.
That was for sure.
This machine, line-of-machine, supported hard drives
as one of the first in this series.
So this was more or less the final iteration of the ICL Comet,
at least in the early years.
That's not the final, but anyway, for now it's the final.
But ATS Electronics, they wanted to develop this further
and they realized that 8-bit computers and CPM
was probably not going to outlive, yeah,
it was obvious that it would be,
that the market would be troubled over by, among else, IBM.
So they wanted to try to be better than the IBM.
So they started developing something that I liked really much.
They started developing a Unix computer.
Now we are back home again.
We like it.
We like Unix machines.
So this was a 14 megahertz computer,
with 2 megabytes of memory and 12 megabytes of hard drive,
which ran a full Unix system.
Can you run anything on 12 megabytes today?
Maybe even the Arduino development suite is larger than that.
And this is actually about the same weight
and this is actually about the same weight
the other computers, but there are more stuff in them.
This was developed in unison with a Swedish company,
which I'm still investigating, and I have a contact.
I'm speaking with a few of the workers from over there,
but I really don't have anything yet.
But I suspect there's an entire chapter about this machine as well,
and I have one of these machines.
By the way, almost all the pictures I've taken myself,
and I have, except for the Comet 2000,
I actually have, either I or the Dressing Museum have all the machines.
This was sold to commerce schools.
I don't know what they used them for.
I'd still like to find that out,
but I actually think there's an entire book in this machine alone
when I start digging through it.
So I don't know what will show up, if anything.
But the Butler machine, when he started selling that in 1981,
it was actually already prepared to do multi-user setups.
So you would have one large machine with a floppy drive,
and you would have five or six terminals
that would all use the same printer and the same floppy drive.
So it only took five years for ICL to catch up with that.
So this machine contains a processor and some memory,
and it wasn't a dump terminal.
It was a semi-intelligent terminal
because it used the hard drive from the central computer,
but it did all its calculations by itself.
So I could load my program into memory,
and I could work on it all day
without having to wait for the master computer,
and I would have my own resources.
That was a pretty clever move.
I haven't looked into the pricing yet,
but this was significantly cheaper,
both because it only had four...
These machines were built on something we call Eurocards,
which is a print on that size,
which has a standard connector,
and you have a row of circuits you can just slide them into,
and all the connectors are just connected parallel
the entire way through.
So you can put anything into that you want.
And that's a good system
because you can get these prints and the racks,
ready-made,
and that's cheaper than building large prints.
And this machine was actually pretty easy for them to develop
because you just take the memory card, the CPU card,
and then build a card for the remote storage,
and then you could start producing these machines.
So this was a cheap research and development process,
and they now could sell more users per machine,
and...
the schools could pay less for more workstations,
which would be...
Yeah, which is a good argument
when your competitors are selling machines for 150,000 drones
that can be used by one person.
Finally, we get to the ICL Combat MPS 8.
So this is when ICL caught fully up to the Butler machine.
This machine is more or less the same.
Everything is built on one board, like on the Butler,
and it has this memory switching,
and then it had a pretty nice thing.
It used a 1.45 megabyte floppy drive.
I don't know if you know anything about CPM,
but 1.44 megabyte of CPM software.
You can almost have every conceivable piece of software
made for a CPM machine on one floppy,
and that one floppy is like eight times faster
than anything else this machine had ever seen.
So this was a huge markup,
and a huge improvement.
The machine also went from costing 30,000 drones a piece
to 5,000 drones a piece.
So this was really, really, really efficient,
but also you can repair it.
I got one which is broken
because the keyboard's LED has broken off,
and you can repair it
because the keyboard has been press-fitted
and melded together.
So, yeah.
So this was the...
I made a video about this.
This was the last Danish 8-bit computer,
and when I made it,
I made the video.
It worked.
You can see that on the picture.
It's full of tensile capacitors,
so it's not working anymore,
but we had it working for just a short while,
and I'm, of course, going to fix it.
But HHS Electronics had realized
that this PC thing will take over the market,
so they actually stopped developing the machines themselves
and was like,
again, I'm going to...
Yeah, they stopped the development
and the sales process themselves
and started making PCs.
Oh, well, they tried.
So they wanted to use Danish as an argument for buying PCs,
and they made an expensive design cabinet
and built the boards in Denmark
and built everything in Denmark
and tried to say,
this is so much better quality,
but it wasn't because...
Yeah, maybe the Chinese factory does it twice as bad,
but they can make four in the time you make one,
so, yeah, I think I talked to the guy.
I think he made 20 of them,
so it wasn't really a thing.
This is more or less the story.
I'm going to finish off with a chapter
where I'm going to quickly run through what happens.
The IBM PC was launched in 1981,
so more or less from the beginning,
they knew this was going to be over
because IBM has already entered the market.
In 1985, Mons Pelle bought the company
which sold his machines.
Bero Christensen died way, way too early in 1989.
1988, HHS Electronics just were like,
we don't want to do this shit anymore
and started making...
And hold on, you can't make this shit up.
Bike lights.
They patented the first ever LED-based bike light
and made a huge fuss about it,
and when people asked them,
oh, but that's the back light,
can we have the front light?
And they said, no, we don't have white LEDs yet.
They are not invented yet.
So they sold back lights,
but actually they sold the patent
to one of Europe's largest producers of bike lights,
Basta, I think they call.
So it's more or less being...
Used today, still.
And then they started selling equipment for ships
and in 1989, they bought a plane.
So somehow they made money.
Unicomal, which was the last...
Oh, no, ICL bought Reinecentralen.
And Unicomal, which was the last company
who actually produced Comal,
closed down in 1993.
2002, Fujitsu acquired ICL.
And 2019,
the last known production software
written in BASIC was taken out of commission.
That was the chimney sweeper
in a small town in Jutland
who made his own software in Comal
that would take care of his business,
which customers am I to visit now
and who am I going to bill and all that.
He wrote that himself and used that until 2019.
I think that's so awesome.
Same year, Mike decided to write a book.
Time for questions.
Thank you very much
for this very interesting history talk.
Are there questions?
So, hello, hello.
So, this Comal language was designed
or inspired by Pascal.
Why not go with...
Just Pascal instead of BASIC?
So, the reason why they didn't do that
was that Comal...
Have you tried working on a Commodore 64?
Okay.
When you have a Commodore 64
and nothing else,
you just turn it on
and you're in BASIC.
Bam.
You write 10
and you write space
and you write print hello world.
Press enter and type run.
Now you're a software developer.
More or less.
That is super easy to teach to students.
Let's try that in Pascal.
Okay.
Now you need to start the computer
and insert a Floppy.
Enter that Floppy.
Start PolyPascal.
That's a keyboard combination
for going from command mode
into text, into insert mode.
Now you need to write use CRT.
Use something.
You need to use the library
in order to print out to the screen.
Then you have to write begin and end
and then write write line
and hello world.
Now you need to compile it.
Now you need to exit your IDE
and run that through the command line.
Which one of those would you prefer to teach
to ground school students?
That was the argument.
So they merged together,
Komal and Pascal,
and made an integrated development environment
and it got hugely popular.
There's probably going to be written books
about that in itself,
but not by me.
I have enough by this book,
I hope, I guess, I think.
Yeah.
So,
until more questions come up,
I can just,
I'm most likely going to publish this book myself.
So,
why is this not plugged in?
No, okay.
Apparently not important.
I'm most likely going to publish this book myself.
So,
if any one of you think this is interesting,
please go to my website
and pre-order.
And this is just a pre-order
because you're essentially just signing up
for a mailing list
and once I'm ready to sell the book,
I'm going to write out and say,
hey,
give me money
and I'll give you a book.
And if you don't want to give me money,
I'm not going to give you a book.
So, that's how it works.
But I hope to raise some money
so I can print some really nice books
with hardcover and golden letters
and make a really, really nice book.
I hope, I hope so.
It might just be a PDF, I don't know.
Let's see.
Any more questions?
Thank you so much for listening.
Oh, that was a question.
So, these machines,
they actually use Zilog Z80 processors,
but did that also mean
that they were compatible
with like abundance of software
from like,
from Sinclair and stuff
because there are lots of software back then
for bookkeeping
and it was really compelling
for people to actually buy one of those.
But did it ever got a chance
to run on these machines?
Can you repeat the last sentence?
Is it possible to run like,
like Z80 software
for the Sinclair on these machines?
So, yeah, it runs CPM.
So, every piece of CPM software
that's not dependent on special hardware
will work.
So, every, more or less,
every text-based piece of CPM software,
we had, we went to Berlin
to the Winter Festival,
Winter Community Festival Berlin in 2019
and displayed one of the machines
running Sork.
Sork is a famous text adventure game
which was classical CPM game
and that was,
that runs on the machines.
So, yes.
Which was, of course,
a really important point
because you could tell the schools
and you could just go
and buy almost any kind of software
except PC software
and that would run on it.
Which was, of course,
why it died later
because everything turned PC
during the 90s.
Well, maybe a short question from me.
On which hardware
was this last Komal software running?
On my laptop,
it's still running.
But, yeah, sure,
the software for TeamSweeper
you were talking about, right?
Actually, that was the correct answer
because I got that software from him
three months ago
and it's running on my laptop now.
But he built it on this,
actually, this machine,
the very first machine I showed you
belonged to one of his friends.
Come on, you can do it.
So, maybe I didn't tell you that,
but this was a machine
where you would buy it
as a kit.
So, the cabinet and the keyboard,
everything was something
the individual builder
chose by himself.
But this was a machine like that
ran the TeamSweeper software.
And then the TeamSweeper
upgraded to a machine like
that one?
No.
Come on, that one.
And had that for some years.
And then, actually,
the friend of the TeamSweeper,
the priest from the same town,
started writing software for ICL.
So, that will be part of the book as well.
And then he got the larger one
and then during, I think it was 87,
he said he bought a 386 PC
and split it to Unicomal
and kept running his software there.
And then just upgraded it.
And then he upgraded the computer
all the way until he had
something like a Core i,
something which is insanely huge
for a piece of software
that could be run on an 8-bit machine
with 64 kilobytes of memory.
I like the irony of that.
And the reason why he stopped using it
was he retired
and he couldn't get any more printers
that would work with a printer port.
So, they went USB.
So, yeah.
Okay.
Any further questions?
Otherwise,
let's thank the speaker again.
And...
Thank you for listening.
Pre-order my book.
With that, we finished our lectures
in the tent today.