Well, then I would like to welcome Joachim,
who is going to give us a talk about a dependently timed drum machine language.
I've been looking forward to this one very much.
Please give Joachim a hand.
Thank you.
Hi, everybody.
I'm Joachim, and I'm a musician, but I'm also a computer scientist.
And sometimes I like to combine the two,
and a programming language is a fun way to combine things.
And...
So that's what we're going to talk about today.
When you listen to an audio signal,
for instance, right now you are listening to an audio signal,
it comes out of the speaker,
and it's continuous in some sense.
But that's, of course, not the way you perceive it.
Likely you are identical,
and you are identifying some things.
Maybe you give them a name.
This guy here on the image has some audio coming into his ear,
and perhaps he perceives this first blue square as a hand clap.
Right?
Or a snare drum.
And likewise, when I'm producing a signal,
I am unlikely to think of the continuity of things.
Rather, I'm saying some words, and they have syllables,
and I can put them somewhere relative to each other in time.
There are various ways of describing how to put events relative to each other in time.
Here is a classic one, sheet music.
All right.
The first...
So let's say that I want to say programming drum patterns.
It's likely that I will say this during the talk.
Then I might use these eight notes here.
They have the same duration relative to each other.
So the sentence will be programming drum patterns.
Right?
But that's not so close to the way I was thinking it.
So...
So maybe I'll make the two latter syllables a little bit faster.
The note here with two bars is a sixteenth note, and it's twice as fast.
Programming drum patterns.
It doesn't sound that natural, but it has some effect.
To fix the amount of time I spend saying my sentence,
I vary the tempo by...
By putting a little indication here of how much time is consumed,
how many quarter notes is consumed per minute.
That's the beats per minute.
The latter one here is four against three against three.
Programming drum patterns.
Neither is close to what I was trying to do when I said programming drum patterns.
And it's actually...
Actually, it's really difficult to get it right with sheet music.
Nonetheless, drummers do put their rhythms in sheet music.
And here is an example.
I have written a program in a programming language called Badumtch
that I made some time ago.
And so here is the program.
The program for the rhythm on the top here is this program.
So let's hear it.
First, we'll need to compile it.
And in this prototype compiler,
type checking is a little bit slow, but that's alright.
In the meantime, we can inspect the type signature of the variable Beat.
As you can see here, the type of beat is 1616, because its duration is 1616th notes.
Now that we have compiled it, it will run a little bit faster, but I will run it again,
this time with the audio channel unmuted.
Alright, something is a little bit overdriven.
Alright, you got it.
And...
So, I mean...
It's a hip-hop beat, but it's not that hip.
It's like an 80s hit, alright?
So, but it's not uncommon to notate it like this nonetheless.
But a hip-hop musician might transform what he's reading a little bit,
and a classic transformation is this quintuplet shuffle.
When I say classic, I mean it was hip in the hip-hop scene some years ago,
like two years.
And after applying the transformation, two eight notes like this become...
Well, think of it like this.
You have two events that happen in time, and they are kind of a family.
The family of two rhythms is the family of things that happen with two durations relative to each other.
After this transformation, the first note is three-fifths, and the latter is only two-fifths.
And for the sake of readability, I have overbarred the quintuplet like this.
I hope you can read it.
Let's do it again.
Let's do it in bottom two.
So, what we're doing is we're adding a phrasing here,
and the first note is a three against two.
And I denote it by putting a list here with a three and a two.
We'll just compile the song again.
While we are compiling, we can inspect the type signature of the variable beat.
Uh-oh.
Let's just type check in Emacs again.
All right.
Let's do it again.
This is actually already much hipper, so I'll change the comment here and express that I'm happier with this.
So, I'll change the comment here.
And express that I'm happier with this.
I'll change it here.
I'll change the comment here.
And express that I'm happier with this.
happier with it with a smiley here. Alright, the type signature of Beat has become 8080
because now it's 8080th notes and we'll come back to why it changed its type like that.
Alright, for some time we've been developing a couple of tools for inputting rhythms into
computers like this and I want to put them into three categories. And the first category
I will call a Grid Editor. On the slide here is an illustration of the Beat plus Baseline
Grid Editor from Linux Multimedia Studio. There's a similar, maybe it's not called the
Beat plus Baseline Editor.
But it's the same thing in Cubase and Pro Tools and Ableton Live also has a drum machine
like this. And the way the program is structured is that it has three sequences, one for each
signal. The lowermost signal here is a bass drum, then there's a snare drum signal and
a hi-hat signal. And to input this rhythm here, you have to input a bass drum and then
an hi-hat. Remember when I said you can't play a bass drum tr Lucid looks clever, who
can't play an eight note rhythm. Obviously you can play an eight note rhythm but you
have to play a five note rhythm. It's like period
rhythm, we have this actual cd tempo section. Right?
And to do so, I'll need to have a finer grid.
And because the least common multiple of 5 and 8 is 40, I'll need a 40-grid, all right?
So and we'll come back to that.
So I need to refine the grid speculatively before I insert my rhythm into the sequencer.
Another alternative is what I would like to call a signal processing language.
Languages like Sonic Pi go into this category.
Here I have denoted the transformed rhythm in a programming language called Chuck, which
was popular some years ago.
Each line changes the velocity of the hi-hat channel and calls some procedures that chuck
in a wave file into the signal.
I have omitted these procedures in the interest of saving space in the slide.
All right?
And then here I have put a comment about where we are in the rhythm.
It's a little bit, it becomes a little bit messy and transformations on programs like
this one, let's say that I had my not so hip hip-hop rhythm and I wanted to make a transformed
quintuplet shuffle rhythm, the transformation is really tedious.
So it's not really feasible for a working musician to input his drum rhythms like this.
Nonetheless, it is possible.
Then there's a third category.
This is a little bit more complicated.
I want to call the third category music score representations.
And here are two examples of such representations.
The first one here is a very used Haskell embedded DSL for notating music.
And it has two operators.
This one here.
This is the at the same time operator.
And this one which is the in sequence operator.
And I have typed in here the hi-hat part of the transformed rhythm and I play it at the
same time as my transformed snare drum pattern and my transformed bass drum pattern.
In C sound.
There's an embedded DSL.
I was in a cell called DSL.
Where you have an instrument that takes some patch cables.
This magic DSL patch cable and some cables that has to be zero and one all the time for
some purpose.
And then a patch cable that goes to the thing that outputs the wave signal.
And then some canonical cables here.
Attack, sustain, decay, release.
And then it takes a string.
Which represents the movement of the drum.
It takes a string.
It's a string.
the events that it has to produce and the first part is the one that defines
the subdivision and here I have typed in the transformed eight nodes in a 20 grid
by writing r20 out here to summarize we have three categories of ways to input
rhythms into computers like this the grid editor has some pros the main pro I think
is that it gives a good syntactic overview with this grid editor you have an overview
or the whole bar and you cannot input something that's slightly longer than the bar or combine
things that will do something unexpected on the other hand you'll have to speculatively select
a grid like this and you can't input a grid like this and you can't input a grid like this
and if you select the wrong grid you either have to turn off the grid and draw in your events by
hand which is very tedious or you have to change the grid and start over and furthermore the ways
that you specialize the grid in Linux multimedia system and in Cubase and in Ableton live which
are the one I tried is specialized for contemporary Western music
meaning that it's much easier to separate a piece of time into two chunks of time that have equal
duration than it is to separate the grid into chunks of time that have different durations in
relation to each other and finally oh now we have signal processing signal processors
in a signal processor you have full control over signals but the way we perceive signals
gestures are different depending on body the moment which biom blockchain has any part in
the Fields hey that the signal coming from on the sounds that we want to give names and
signal processing languages have post structuring mechanisms because it had all of the signal
processing heavens at a different level of abstraction finally we have the music representation
sheet representations and they have some pros to my favoriteБ Racing tough but I still enjoy large
system which in오라анов daar global representation sheet representations and they have some pros – my favorite pro is that it has a concise familiar notation so I'm a musician but I'veCOmefidently just that café music or something like that so if we can't write drastically here you've got to have the sound dropped later
advice foreign going right away and so Google is out I have the exchange it's not that time prior
approach and it's good how to do it so you typically do taking this thing however this is no reaction to you
This QN variable here, which represents a quarter note, is very easy to understand.
And talking about loudness, these variables here, forte and mezzoforte, are recognizable from the music sheet.
But the structure of the music sheet is gone.
And if one of these parts is longer than the other, then the duration of the whole thing is the duration of the longest thing.
And if you combine them, either you get some audio clipped out or you get a rest somewhere.
And it's really difficult to hear what the error is.
It also trades off the syntactic constraints that we had in the sequencer or in the grid editor.
Okay.
For this expressive power of expressing rhythms any way we want.
It also inherits an unfortunate flaw from sheet music.
That you cannot actually talk about a note by itself.
So if you input a note into a music sheet, you cannot say a C.
You have to say C for one quarter note.
So the duration is embedded into the thing.
That you're saying.
And it has to be like that all the time.
So it's kind of, it's optimized for reading.
And it's very, that's fine if you want to give this music sheet to a person who has to read it.
But it gives you some limitations for expressibility.
All right.
So I wanted to design a programming language that solved at least some of these issues.
And I wanted to be a declarative programming language.
And I want to obtain this kind, the same kind of expressiveness that you get from a music score representation.
But I also want it to be composable.
And I want to separate things out.
So I actually want to talk about the signal separate from the rhythm.
And finally, I still want to preserve these alignment constraints that you get syntactically from your grid editor.
The last part here.
About preserving alignment constraints is where dependent types come in.
As you might notice from the title of the talk.
It's a dependently timed programming language.
And I'll just quickly brush that up.
What I mean by a dependent type.
If this is a little bit hard to follow, don't worry.
But if you plan to attend the workshop.
The workshop tomorrow and it felt a little bit fast, it's best if you show up at 9.
In the lambda calculus.
All right.
In the lambda calculus, here is a syntax for the lambda calculus.
We can have a variable or we can have an abstraction which is annotated by a type or a term.
Or we can apply a term to a term.
Right.
And it has some types.
And it has some typing rules.
So here is the syntax for terms and the syntax for types.
It has these typing judgments.
And the abstraction typing judgment is an abstraction from terms over terms.
And the application rule is applying a term to a term.
So clearly nothing can depend or abstract over a type in this system.
One way.
We could decide to extend it was that we could extend the syntax for types with this type variable.
And then introduce a new abstraction.
Namely that a term can abstract over a type.
And a term can be applied to a type.
Here is an intuition.
Let's say that you have a program that takes as arguments two lists.
And appends them together.
But it only works.
So long as the argument takes two lists.
So long as the arguments, the elements of this list are of the same type.
So this is basically polymorphism.
Alright.
Something else we can do is that we can let types abstract over types.
And just copy the typing rules for terms for types.
And then introduce this simpler thing that types types.
Kinds.
And so now you have terms.
Terms of different types.
And types of different kinds.
And they still abstract over each other.
Finally.
You can let a type abstract over a term.
And.
Oh.
Let's just have an intuition about this one actually.
Applying a type to a type.
Let's say that you have a type maybe a.
And then you apply it to an integer.
It becomes maybe int.
Right.
So maybe.
Has kind arrow.
And maybe int has kind star.
Alright.
The intuition about this one.
It's.
You have an abstraction.
From a type over a term.
Which means that you can now apply.
A type to a term.
And for intuition.
You can apply.
A list to an integer.
And say that.
The type is the type of all integers.
Of length n.
For some variable n in your program.
And.
This is exactly how we are going to constrain.
Our rhythms.
Later.
Alright.
An overview over the language.
The primitives of the language are signals.
And.
For now.
Signals are names.
Of wave files.
In a folder.
Next to.
The program.
So the program that we just listened to.
It had a folder here called samples.
And.
The samples.
They sound like this.
Alright.
And.
The valid.
Signals to talk about.
Are.
The.
Names of.
Wave files.
The user definable parts.
Are patterns.
Namely.
The sequence that you put into.
A grid editor.
Rhythms.
Which relate.
Patterns.
To a grid.
And.
Grooves.
Which.
Associates.
Rhythms.
With signals.
I'll make.
An informative.
Video.
About.
Rhythms.
And.
Signals.
Rhythms.
And.
Make.
An informal.
Introduction.
Here.
Is a program.
The program.
Has.
A voice.
Voice.
Is a groove.
And.
It.
Associates.
The signal.
Hi hat.
To this pattern.
Here.
The pattern.
Has.
A subdivision.
Of.
The four.
First.
It divides.
Time.
Into four.
Then.
It divides.
Each.
Node.
And.
For.
The.
Ease.
Of.
Illustration.
I.
Have.
Made.
A.
Graphic.
That.
Shows.
Like.
Where.
The.
Events.
Happen.
The.
Transformation.
That.
We.
Performed.
In.
The.
Program.
Was.
The.
Form.
Of.
Eight.
Notes.
And.
For.
Each.
Pair.
We.
Related.
Them.
In.
Duration.
To.
Each.
Other.
Three.
Against.
Two.
And.
What.
Bottom.
Teach.
Did.
To.
Infer.
The.
New.
Type.
Was.
The.
Courses.
Grid.
That.
Could.
Hold.
The.
Rhythm.
One.
Final.
Operation.
That.
You.
Can.
Decide.
To.
Do.
Is.
The.
One.
That.
I.
Have.
Denoted.
Here.
Which.
Moves.
A.
Rhythm.
To.
A.
Program.
Here.
Is.
A.
Program.
As.
You.
Can.
See.
From.
The.
Common.
Here.
It's.
A.
White.
Man's.
Hip-Hop.
Program.
And.
Let's.
Just.
Play.
It.
Like.
A.
Beat.
Has.
The.
Type.
Bottom.
Tish.
32.
16.
Because.
It's.
Duration.
Is.
32.
16th.
Note.
I'm.
A.
White.
Guy.
I.
Like.
Hip-Hop.
But.
This.
Hip-Hop.
Is.
A.
And.
Of.
Course.
When.
You.
Write.
A.
Hip-Hop.
Beat.
You.
Want.
To.
Make.
Something.
Keep.
Up.
All.
Right.
And.
So.
To.
Make.
Something.
Keep.
Up.
We.
Can.
Look.
At.
What.
We.
Have.
To.
Make.
Something.
It's.
A.
Samba.
The.
Roto.
Rhythm.
And.
Some.
Years.
Ago.
The.
Musicologist.
Fabian.
Guyon.
Looked.
At.
Some.
Of.
These.
Samba.
The.
Roto.
Rhythm.
And.
A.
Hip-Hop.
So.
This.
Will.
Be.
A.
Kind.
Of.
A.
Roto.
Samba.
A.
Roto.
Right, but it doesn't swing so well.
Actually, the latter two are delayed a little bit.
And I want to put this into my hip-hop beat.
Let's try it out.
Alright.
To put the hip-hop beat a little bit behind,
we use the arrow to the left operator.
It looks like this.
And then we put it a little bit behind.
Let's say we put it 1 16th note behind.
1 64th note behind.
Alright.
And let's listen to it again.
Also, let's inspect the type of beat.
Uh oh, let's type check in Emacs again.
It has become 128 64th note,
because we need a finer grid to associate this latter 16th note with somewhere a little bit ahead.
I still think it sounds a little bit white.
Because the snare drum and the kick drum are still right on time,
let's leave a little bit of space around the pulse.
By putting the snare drum a little bit behind the pulse
and the kick drum a little bit ahead of the pulse.
We put the snare drum a little bit behind the pulse
by using the arrow to the right operator.
This one you will have already seen before.
It's type checking.
Let's inspect the type of beat.
It's a much finer grid.
Alright.
Actually, now it sounds much hipper.
The finer grid makes it much hipper.
Now it's a Brazilian man's hip-hop.
And I'll change the comment out here as well,
because I like it.
Alright.
There's a little bit of formalism to bottom teeth as well.
We'll go over that now.
So just to repeat.
The syntax is signals are well-formed variable names of signals.
Then you can have an accent which represents loudness.
And because we are programmers, we'll just represent it with a byte.
So it's a number from 0 to f.
And...
Then in the rest of the syntax,
I'm going to use these letters for natural numbers
and q's for rationals.
A groove is either a signature that demands a duration on our groove
and it gives a type error if the groove is either too long or too short.
So you can state that your groove is in 4-4.
I actually think we did already.
Ah yeah, here it was.
Alright.
So if I change the signature here...
I get a type error.
First it tried to refine the grid,
and it got to refine it to 320.
But then it realized that to be 3 quarter notes,
the rhythm should be 320 notes,
and 240 is not 320.
The compiler says.
I'll agree that we can extend bottom teeth to have better type errors
sometime in the future.
Alright.
A groove can also be a voice,
which associates a rhythm with a signal,
as we did with the hi-hat.
It can be a repetition of a groove,
it can be a groove played at the same time as another groove,
and it can be a groove played before another groove.
And a rhythm can be a subdivision followed by a pattern,
or it can be a phrasing of a subdivision followed by a pattern.
We did this with the shuffle transformation.
It can also be a rhythm which is a little bit ahead,
as we did with the Brazilian man's hip-hop.
It can be a rhythm which is a little bit behind,
and it can be a rhythm followed by another rhythm.
Finally, a pattern can be an accentuation,
and a nex,
which is the continuation of a previous event.
The reason for the nex is that when we refine the grid,
we want to enforce the duration of the previous rhythm,
and it can also be a rest or an abyss,
or it can be the empty pattern.
And the typing judgment that we used to infer
the causes of the grid comes following.
The typing judgment for patterns is that the empty pattern
is the pattern that contains no events.
If you add an event to a pattern,
you get a pattern that has one more event.
Alright, the typing judgment for rhythms.
A rhythm is parameterized with how many events
and how coarse the grid.
The Toplet rule states a subdivision and a pattern,
and the rhythm has as many events as the pattern,
but the subdivision is the product of the subdivisions.
Let's say we have eight notes,
which we wrote by separating time into four equally sized pieces,
and then separating each piece into two.
So, computed the product of four and two,
and got eight notes.
Likewise, I just got a note that we have ten minutes left,
so I'll go very quickly over this one.
The phrasing, of course, refines the grid enough
that you can separate the grid into chunks
that have the duration of the sum of whatever you separated.
For instance,
for the shuffle rhythm,
we wanted to separate our two eight notes
into five equally sized parts.
So we multiply the number of events happening
and the coarseness of the grid by five.
Moving rhythms ahead and behind
doesn't change their duration.
It just changes where they are realized in time,
and the duration of...
The sequence of two rhythms is, of course,
the sum of the events.
With this extra rule that refines the grid,
the grid is refined to the least common multiple
of the coarseness of the two grids.
There's also a typing judgment for grooves.
A signature is just a groove
which requires a coarseness of the grid
and a number of events.
A voice just has the same duration
as the rhythm that it's associated with,
and repeating a groove
just multiplies the number of events by how far.
All right?
And, well,
the sequence and simultaneous operators
have typing rules very similar to those of rhythms.
But you can ask me questions afterwards.
All right?
Now we'll have a demonstration running.
And here I typed in some world music.
There's a Gnarwen rhythm from Morocco,
an African Tsongkhlebe rhythm,
a pulsating...
It's like a reggae...
bass drum pulse,
a hip-hop shuffle hi-hat,
and a backbeat which makes everything sound
a little bit more pop.
And while it's playing,
I'll take questions.
Here.
All right, it's playing in a while
because it just has to type check.
We will not inspect the type of this rhythm.
All right.
Coming up.
All right, yeah.
So here is the Gnarwen...
Shaker pattern.
All right.
And while that's playing,
I think it will be playing for three or five minutes.
I'll take questions if there are any.
Yeah.
Any questions?
No.
So you have the signature statement for grooves.
Couldn't you also express that by simply stating
the type of the term that you have,
like you would normally do in Akda,
instead of having it as part of your language?
The type of signature?
So the signature term itself,
only it looks like it's only sort of enforcing the type yes yeah but why doesn't you can you
just say for example that beat has the type groove four four and then the normal actor
type checker would sort of enforce it right that's a good question you cannot so
but i'll explain why all right so it's because when you state the signature you state
that it can fit into four quarter notes
which will hold even though you state a rhythm which cannot be contained in a four grid
so 128 or 128 rhythm will still fit into the type signature of 4-4
but if you put 4-4 in the type signature you will get an error that 4 is not 128.
anyone
else
no then i think we should give Joachim a big hand for this excellent presentation