The next speaker we have is me, who will talk about Funion, a Tor client in Elixir.
Let's give him a hand.
Okay, so hello and welcome to my talk about Funion.
It's a Tor client I've written in Elixir in order to learn Tor and to learn Elixir, but
I will talk about this very soon.
And I want to ask a few questions to the audience.
Who of you is quite familiar with the Tor protocol, I mean just the basics in the sense
of you know what a circuit is, what a connection is, what a stream is, and like, you know the
ESP?
EFF graphics, okay, nice.
And who of you has used Erlang or Elixir?
Oh, that's quite a high amount.
I think it gets higher the more north you go in Europe, but yeah, nice.
So yeah, a few things about me.
I'm Emil, I go by any pronouns.
I've graduated high school this summer, and I'm going to study pure mathematics and computer
science beginning in October.
I contribute to open source projects since 2018, some of them include Curl, Rosenpass,
there are some others as well, and I've been doing Tor since October of last year.
And yeah, I'm also available on the Fediverse and GitHub.
So first of all, I have to do some acknowledgements at first.
I would really like to thank Alex, he was always helping me since day one, I mean I've
posted this on my Mastodon account, and he immediately supported me.
Thank you, Alex.
He supported me there and was always there to answer questions, so many thanks to you.
And then also many thanks to the Tala authors.
For those of you who don't know what Tala is, Tala is an implementation of Tor done
in Erlang, and this also helped me a lot because I was required to use the Erlang crypto library,
and it definitely had some weird things in it, and looking at the Tala source could definitely
help me there.
And I also have to thank the people who are in the chat.
TorDev IRC channel on OFTC, most notably Nick Mathewson, Roger Dingledine, Ian Jackson,
Trinity Pointard, and others, it's in no particular order.
Yeah, so what have I actually done?
I've written a Tor client in Elixir, it's an onion proxy, it's not a relay, it's like
a thing you actually use to connect to the Tor network on your computer.
It implements only the core, only like the bare bones of the Tor protocol.
The torspec.txt document and the certspec.txt document found in the Tor specification repository.
And it is more of an educational thing rather than something that people, if you really
depend on privacy, you probably should not use that.
And it still lacks many features such as directory support, hidden services, a SOX proxy, support
to be a relay, and so on.
And it probably also suffers from side channel attacks because I didn't pay that much attention
to it as I was just trying to get a Tor client working.
And yeah, but hackers are very welcome.
If you would like to implement some of these things or something completely else, just
come to me and I will invite you to a MATE for sure.
Yeah, so what was my motivation behind that?
So as I've said, I've graduated from high school.
And in Germany, it generally works like that.
School ends in March, and the finals are in April.
So you have like a month free in order to prepare yourself for the exams.
But let's be honest, you don't use a month for that, you use like the night before the
exam for that.
So yeah, you could do something productive, party all the time, or learn for the finals.
I've did both of it, and this like on the day before.
So yeah, it was a good time, a time killer as well.
Yeah.
My background.
It's like I've been doing low-level C development and Rust development for like three years.
So I was more like a low-level guy and had no prior experience with Elixir and functional
programming in general.
And I began contributing to RT, which is Tor's re-implementation in Rust in the autumn of
last year.
And it got me hooked.
I was really fascinated by the protocol itself.
But then earlier this year, I saw the computer file video on Erlang.
And I got really amazed by that.
It was an eye-opening experience, but I will come to this very soon.
And because I had so much free time, I simply decided, okay, I'm going to learn Elixir,
functional programming, and Tor with this project.
And this is what came out in the end.
So yeah, I will talk a little bit about Elixir and Erlang, what those technologies are, and
because they...
Yeah.
They have quite some differences from like the average programming language.
So Elixir and Erlang are functional programming languages that both compile to the same virtual
machine in bytecode.
It's quite similar to Java and Kotlin and to JVM, respectively.
Because of that, Erlang libraries can also be used from inside Elixir and vice versa.
And it's an extremely fault-tolerant language.
It has like the slogan, write once, run forever.
And it emphasizes process separation and isolation.
And like, as a real open BSD diehard in my youth, this gave me really, really wet dreams.
And I just got amazed by the concept in general.
And Erlang and Elixir, the entire ecosystem around it, it's like the first time IPC is
actually easy and doable.
And I really do not want to use Unix IPC again after I've did Elixir for the first time.
So I'm going to talk a little bit about that.
And then I'm going to talk a little bit about how to use it.
And in my opinion, it's also one of the most underrated technologies that are out there.
So especially in network-facing applications, there's like this traditional approach.
The traditional approach usually works like there's one monolithic process, and it handles
multiple connections through either an event loop or a synchronity.
Both of the solutions have their downsides and pitfalls.
An event loop destroys the linear execution flow of a program, whereas asynchronicity,
in my opinion, is like the purpose of programming, because once it's inside your project, you
can almost never get it out.
I mean, everyone who has done ASIC and Rust probably knows what I'm talking about.
And that's like lots of craft.
So you might ask, why don't you just use threads for handling multiple connections?
I mean, that's actually what many beginners do, because it sounds like the most intuitive.
But there are definitely some downsides to it.
Most notably, on modern Linux systems, a thread takes up to eight megabytes stack at least,
and this becomes a problem.
It's okay if you handle like 10 connections, but it becomes a real problem if you have
like 10,000 connections, because you quickly run out of memory then.
However, there are some notable exceptions, most notably OpenSSH and PostgreSQL, who spawn
a new process for every authenticated connection.
So they are not vulnerable to denial-of-service attacks that much, because you have to be
authenticated before it forks.
But the Elixir process is quite different.
Actually, Elixir does it one process per connection.
I will tell what the difference about a thread and a process is in a second.
But they are not real OS processes, so they do not take like an eight megabyte stack for
each thing.
They offer isolation.
And they make the code, in my opinion, much easier.
And this isolation leads to, in my opinion, a much bigger security benefit.
So you might be wondering, isn't that like Go routines?
They are also like very cheap.
And sort of.
That's kind of true.
They are very similar.
From an OS perspective, they are very similar implemented.
But the major difference is that Go routines are more conceptualized as threads, whereas
Elixir processes are like the name suggests.
It's more like processes.
The difference is that a thread can access all resources inside a process, whereas a
process itself is its own isolated unit that exists and runs on its own.
This is also the reason why in multi-thread applications, you often have to deal with
things like mute access and those kind of lock mechanisms.
You do not have that when you use processes, at least.
You sometimes do have that as well, but it's something different then.
And, yeah.
Okay.
So.
It has an extreme security benefit, because if one process gets taken over by an attacker,
the impact they can do is much less significant.
So yeah.
Let's look at my project from like 10,000 feet.
I've developed it using Elixir 1.15.
It supports the link protocol version 4 of the top protocol only, because it's like not...
I was a bit too lazy to implement version 4.
It's like version 5, because it had like a feature...
Yeah.
I wasn't yet motivated to do that.
And version 3...
Well, the difference between version 3 and version 4 is like very minimal, and version
1 and 2 are like really, really old, really legacy.
I'm not even sure if CTOR still supports them.
And, yeah.
The code is pretty good documented, in my opinion.
It has a consistent type spec almost all over the place.
And its design is also very modular.
I got inspired by Arty.
So, there are like...
I mean, it's a very, very, very, very, very, very, very, very, very, very, very, very, very,
very, very, very, very, very, very, very, very, very, very, very, very, very, very, very, very,
very, very, very, very, very, very, very, very, very, very, very, very, very, very, very, very
good.
I would use that here is the code.
And, yeah.
The code is pretty good documented, in my opinion.
It has a consistent type spec almost all over the place.
And its design is also very modular.
I got inspired by Arty.
So, there are like 4 modules right now.
Tor-Cell, which handles like the cells, is your data structure.
Tor-Cert, which handles the elliptic curve certificates, which is a custom tour certificate
format.
Then, there's Tor-Crypto, which does like the handshakes and other things like that,
and stuff.
related to cryptography. And then there's also the Tor Proto module, which is like the
heart of the entire thing. But the most complexity really lies within the Tor Cell and the Tor
Proto module. So let's take a look at the Tor Cell thing. It implements the cells, which
are Tor's basic unit of communication. All traffic that is sent through the Tor socket
is done in cells. And the parsing takes place with pattern matching, which is like a really
cool thing that's supported by Erlang and Elixir. It basically allows you to parse a
protocol within the language. And not many languages offer that as well. And yeah, a
cell has three fields, a circ ID, which is like a 32-bit integer, which indicates to
which circuit this thing belongs. Then there's the command field, which is an atom containing
the, yeah, the circuit.
Yeah.
What the cell means, like the semantic value of it. And the payload is dependent on the
command, and it contains a decoded payload that is actually, yeah, viable data then.
This module, however, performs no cryptography. This is done outside of it. It doesn't even
validate the certs and those kind of things. It just parsed them into plain, boring Elixir
data structures to be operated on later on.
So these are the connection cells, but Tor also has relay cells. They are the
actual cells that use the onion routing principle. That is, they are encrypted, and a layer gets
removed at every hop, or a layer gets added at every hop if it's going backward. The
decrypted relay cells are implemented in the Tor cell.relay cell data structure. And once
they are encrypted, their ciphertext goes into a Tor cell.relay data structure. Yeah.
And the decrypted one has three fields. Command, which is also a decrypted one. And then the
stream ID, which is a 16-bit integer indicating to which stream this belongs. And then there's
the data containing the decoded data eventually. It has two public functions, decrypt and encrypt.
Decrypt takes an onion skin, the stream cipher, an array of stream cipher keys for the backward
direction, and a digest, and speaking more concrete, the backward digest, which is used to know if a cell has been
fully decrypted. And it returns a tuple containing a boolean. If the boolean is true, the cell
has been fully decrypted. If it's false, there are still onion skins left. The second item
is either the decoder Tor cell.relay cell, or it's an onion skin, which is still ciphertext,
but with a certain amount of onion skins removed from it. And the last one is the updated backward
digest. With encrypt, it's quite similar. You pass in the plaintext relay cell, and
then an array of forward symmetric cipher keys, symmetric stream cipher keys, and the forward
digest. What you get in return is the onion skin of it, and the forward digest, and then
you can place the onion skin into the encrypted cell and send it over the wire.
Then there's also the Tor crypto module, which performs various cryptographic operations
that are simply required by Tor, most notably the Antor handshake, which is used for search
circuits, for establishing circuits. It also offers a small abstraction about the digest
implementation, and it also implements the encryption and decryption of onion skins.
I've called them onion streams because they are stream cipher, and so they have a state.
And it's a pretty small module. It's like only 150 lines of code or something. Yeah.
But the real stuff is going on in the Tor proto module.
Yeah.
Which implements the actual Tor protocol. It's implemented using GenServer and a client
API. And it is highly process-oriented. That is, there is a separation of resource as much
as possible, which you can see in the next slide. That is, this is an average session
using that. So there are multiple connection processes.
Each connection has a satellite process, and also multiple circuits. And each circuit
then also has several streams, and they communicate in a linear fashion. So it's not that the
connection communicates with the stream, but when the connection communicates with the
stream, it passes through the circuit. So it just talks to the parent in such a kind
of fashion. Yeah. Here you can see it in a more smaller version, if the previous slide
was a bit overwhelming. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
Yeah. Yeah.
Okay. And I will... and what's a bit notable is that all of these processes except the
stream process have a thing called a pit FIFOS.
The thing is that cells have to be enqueued for processes, so they can request them and
obtain them from the parent, respectively. And the pit FIFOS is effectively just a map
are the process identifiers, and the values are FIFOs.
And so we are going to have a look at the first process now,
which is the connection process.
It manages a connection of the top protocol,
and it's responsible for spawning the circuit processes
through a call I've called create.
It also spawns a single satellite process
that handles the raw TLS socket.
Why this has to be done, I will explain that in a second.
And it gets pulled by the satellite process
every time a new cell arrives.
And those cells are then either processed by the connection
if the circuit ID is zero,
or are redirected to the appropriate circuits
if their circuit ID is not zero, respectively.
And if that's the case, it pulls the appropriate circuits,
and that's the state of it.
So there's the circuits map,
that is like simply a mapping of the circuit IDs
with their accompanying pits.
Then there's the FIFOs,
which contain the enqueued, not yet fetched cells
for all of the circuits.
Then there's the router field,
which just stores the onion router we are connected to.
And then there's also the satellite process,
and then there's also the satellite field
that contains the pit of the satellite process.
So yeah.
And generally, the workflow,
if it works like that,
the satellite process pulls the connection process,
and the connection process talks to the satellite process
by sending either the queue messages,
or when it sends a queue,
it gets a cell that's in the FIFO.
And if you send cell,
it simply sends a cell outside of it.
And with the circuit, it's quite similar.
The connection pulls the circuit,
and the circuit, either the queue sends a cell
or informs the parent that it's,
that it's going to die now.
So yeah, let's talk about the satellite process a bit now.
It creates and manages the raw TLS socket,
and it works on cell level.
So the serialization and deserialization of cells
happens there,
process just sends cells there,
and they do everything that is left to do then.
It pulls the parent connection process
whenever a cell has been decoded and enqueued successfully,
and it pulls the parent connection process whenever a cell has been decoded and enqueued successfully,
and the state consists of the following fields.
First and foremost, a buffer,
because it receives the raw TCP,
the raw, yeah, TCP TLS data.
There might be data that cannot be fully parsed yet,
because there's not much,
there's not yet enough data to construct a full cell from it.
Then there's also the connection,
which is the pit of the connection process.
Then there's the FIFOs.
In fact, it could be called just FIFO.
The plural is a bit misleading here.
And it contains the enqueued cells for the connection.
Then there's the socket field,
which just contains the actual TLS socket.
And then there's the virginity Boolean.
This has just one purpose.
Usually until a connection,
until the first version cell has been received,
all circuit ID fields are 2 byte integers
instead of 4 byte integers,
because of backward compatibility.
And once the first circuit,
once the first version cell has arrived from the responder,
it will set this thing to false.
So the circuit ID will then be parsed
with 4 byte integers from there on.
And yeah, you might be asking,
why is there a satellite?
I mean, the idea of a separate process
just for handling the TLS connection
may sound a bit unintuitive.
And you might be wondering,
why not do that in the connection process directly?
But there are several reasons for that.
Most notably,
the connection process has to receive data
while it's currently already processing a request.
In other languages,
you would simply call a receive thing,
which would block until the data arrives.
Unfortunately, that's not the Elixir way to do it,
because in Elixir,
you do not obtain the data from the socket
by using a receive or something like that.
Instead, the raw data gets delivered
to the process mailbox.
And I would have to do a manual receive then,
like the Erlang Elixir receive keyword.
And this is, I wouldn't say it's discouraged,
but it's discouraged in the way I'm doing it,
because I'm using GenServer.
And the entire purpose of GenServer
is to get rid of these receive statements.
So that would be a bit counterintuitive.
And beside this,
it also offers the great advantage
that the TLS socket is in its separate process.
Which is very good,
because the TLS socket also contains cryptographic data,
which is nice if it's separated in its own thing.
So yeah, then there are also the circuit processes.
They obviously manage a circuit of the top protocol.
And what's really cool about it
is that they are the only process
that have the real cryptographic keys,
like the shared secret,
and the other keys derived from that.
So if the other processes get pawned,
it's not as critical as if that one would get pawned,
because that's the one holding the keys.
And it spawns the stream processes,
which are then the actual TCP streams.
We will talk about that very soon either.
And it gets pulled by the connection process
every time a cell for that circuit has arrived.
And if it receives that cell,
it does something.
Most notably, if it's a relay cell,
it performs a decryption encryption there.
And if the decrypted relay cell
happens to be associated with a stream that's open,
it will do the same that the connection does with the circuit.
It will pull the stream and enqueue that cell for it.
And yeah, the state consists of, obviously,
the circuit ID that was assigned to it by the connection.
Then it contains the pit of the appropriate connection.
And it also contains the FIFOs,
which is the network field to store the enqueued cells.
Then there's also the hops array,
which is an array of all hops the circuit is extended to,
including the cryptographic keys.
They're also stored inside that.
And last but not least,
there's also a map of all stream IDs
with their appropriate stream processes.
And here you can see how it works
in combination with the connection stream processes.
So the connection process pulls whenever a new cell arrives,
the circuit decues it.
And similar, it goes with the stream.
The circuit pulls the stream if new data has arrived,
and the stream then sends these messages,
like it either decues a cell from it,
it sends a cell,
or it notifies circuits that the stream is now going to die.
What's quite interesting is that the send cell
contains, like, the plaintext cell,
and the encryption, like I said, takes place here.
So the stream doesn't know anything
about the cryptographic keys,
which is really nice in my opinion.
And, yeah, it manages a stream.
So, yeah, I've talked about the stream processes quite a bit.
So what are they actually?
They manage a stream of the top protocol
that is an actual TCP connection.
During the creation, it accepts a closure
that handles the received data,
which is, like, an amazing thing.
My first idea for that design was to simply include a PIP
rather than a closure,
and the PIP would then, like, handle incoming traffic there.
But that's actually not that good idea
because I would have to define a message format for it
and those kind of things.
But a closure, it gives you, like, unlimited power.
It's much cooler because a closure can also use
the local scope and those kind of things.
And it gets pulled by the circuit
if an appropriate stream relay cell has arrived.
And, like I've said, no encryption and decryption
is performed there.
And it accepts...
And it accepts data from external processes
using the client API.
So, yeah, how does the client API actually work in that sense?
I've talked about it quite a bit.
So first and foremost, a connection is created.
Afterwards, a circuit is created on that connection.
Presumably more circuits as well.
The circuit is extended two times
to have, like, a three-hopped circuit
because that's what Tor likes to do.
Then it creates a stream with providing a closure.
I already said that this offers, like, unlimited power.
Then, optionally, data can be sent to that TCP stream.
And once it's done, you terminate the stream,
you terminate the circuit, and you terminate the connection.
However, this is done recursively.
Like, if you forget these things
and just terminate the connection,
the connection will recursively terminate the circuits,
which will terminate all associated streams.
So what are the upcoming features?
First, what are my plans for this project?
Like I've said, it was more a thing to learn Elixir
and to learn Tor a bit.
I definitely accomplished the first thing.
I feel pretty confident with Elixir now.
But with Tor, it's like, it's a Sisyphus task, you know?
Tor is like, there's so much things you can learn about it,
and it's still a very open field of research.
But I hope I can still contribute to Tor
and do some stuff there
because it's a really amazing project
and it's really interesting as well.
Yeah, currently we have a priority
to implement the directory protocol
as well as the path protocol
because right now all routers are hard-coded
when you want to connect to them,
which is not very nice,
especially because you, like, have to redo this,
like, every three weeks when the keys expire.
Hidden services would also be nice,
but I think that this would really be really hard.
But maybe I have the time.
We will see.
And relay support is not planned yet.
But I'm not against this.
But it's simply not on my priority list either.
But as I've said, I'm already,
I'm starting to go to university very soon
and I do not know how much free time I will have then.
So I'm not sure how the project will continue.
And the development takes place in our fossil repository.
We also have a GitHub mirror available here.
And pull requests and issues are more than welcome.
So while I've developed this,
there were also many pitfalls I've encountered.
And I'm especially talking to you,
future implementer of another Tor specification.
I think you owe me a beer.
But fortunately those pitfalls I've encountered,
you should not encounter them
because I've submitted quite a few patches
to the specification in order to fix them.
Hopefully.
So what were the greatest pitfalls in an ascending order?
First and foremost,
circuit IDs need to have a most significant byte of 1.
I forgot that
because I didn't read the specification that carefully.
But there was also,
I wouldn't call it a mistake in the specification,
but the specification wasn't that clear
that this is like a really hard must requirement.
It just said that it's done,
but it doesn't say it like it must be done.
I fixed that.
Because otherwise nothing will work.
And it took me like,
an afternoon to figure that out.
I could have done that much easier
if I had read it properly.
Or if it would have been a must statement.
Another pitfall was that
circuit extensions have to be done
in a relay early cell
and not in a relay cell.
The purpose behind that design decision
is that you simply do not extend the circuits indefinitely
with relay early cells,
there's like a hard limit.
I think it's something like eight.
So once there are more like eight relay early cells
received from that connection,
everything will fail.
And this was also only slightly mentioned in the spec.
If I had read it a bit more carefully,
I think I wouldn't have had that problem.
It was a bit frustrating,
but it eventually worked out
because the creation of a circuit worked,
but the extension didn't work.
And I was like,
well, am I doing the handshake wrong?
I was just looking into the handshake code
because it worked like the first time,
but not the other times.
But in fact,
it turned out to be a much different problem
than I initially assumed.
So then there's like the number two,
which is,
I definitely thought way too complicated
in the digits verification.
Everyone who has implemented Tor on their own
knows what I'm talking about.
The digits verification is something like,
if the digits is verified,
if it's valid,
a relay cell has ended,
it's reached the end,
and it can be,
and it's fully decoded now.
And I was thinking way too complicated about it
because relay cells contain a field
that's called digits,
which is four byte long.
And the digits is like all relay cells
that have been sent so far.
However,
the digits field has to be set to zero
because you cannot like include the digits
if it hasn't been computed yet.
And I thought like,
okay,
the zero digits is like only a temporary thing.
And then like the real digits,
that was the temporary thing,
gets sent to the real digits.
I was thinking way too complicated.
You can still see my mistakes in the Git logs.
And,
but I'm very proud that I hopefully fixed that for you
because I've written an entire section
of Tor specification providing a pseudo code.
So hopefully this doesn't happen again.
And the last thing,
which was like definitely one of the most frustrating
experiences in my life,
was realizing that Tor or not realizing
that Tor uses a symmetric stream cipher
for the onion skins.
I assumed that it would use a block cipher
for whatever reason.
I'm not quite sure why.
And I mean,
thinking about this a bit further,
it makes like no sense
because the onion skins are 509 byte long
and no sane block cipher would return such an odd value.
But it took me a long time to figure it out.
And when I eventually figured out,
I was just like,
AES 128 CTR,
okay,
not sure what the CTR means,
just ignore it.
Just still continue using the block cipher functions,
which eventually resulted in that I didn't kept a state at all.
And this result in the really nasty bug
that the first encryption always worked,
but all later ones failed
because I always reinitialize the state for every encryption.
And this was so hard to figure out.
And when I eventually figured it out,
I was really,
really mad
because everyone who has done functional programming knows that
when you have a state,
it taints throughout the code base.
And I didn't design it with that state design in mind at first place.
So I had to redesign quite a bit,
although it wasn't that bad
because the Erlang crypto stream cipher module
is not functional.
It has side effects,
which is a bit ugly.
But in that case,
I had like,
luck and misfortune,
or fortune and misfortune.
Yeah, so thank you Erlang guys.
I'm not sure.
Yeah.
And you are welcome for these things,
future tour implementer.
I won't be the last one.
So now I'm going to do a quick presentation of,
a quick demonstration of what I have done.
Yeah, let me move that terminal window
right over there.
I hope this works now.
Oh no,
that's the wrong directory.
So,
sorry,
I can't mirror the screens right now.
That's a good idea.
How do I attach to that session from elsewhere?
A,
and you shall.
Thank you.
My neck is thanking me for that.
What was it?
Tmax.
Tmax,
space,
A,
enter.
Space,
A,
enter.
Thank you.
What do you mean?
Oh,
okay.
Yeah,
sure.
Makes sense.
Thank you.
Okay,
so I'm focused.
Oh,
I'm just making it a bit.
Okay,
now,
that should it be.
And now let me get back to the main screen.
So,
yeah.
ah,
dang it.
It has no,
can I open E-mail?
Can I open E-mix here?
There was like a fee,
a way to open E-mix without X11.
NV minus N,
NV,
NW.
Thank you.
Okay,
so,
yeah,
this is much better.
So,
this is basically a list of three,
on your route,
as we are going to connect to now.
They all contain,
all contain the nickname, the identity, which is like the fingerprint of the RSA identity key,
then it obviously contains the IP, the port on which it's running, and then it contains some
cryptographic keys, most notably the RSA identity key, the ED25519 identity key,
the elliptic curve signing key, and also the X25519 enter key, which is used for the handshake.
And I've extracted them manually from the Tor directory just now, like two hours ago.
So how do we use this thing? First, we start a connection by calling this function,
connection initiator start link, and then provide the guard node, the information of the guard node.
I will do a short sleep here so you can see that it's working. If I'm splitting the
things, I can see that it's working. If I'm splitting the things, I can see that it's working.
Tmux. Okay, you see this as well now? Yeah, nice. If I run it, you now should see that
quite a few debug statements. So, you see it created a TLS connection, it created a
satellite process, sent a version cell, received a version cell, decided to use that link protocol
version, validated the certificates, sent a net info cell, and in general, finished
the handshake. So, we just created the connection, and now we want to create a circuit on it.
How do we do that? Very easy. We also use a function, toproto.connection.initiate, that's
uppercase, .create, and just provide the connection process. And now we can see, when we run it
again.
Oh, oh, you can't really see that. Oh, you can? You can now. Yeah, you can see that now,
after the established connection, it sends a circuit handshake, it receives a reply,
the circuit handshake is valid, there's a cryptographic function inside it to validate
it, and then it's finished, and then it was finally created. But that's not still that
nice, because, you know, we just have it like with one hop, and we need to extend it
quickly.
quite a bit. So let us do that. We use TorProto.Circuit.Initiator.Extend and then we provide the circuit and
the hop we are extending to. I am doing this with both of them. So it gets directly extended
to the exit node which in that case is VinculumGate and then when that is done we should see,
okay, so it should focus, yeah. We can see that it now gets extended to Adrian and last
but not least it gets extended to VinculumGate, doing the handshake all over again but with
different cryptographic keys for sure then. Now we want to create a stream because we
actually want to send some data and what would be cooler than fetch our IP through Tor,
so I can show you that it actually works.
We do that by also using a function in the circuit module
that is connect, what a surprise.
And in it we provide, what was it?
It was the circuit, it was the host name.
Let's do ifconfig.me.
Let's use port 80, and then we need to provide a closure.
We will write that closure now.
It is basically just a function with one parameter.
And here we just do, well, I like to just log it,
log out dot, just do an info statement with the data.
And yeah, and when we run that,
we should see that we have forgot
something.
Yes, this 2 doesn't belong there.
And we see that nothing happens afterwards
except that it connects now to something
because, well, we are not sending data right now.
So it does not receive an HTTP request.
The end points, which we will do now.
Then we simply use top-proto.dream.initiator.sendData
alongside the stream.
And then the data, we simply do an HTTP 1.1 request.
Biffconfig.me backslash r backslash n backslash r backslash n.
Long live these MS-DOS line endings.
Everyone loves them.
And now we should see that we get a reply.
And we see that our IP is 776820.217,
which happens to be exactly this IP here.
And I forgot a very important thing to clean it up.
We do that by simply terminating the connection
because the connection, like I said,
will then terminate everything else recursively.
This is done by just stopping it.
This is providing the connection.
And when we do it,
we should see like some destroy things.
Okay, that shouldn't have happened.
I think maybe it's a bit busy right now, the exit node.
Or it could be an async issue.
Maybe try that.
Yeah, okay.
It was an async thing.
And now we can see that it successfully terminates all streams,
then destroys the circuit.
Then it says, well, I've terminated all circuits.
The TLS connection gets closed.
And finally,
everything was properly closed.
So, yeah.
I now have a thank you slide,
but I'm too busy,
or I do not want to start the presentation all over again.
I'm too lazy for that.
So, thank you.
Are there any questions?
So, you said,
you shouldn't use this at this stage.
And I know that RT is also designed,
so RT is the Rust implementation,
just to reiterate that it's also designed to be used as a library
by other programs.
But of course,
your implementation is on the Beam virtual machine.
So, do you think eventually the library will be production ready
so that programs on the Beam VM can also use the Tor protocol?
Yes and no.
I would really hope that this could work eventually.
I mean, I'm designing it as a library.
After all, I'm documenting it.
And it's all a matter of time.
Like, if I have the time and motivation,
it will eventually be that case.
But I can't know that because I do not know the future.
And the no part is because of the following.
Many people often claim that you should only write cryptographic applications
in like C or Rust because they are
like the only commonly used programming languages that allow you to do,
to control everything.
Like in C and Rust, if you really want to,
you can control each and every CPU instruction.
You have full control over the memory,
which is a critical part in avoiding side channel attacks.
Most notably, the probably most famous example is overwriting memory with zeros,
like private keys, once you are done with using them.
And this is, for example, a thing that's impossible
or really, really hard to do in Go right now.
And yeah, so,
I would hope it would be productive for you one day.
But of course, you always have the side channel issue that you simply have
because it's a high level language.
Hello.
Hi.
Are there any privacy implications of using a non-standard client
that is not a standard client?
Yes.
Like the version cells, do they leak anything?
Okay.
I mean, if you use that,
like if that client becomes really widespread in this current stage,
it will become known that it's,
that you are not using the official Tor implementation.
So, people will know that you use a different Tor implementation,
which already reduces the privacy quite a bit
because in an anonymity network,
it's important that all peers look similar.
Or even the same.
So, this is definitely a privacy implication,
but it's not a thing that's,
it's possible to fix that.
I mean, like I've said,
I also haven't implemented all things of the Tor specs,
so there are quite some differences in features that can be spotted
compared to the official Tor implementation.
And yeah, and on the other side, you also have like a downside.
This is a project done by me.
I'm the only one who has probably reviewed it.
I haven't reviewed the code yet.
And with Tor, you have like thousands of eyes have already seen that.
And it's a thing that I can simply not offer
because it hasn't been audited that much yet.
Thank you for being here, Emil.
Let's give him a round of applause.