Let's give a big hand to the last speaker we have this year, Tick with Goodbye World.
Thank you everybody.
We are nearing the end of what has been an amazing BornHack 2023.
It is always a bit weird.
The week goes by incredibly fast, it feels like, and so much has happened that it can
be difficult to get your head around it.
We had some weather over the last couple of days.
We have reduced the number of pavilions significantly on the site.
I guess we considered starting teardown early, an unplanned teardown.
Most of the important things are still standing, and we hope that the worst of the weather has
passed, especially right after this, where we hope to take down the big tent.
Please stay dry.
I have a lot of fun stats about the week that went by, and some practical info.
I want to start out by talking a little bit about Grafen.
As you remember from Hello World, and as most of you know, we lost an organizer this year,
last year, but between the last BornHack and this BornHack.
We have been struggling to figure out a good way to remember him, and we've decided to
plant a tree here at Hylgedam.
It will be placed out here by the radio tower, and it is being delivered the day after tomorrow,
probably.
There's some logistics involved when you're getting a sizable tree delivered, but we hope
it will be here.
It will be delivered later than Thursday.
We have put up a mailbox in the bar where everybody is encouraged to write a letter
to Grafen, and all the letters will be buried under the tree, put in the hole before we
put in the tree when we put it in on Thursday or whenever it's going to be.
The mailbox is in the bar, and we hope you will take time to write down some thoughts.
Nobody will ever read it.
So.
It's more for you than for anyone else.
The tree is a silver linden.
I don't know much about trees, but it's pretty, and we hope it will be here for many years.
Thank you.
Okay.
Let's get on to the more fun stuff.
Statistics.
We all love that, right?
The program grew significantly this year.
There was a few fewer talks, but overall it was a more full program than it has ever been
before.
I want to give a big thank you to everybody who submitted.
We had 23 of the regular talks, which is fewer than last year, 11 lightning talks, which
is quite a bit more than last year, 18 workshops, which is a lot, and some of them were way
overcrowded, so there could probably have been more.
We had the panel debate, which was, again, a great success, and 12 meetups this year,
which is double what we had last year, a couple of music acts, and 19 recreational events.
Thank you.
I just had to talk about some of the events, various things submitted by villages and everything.
It's been so good to see all the activities going on.
The content team has been working hard putting this together, and all the people who've submitted,
thank you all.
Let's give everybody involved a big round of applause.
Of course, let's not forget the video team, who are tirelessly working to stream locally
and stream online.
All this is doing a great job.
Also everything is being recorded so we can go, let's give it a month, we have to recover
a bit but pretty soon you'll be able to see it on media.ccc.de once we've done the post
processing and stuff.
And the video team has been handling all that like pros so thank you for that.
The NOC team has as always delivered an impressive infrastructure out here in the middle of nowhere.
We had very fast uplink speeds, I think I saw a speed test from a tent of eight and
a half gigabits or something, and that's to the outside world, 35 access points were put
up by NOC for the Wi-Fi, 300 almost, 350 unique connected devices, oh no, max, simultaneous
I think it means.
So that's it.
Quite some data was pulled through our connection, 42 terabytes uploaded and 6 terabytes downloaded
and of the 42 terabytes, a single tent and a single user is responsible for 90% of it,
so well done.
I happen to know it is data going to a really good course so it is very good to see.
Bar numbers, as you know we depend on the bar to stay above water financially and you
have been very good at using the bar, we really appreciate it.
There's some impressive stats from down there, they sold 3700 things, over 2600 transactions,
628 cocktails, I may be responsible for quite a few of those.
619 liters of beer, I am absolutely responsible for zero of those.
Okay.
445 liters of mate, same, 17 tsunamis, I may also be involved there and we had this
year four free kegs bought by participants in the bar and put up for free for everybody
to drink, three of them were weddings and the last one was 40 around birthday.
The bar has been open almost like I've been awake, there hasn't been many times where
I've walked by the bar.
And it's been closed and it's down to an amazing bar team both constructing it and keeping
it alive and involving over the week and also tending, cleaning up and doing everything
that's needed to keep our bar running.
Let's give them a big round of applause.
So the game team once again.
Organised.
Amazing.
token game. It's
sort of a treasure hunt for little text strings
all over the venue. They are offline
and online and all over
the place. 60 people
took place in the
contest and
27 tokens were found
and 242 times
a token was found. Game team,
do we have a winner to announce?
They have been announced. Oh, I didn't see.
Sorry. The winner has been announced
and I hope they are happy they got a free ticket
for next year's event.
Let's give a
big round of applause to the game team.
Between the token game and
the Jeopardy and everything,
they are really doing a lot of work
that used to fall on Orga,
so we are very, very happy with
that and it's working so well, so
thank you.
The shuttle team has
also been busy this year. They almost
got out of it. We almost didn't get a shuttle car
but we managed to get one
last minute thanks to Dennis
who helped find a sponsor.
The shuttle team does the drives
back and forth to the station mostly and
to the supermarket occasionally.
trips and
a lot of communication and coordination in
the mailbox and a few
jumping runs. They are still
doing shuttle runs, so
when you need to leave tomorrow or
whenever you need to leave, you can
write an email to the shuttle team
and hopefully they can take you.
I don't even
see, I hope Floma is here
and some of the
other shuttle team people because
they really provide a service that, for
participants at least, makes it so much easier
to get to and from the event, so thank you
to them.
The power team has again,
rolled out an impressive amount of copper on
the venue so we could all get
something resembling 230
volts.
It is tricky
with the
resources we have
available and the way the power is wired
on the venue. It is very difficult to
provide stable power
at the voltages we would like to but
they are again and again
proving that it can be done with
a few
low voltages.
It is very hard to avoid completely
because with the weather we have been having
it is tricky keeping water out of everything.
And when you do take down your village,
please unplug stuff before you start touching
the roof and stuff so we don't get any
outages during teardown.
The power team has been very quick to respond
when there has been outages.
They go from the distribution point
to the
distribution point.
The power team has been very quick to respond
when there has been outages.
They go from the distribution point to the
distribution point and try to turn it off
and isolate and eventually find the culprit
and get it fixed and everybody
has power again. It is usually a quick process.
Thank you so much to the power
team, Flemming and the others.
As you know
we are, as you may know,
we are about 10 people or 11 people
in the ORGA group and it takes
maybe 50 people to run this event
or more. We would
be unable to
even begin considering doing this
if we didn't get all the help
from all the volunteers. Especially this
year it has been a joy.
There has been volunteer meetings every day
at 14 in the
what used to be the start end across from
the info desk until it disappeared.
And people have
been willing and
have been helping out even
on their own, discovering things
and just putting a message in the signal group
this was off, I fixed it, you don't need to
worry about it. It is such a
huge load off of
ORGA specs which means that
we've had excess cycles
to do other stuff that would usually
pile up towards the end of the event.
Stuff like economy
stuff that's usually
lying because that can be
pushed forward.
It means a lot to us because
when we get home we, like everybody else,
need to wind down and
that's difficult when you know you have a pile of work
waiting for you. And a lot of that
has already been done from day to day
and that's all thanks to all the volunteers.
Can everybody who helped out please stand up
and be applauded.
Thank you.
We are
preparing tear down
at
right after this talk we'll take down
this tent. I'll talk more about that
after. But tomorrow
at noon the event is officially over
and then we'll start taking down power and
network and all the infrastructure
until noon tomorrow
there will be full power and network
and everything. The only thing we are taking down
is this tent. But
we do need help with tear down
so if you have one or two
extra days and you can stick around and help us
sort, carry,
stack stuff, return
it, get it ready to return to
all the suppliers who are showing up
Thursday or Friday to do
pickups, then it
I mean the more the merrier. We can always
use more hands. Jonathan is cooking
from starting tomorrow evening
and it's always
yes.
And it is actually always
good fun even though it's of course
hard work and you have a full week
of event and maybe even build up
in your system already.
The more the merrier.
Not all of it is hard work and hopefully
the weather will treat us
nicely and
yeah, maybe some
bar leftovers. It's usually
a good time. Fires every
evening and everything you
can want. All
the work you could ask for.
Yeah.
Even a little helps. Even a half a day
or something. So please consider
staying for tear down.
We had the first coordination
meeting at 1600
in the bar start tent where we also had
the volunteer meetings during
during build up. The tent is disassembling
itself as we speak. It knows
what's about to happen.
So at
16 tomorrow in the
start tent by the bar we will have the first
coordination meeting and at 19 we will
have the first official tear down meal
and those of you who have tried it before know
after each meal there will
be 9, 13 and 19
we have a coordination meeting
and hand out the tasks.
We have the venue until
Saturday officially. We are aiming
for most things to be fixed by
Friday.
Barring any
violent weather or something can
easily delay things but
we think we should be
ready around Friday, Saturday.
We would like to know what you thought
of the event. Sometimes
it's easier to sit down and gather
your thoughts and put it in writing so
we have the, and it's easier for us
to remember.
Bornhack.dk feedback
please post positive and negative feedback
is greatly appreciated
and there's also an option
on the individual events in the program
to give feedback to the speaker
about the event and
that is also appreciated by the content team
because then they know what to get more of
next year so
the program can be even better.
If you lost anything or you found
something then please take it to the info desk
and we will try to get it untangled
and get the right stuff sent home with the right
people so nobody leaves anything
in funeral.
Our food vendor
will leave
tomorrow around 14
so there's time to get lunch tomorrow
and then there will be a
tear down meal in the
dinner in the cabin from 19
but you do need to
we're not serving
volunteer lunch tomorrow
so make sure you eat on your own
and then we will start taking
care of the meals starting tomorrow evening.
The food area
tent will stay up until
Thursday and we will start
taking it down there so there's also the option
of cooking for yourself over the next couple of days.
The food area team has been keeping
and we are talking about a
two man army or two person army
has been keeping the food area so
nice and tidy so let's give them a
big round of applause.
It's a fun story because
we didn't quite
understand what happened
suddenly the food area started being really
messy and dirty and we had to get cleaners
to fix it and everything and it turned out that
these two lovely people just missed a couple of
born hacks and wasn't doing all the cleaning
they were usually doing and suddenly
the absence of something
like that becomes very obvious when it's
not there so they have been doing this
we just maybe
forgot to notice or appreciate it
fantastic work thank you.
applause
okay we
have a tradition that goes back all
the way to the first born hack that
the speakers chair is built
carefully and lovingly and
artfully and then
when we are done with it we burn it
and it's kind of a weird tradition
but it is a tradition nonetheless
and
tomorrow evening whether permitting or
otherwise Thursday we are probably
having a fire anyway but
one of these days the
speakers chair is going
it's usually great fun
we can get rid of some hand sanitizer
while we are at it
laughter
so post camp
blues can be pretty rough
being surrounded by so many lovely
people and
enjoying the content and
the environment and the community
and the feeling of togetherness
and then returning to
a pretty bleak reality
on the outside of these walls can be
a little rough and
and that's I mean
there's nothing to do
you have to come down when you've
been up right but
there's some suggested remedies
for when you feel the sadness
watch some of the talks you missed
we are getting them up as soon as
we can you can play with your bass
or some of the previous years badges
you can organize all your pictures and
send the cool ones to us if they are
in a creative commons lies under
creative commons license so we can use
them we would greatly appreciate that
stay in touch online
we have the ISE channel we have the
signal groups talk to old and new
friends keep the community going
throughout the year
buy a ticket for born hack 2024
they will be for sale as soon as we've
recovered from this during the fall at
some point
and keep on hacking
applause
born hack 2024 has moved forward slightly
it is scheduled
for the 17th to the 24th
of July 2024
it's a Wednesday to Wednesday
we realize moving it is going to be
inconvenient for some people
for other people it will be convenient
there's no way to
make everybody happy with this
the current dates in
like mid-August that we've been doing
for some years
conflict with the big German and Dutch
camps in a way that makes it really
difficult for us to get the venue because
this venue has to be booked about two
years in advance and when the big Dutch
and German events don't decide on their
dates until eight months before then we
have
as you can see an impossible job of
picking a date that doesn't fit the
conflict because we are the small
camp if we end up being
at the same time a CCC camp or the
Dutch events we will lose
even Orga would not show up because we
want to go to the big events too
so we want to avoid that and
I mean
moving it ahead a bit means that we dodge
both the big German and the big
Dutch events there will be other conflicts
some people might be unable to attend
that have been coming for years we are very
sorry about that hopefully this will
allow other people to come and
at the very least it will make it so we
don't have to ask the venue people to
move other people who rented the venue
where we needed so they have to
cancel other
renters at Hylkedam so they can
fit us in
they did it twice
and we've been here in four years and it's just
too stressful and it's too much to ask
we cannot keep doing this and we cannot
demand from CCC or the Dutch
events that they put their dates
out several years in advance
that's not going to happen the only way we can do
this is to kind of
roll with the punches and move
to a place in the calendar that
doesn't have so many big events
so BornHack 2024
will be from the 17th to the 24th
of July we hope very much to
see you all there
speaking of avoiding Hacker Blues
another way of doing that is just to keep
on trucking when we're done with
Teardown we will
repeat our great
success from 2019
where the CCC camp was also right after
BornHack what we did was basically
finish Teardown pack everything
and then do a big convoy of
10-15 vehicles and just drive
down there with radios and
everything it was amazingly
good fun and we arrived
at CCC camp
maybe one vehicle didn't
get there until 48 hours later
it's quite a story you can ask Omni about that
but mostly
it went very well
and we are repeating it
so as soon as we are done here
everybody gets in their cars and we
drive
to CCC camp
you are welcome to
if you need to leave and come
back you can do that but most people will probably
stay and help with Teardown and then leave
when we are done it should be good fun
and it's a good way to recover
what better way to recover from BornHack
than by going to another
hacker camp
okay we have some inventory
left in the bar that we don't want to
carry around too much we would like
all of you to take it home
so we are selling booze bottles
and infodesk at reduced prices
you can get a full bottle for
200 hacks instead of 300
and there is Ackervit
and vodka and Säbeblöd
up there also mate
and beer I think
it should be already ready in the infodesk
I don't think they will open about now
and be open today
and also tomorrow
so when you leave
or about to leave consider going by there
and getting some nice Säbeblöd
or Ackervit or vodka to take home
it is also a good way to get rid of the hacker blues
okay I'm almost done
we would like some help
right now with taking down the speakers tent
this is a massively parallelizable
job we could almost do it
with the GPU
but we do need some help
so
it is
once people get up and start running
around it gets a bit chaotic
so I'm going to go over it slowly
and explain what we would like
and once we start
please everybody be careful
nobody hurt themselves we used to time
taking down of the speakers tent
we don't do that anymore because people are way too competitive
and will end up hurting themselves
and we of course
don't want that
we have a bunch of helmets that we are getting
for when the frame has to come down
but before all that
the very first thing is
you get up take the chair you are sitting on
and take it to the car
park right outside and stack it inside
that I'm guessing
two people inside it to stack
and then an anthill
of people taking out chairs
after that
we are taking out all the tables
there is a row of metal frames
out here the tables go on the metal frame
20 high or so
and then they get a ratchet strap
there will be organizers in these black
auger vests at all the stacks
and they know all of them know
how to stack it
so there is nothing worse than having
to restack a stack
of tables that turned out to be stacked wrongly
or a stack of floor plates
in two or three days
before they pick it up because our arms
are hanging down there at that point
so let's get it right the first time
so it's much better to do it a little slowly
a little more slowly
than to get it wrong and we have to redo it
and especially the chairs
sorry the tables and the floor plates
have historically been
sources of
restacking work
so let's get it right
and just check with the vests before you leave anything
even though you think you might know
it's a very
we're all very capable in our
daily work and stuff and it's easy to
I know how to do this I'll just get it going
but please check with somebody in a vest
before you place things
the chairs go to the auger van
the tables go on the
the frames
out here and the floors go
on the wooden pallets that have the big
wooden plates on top
the floors
kind of snap into each other when you stack them
so it's not like a pile
it's a very neat pile when you're done
so they click into each other
so they're completely straight the sides
so if they're not straight they have to be
restacked so put it down
get it into place so it clicks in
and then put the next one in
the video team
will start taking down all this stuff
and they will
handle that themselves
so tables and chairs and when we're done with that
we can start taking up the floor
and putting that down and taking down the sides
and folding those and putting them on the pallets
if you have questions
or doubts then stop
working and just stand around
look what others are doing or come ask an auger person
much rather get it
right than doing it twice
that is it we love you all
we will see you next year and thank you for
everything
applause