For our next speaker, we have Nikolaj, who will be talking about some sexy SSH hacks.
Make sure to give him a round of applause.
All right.
So hopefully you are ready for 45 minutes of random SSH talk.
So question, how many people have used SSH before?
A lot of people.
Great.
If you haven't used SSH before, this is going to be very boring.
How many have used it within the last month?
And a week?
Today?
Okay.
A lot of people, great.
So I use SSH maybe not on a daily basis, but at least on a weekly basis.
And I probably use it the same way as you use it, you know, SSH into a random server
and run a few commands.
Maybe copy and paste a file.
All the usual stuff.
And I've been using SSH for quite some time.
And then three years ago, I was sitting in the Pyjamas camp and we were creating these
weird machines.
And then I found out you can actually make a snake game in the login prompt of SSH.
So that looks, yeah, this is like some time ago, that looks like this.
So that kind of like piqued my interest in SSH.
And I was like, what else can I do?
And just for the fun of it, let's actually try to demo it.
So SSH, snake, whatever.
And then when I log in, normally you can log in with a username and password, right?
You can log in with a public key where you sign something.
But you can also send this like challenge response.
I think that's pretty cool because then your challenge can just be, you know, the full
game state.
And as you can see, I cannot actually render like NC escape codes.
So I'm going to do that.
I'm going to do that.
But I'm pretty sure three years ago at my setup at that time it worked.
So if this works for you and you don't get that weird like escape code in the top, then
I would love to see your setup because then it should actually work for you.
And you can see I'm kind of just, you know, my answer to the game state is a, you know,
arrow down and then enter and then I can play snake.
And it's, you know, a bit broken, but it kind of works.
I think that is very cool.
And I, you know, I kind of like building these.
We have machines.
So let me go back.
All right.
So this is the agenda.
And as I said, I did for the last about three years, I've just been writing down, you know,
fun, cool hacks from Hacker News and so on.
And then try to, you know, merge them into a presentation.
And then two weeks ago, somebody asked me, so whenever you say SSH, you mean SSH 2.0,
right?
What is SSH 1?
I was like, oh, shit, I have no idea.
So.
So we also.
All right.
So who am I?
My name is Anirudh Subol.
I have the domain sub.org, which is a bit weird because you have to purely code it.
So if you see this weird XN whatever domain, that is my domain.
I love doing weird hacks, making snake game as a login prompt.
And I also like to play capture the flag.
I think that's a very nice way to have a useful way or like a good reason to spend, you know,
three hours reading an RFC.
All right.
So.
Anyways.
What is SSH 1.0?
So if you look up the spec, the SSH 2.0 spec, you find this quote saying that, you know,
the best documentation is in the source code of a specific client of SSH 1.0.
And then there's a link to an FTP server.
And this is, you know, 20 years ago.
So I was a bit, you know, I wonder if I can find it.
But surprisingly, and this is why I love the Internet, right?
You just FTP into the web server.
And for 20 years, they have been hosting, you know, a random version of the source code
of SSH 1.0 and drinking games going back all the way to 1993.
So that's, I mean, that's fucking cool.
And I hope that in 20 years from now, we can still find the source code of, you know, old
defecated software.
Architecture wise, I read a bit on SSH 1.0, but I was like, it's not so interesting.
And from a very high level perspective, there's not a lot of changes.
Like, there's, you know, an awful lot of changes.
There's, you know, another hash function, another format of input outputs and so on.
But that's not the fun part.
I think the more fun part about SSH 1.0 is kind of like, why do we have SSH 1.0?
And you know, this is almost before my time, right?
So I don't have any memory of it.
But apparently before SSH, you had RSH and RCP and so on, right, where you could copy
paste the file.
And it, you know, it would do what you want.
It would do what you expect it to do, just, you know, without any encryption, yay.
Then came NSA and Let's Encrypt.
And today, it's another time, right?
So of course, we want to encrypt our communication.
So that's the kind of like the main diff, let's say it like that, right?
You just add TLS to something else.
All right.
So let's look at SSH from an IFC perspective.
And let's start with SSH.
Let's start with SSH.
And if you go to the IFC spec, you see there's like three main parts of it.
So it's very simple, right?
You connect to a server.
You do a like a key exchange dance, and then you have a secure connection to the server.
Then you have a protocol for authentication.
And then finally, when you have this secure authenticated protocol, you can split that
into like multiple logical channels, right?
So you can do port forwarding.
You can do X11 forwarding.
You can have a shell.
Right?
So I'll mostly be focusing on like the two top parts.
All right.
So the way I like to approach a new protocol is just to play around with it.
Before I would never start reading the IFC.
I would just connect to it.
So what happens when you just connect to an SSH server?
Let's try it.
Right?
So let's kill it.
So netcat my server port 22.
Right?
So I didn't really know what to expect, right?
I would maybe expect a bunch of binary stuff, but actually you get a text string.
And then if you put something in, you get another text string out, right?
So I went and looked at the spec, and the spec tells you, oh, this is the format of
the banner, right?
You need to see this from the server, and then you know as a client that you can connect
to it.
And already now from a security point of view, this is something you need to pass, right?
You need to look at, you know, what is the maximum length of the line.
Also what if you get a line that doesn't start with SSH 1?
Then the spec tells you, oh, just continue reading a line.
So you can set up a bunch of fun stuff.
You can set up something called, like the project name is awesome, right?
Endless SSH that just continues sending a banner forever.
And then if your client doesn't time out, or you stop after some amount of time, it'll
just continue being stuck trying to connect forever, right?
So maybe if you all set this up, then, you know, you'll have no spammers on the internet.
Just kidding.
Another thing you can do with this is that you have these polyglot files.
So you have a file where if you pass it as a PNG, it's a valid PNG with stuff at the end.
And if you pass it as a zip file, which you pass from the bottom, right, it's a valid
zip file with stuff in the front you just ignore.
And you can kind of do the same with SSH.
And you can have an SSH server sending a banner being like, I'm an HTTP server.
And if you're an HTTP client, you'll just read, you know, the length of the body, and
then you will stop.
And if you are an SSH client, you will just, you know, ignore the banner, and then you
will continue connecting.
So I tried to set that up the other day, and it works surprisingly well.
So if you do the same, now we can try to just curl it on port.
I didn't know what port to use.
So I used 4.22.
I think that's a pretty nice port for SSH and HTTP.
So I curl it.
I get, you know, a valid reply back.
It's just a web server, right?
But if I instead, instead of curling it, I do SSH on this port, then it's an SSH server.
Yeah.
So.
So this is not very useful, right?
But it's just fun to play around with the protocol.
And in a way, it's also a bit scary, right?
Because this is not, maybe not something that should be fun to play around with.
It's maybe not something that should be flexible, right?
So I think one takeaway is if you design software like this, maybe you should be more restrictive,
right?
Like maybe the banner is just one line, and, you know, no infinite amount of text can just
be there, right?
So yeah.
Polyglot.
Don't do that.
All right.
But let's not, you know, get, like, let's go back a step, right?
So I connect.
I get a banner.
I assume there's no malicious stuff.
How do I turn, you know, my connection into a secure connection?
All right.
So I do the normal Diffie-Hellman dance, right?
I generate a secret.
The server generates a secret, just like a number.
You combine the number with maybe a generator on a field, and then you get a public key.
The public key is random.
Like both the public keys are random.
Okay.
So you have a random write.
You have a secret.
You send only the public keys.
Holy Moses.
And then if you have a passive attacker, they can only see the public keys, and you cannot
turn the public key.
You have to combine a secret key with a public key to turn it into the shared secret.
So with this setup, we know that any passive attackers will be defeated, but there could
be an active attacker just replacing the key.
And in this case...
So I basically only get, like, a secure connection between me and somebody, right?
Me and an attacker, active attacker, or me or the actual server.
So what happens afterwards is the server will take its other public key and sign this transaction.
Yeah.
And then you can kind of...
The server can prove to me that this, whatever random public key I get, is actually signed
by the actual server.
But how do I trust the actual server key?
So there's a pretty nice quote from the RFC.
This is from...
I think it's from 2006 or something, right?
So it tells you this whole kind of, like, you need to map a server name into a public
key.
And how do you do that?
Well, I mean, you can have, like, a database of public keys, the known host file.
You can use, like, a certificate authority kind of setup, like we do with TLS.
Or you can use...
Or you can trust the key on first use, which is what we normally do.
We see a random key, just do, like, yes, I believe this key is good.
And then you save the, like, the hash of the key for next time.
But then the spec tells us, like, oh, but at some point, you know, in the future, of
course, somebody will create a, like, widely deployed key infrastructure that we can just
use.
And this is, again, like, 20 years ago, and we don't really have a good PKI, or do we?
So I'll probably not be very popular in this sense.
But we actually do have, like, a widely deployed PKI.
We have DNSSEC, which everybody loves to hate, but it's actually a pretty cool setup.
So if my domain name is signed by DNS, and I put my public key in DNS, then I, you know,
I can just distribute it.
And there's, like, a spec for that.
And the format is fairly simple, right?
You have, like, a dedicated DNS record, where you try to put in the algorithm of the key,
and then the type of the fingerprint. I've read a lot of the spec and SSH is very flexible.
Like whenever you can have multiple types, you will be able to have multiple types. It's
never just hash it with this algorithm. It's always have a type of the hash and then you
know, yeah. So it's a bit complicated, right? But this is how it looked originally on my
setup, right? So I have my domain name. I have multiple keys on my server because that's
the default. Then I pick one of the keys, host, DSA, whatever. I hash it and then I
put in the hash and DNS. Then in my local config, I can say, please look up DNS. Make
sure that the DNS record is authenticated and then stuff should just work without the
known host file and no trust on first use. So let's try that.
Okay.
And my domain name was. So first of all, you'll see I don't have like many keys left. I only
have like a single key. And I think that's a very sane default. Like just if you don't
need, I think by default, you know, your SSH server, whatever will come with like multiple
keys of types.
So on, you know, just delete the three of them and see if it still works. So in this
case, I'm using a Type 4 key, which I think when I took this screenshot was not a thing.
So it's still a very evolving set up. So this is like one of these fancy ED 255-119 keys.
And then you see I have a hash of the keys. So if I go to my SSH folder and my known host,
this one, and just kill it, right?
Then, now I have no idea about any server fingerprints,
but if I try to log into my website,
then, hopefully, ah, okay, damn.
And it doesn't work because I don't have my key added.
Yeah, that's because I have another demo later.
Demo gods, please, what is my password?
Is it not that one?
It should be that one.
Okay, whey!
I know my password, okay, awesome.
So, what I'm trying to do, I'm trying to SSH in the right,
but I have no idea what the fingerprint should be.
And hopefully, it's a bit slow, I'll get in, right?
So, that is pretty awesome.
And what happens if you try to then authenticate
to something without a fingerprint in DNS?
Let's take this one, then you'll get the normal,
you know, prompt saying here, say,
a fingerprint of this server's key.
I have no idea, do you want to trust on first use?
I can be yes, no, whatever.
And what happens if I try to log into a broken setup?
Then, I'll get this big fat warning saying, you know,
I actually found a fingerprint,
and the fingerprint is wrong, right?
So, like, an even bigger error message.
But I think this is a nice setup because if you,
if you have a fingerprint, and you have a fingerprint,
and you have a fingerprint, and you have a fingerprint,
if you manage a lot of servers,
at least in my experience, every now and then,
you might change the key for various reasons,
or you might lose your known host file, or whatnot.
So, it is, instead of just being yes,
then, you know, try to put it in DNS.
It's pretty cool.
All right.
Yeah.
Yes.
Okay, so what is the requirement, right?
So, you need a DNS provider that supports
this very specific record type, right?
SSH, FP.
So, that's a bit annoying.
Then, you need to trust DNS, right?
So, you need DNS on your domain and on your clients.
And then, I don't know how many people used Gratis DNS,
but they changed to one.com,
and one.com did not support SSH FP,
and they, you know, this changed, occurred, why?
And then, I don't know how many people used Gratis DNS, but they changed to one.com, and one.com did not support SSH FP, and they, you know, this changed, occurred, why?
I was testing around and changing my key,
so I was stuck with this, you know, forever warning,
because I cannot change my DNS record
because I'm stuck on a provider that does not support it,
and I'm using a new key.
So, that was a bit annoying.
But anyways, they support it now, which is pretty cool.
All right.
So, going back a bit, right?
So, I'm connecting to a server,
we're doing the Diffie-Hellman dance,
I'm trusting the key because I have some way of trusting it.
What then, right?
So, I have a, like a shared secret,
the stuff below, in the bottom of the picture, if all.
And so, for some of the next slides,
I just have some stuff, you know,
I like about SSH and some stuff I don't like.
So, what I like is they have this exchange hash,
so the key, of course, you never would,
don't ever share that, right?
Don't put it in log files, don't do stuff like that.
But you would love to have a way to like reference to the key.
So, it's a very simple protocol set up, right?
You just be like, here's the key,
that secret, hash the key, and then this is public.
I think that's a pretty nice set up,
because then you can like refer to this,
you know, temporary set up we have.
Then next, we kind of like want to split this key
into multiple keys, and what SSH does is,
it just hashes together, you know,
this secret key with, you know, the letter A,
the letter B, the letter C, and so on.
I kind of like this set up, it's pretty simple.
Probably, like, if you should design a new SSH 3.0,
whatever, you should use a, like,
a real key iteration function.
But, I mean, this is a pretty neat, like, easy set up.
But there's something a bit weird, right?
Why do I need so many keys, right?
It's quite a lot of keys.
And that's the next thing, right?
So, the spec tells you, you need to, like,
you do have a secure connection,
you have a bunch of, you know, packages
with control messages going back and forth,
and then you agree on, should we compress data,
which type of cipher should we use,
and so on.
And the spec tells you, you must be able to,
you know, independently of the direction,
change the selected cipher and compression, and so on.
So, it's perfectly valid for me to send compressed AES
to my server, and then get uncompressed
DES-encrypted data back.
And that's super, super weird.
But it's valid SSL, SSH.
So, again, I would love to see this being removed
from the spec, just, you know, it should be the same.
Right, I should never want to use one cipher,
going to my server, and then another cipher going back.
Okay, so, I can encrypt data, but how do I know
somebody is not going to just, you know,
do random bit flips, right?
AES does not protect against bit flips.
At least, you know, I can do some stuff with it.
So, the underlying protocol is called
the binary package protocol in SSH.
And the format is quite simple.
It's, you know, you encrypt some data,
and then you have a, like a message authentication code
giving you integrity after the encrypted data.
And then, you know, this inner package is just, you know,
the length of the package, the length of some padding,
and then the package, and then the padding.
It looks like this.
And this is a very weird setup, because how, like,
how do we pass it?
So, you get some ciphertext, but you maybe don't know
how much ciphertext it needs.
And the only way to figure out is if you decrypt
the first block, and then you can,
after you have decrypted, like, the first block
of the ciphertext, you can figure out,
ah, I need to read a few more packages,
and then you can check the MAC.
But that means I can now do, I can start tampering
with, like, the first part of the, of whatever this is,
right, because you have no idea how to check it
without just decrypting it.
And then you can do these, like, kind of like
active attack against the cipher.
For instance, if I want to decrypt a package
that contains all F, or I believe it's, like,
F, F, F, F, F, F, F, and I put that as the first package,
and you decrypt it, and you figure out, oh,
so the length must be F, F, F, F, F,
so you just continue reading data from the wire
until, you know, you get F, F, F, F, F data,
which, of course, won't happen, right?
But if it's zero, zero, zero, zero, zero,
then, you know, you know that there should be no more data,
so you can check the MAC, the MAC will fail,
and you close the connection.
So now you can do these attacks where you can at least
guess some stuff from the cipher.
This is called encryption and MACing,
and it's a bit kind of like in, I would say,
2000 wipes, where you didn't really know how to do it,
right, there's also encryption, then MACing,
which is almost the same.
What you should do is called,
sorry, MAC then encrypt,
what you should do is encrypt then MAC, ETM,
and in ETM, you just do the order a bit different,
but now you need to, now you can check the MAC
before you even try to decrypt data.
But this require the length to be public, right,
but the length is already a bit public, right,
because you already need to know, if you're an attacker,
you can just, you know, look at the length
of the encrypted data on the wire,
so it doesn't really leak anything.
And if you want to enable this,
then you can configure your server and your client
to accept only ciphers ending with ETM.
So you'll also see that in my config later,
that you can just go in and enable this, right,
so this is an OpenSSH extension,
so it's not part of the original spec,
but it's a much better way of doing it.
And, yeah.
So there's another, like, a cool trick, actually,
as I said to Stas, which is that the MAC is not only the,
I was lying a bit here, right,
it's not only the inner part of the message,
it's actually the, whoops, it's actually a sequence number,
and then the inner part of the message.
And the sequence number is not sent over the wire,
but it's just, you know, a counter going up,
and the idea here is that if you reorder packages,
then the sequence number will be incorrect,
and then you can detect somebody reordering packages.
So this is pretty neat, but I read a lot of, you know,
message threads about people being a bit annoyed,
because it also means that the input to the MAC function
is not the same as the input to the encryption function.
So if you wanna replace all of this with just AES
in GCM mode, which is authenticated,
then you have this, you know, a bit annoying thing
where you need to, you're not encrypting the same stuff
as what you're actually checking.
It's not an issue, it's just a bit annoying.
So yeah, somebody spent a long time on that.
All right, so I have a way to connect to a server.
The server, we agree with, we generate a secure channel.
I can authenticate that the server is actually
who it tells me it is, but the server have no idea who I am.
So you need to, now we go to the next step,
the authentication protocol.
And in the authentication protocol,
you select a method, and there's, of course, a few more,
in later extensions.
What I find pretty fun is that password authentication
is not required, so it's valid, again, to be an SSH server,
and be like, no, I don't wanna do passwords.
I think that's pretty cool.
I guess most people, the first time you use SSH,
you just have a username and password.
But actually, you can be like,
I only want to support public keys.
Another thing is, you can also have a non method,
so you can just connect to a server, be like, I'm root,
and I don't need to authenticate.
I just want to authenticate who I am.
Of course, the server is not going to allow that, right?
But it is technically valid for the server to be like,
okay, I guess.
And then, yeah, let's see, oh, wait a minute.
So you have this ping pong flow where you get a list of,
the server can tell you, oh, but you need public key
and the passwords.
Or for the snake game I did initially, you have this challenge,
for the snake game I did initially, you have this challenge,
response method.
And for every reply you get from the server,
the server can tell you that you had a partial success
when you logged in.
So for instance, you'd be like,
I would like to log in with this username and password.
You log in, and then the server's like, that's good,
but you need to prove a bit more.
So you can also use this to have two factor when you log in.
Yeah, of course, if you do two factor,
you should also have some kind of rate limits, right?
Because it's very easy to boot for us otherwise.
And this is the request you sign if you use a public key.
It's fairly simple, right?
You have, you put in, I would like to do,
like the service name is, I think,
the difference between X11 forwarding and just a shell.
You put in your username,
then you put in your session identifier.
That's the public part of the shared secret from before.
So that's pretty cool,
but that kind of like binds this signature
to the channel I have right now
that is generated uniquely to this session.
And then I put my public key, and that's it.
There's like one field missing from this one,
which is not part of the spec,
but it would have made the spec so much nicer.
So I'm only signing that,
I'm now connecting to whatever this is.
But if I connect to one server,
and from that server I'd like to connect to another server,
and to another server, and to another server,
then this, which is agent forwarding,
we'll talk about later,
then all these signatures,
they will be signed by my key on my laptop,
but I don't know what I'm assigning.
I'm just signing random session identifiers.
So the other servers along the way, they can just be like, okay,
you would like to connect to GitHub?
Yes, just sign this signature.
And then they actually are in the process of connecting
to like an internal server or whatnot.
So this would have been much nicer
if you had the public key of who you are actually connecting to.
All right, and then there's a pretty nice project
by a guy called Filippo,
who has scraped all public GitHub keys.
And then when you log into the server,
I'll send my,
my key, whoops,
that one, like the key in the bottom of it.
And then he can just, you know,
do like a reverse lookup, right?
So this key must be somebody.
And that works quite well.
Let's try it.
Filippo.
Yes, I'd like to connect.
And then,
and then he can look up that the key I have is connected
to my GitHub, right?
So that's, that's very revealing.
And you can actually also do the opposite,
which is pretty cool.
So when you connect to an SSH server,
you can send a list of public keys,
and then you can ask the server,
which of these public keys works for this user on this account?
On this system.
And then the server can reply back saying,
oh, the, you know, the third key works.
And the reason you,
you can do that is because let's say you have a,
like a physical hardware key you need to click to use,
then you don't want the user to,
to, you know, click a bunch of hardware keys
to find the right key that actually works.
And, but it also means that,
let's say I want to,
to, to reveal some kind of a Tor hidden service.
All right, then I might SSH into the hidden service.
And then I might just, you know,
start from the, from the beginning of all the GitHub keys
and try like, can this key authenticate?
Can this key authenticate?
And then maybe I'll find a key and then I can, you know,
look up that somebody has access to us to,
might have access to a hidden service,
like a public name.
So that's, I think that's also a bit of a,
I don't know if I like it or if I don't like it
as part of the spec.
I understand the idea, but I, I think it's a bit,
I think it's a bit of a, I think it's a bit of a,
I think it's a bit weird
that you can actually query a server.
The server can, of course, just lie,
say like, no, none of the key works.
But then if you actually use the key, it will work.
All right, so if I,
if I SSH from, from my system into another system,
and then I would like to SSH from that other system
and further along the way,
then I probably don't want to copy paste my keys around.
So I can use,
something called agent forwarding.
And let's actually test that, right?
So,
so I have a demo system.
On the demo system, I start an SSH agent.
Then in my agent, I add a, one of my keys.
So now I, it basically just a background process, right?
Then if I, from this system, SSH into a,
excuse me,
a moment.
To this system.
Whoop.
Okay, so I'm, you know, from one system,
jumping into another system.
Nope, sorry.
And I'm forwarding my agents.
Then from the terminal in the bottom,
I'll jump to the second system directly.
And from this system, I'm going to look at what,
which file I attempt.
So that's a few files, but nothing, nothing important, right?
So from the top system, the demo box,
I'm jumping into the Hetzner box.
And from the Hetzner box, I now have forwarded agents.
So if I look at and attempt again,
I should be able to see an SSH folder.
And if I go to that folder,
then I can see that there is a socket available.
So if I write something to this socket,
it will be forwarded back from,
through the SSH connection, back to the original box.
And this is very dangerous, right?
Because if I'm root on the, on the bottom window,
then I of course have access to the socket, right?
The socket can only be protected by
whoever the first user is.
So that means that I can now, from the, from the Hetzner box,
from the bottom, from the attacker's point of view,
I can just ask the socket to sign a request
on the behalf of the first user.
And so the demo is a bit boring
because you just set an environment variable,
and then you use all the normal SSH tools.
So I'm not going to demo it.
But what is cool is that in very new versions of OpenSSH,
you can actually use something called agent restriction.
The problem is agent restrictions require changes
to all of your binaries, right?
Like your SSH agent, SSH add, and SSH statement.
But if you have these newer versions,
then you can specify a conflict like this.
When I add, before when I added the key,
I just added to the agent, you know,
this key is available for everybody
to do basically everything, right?
Sign stuff on my regard.
With this, I can do basically anything, right?
With this new setup, I can tell the agent,
when you get a request to sign something,
you should actually check what you're signing.
So in this case, I'm saying, if I'm trying to,
so like a common case, I think, would be,
I'm often SSH-ing into my server,
and for my server, I would like to SSH into GitHub
because I have my stuff on GitHub, right?
But I don't want to copy my file,
my private key to my server.
So it would be nice just to be,
to make it a little bit easier.
To add the restriction that the agent
must only sign the user git on the domain
git.data.coop, for instance.
And if you go back like a ton of slides,
you see that that's not possible with this format.
So you need to change the format, right?
I can only check the username
because this is the request I'm getting on my agent to sign.
But with this new setup, you know,
there are some changes to the, to, to, to, to, to, to, to, to,
to what I'm actually signing,
which is why you need all the changes in the binaries.
And, but then you can actually, you know,
change these things.
Another kind of like implementation detail is that
it doesn't really make sense to restrict stuff
on a hostname basis,
because one key can have multiple hostnames,
or how do I kind of like check that?
So what actually happens behind the scenes is that,
SSH add will look up what is the host key
for these domains and then add the restriction there.
Right?
This is fun and awesome, but it's very new,
so it might not work, but if you can use it,
then you should absolutely restrict stuff
if you're going to forward your agents.
And then you should absolutely only forward your agent
if you must, because it's very dangerous,
because if somebody can attack the server
you're SSHing into, then they can just ask your agent
to sign anything.
All right, so that's kind of like the first part
of the presentation, and then let's go through
some other, you know, random notes.
First is, if you're using an ISA key,
which you might be, because that's the standard,
then you know, don't, this is ugly as fuck.
Instead, you should generate a new key of type,
an elliptic curve key if you can,
and you get the same security level,
it's just much smaller, which is very cool,
and some, often it's much easier to actually implement.
So, absolutely do that.
Yay.
Next, you can do some pretty neat stuff
with FIDO keys, like USB sticks,
but also if you have the mid-ID device,
you can also use that.
I forgot it, so I cannot share a demo with it.
One, a bit, and, and, and, and, and, and, and, and, and, and,
and, and, and, and, and, and, and, and, and, and, and,
and, I'm still playing around
cause there's not a FIDO key,
okay?
This ad also, Google overwhelmed an E-mail system
of the ED245 format to GTP is,
if you have natural- generatedthing.
But go for it if you have a headless,
but it's possible to,
so you'll have the extra,
of course you guys can do this,
if you, to be an E 3 dots focus,
and then you are that way.
Doesn't, it's pretty easy because you can use them for,
oh, oh, T.
I think that stands for security key, maybe.
The key is very long, because it actually contains
a proof that, or it can contain a proof
that it was signed on some hardware.
So they are a bit long and annoying.
You can also, I think, include in the key
if you need to physically click on the key
to sign the request, or if you can just send the request
to the key and then it will automatically sign.
I was hoping that when they implemented this,
they would do some kind of fancy,
how do we cheat the key, because the FIDO2 standard
is not very, that's meant for browsers, right?
How do you merge SSH into that?
They're not doing anything fancy,
like trying to get the key to believe
that it's actually signing a web request,
but it's an open SSH request.
They're just telling the key,
what I showed before, what you're signing.
You're signing something completely different
if you're using one of these keys.
So that's not very fun.
You can most likely also use a TPM, which is very cool.
So I think this is from Ledger,
the Bitcoin, crypto, whatever company.
They have actually been pushing pretty hard for this.
So the TPM standard is apparently very new.
There's a tool called TPM2PKCS11,
which is like the talk to a smart card standard.
And it is most likely in your distro.
Today, so I tried it before and it worked super nice.
And that's why my key was failing.
So let's see, go back here.
So in this demo, I have no identities added
to my SSH agents, meaning that it's going to fail
when I log into stuff.
And if I look in my SSH folder,
you see that I have no keys in my folder.
That's why I had to do the SSH add before.
So you would very much expect that if I try to SSH into something,
that I have no keys in my folder. That's why I had to do the SSH add before.
Then that will fail.
I have no keys on disk.
So let's try it.
And then it asked me for a pin.
And now in this case, SSH is a label in my TPM.
And I really hope I can remember the key.
And then it worked, right?
So this is very cool.
Now it means that if you had my laptop,
there's nothing to steal.
You can ask my laptop, there's nothing to steal.
You can ask my TPM live to sign something.
But when I close down the screen,
or shut down, pull out the battery,
then I know that nobody can re-sign stuff on my behalf.
There's a bunch of stuff that doesn't really work,
or you get a bunch of error messages when you do it,
but that's, yeah.
All right, so I have a bunch of random configs,
and I'll go through them very quickly,
because I guess you all know them.
So aliases are very cool.
And let's actually look at my SSH config.
SSH config.
So aliases.
I have a bunch of stuff that I just don't remember
the name of, so you can add this maps to that,
and then you can also tap complete it.
And if you have weird options,
then you can also add that to your config.
Then if you ever do like a SCP and you copy paste a file,
but you cannot remember what that path is again,
then you should for sure look into multiplexing
or control master.
Let's see if we can do a good demo.
So currently it is disabled.
So if I go, let's remove all of this.
Let's see.
So what is the, I'm trying to tap complete,
oh it's slow, slow, slow.
Oh, okay that's a root, what's in root?
So slow, right?
Let's enable the control master.
And let's try again.
Oops.
What's in root?
Okay.
That's slow, that's good.
in root, it takes a long time to generate the first connection, but now I am connected
so I should be able to easily see, there is a bunch of files in temp, I don't want to
show my files, but I can actually pretty quickly tap complete stuff and how does it work? If
I go to my SSH folder, I have a folder called control master and in this folder I just have
a socket and the socket, whenever I need to create a new connection, it just looks
in this folder, is there already a socket. You see that the socket is a user name at
domain port and that comes from the config, so I spent a lot of time debugging why random
options didn't work and in my case it was because I was adding the option down here,
but I had a control master already open.
So SSH did not know that I changed the options, so you see RP, RHP, whatever, you can add
more stuff to that and it probably should be much more like, I would love for this to
be like a hash of everything, every single option, so if I went down here and changed
one of the options, it would automatically know that it has to create a new socket, that
doesn't work, you easily get stuck on that. And then you see this is to get the TPM working,
adding all the ETM stuff, if you use kitty then you probably want to ask, automatically
send environment variables to unbrick your terminal and so on. So a lot of options, they
are very nice, look into it, jump host, also instead of first SSH-ing into something and
then SSH-ing further along.
All right, hardening, if you change all the configs I showed you, ETM, removing old ciphers
deleting old keys and so on, you probably will see this in your log, random people trying
to connect to a server, to brute force and then they can't even do like a key exchange,
I think that's pretty cool, I hope some spammer somewhere is trying to debug why they also
get where they were in their int, that would be fun.
There's a very nice tool called SSH-out audit, where you can test both your server and your
client, they write something about, you know, there's some ciphers made by NIST that might
be backdoored.
I think that's a bit bullshit, but what not.
And I tried to get recently this CV found in agent forwarding, and the idea was that
if you do agent forwarding, then on, so I'm on one server, I go to another server and
I have forwarded my agents, right, I have a socket that you can use to ask my agent
to sign something.
That's bad by itself, but what if I on this attacker system could get my agent to do RCE,
if I could do like a remote code execution on the original system.
And then there are some people who found out that, you know, there's a bug, it's written
in C, surprise, surprise, but actually I couldn't get it to work, which was a bit annoying,
right?
But to get it to work, you would do the following.
First of all, you would do the following.
First, you would send the socket of whoever you are targeting, and then you can use SSH
add to ask the agent on the target system to load a library, and apparently there's
no like restrictions on what library can you load.
The only restriction is it has to be a library already on your system.
And then they found out that if you install the right amount of packages from, at least
from, you know, some Ubuntu packages.
Then you can actually get them to execute code by just loading and unloading them.
And that's very amazing.
So in this case, if you load this binary, then your stack will be executable.
Then there are like, of course, there's a buffer overflow in some codes.
So you could, you could store a bunch of stuff on the stack.
Then if you load this library, there's a, whatever signal handler that would be registered,
but it'll put it on the stack.
It'll point to some memory address.
And then you unload the library, so now it points to nothing, right?
Then you load this one, and it has some kind of no deletes thingy.
So now this sick handler will point to some random place in this new library.
You unload it, but it has no deletes, so it's still there.
And then if you load this one, it will trigger the signal handler.
The signal handler will run some random code somewhere, which will end up jumping to your
stack, and the stack is full of knobs.
And then some codes.
So this was like, from a research perspective, super amazing.
From an SSH perspective, it's not very relevant, right?
If you do agent forwarding on a system that is already compromised, you have already lost.
Yeah, so very cool, look into it.
Final remarks.
I was expecting the counter to be much higher, right, but I only lost access to my server
one time.
I lost access three years, and then I had the broken DNS.
But if you play around with stuff, make sure you can get access, right?
It's very easy to lock yourself out of the system.
And then, final final, when you go home and generate a bunch of new fancy ED-25519 keys,
then you can use OpenSSH SSH copy ID to just copy all your keys over to servers.
This is a very nice tool.
So you just, you know.
Copy all my keys to a new server, and then you're good.
So that's actually it.
Yeah.
Do we have any questions?
So you just said.
You can use SSH copy ID to copy all of our keys to a server.
Would it, I mean, would it make sense to have, like, different SSH keys for different servers,
or is that not really that important?
Yeah.
Yeah, I should probably correct it a bit.
So you can copy all your public keys to a server, but of course it makes you, if you
have many public keys, you might restrict, like, if I have one very important server,
I probably don't want all of my keys there.
I don't need the, for fun.
Yeah.
I don't protect the keys or whatnot.
So for sure, if you actually do this on a mall, not on just a hobby level, then you
should not just randomly copy keys, yeah.
Thanks for that talk.
I was wondering, do you know, having looked at the protocol, if you don't verify the server's
public key, but you're using public key authentication, so the server knows your public key.
But you don't know it, can somebody actually do a man-in-the-middle attack, or could they
just give you a fake shell?
Like obviously they could give you a different server, so you try to log in and the man-in-the-middle
just gives you a different server completely.
You can't authenticate the server.
But it seems like the encryption could be reliant on your authentication key in some
way, and I'm wondering if you know if SSH does that.
Like if you're a man-in-the-middle and the user doesn't know the server's public key,
can you actually man-in-the-middle?
Can you man-in-the-middle them when they're using public key authentication?
Yeah, so you are going to sign the session identifier hash, right?
And that should point uniquely to my current session.
So that would be towards the real server or towards a completely fake man-in-the-middle
server.
So if I haven't checked, like if I don't know the server's public key and I'm connecting
to a wrong server, then yeah.
Then I'm not sure.
I think I would have to draw it, but I think I would be cheated, but you cannot take my
proof and forward it to the other server.
Yeah.
Yes, I agree with that.
So the server key is in the key exchange phase, which is quite early, way, way before there
is any authentication of the client.
Going on.
And once the client gets an authentication challenge for the public key, it will sign
it, right?
Yeah.
And there's no verification of the server anymore at that stage.
Any more questions?
Okay.
Thank you.
What?
Don't fire me so late.
Let's give Nicolai another round of applause for a fantastic talk.