To find information on how an internet exchange operates, there is some information that is
a very high level and doesn't really explain too much.
And then there is also the administration of talking to RIPE and what objects do you
need and how do you get IP addresses and stuff like that.
There's many policies included, and yes, I wrote everything as an acronym soup because
that's pretty much what it is.
So Labix is a community-run internet exchange.
We made this because I like BGP and network routing, and I would like to play more with
it.
So in Labasat we have a facility called Labicolo.
We will get more into that.
At some point.
But we offer a service called a route server.
Again I will get more into it.
What that is, we can assist you in how should you talk to a local internet registry to get
an AS number and IP addresses.
You can actually start looking into real network routing stuff and not just play with it in
a virtual machine.
You can do BGP stuff, BGP security, and research and build on what is RPKI and things like this.
Also, yes, I wrote 9KM2, we don't have that currently, but we will very soon set that
up to 9KM2.
It's currently 1,500, like most.
So what is an internet exchange?
Well, it's a very simple way.
It's a VLAN on a little switch.
It's a very simple way.
And then some networks are connected to it.
Well, that doesn't really say much.
So let me explain what is the internet.
First, this is how you do it, how to do internet routing or network routing.
We have some prefixes.
You find a facility that would like to host you, that includes some power and cooling
and stuff like that.
You install your machines.
You set up a routing daemon.
There could be like a bird.
If you do that, it's a bird.
You can use Linux or other things.
Then you have some peers that are operating network operators.
And you will peer with them to get their content.
And then you also need a transit uplink, which is how do you, well, now you're in like facility
with, and you can connect with the other people in that facility, but how do you connect with
the rest of the world?
We're not Copenhagen.
It's just, it doesn't contain the whole network.
Yeah.
It's just the whole internet.
So you need a transit that says we will like to transport the traffic from your network
over to the destination and profit, I guess.
So let's set a scenario.
You want Eyeball ISP.
You are currently located in Hyggedam, coincidentally where we are, and an Eyeball ISP is that we
have some customers.
And Eyeballs, they consume content that could be watching their favorite series or watching
the news or somehow get content.
You don't host servers necessarily.
So for you to be able to have, to say, like when a customer wants to, when a customer
wants to...
Connect to another provider to get content, you need some IP addresses.
That is, well, hopefully most of you know, some is like an address, like a postal address
where I do the thing you need to go.
You also need that for your servers.
Then yeah, you need housing and fiber stuff.
I won't go into the fiber stuff.
I don't dig too much into layer one things.
Layer three, in this case.
So how does the network connect with other networks?
You probably cannot see my mouse.
So we have in the left, it's called, well, in this case, it's called Acme.
This is one network provider.
What if Acme is, Acme one and Acme two are not located in the same city and the same
facility?
Well.
So in our lovely picture here, we can have, we have two transit providers that need to
go through first.
So says Comcast and say DDT, which are some providers in the world that exist.
And then we can go into Acme number two.
That could be where all the nice services are hosted or similar.
It could also be that.
What if Acme one is not located in the same city and the same facility?
Well, Acme one and Acme two are located in the same city, they're just not really connected.
And it would be perhaps too expensive to connect them.
So let's look at what is an autonomous system.
It says AS one and AS two here, AS something, something, something in other ones.
So we have a lovely RFC that describes AS as a connected group of one or more prefixes
run by one or more network operators.
Which has a set of prefixes.
Has a single and clearly defined routing policy.
I can explain a tiny bit more on that.
But it is the most clear explanation I have found until now.
So that's why it's here.
So an AS is an organization, as I said, and we have used what we call AS numbers or ASNs
to identify.
Identify an organization.
That could be your transit provider.
That could also be your friends in the other side of the facility.
And they have some, well, you and the other ASs have some prefixes allocated to them so
you know where the content should go or the traffic should go.
So the routing policy.
Well it's found in databases.
Regional internet.
Registry database like RIPE's database.
These routing policies says something like I have authorized to use these IP prefixes
and they should, so now see IP prefixes at all traffic to these prefixes should be different
to me.
It could also be that you have some customers that may be a little bit more fancy with their
networking.
And they would also like to announce through you.
So you are their transit.
And that could be some business customers, for example, or in our case, Labitat or me
where Labitat is my uplink.
I have included a lot of places, links to things that could be read more since I found
this useful.
I have left them in.
Okay.
So peering and transit.
Well first peering is that we agree it's free to both of us.
There is some optics fibers included and like things like cross connect where you have to
like you are located in data center and you would like to connect to the other side of
the data center.
So the data center takes a bit of money for that.
It costs usually some X amount per month.
Okay.
So that's that.
So we only send traffic to each other.
That is totally fine.
As long as we don't, that's like a balance and we don't tip the balance where I send
a lot of traffic to you and you don't send that much traffic to me.
But it's fine.
We peer with a lot of people.
Then we also have transit.
So transit is, yes, where it costs per megabit.
And this I will transport traffic from you to other networks.
Okay.
As I always said, it's if you want to go to other side of the globe, you perhaps don't
have the funds to lay a cable over the Atlantic or something similar.
So someone has done that for you and you would just pay them.
Well what is the instant exchange then?
We keep local traffic local.
We avoid what we call the Trombone effect.
This is an image.
Okay.
This is an image of the United States, San Francisco, New York, and Los Angeles.
So what would be the shortest path between San Francisco and Los Angeles?
Clearly not New York at least.
That can sometimes happen with how due to some characteristics with our network routing,
you usually don't have a lot of traffic.
Okay.
You look at the shortest path, for example, in many, many cases, also other things.
But it could be that your transit just didn't have a direct connection between San Francisco
and Los Angeles.
So you would need to go over New York.
So we have the instant exchange to avoid these kind of things.
It also gives lower latency because, again, we keep local traffic local.
It's easier to interconnect with other networks.
So what if we are two small providers and we don't necessarily have the need to connect
to each other?
But why should we pay transit when we are located in the same facility?
We can't justify paying the fees to have this cross-connect active.
We have similar things.
So when you have the internet exchange, it makes things a bit easier when you are local.
So here is a very, very simplified topology of an internet exchange point.
Well there are four providers of some kind.
They all connect with one link into a Meet Me room, as we call it.
And they connect to a meeting room.
With this, we now, instead of everybody connecting to each other, I have one cable to you, you
have one cable to you, I have one cable to you, we just have one cable in and then we
get the traffic via that cable.
That could be like a larger cable, for example.
What I showed here is, yes, we do have the meet-me-room, but in an internet exchange,
we also can go from what we call bilateral to multilateral peering.
It is from many-to-many to one-to-many, as the image also shows.
We have the route server.
Again, I have explained this because it was not easy for me in the first five hours to
understand, why do we need a route server?
It was not clear, but now it is more clear for me at least.
So the control plane traffic is now aggregated to the route server.
We don't necessarily aggregate the data plane traffic.
but we at least control the traffic.
It kind of looks like this.
So we need less maintenance, we need less points,
like less configurations that you can screw up with.
If I'm already connected to a route server
and we have some new clients that comes to our IXP
and then joins the route server,
we can immediately peer with each other
without necessarily agreeing
and talk to each other directly.
We can have our peering policy set as,
yes, I would like to accept everybody who's on the route server.
We can also have a little more sense
on what is going on in our IXP, like traffic stats.
So our route server looks like this.
It's a very, very, very, very, very, very, very, very,
very, very small machine.
It uses six for the power.
We chose this because it was free and we had it,
I had it in my storage.
So it fits really well for our use case.
The Labasat Internet Exchange is only
for very small devices, embedded devices,
like APU2 or Raspberry Pi.
So,
yeah, it didn't really make sense to have a large machine
that could do fancy stuff and have many more routes
and things like that.
So the software is, well, Debian is,
we use a route server as a config parser
to then to create our BERT config.
We use BERT as a BTP speaker.
So a route server does a very, very, very, very, very, very,
there's a lot of automation of,
like we have a list of clients and we have some,
we have some AS sets and we have some prefixes
and similar things.
And then a route server creates all the,
all the 300,000 line config files.
So we don't need to maintain that.
Yes, server hosting, it's located in Labicorps,
again, there's links all over the place.
And we, yeah, Oliver and Eskian will go more into details
on the Labicorps on a talk on Sunday, so.
But there's a very short version is,
it's intended for things like Raspberry Pis and APU2s.
But at Bornhag, you can connect to a Labifer village,
or you can connect via BERT.
You can connect via VLAN, which I haven't received yet.
So, yeah, but you can connect.
So we have, we have made it so,
since our uplink is very nice,
that we have transported the VLAN via Labitat
and then over FiberVue,
and which is then Bornhag's uplink.
And that means we can have the whole VLAN transported,
and that means we can have the whole VLAN transported,
and that the whole peeing line transported down to the camp.
That's a bit weird, but we can, since we could, we did it.
So our switch looks like,
our switch and our rack looks like this.
It's a horrible mess.
But again, the switch was a pre-used thing,
it's a Cisco switch.
We are all using it.
It could do Mac port filtering, and that's like,
fine, it's nice for writing loops.
So, yeah, it's a switch,
that's not really much to show,
other than they can do that.
We actually tested out a switch which we found out
could not use Mac port filtering, so yeah.
That's why we keep this.
We have a peeing policy set up.
So when you join a Internet Exchange or join,
start peering with other networks,
it, you accept that peering policy.
So it could be like, I only accept traffic
that is distant to you, and how, and sorry,
you only, I want to send traffic distant to you,
and you want to send traffic distant to me.
In a Internet Exchange, we have a few more things,
not much.
Not much. Well, we say a few things, not much.
We can say we will accept IPv4, ARP and IPv6 addresses, Ethernet frames, sorry.
We do not like ProxyARP, we do not like OSPF and other kinds of things.
We will do make port filtering again to avoid a lot of loops and the same with ProxyARP,
it creates funny things on the network.
So yes, we will not, routes learned through the peering network are not allowed to be
announced by BGP and we also would not like to be connected via a tunnel of some kind
where the MTU is lower than 1500.
So this means you have to be directly connected to us and not a remote IEX which defeats a
lot of the purposes of an internet exchange.
Though I have nothing against remote internet exchanges, but for all purposes, it didn't
really fit.
So well, you have to get some IP address.
Also, internet resources, I call it here, but yeah, IP allocations.
So an AS number and an IP address is like, there is a large pool, I usually call it a
cake, so a large cake, IANA owns a cake and then RIPE, which is the organization handing
out IP addresses in Europe and Russia and Middle East.
They get a bit smaller.
They get a bit smaller piece of the cake, which they can then hand out.
So you have the local internet registry that then they can then have a little smaller piece
of the cake, which they can then hand out to you.
So RIPE do not want to talk to you, and they have decided that they do not talk to you
unless you are a local internet registry.
And that means you are RIPE NCC.
That means you are RIPE NCC.
That means you are RIPE NCC member.
I am a private person, so if I want an AS number, I do not necessarily want to pay the
1,600 euro fee per year to be able to talk to RIPE.
So you need a sponsoring LIA to be able to get addresses.
You can find some nice people.
You can also pay a bit for it, and there are multiple ways to do it.
So we have found a LIA that we really like.
It is a project called Free Transit Project, and they are some nice people.
So what is the difference between IP addresses when you have an IXP and you are a network
operator is that you would usually like your IP address to be globally routable.
That means it is your IP addresses, and the route to them is in everybody's routing table.
So basically what you are doing here is you are going to go to the IP addresses at this
IP address and you are going to go to your IP addresses at this IP address and the IP address
and the IP address is in this IP address.
So, that is reasonable, but when you have an IXP, you do not necessarily want to be
globally routable.
There's no reasons for the routers in your network to have a global route.
It should only be the routers on the peering LAN which should be able to connect to you.
So yeah.
You have the, well, yeah, when you, well, so how do you, how do I know that you have
some resources allocated?
It is available in the regional Internet registries databases, again, like RIPE, that we use in
our case.
And you, so what you need to create an IX, or just as a person, you need an organization
object, you need a maintainer object, you need a person object, and also, as a network
operator, you need an AS set.
This is for other networks to include in their routing policies, so they, so others can know
that you are a network operator.
Okay.
And that they are allowed to announce your prefixes, for example.
And I've, again, included a course in, a small, very nice course, in the bottom here.
So I also found out there's some miscellaneous info I could never have guessed.
When talking to our local Internet registry, which then forwarded it all directly to RIPE,
well, the obvious one is that, well, your IX needs a name.
So you need a name.
Yeah.
I guess.
So do you also, like, want a route server?
You have to, like, think of that.
And you probably do.
So then that means you need an AS number.
And also, you should probably get a 16-bit AS number, because you never know if some
customers bring really old equipment that cannot handle 32-bit AS numbers.
A little bonus is that, also, that a 32-bit AS number is a bit more expensive than a 32-bit
AS number.
A 32-bit AS number fits on a Danish number plate.
So you can get some, you can find a number plate that is valid in Denmark.
So you also need some prefixes.
And this is one of the reasons why I said this, but not global routable and globally
routable.
You do have a shortage of IPv4 IP addresses, so RIPE is not very keen to hand them out
unless you really, really need.
They have set aside some addresses.
And that's why you say, yes, I so and so swear that I would not use these two as normal services.
And then you will get them.
Hooray.
I will do that.
And then you will get the IP address if you really need, but you probably do not need
a large address.
We use six addresses out of a lot.
So yeah.
So, yeah, again, things I had not thought of was get a hold of a seed or contract confirming
connectivity to IXP Colo site.
I had to find our bell to our uplink.
Oh, yeah.
I guess it makes sense that our facilities somehow should have an uplink.
You also need to say, yes, I do have three customers that are willing to appear at our
XP, so I'm not just creating an XP for one, for me, and then I have no customers.
This also matters if you want to go in and be present on peeringdb as an XP.
Again, it's like the magic number is at least three, and also with the XP database.
These are some databases that network operators use to find out what XP should we go to and
what facilities should we go to and who is there.
So it's a very nice way.
It's a way of network operators talking to each other.
It's kind of like a social media, but we don't post pictures.
We just post where we are.
So yeah, again, facilities, like what is my address, and then you also need at least one
contact person and a phone number.
Just things I didn't know, and then it took five days extra to get all these.
So if you can send it at the same time, it will save a few days of talking back and forth.
So yes, the local internet registry, well, we use the Free Transit project.
I have used it for my own AS number.
There are some nice people, also some hackers.
So I like this, but also I have a bias because I know some of them personally.
Yeah.
So if you want to find some local internet registry services, you can search on an engine
right there service, and someone will gladly take your money to get an AS number and some
prefixes.
It is really expensive as just an organization to get IPv4 addresses, but I won't dwell too
much into that.
It's just because we have a shortage, and there's a market for that shortage.
So yeah.
So similar projects, well...
Sorry.
My tech phone is calling.
Okay.
There we go.
I'm not answering that.
Sorry.
No.
It's all right.
It's fine.
Thank you.
Thank you so much.
Oh, hello.
Thank you.
Nice to meet you.
Yeah.
Thank you.
Thanks, guys.
All right.
Thanks, everyone.
Thank you.
There are many internet exchanges in the world that are community run by network operators,
and it kind of makes sense.
Some people got to get an OAB and said, hey, why don't we do this?
And then they did this.
So yeah, that is also commercially run, a lot of them also, but I find it kind of inspiring
that a lot of them are just, hey, let's do this, and then we did this, and people donated
equipment and money and hosting and stuff, and it kind of just worked really nice.
So yeah.
That's all.
There's also some hosting, some projects similar to ours, our hackerspace.
We have Coloclue in Amsterdam, we have K-Space in Tallinn, we have Community Rec in Zurich.
They offer some hosting of some kind also to small machines and some for larger machines
for private persons or small businesses.
There's also BGP.whatthefuck.
They do BGP stuff similar to us, but they are just in Warsaw instead.
And we have InBerlin also, which I learned recently also existed.
So if you're interested in finding some of these, I will say thanks to my collaborators.
So I did this as a school project also, so hooray, I got easy test points for this thing.
Olivia and Daniel.
They helped me build this, and we also have Jori, which is from the Free Transit project
and really nice.
And then Aspern Tønnesen for having way too much knowledge about networking.
And it's a bit dangerous asking a question because then you get a very long answer.
So here are some good resources, like PNGDB, the interconnection database.
Yes, knock meetups like we have in Denmark.
Most countries have them.
That's the RIPE Academy.
I learned a lot on IPv6 with the course.
That was really nice.
You don't have to take the certificate.
You can take the course.
You can also pay to take the certificate if you want, but you can learn a lot for free.
And yes, the Network Start Research Center.
They also helped me in some of the introductions and slides they have.
It was really nice.
That's also, I didn't go into BGP filtering.
It's a very important thing of network security.
But there is a small guide that InnoNog have made collaboratively, and then InnoNog also
have a thing they call InnoNog Ring.
It's a nice way to find out how reachable is my prefix.
And you can find us in Bornhag, in the Labitat or Labifery Village, as a tech number.
And in all other days, you can find us on Labitat.
We have a website for the IX.
You can also find us on PNGDB.
So if you already got an AS number, you can join us.
Yes.
We would very much like to have you.
Again, VLAN is not decided.
We can also, if you bring a machine, we can probably host it.
And if anyone wants to kind of sponsor this project, because it's been paid out of my
money until now, it wasn't really that expensive, but still, I'm a student, so money.
All hardware is just things we found.
And we're very nice with some updates.
Thank you.
Updated hardware and maybe a second Uplink, because you never know, some machine may just
dig up the road and kill the whole Uplink or something, something.
And we like stickers.
So what is next for this project?
Well, we have RxP running, which is pretty nice.
We have a route server running.
But we would also like to have some, well, more peers, of course, but Looking Glass,
which we have not set up.
But I would very much like to set up ARP sponge to limit ARP requests, yeah, more monitoring,
more documentation, and set up a RPKI relay.
I have set up one for my own network, but not for this.
It uses a very inefficient way to check if AS number and prefix match.
So, yeah.
All right.
Thank you for listening.
Here's to you all.
Good talk.
Thank you.
Bye bye.
.
Thank you.
You