Okay, we are about to begin the next presentation.
We have Benjamin who is here to talk about an introduction to digital consent, why a
new definition with new tools and specifications are needed.
Let's give a round of applause for Benjamin.
Thank you so much.
I have a quick sponsorship message before starting the talk, so I just want to start
with that so I don't forget it.
A Danish organization called Django Denmark is hosting Django Day, like an annual one-day
event for Django people.
It's in Copenhagen.
We found a really lovely venue on Nørrebro and talks are coming in and tickets are on
sale and so on.
So that's on the 6th of January.
And that's the website for that.
So I hope that maybe you're interested.
There is also a little Django perspective in this talk.
So I'm a software developer and I want to talk about consent with the background that
I have as a software developer.
And maybe I'm not.
Maybe I'm not so precise on the legal aspect.
So this is not like legal advice about how to do consent.
But I hope it aligns with your understanding of GDPR and those sorts of legal obligations
that we have when we build systems with data, basically.
So it's also the first time in a long time that I'm doing a talk.
And last time I was part of a conference.
I was part of a conference.
And last time I was preparing a talk, I found out that I was very confused around what focus
to find.
So now I ask, like, why do I think this is a talk to present here for you and for your
sake, for my sake?
And let's just make those terms clear.
Let's make the purpose of the talk clear.
I really want, like, more people to care about the question of consent, digital consent.
But in order so that we can build something, and so that we can build something together.
So I'll try to, as a software developer, maintain the aspect that we talk a lot about consent,
but in the end, let's try to make it – turn it into a tool so that when we want to, you're
going to be able to implement it.
So if you're going to be able to do it, you're going to be able to do it.
So that's part of the talk.
Yeah.
have consent for something in an application, we're doing it the best possible way. So I
hope you agree to that. Some of it is below the phone suit. It's also Latin. So I'll try
to cover these four aspects here. First, those pesky cookie banners that we all know about.
They're everywhere. And then I'll talk a bit about consent, like what can we say, what
sort of properties can we attach to consent in order to have a definition of it. Then
from that definition, can we specify something that we can use to implement software? And
then finally I'll just share a little bit about what I've been trying to do. I hope
that people can hear because it's very loud for me up here with the rain. Okay. Cool.
So those pesky cookie banners.
I'll just show you a few examples to get the thought process started, what's happening
right now with consent.
It's basically that people want to continue to use and share data, it's still okay.
They want to continue to use and share data the same way, kind of business as usual, but
we'll just add even more layers of terms and conditions.
And I've been annoyed at it and posted stuff on social media when I saw a dialogue that
I didn't like, and I was trying to figure out some examples before the talk, and basically
I just said, you know what, I don't want to do this.
I don't want to do this.
I just went to the first two kind of random pages that I found, so these are not, these
examples are not cherry-picked.
I just went on the normal internet and looked, and I went to wordpress.com, and they say
they're the world's most popular website building tool, so let's hope they get consent right
and I would say they don't.
You go to the front page, and there is no consent dialogue at all, but there is trackers.
So there is trackers on the website.
Okay.
For the stream, people, I can say there is a very heavy rain coming down right now, so
we have a lot of problems with the sound in here.
I'll let folks move a little bit.
Yeah, okay.
So people are just moving around in the room here so that we can sit a little bit closer.
Okay.
And then we hope the rain will cool off.
That's a lot better.
Okay.
Yeah, it was the weather not the technique.
Yeah.
So now the sound is better, and people are closer to the microphone.
I guess we continue.
I went to the front page of wordpress.com, and there was no consent dialogue.
I click get started.
Okay.
I go to the second page, and then the consent dialogue pops up.
I think the designers of the web site decided that the consent dialogue is probably not
a good user experience, so they want to hide that on a secondary page.
I looked at the trackers, and they were the same on those two pages, as far as I could
tell.
And then of course, they have this silly thing where you need to generate a story where you
will know the text you want to have the new cerums.
No, no.
No.
That's it.
to click customize, and then you have to toggle something in order to actually reject it.
That's a pattern of, you know, trying to make people accept things, called a dark pattern
often. Then I have a different example here that is, like, really, that's when you go
to Bloomberg.com, it's a giant thing you have to either accept all or reject all. And
what I thought was very interesting about this one is a text that reads that you can
actually manage those choices any time, which I would understand that it's a good effect
for this dialogue. You can manage those choices any time you want, but that doesn't really
make sense, because if I go to the website again with a different browser session, how
am I going to manage those choices from the previous visit? It's bizarre. The link just
points to a generic page that's dependent on the cookie. So that's one of those real
absurdities of revoking.
Making cookie consent, like, how do you... You may need to actually store those cookies
yourself in order to revisit the sites. You may also need to have a log of your own IP
addresses you've been delegated and whatever goes into your fingerprint that's used for
this kind of ad profiling.
Looking at the... Looking at those terms and conditions, I think it's very important to
remember that the terms and conditions, those consent dialogues, they all contain something
about profiling. So that's not profiling that is explicit, but it says that it may contain
this and this and this element. And so in order to revoke it, I would post that then
the user needs to be able to know that about their own web browsing in order to, for instance,
invoke the right to be forgotten.
Or the right to have... To see your own data. All those individual GDPR rights. And that
is absurd. I think no one's going to do that. Even on the highest technical level, knowing
that and putting it into practice seems very far-fetched.
So some other absurdities that...
SIGNDAL
As Resources Engine.
SPEAKER 3
SAMUEL MITCHELL
That kind of Listenability's problem here is that we notice is that there is actually
a great HTTP header, do not track header, and it seems to me that it would be easier
if the ones that own websites instead would read that header, instead of letting everyone
have to read those awfully long terms and conditions. That's just a very simple solution
to not consent to tracking. And then if that header is set, you don't even have to show
show those dialogues, you can give the user a better experience.
And then there's browser extensions, kind of doing the same, let's say you own a website
and you can see that people are using tracker bloggers or ad bloggers, that's probably because
they do not consent to the tracking, right, so you don't need to show them the dialogue.
And then there is the very strange behavior of saying, like, if you continue browsing
this website, then you automatically agree.
Like how do you note that someone actually saw that dialogue?
And you might as well have missed it.
That's the case of the Bloomberg thing here.
They have in the background there, you can see there is a tiny, small, like yellow thing
that says that they have updated their terms and conditions and if you continue surfing
the site, you can see that they are updating their terms and conditions.
And if you continue surfing the site, you can see that they are updating their terms
and conditions.
And if you continue surfing the site, you just automatically agree to those changes.
Very strange, I would say.
Okay.
So let's be a little bit positive now.
I would say that there is maybe an okay thing to think about during the past, like GDPR
times and maybe the past, I don't know, maybe it's a decade now that the cookie banners
have been out.
But they did spread an awareness of tracking and so on in the larger population, right?
And maybe that's an advantage.
It could also be a disadvantage, though, because we get this, you know, this consent fatigue.
We have to look at way too many things and consent to them.
So of course, we just stop looking.
We stop caring.
And that's quite human.
Oh, this talk just keeps getting gloomier and gloomier.
So the normalizing is part of the fatigue, you could say, but it's also part of maybe
saying, you know, oh, this tracking, it's innocent.
Everyone does it.
Like, it's completely fine that we have a...
It's completely fine that we have a...
I think one of the cookie consent frameworks, they advertise that they automatically have
an updated list of 2,000 third-party tracking companies, data processors, it's quite a lot,
but then that's kind of just normal.
And I think even worse is like that.
We get a bit like nihilism is creeping in, like Big Tech is just doing whatever they
want with our data and we can't even read all these dialogues that we keep getting thrown
at us.
But yeah, good news.
I think that cookie consent is not really any consent thing.
Maybe we should find a better word for it.
It's very hard to claim that this is informed consent.
And we already can see how like very explicit revocations of consent that are being indicated
in HTTP headers are being ignored.
And yes, I think I've argued the case that it's in practice it's not possible to revoke
this type of consent.
I asked a bit around, and I was happy to see that the general born hack audience in the
Fediverse also had a majority of saying let's reject this as a solution to tracking.
Like asking for consent in this way doesn't make tracking okay is how I would interpret
the response here.
But also that...
Yeah.
I think some people have kind of given up hope.
Some people also believe that we can improve cookie banners so that the consent can work.
I'd really like to hear from them also.
Let's say that we had a workshop and we could talk a bit more about our experiences with
both cookie consent, but also other types of consents where you...
I agree to some terms and conditions in a shop or with the public sector, then it would
be a great fit to ask these basic simple questions.
Is the consent I'm dealing with here, is it informed consent, meaning that the user knows
what's going on and how to withdraw that, and also the curious case because often this
legitimate interest is being...
Yeah.
...mixed up.
Often there is a blurry line that looks like you have to consent to something, but actually
it's called legitimate interest.
But I'll try to come back to that, but that's a great idea for a workshop, I think, so I
hope someone would be interested in that too.
So moving on from the cookie banners.
Yeah.
So moving on from the cookie banners, let's try to define something.
Let's try to say what properties should real consent contain, and I don't know, strong
consent, true consent, just kind of trying to distance it from this mix-up with the cookie
banners.
First of all, real consent should be voluntary.
Yeah.
It's a voluntary thing, so if there is only one button called accept, and you need to
accept in order to access something, it's not consent, it's an agreement or it's like
the terms, but that's nothing to do with consent.
We want the term to have meaning, and that meaning comes when it's a voluntary declaration
or agreement between.
Yeah.
Two parties.
And secondly, it needs to be informed, so all this stuff about agreeing without reading,
we need to get into a situation where someone consenting to something actually has an incentive
to be informed about it.
Then it should be revocable.
That's also a very hard technical term, technical task, so to implement that a consent is suddenly
being revoked.
That could happen any time to the system, needs to get a signal, needs to do something,
needs to scrub data, maybe tell other systems that they need to do the same.
That can become quite complicated.
Then it needs to be manageable by the user.
So what does that mean?
That could mean that the user needs a copy of what they're consenting to, or they need
some kind of permanent access to the system.
Maybe they need to store it in a wallet.
Yeah.
There are many ways probably of implementing this.
And then it needs to be auditable, so we need to be able to say when we did this, and this
action requires consent, then we need to track the action in a way that we can prove that
we had the consent when we did that.
So it needs to be auditable by someone.
And especially when it comes to consent.
When it comes to GDPR, then users can at any point in time require that you show proof
that what you did was based on consent or legitimate interest.
But you need to be able to prove that.
And other functions from GDPR is this right to be forgotten and also the right to have
your data corrected and so on.
Good point.
Thank you.
It's good to have all of that.
And then it's a task now to implement.
I just want to show this table, though, because what we found when working with specification
for consent was that people working with other systems that needed consent, they were sometimes
confusing it with a normal agreement, but also they were asking the question, can we
also use this consent system?
Can we use it to store regular agreements, any kind of contract in?
And that's where the consent specification gets too muddy.
So we want to be strict on what is consent and what is something else like a regular
contract.
The first thing was this point of it being voluntary.
Like if there is a reject and an accept button, then we're good.
Then it's voluntary.
People can reject it.
The system understands the rejection.
Then we need to have a purpose declared, an intention.
That's kind of what consent does.
You say yes to something that then happens, probably also has expiry.
But with contracts and agreements, then you have more like requirements or obligations
that have to happen.
Yeah.
And they probably also will happen.
Because contracts and agreements, they have like things about what happens if you don't
do that.
It's a promise of some kind, whereas consent, the one that gives the consent can just revoke
it.
So I put those in contrast.
And then the auditable part is something where I would say that the contract and agreement
often is signed in a way that in itself, it becomes a contract.
It becomes a contract.
It becomes the object that upholds its own content, where the consent relates to a lot
of actions that need to prove that they are related to that particular consent.
So some examples that are not cookie banners is that government, for instance, I'll just
mention the two last ones.
I'll just mention the two last ones.
But a very typical government institution will want to get your personal data from a
registry somewhere or exchange data in some kind of way to do an administrative task.
That needs consent often.
But that's because you can reject it.
So if you reject it, you replace it with another process.
Then you can just like give them the information by showing your ID or by fetching it from
somewhere and manually handing it over and so on.
Another example is communication where you accept that someone sends you a newsletter
and when you withdraw that consent, they stop sending you the newsletter.
And then the one sending out the newsletter can, of course, store like now I sent to these
people based on this consent.
You can anonymize or hash the email addresses.
So you can build a nice little system that's consent-based.
And then you can send out the newsletter.
And then the one sending out the newsletter can, of course, store like now I sent to these
people based on this consent.
And actually, it's the subscribe-unsubscribe function of the newsletter.
So when we build this, we need to ask some questions like in order to establish informed
consent, there are some risks.
And the best example of consent when it comes to risks is medical consent.
There will be a lot of risks.
There are risks implied with a medical procedure.
And if the patient is conscious, you want informed consent.
And they are incentivized to read it because the risks are very high.
Whereas in the example of data exchange, the user can perceive no risk at all and not want
to read it.
And that's where it gets a little bit more of a UX task, like how do we present this
thing?
So the user actually perceives an incentive to go through it.
And that's a task not just for the legal department.
I think if you just ask the legal department to do the whole consent thing, you're going
to get a legal text.
And then you will have the problem of turning the legal text into informed consent.
You need something that feeds people an understanding of the purpose and the risks and so on.
And then the last part is also to ask, like, is any of this in the user's interest?
Maybe ask that.
And then if the answer is no, then ask if consent is really the solution then, if you're
doing something against the user's interest or not zero interest in it.
It's hard to push in consent because it will not be informed consent.
So try to put this proposal.
Kind of.
It's a little bit academic.
That consent is understood as a voluntary, well informed and revocable declaration by
an individual for another party to use and process that data in a specific way.
And we have established a similar definition in a project that I'm part of that is government
oriented.
It's a little bit like a slightly simpler version of it.
So before giving the talk, I decided to add some more to the definition to make sure it's
like a good and strong definition.
So then in this project called GovStack, where we are working with a specification for consent,
we have also had to add something.
So like as an example.
An example of what consent is not.
And that's like the second clause to the definition is, let's say, the use of consent should be
avoided in these cases.
When a person is simply informed by an organization, it's like it's just an information and you
cannot project it or whatever.
And when the consent.
It's like a system or a platform that is dealing with consent has no way to identify the person.
Or like has no way to establish the consent is actually real.
Because then the owner of the consent platform can also suddenly like invent consent.
That's not so good.
So we want a system that's like tied up to some other system that can ensure that there
is a signature.
So something like that.
So some kind of stamp on the consent.
I'll get back to the data models for this because now is the time for getting closer
to I've made a typo there for the specification for digital consent.
And I have copy pasted the typo to each and every of the following slides.
So the high level requirement is to say we need privacy by design and privacy by default.
I hope that you've heard that.
I hope that you've heard the terms before because I just really like those terms and
they're a very good starting point for specifying the system.
And in privacy by design, we want to say we start to design our whole system of data models,
not just the consent models, but also in the rest of the system when something has to do
with consent.
We need to sort of plug in.
We need to plug in.
We need to plug it into our consent system so that we know what to do when consent expires.
So like do things based on the fact that consent should exist.
If you are doing an operation in a system, maybe you need to check for the consent before
even proceeding.
That could be a way.
Then we also want the privacy by default.
So that's very simple with this.
Like we just assume that the user.
The user hasn't consented.
That's how we design the whole system.
There is no consent.
And then we have the entire track of how the system should work without the consent.
So the advantage is that actually consent can be a liability in itself if you're storing
a lot of consent with person-identifiable information next to the consent, then the
consent system in itself contains things that are privacy-related.
And if people are rejecting something and you are then storing their rejection, then
you're storing the fact that this person doesn't want to do this.
So we can get rid of that by defaulting to having a rejection state.
Okay.
We did some work in the GovStack project, and these are five pillars of the work.
Firstly we have done this based on some use cases.
And the first use case is related to a mother and child that goes to a health care center.
And how this child is being registered in the health care center.
And the second one is about payment in a public sector also.
So benefits, you can say.
And how to do those payouts and sort of manage data around citizens.
We're not quite there yet.
There's a lot of complexity in this.
But we've started now to have enough that we can say that we have a functional specification
for the most simple things.
And there are some requirements, some UX requirements, some data models, and an open API specification.
In the functional requirements, you need the administration part of the system.
Someone needs to be able to configure and set up a system.
Everything.
So the administrator or configuration owner, those are the ones that are responsible for
adding things that are like the texts that the user sees and should be able to update
those texts and see how things work out.
Maybe mass reject everything when the consent is updated.
The administrator also needs to be able to configure.
And that's what we're trying to do.
Okay.
Thank you.
All right.
Then we've got the general policy, privacy policy, that guides maybe all the handling
of data inside the organization.
So we've got a bunch of functionality there.
Then we've got the individual user who is in need of seeing her consent agreement, as
we call it.
So being...
So being a...
being presented by something to consent to, and then actually accepting or rejecting that.
What we're used to seeing is like mega collections of a million things to toggle on and off,
and we've just kind of envisioned that there is one thing at a time, and then you click
accept or reject, and of course, they need to be able to look at what they have consented
to later, and they need to be able to send revocations for things later in time.
So it's kind of obvious.
The other part is not so obvious.
That's the auditing part, and we've kept that separate.
From the audit part, we've kept that separate.
System administration and users' individual functions.
So this is an area that I think we will have a lot of future work with, and kind of understanding
this whole aspect of what does auditing versus privacy mean, like what are we actually now
delegating the auditor to have access to?
Auditing can also happen through that someone looks into the consent system to see what
is stored in the system, but it can also happen that auditors should be able to access the
system that is doing stuff based on consent to see that things matches.
Auditing can also be that a third party is owning copies of what is happening in this
consent platform, and then able to do their own auditing afterwards.
We've tried not to.
We've tried not to specify exactly how that happens, but to have a larger palette for
that.
Then we have the UX requirements, which I really wanted to have shown some of the mockups,
but I didn't have the latest copy.
But it's fairly simple requirements.
I think that's the common sense that you would have if you thought about consent from your
own perspective.
Like, how would I like to be able to do this?
How would I like to be asked?
The first requirement that I really liked in this UX specification was that we want
to just be clear about what data do we need, or what are we doing here?
Why are we doing it, and what does the user benefit from this or risk from it?
And then the duration is also really important.
Like, is this indefinite, or is it just some data that we have for a week, and then we
nuke it again?
Super nice things to be reminded of, and I think that reading the UX specification can
even end up being the entry point for understanding this platform, however it's made up.
They also had a really nice note in the UX requirements, which is kind of a different
take on what I have said earlier.
That the system...
If the user...
If the users reject the consent request, then the ones that are designing UX for a whole
application, they need to actually have a user journey where the consent is rejected.
Many people always think how people would like to use their system in the accept kind
of scenario, and then they forget that there is also a user journey where consent has been
rejected.
Very important also.
When you're having the first exchange with the user and showing we need your consent
here, of course, it should be visible.
What do you do then if you change your mind?
I've also seen UX mockups that actually lodge a consent dialogue in a survey all the way
through the survey.
So you start by saying, yes, I can accept this, but then as you're asked more and more
questions in the survey, you're reminded that...
Oh, no.
Now I'm sharing this data, now I'm sharing this data, so then you can actually reject
having your personal details attached to the answer or something like that.
But have this information about changing your mind visible and have first class user interface
for it.
So then we had some data.
We had some data models, and now is the time that I can again say that I'm a software developer,
so I kind of want to get to this step because then I know what to do.
And this was the most simple version we could come up with to just show what are the general
entities in the system.
We have this configuration area.
That's where we manage the components of consent.
So then we have the individual models that store the consent of the individuals to something.
And our terminology is that...
And this is the core of building this system.
It's to understand this.
So this is data models, because then I think we'll go to a nice place where consent makes
sense, or at least makes more sense, is to model with a data policy.
So that's your general policy for data.
Keep that separate.
And then the consent agreement itself, which is the purpose, what data and why and for
how long and so on.
some properties. We call that a consent agreement. And then we have a consent record. So a consent
record, as you can see with the arrow, that's the link between an individual and a consent
agreement stating that the individual has consented to it. And now, of course, I should
say that we have a model that's called individual, but whether or not it's a natural person,
that doesn't matter to this system. It can be any kind of unique. If it's just an email
address, many just contains a hash of the email address, and then that's all the system
knows. So, we also have the data. We have a data
provider, a consumer or a processor.
Maybe....
But they also need to be able to look at consent in order to determine if the operation that
they are doing has consent stored.
Then there is also a procedure, of course, that makes sure that the system can return
yes or no, but not necessarily state whether the user exists or not.
It's an API, basically.
So I really like this slide.
I think that's...
Sorry it took so long to get here.
But if you have any questions around it, then be sure to ask them if we have time.
Now I'll just make it a little bit worse, because I thought this was okay simple.
Okay.
And add a little bit.
What I'm adding here is the auditing part, because what we are especially interested
in is that if the user changes their mind, or the consent agreement changes, or the data
policy changes, then we need to track that.
Otherwise, we don't know anything about the past.
So in the specification...
We have proposed that there is a revisioning system that can track things, if it's okay
to track them.
And we have signatures.
And if there is a way for the individual to actually sign their consent, of course they
should be able to do that, especially if it's the public sector.
They have all sorts of platforms for that.
And we've also added the lifecycle.
And preparing the system, the specification, was a way of understanding that consent has
a lifecycle from where it hatches in a legal department, maybe, that says, we need this,
and then in a place where the whole...
The whole legal aspect of it maybe is being prepared.
And then people interact with the system, but it may get used, it may change.
That's why we have the revisioning.
And finally, we need to be able to establish proofs, both so that systems that are using
it can see that there is consent, and so that auditing can see that.
So this high-level view is also...
Okay.
Turned into an open API specification where it's like specific schemas with specific fields,
so that's very nice.
All of this is just a specification, though, so it's not an actual tool.
So I want to go further now, because...
What I think we are ready to do is to take this specification, build an open source tool
that is...
Not necessarily...
Not necessarily for governments.
That's probably very heavy.
But at least can work for organizations that we are dealing with in our everyday life that
wants to ask our users simple things, like send a newsletter or store some information,
because we want to do a statistic in our organization about something.
Let's have a tool that can do that the right way.
And...
Okay.
I thought that since I'm from the Django world, I thought that we can build it with Django,
because it's so nice to write data models in Django, and it's kind of like a rapid thing,
so we can get quickly from prototype to something that we can implement in a real project.
And I hope that this platform will turn into something that can both be a standalone platform,
that has an API.
So that you don't need to use Django in order to use the application here.
But if you use Django, then you can also do some added things.
So especially I'm thinking about adding a specific Django consent field that data models
can say, I'm a row in a database that's based on consent.
And if the consent changes, then I want to be deleted, or I want to be...
Have this particular field anonymized.
Okay.
So whatever that can...
And people have been playing around with this before, but I found that the older tools were
based on GDPR understandings, and they were kind of abandoned now.
So the idea was to start the project and have these thoughts around the consent definition
and specification from GovStack used as a way to bootstrap the project.
So it has a...
It has a repository.
I just added a matrix channel today.
So if you're interested in joining that channel, and just...
You can use it to get updated on how it's going with the project, and you're also very
welcome to participate in it.
And then I wanted to add that I'm here, but only today at the event.
So I hope you enjoyed that.
Thank you.
Bye-bye.
Sorry.
You have to grab me to talk some more about consent.
Maybe here.
Maybe in the back.
I will use your input.
I hope that's okay.
So if you tell me something about how you think about consent, I will definitely get
inspired and try it and use that.
If you want to get involved in the project, that would be super awesome.
And my last recommendation here is that there is a super nice little episode of all hail
and всем ... maod.
the algorithm, which is an Al Jazeera series, that some years ago actually took up the point
of concept and really communicates it super well, makes it exciting and makes it essential
for everyday folks.
I take questions if there are any.
Thank you.
Do we have any questions for Benjamin?
We talked about this a bit earlier, but it seems to me the biggest players in the game
of tracking people's PII have a vested interest in not really getting consent from people
and patterns of behavior that indicate that they're not really interested in informed
user consent.
They're interested in mainstream consent.
They're interested in maintaining their status quo and finding loopholes that allow them to
continue doing that.
And I think it's great that we think about how we can serve our users and how we can
respect their data and their privacy, but it feels to me like the biggest problem is
these bigger organizations that aren't going to play ball no matter what solutions exist.
And I was wondering what you think about that and ways that you see of affecting a more
positive change.
Given those actors, like Google, Facebook, other tech.
Yeah.
That's a really great question.
I think there is some kind of tactical political game buried here that maybe we should stop
even allowing them the right to use the word consent for these cookie banners.
Maybe it's better to just say cookie banners.
And then if we can get as far as building a tool that deals with this, I think it's really
important.
Yeah.
And if we can get as far as building a tool that deals with real consent, I think we'll
discover that the tool is absolutely useless for the type of data sharing that cookie banners
are used for.
So we'll just have a great tool that is great for actual consent and then it's easier to
see the differences.
If that can work as a strategy, I would pick that because it's always nice to be able to
show like the real consent.
And, yes, they will not, I mean, I'm pretty sure that at some point someone's going to
make a proposal in the European Parliament because now it has, it's not the same Parliament
that gave us GDPR, it's a different Parliament, and someone's going to say, look at this.
This is absurd.
Let's get rid of it and go back to the good old days where we just shared data without
even having the cookie banners.
I mean, maybe that could even be better for actually having consent now that everyone
understands it.
It's kind of weird to have a cookie banner that you just kind of know that it's being
mismanaged and it's not really authentic, so, yeah, that's...
Do you have one more question?
Thank you.
I had a similar thought, but I think during the presentation you, without intending, proposed
an approach to dealing with the disservices that don't respect end user freedom.
You said it's impractical to record every IP address I've used and every website I've
accessed, but actually I don't think so.
We could make a browser extension that does that and automatically request to be forgotten.
Would that be a reasonable approach for dealing with the sort of company that we were just
discussing?
Yeah, I didn't think anyone would say that, but I'm glad you say it, because if someone
can establish what they are doing as a person and giving and not giving consent to, and
then use that to inquire into their data in a very precise manner and finding out that
things are happening or not happening as they should be, then we have a case that can be
a legal case, right?
Then we can escalate from there.
But I mean...
With all those pages in a typical browser...
Yeah.
With all these political consent cookie bannas, I should say, sorry, it seems like there's
a very lot of legal details going on, so it would be a big thing if we get that, but if
we make the first step and we can see that there is something more, then I think it's
worth doing, especially with the do not track header.
Maybe that's also a simple way to establish, I'm using a do not track header, why are you
not respecting it?
Should you legally respect that?
I'm interested in why you connect government building blocks to consent.
Because from my understanding, most of what we do in government don't really need any consent.
So is government here actually the holder of the consents?
Or why is government involved?
So I didn't include anything on the GovStack project because I was afraid that would take up a lot of time to explain.
But GovStack is essentially not a government-owned project,
but it does have governments in it that the German foreign aid ministry is in it, Estonian government is in it.
The ITU, the International Telecoms Union is in it, and the Digital Impact Alliance is in it.
So these organizations, they wanted from the beginning to be able to supply that functionality
from an understanding that it is the right thing to do.
But there's many places where you don't need it.
You could just, like...
You could not have this so-called building block in your set of building blocks
because the legal situation would say you can do whatever you want because you're a government.
But I think when the tool is available, at least even though the government doesn't have to,
then they could.
And what we found also when we were building this specification
was that there aren't any tools that satisfy our specification.
So I think that was...
It was an important discovery in itself, was to work with this, set up the specification,
and then discover, hey, we actually need open source tools.
And GovStack is based on open source.
That makes it also interesting, digital common goods in this context.
And we need a digital common good that can satisfy this consent specification.
Yeah.
Thank you.
Sorry, I wasn't for the whole talk.
So I apologize in advance if I'm asking something that you already brought to the topic.
But I have two questions.
Actually, the first one.
So talking about legal, have you made some approach to some kind of organization?
Like, I mean, we have an organization called Legal Tech Lab.
So legal tech is kind of a buzzword for now.
Is there something happening in that, and that you can make a case regarding, like,
hey, I'm not giving consent, or this consent was not acquired in a legal attaining context.
So this is not valid.
Therefore, you're not permitted to keep my data.
So that's the first question that I have.
It's unfortunate that I don't...
Personally...
Go out and do the work of seeing what's going on in that department.
But it's a very...
It seems like in the room there is actually a little spark of energy to also go that direction.
So we could say, like, we are building a tool that can actually do the things we want in relation to consent.
But then we also want to expose, like, these practices of fake consent.
Or, like, not respecting the consent.
So I would encourage myself and everyone to look for that.
Because it could be something, yeah.
And, yeah, the second question that I had is, like, also considering, like,
reaching to the parliament for having something to pass by.
That will require, for instance, taking a look at vulnerable groups.
Like, like...
Let's say, Germany is not my first language.
So I will just be giving consent in order to get into a website to search for an apartment.
So things of that nature.
Saying, like, okay, if you are requesting consent from this person,
at least have the decency to put the information on the language that they can understand.
Or for sites that are just providing that in a certain language.
Or also looking at...
I mean, it's not necessarily people that, for them, would be like,
yeah, I mean, I don't know.
I just want to see pictures of my nieces.
Just get me in there.
I will consent to anything.
So it feels like kind of taking advantage.
So I was just asking if this is also something that can be considered.
Yeah.
It definitely makes me want to say again, like, the informed part of consent,
it should be part of the definition.
If there is no informed consent, then it's not really consent.
What is it, then?
I don't know.
The second part was that I forgot to mention accessibility and UX requirements.
So, of course, UX has to be catering for the user's needs.
Yeah, super basic stuff.
I should have added that.
Thank you.
In my experience,
users, or everyday users, they find it very hard to make that risk assessment of what
is the consequence of me giving, except that you can use my data.
So how will this tool help people do that risk assessment?
I know for the site, okay, I can see if I make a consent, I can do this, I cannot do
that.
I understand that.
But in the broader picture, how will it help that assessment?
I think it's really important.
Yeah.
I think that knowing that you can always go back and revoke your consent, and from
the beginning, knowing how to do that is super critical because, yes, we cannot guarantee
that the user actually reads what they accept.
There's no guarantee of that.
They scroll through the window in two seconds, or five seconds, or 20 seconds.
When have they read it?
It's...
These types of functionality doesn't work, but maybe establishing a convention about
consent, so that if you have a user interface, then kind of the same way that we are switching
between light, dark mode themes, or switching languages, we also know that this icon means
consent.
I don't even know if...
Maybe someone uses the checkbox to say it's about consent, but yeah.
Like a...
Well-established convention for consent will mean that people can change it, and then
have a system that understands that consent can always change at any time.
That's...
Awesome.
We are at the hour.
Let's give a round of applause for Benjamin.
Yeah.
Thank you for listening.