The next speakers we have is Karen Melchior, a member of the European Parliament, and Jesper
Lund, the chair of the IT poll.
They will speak about chat control.
The next month will be critical.
Please give them a hand.
Thank you very much, and thanks for coming to this, I think, one of several presentations
about chat control, a surveillance proposal from the EU Commission.
And there was a talk yesterday by Jan, and today we will focus on what is happening at
the political institutions.
And in the EU, and why the next couple of months will be critical for our fundamental
rights in the years to come.
So this is a quick outline.
We will do a very quick outline of what chat control is about, and what is the real name
of chat control.
And then we will, without hopefully making it too boring, explain how the EU law-making
process works.
Because a sort of...
Some understanding of that is very useful to sort of, first of all, influence the process,
but also understand why does it matter that council did this and that, and so forth.
And in the end, we will suggest how you, or those listening to this online, or seeing
it afterwards, can try to influence the process so that this mass surveillance proposal can
be implemented.
Thank you.
And I think that is very important.
But I think that's a good point.
And I think that's a good point.
I think that's a good point.
So, to be honest, I think that the proposal doesn't become reality.
And then this is...
Really the crux of the issue when we're looking at the proposals.
Every time we have a presentation of the Commission's proposal, the proponents of the proposal
will start out with spending ten minutes, 20 minutes out of an hour explaining how terrible
sexual abuse of children is, and how it's grown online in the last couple of years.
And it's...
It's not...
and sort of really explaining what has happened to the children
and how difficult it is for the police to prosecute the criminals that have committed this
without actually going into sort of, okay, there are criminal networks that are behind this
and there are things going on in the physical space.
They just jump to, okay, we need to do something about this online
because we need to save the children.
And look at these two cute young girls.
Who would be able to say no to save them from being abused?
Who would say no to actually help children from experiencing horrible things
and being subject to criminals and criminal networks
and having their pictures and images shared across the world?
That makes it very difficult to say the children's safety online proposal,
child sexual abuse material handling is something that we don't want to do anything about.
And that is ridiculous.
That is really the political environment and the discussion and the debate
that we're going into when we're talking about this.
So we need to remember to think about the feelings of the people that we're talking to
and not only think about the sort of technicalities
because we all want to save children from abuse,
but we actually want to do it in a way that works.
And what we have on the table doesn't work.
And we want to let the politicians know that, and I'm one of them,
that we're going to do it in a way that works.
And we want to let the politicians know that, I'm one of them,
And we want to have legislation that can save the kids in a way that works.
And as I was mentioning with the Kids Online Safety Act, it's not only in the EU.
We are having proposals being made across the world.
We have in the US where they're also mixing it up with a little bit of some of the content
that we had in the DSA in the EU.
The UK also has an online safety bill that is proposing some of the same things.
On client scanning, so this is a sort of global phenomenon.
And therefore, we need to help each other across the different countries and regions to fight this
and try and find strategies that work.
Because just saying no to saving the kids is not going to appeal to sort of the masses.
And we need to make sure that we have technology that works, technical arguments
for why the proposals that they have don't work.
But at the same time, saying we're actually doing this to help the kids
as well.
So, this, the next couple of minutes will be a quick outline
of what is about and also revealing the real name.
So, that's why it's called on social media.
I think a phrase coined by Patrick Byer of the German Pirate Party.
So, the full name is Regulation Laying Down Rules to Prevent and Combat Child Sexual Abuse.
At ICPOL is a member of the board.
I'm a member of ITRI and I participate actually in ITRI's work on this file.
We call it the CSA Regulation or CSAR and that is, obviously, we don't have time to go
through everything and that would be incredibly boring.
So, I'll just focus on the most interesting parts or the most troublesome parts
of the CSA Regulation and clearly the most,
the absolutely most troublesome part is the Article 7 through 11 on detection orders,
which is sort of basically why it's called chat control.
These can apply to messenger services or interpersonal communication services
as they are officially called and hosting services.
And so, messenger services are always private communication services.
Hosting services can be public services like social media, but it can also be,
really, private services like cloud storage on Google Drive, Microsoft OneDrive and whatever
it's called.
And if a service provider is issued a so-called detection order, that will be an obligation
to scan all users' content for three different things, depending on which type of order is
given.
Known child sexual abuse material, which is, which will be done using some hashing matching
algorithm.
Okay.
Or perceptual hashing, typically.
But there are also possibilities for detection orders for unknown child sexual abuse material
and grooming.
And the latter two will be done through some sort of AI classifiers that come with extremely
high error rates.
These orders, detection orders cannot be issued to all services.
There's a requirement of significant risk of child sexual abuse after the so-called
detection measures that I'll talk about in a minute.
But the way that significant risk is defined in the regulation itself will very likely
in practice mean that a lot of services will have a significant risk that they can be used
or abused for something bad involving children.
Especially as the very purpose of messenger services is that people can communicate privately
without the service provider monitoring what people are talking about.
Okay.
And that means it will actually be very difficult for the service provider to say that there
is not a significant risk of the service being used for child sexual abuse.
One interesting thing is to say, well, what about encrypted services where, which are
specifically designed so that it's impossible to scan the content of people's communication?
Well, encryption is barely mentioned in the proposal itself.
Okay.
So, the proposal itself, but it is presented as technologically neutral, which means that
it will simply be up to the service provider to figure out how to do the impossible of
scanning communication content that is end-to-end encrypted.
This is not explained particularly well in the proposal itself.
But there was a Q&A published by the Commission along with the proposal where it is spelled
out that...
Okay.
Very well.
Well, let me just add something here.
And there's this question about encryption.
So, there is a sort ofjection that we're missing points about how that can be
subject to some sort of demasiado special CE regulations.
Can we be compensatory to other solutions by saying this in appelleged Hermann and
to Hermann and come to STF-34 and say if the service provider just needs 완전 security
of its services, why can't we knit them apart inside out.
And it is a different topic, especially in the context of KPMG, and they are lumière
intellect that EagleE vér.
That's theahrw they do it by.
Right.
Yes!
There's a lot that goes into that ahe.
Because, you know, because while our home office sł u2smashnár scurp lose
this for reasons of time, because we want to get to the interesting stuff, what can
be done about these bad things.
And we will distribute the slides afterwards, so don't worry about that.
I also want to talk a bit about risk assessment and risk mitigation, which is something that
is supposed to come before detection orders can be issued.
This is sort of a mixed bag of something that is, some is good, some is bad.
So taking the positive hat on is about making services, platforms safer for children, which
is an admirable objective and a good idea.
And if this is something that service providers haven't done already, then having an obligation
in EU law to do it is a good idea.
The problem with this is that it's not a good idea.
The problem with this is that it's done in a way that presents the internet as inherently
dangerous, and if something is inherently dangerous, we should keep children away from
it.
So just to walk you through what will happen, service providers will first be required to
assess the risk of their services being used for child sexual abuse, which is a difficult
exercise, and then they should take mitigation measures.
The risk assessment is a good idea.
The problem with this is that it's rather vaguely defined, except the sort of the notion
that the incident is a dangerous space.
And the only thing that is sort of really concrete is that online age verification is
a good idea in the eyes of the Commission.
But some incentives are created to make services safer, which, so maybe having less sharing
of personal data by default, especially for accounts belonging to children, that would
be a great idea.
But that is actually not in the Commission proposal, but in some of the amendments that
are coming out.
And then the sort of heavily contested idea of age verification that is also coming up
in sort of national politics in Denmark, Germany, the UK, with the online safety bill, and France,
and maybe potentially other countries.
That is a not so good idea.
And by the way, there's also, I don't really have time to go into that, there's also an
age verification requirement for app stores, which will apply to all app stores, whether
they are large, like Apple's app store, or Google Play app store, or small, such as fDroid,
the alternative app store for Android devices.
And since these alternative app stores really don't know their users, they have no way of
enforcing age verification.
So, the problem with online age verification, which I won't really have time to go into,
is that there's no good way to do it.
But it is being proposed, and typically it involves bad solutions, such as uploading
copies of ID documents, which sort of invites identity theft, doing some form of biometric
facial analysis.
A company called Yoti.
Yoti?
Yoti is heavily invested in doing that, which is at best an estimation of your age, not
a verification of your age, checks your payment cards, and then maybe 10, 15 years from now,
some really fancy solutions where you can prove your age anonymously without revealing
anything, but this is nowhere ready for deployment.
Irrespective of what comes out of this, there's a risk of digital exclusion, users that will
not be able to comply with these age verification requirements.
So, there's a risk of digital exclusion.
So, there's a risk of digital exclusion, users that will not be able to comply with these
age verification requirements, whether they are children or adults, will be locked out
of online services that they want to use, potentially even including Digipedia.
We thought we'd give you a quick outline of how legislation in the European Union works.
If you study political science or law, you will spend years of classes and 10 or 20 ECTS
points on this.
So, we're going to do it very briefly.
Okay.
In basically one slide, the Commission comes with a proposal, then both the member states
and the Council, and us in the European Parliament, we look at it together.
The Commission came with a proposal last year in May, and already at last year's Bonhack,
there was a group of us that got together and said, this looks really bad, let's try
and do something about it.
That's why we have, together with Jorn, who talked yesterday, we have set up a website
called chatcontrol.dk and .com.
We also have a mailing list, so please support us on working on that so that we can influence
both member states and the parliamentarians.
We are in the Parliament in the process of making our amendments to the Commission proposal,
and we'll probably have a vote here in the fall on this.
The member states are also making their amendments and trying to have a joint position, and that's
where the...
We're advocating for national parliaments come in, and then after both the member states
and the parliament have come with their positions, then you go into what's called trilogue negotiations
where we sit down together with the Commission, the presidency of the European Council, so
that's going to be Belgium.
That was Belgium this spring, and then now it's Spain, and then you'll have Hungary and
Poland.
And then you'll have...
In the next coming six-month periods.
And that's when they sit in an enclosed room and try to hash things out and figure out
how the legislation will look like.
And that's, as Jesper has written down, it's typically somewhere between the parliament
and the council position.
And Jesper is going to talk us through the way it looks in the council between all of
the member states.
Yeah, I'll do the bad guys, and Karen will do the good guys.
That's how we divided the EU legislature on this file.
No, just kidding, actually a couple of months ago I was more optimistic about Council than
Parliament, but there was a bombshell event in April that changed a lot in Parliament,
but not in Council.
So a working group, the Law Enforcement Working Party, and don't be confused by the word,
it has nothing to do with parties, it's sort of a working group that is always called Working
Parties.
The Law Enforcement Working Party has worked on this proposal since June last year, and
they are, so the plan they have announced is that on 28 September they will adopt their
position.
This has to be done at a meeting where the ministers are present, the Interior and Justice
Ministers.
So they...
They have a Justice and Home Affairs Council, which will be held on the 28th September,
where their plan is to adopt the Council position, which so becomes the negotiating position
for the EU member states when they get together with the European Parliament in the trilogues
that Karen talked about.
And looking at the, sort of the most recent Council text, it has a lot of amendments,
but...
But it has very few amendments to detection orders.
They still apply general and indiscriminately to all users, irrespective of whether they
are suspected of actual involvement in child sexual abuse or not.
So the only thing that Council saw a need to exclude was real-time voice calls.
Everything else, including encrypted services, are still included in the...
In this group of the proposal.
There was, a couple of weeks ago, under the former Swedish presidency, a proposal to exclude
or not necessarily exclude encrypted services from the proposal, but to protect them from
detection orders and at least make sure that encryption is not undermined.
And this was framed in a way that clients are scanning, that I'm sure Jan talked about
yesterday, pending the spyware on your mobile phone.
So...
So if you look at this last panel, you can see just the amount of changes to
that proposal.
To a extent.
In fact, what you see is two deception changes as well.
So the first one was a perception of all needs.
not talk about. One interesting thing is that they decided to completely ignore a
legal opinion that the member states themselves requested from the Council
Legal Service. The specialist lawyers are employed to advise member states on
whether a proposal complies with EU primary law, including the Charter of
Fundamental Rights. They don't usually ask for such an opinion because there's
a presumption that new laws are consistent with the Constitution of the
EU, but in this case they did, and they got a very unusual opinion back at the
end of April, which clearly said, no, this is not consistent, this does not comply
with the Charter of Fundamental Rights. And I must say in Italy we have done our
own fundamental rights assessment and
that was actually quite lacking, or at least not quite lacking. That was
sort of less complete than the one that the Council Legal Service did, and we're
supposed to be the radicals on fundamental rights, but in this case we
were not. So just to quickly summarize, they used the data retention case law, we
did that as well, and concluded that general and indiscriminate detection
orders are not limited to what is strictly necessary, which is sort of the
yardstick for doing something in
public.
They also, and this is where it gets really unusual, said that the proposal is
likely to violate the essence of the right to privacy, and that is the sort of
generalized scanning of content of communications for everybody. It goes
back to the first SRAMS judgment in 2015, where they were referring to the
National Security Agency, and they said, well, we're not going to do that, and we're not going to do that, and we're not going to do that, and we're not going to do that, and we're not going to do that.
So basically, they pointed out that this would create a state of sort of a
permanent surveillance society, where all interpersonal communications are
monitored. And the lawyers, the clever lawyers, pointed out that detection
orders must be targeted against individuals where there's actual
suspicion of involvement in child sexual abuse, not the general population. Very
Very interesting, they also pointed out that doing this on end-to-end encrypted services
where they use the word backdoor, although it doesn't really have a legal meaning, creates
an additional interference with a right to data security, which is very interesting.
To make a long story short, the commission response to all this was that, well, the content
is the crime, so we need to monitor everybody's communication, which is a completely untested
legal argument, so it will be interesting if this ever gets to the Court of Justice
what the judges will say to the commission.
But member states are seemingly set to ignore this altogether, so what can possibly stop
a disaster with the CSA regulation in council?
A better negotiating position?
A negotiation for member states that does not include mass surveillance?
Well, if there is a blocking minority for member states representing at least 35% of
the EU population, it's not enough to have a majority in council, there needs to be a
supermajority of 65% of the EU population, but if there's a blocking minority, they can
in principle stop the position.
Okay.
So, I think, in its current form, going forward, and we know there's substantial disagreement
in the law enforcement working party about detection orders in the child sexual abuse
regulation, that is why they requested the legal opinion from the council legal service.
It is also why they sort of escalated their disagreement to the ambassador level in Corabier
– I'm not pronouncing this correctly – in the end of May.
That's why.
But the ambassadors basically reaffirmed, we want to monitor everybody, potentially
even including all your communication.
Some of the good guys, the good member states include Germany, Austria, the Netherlands,
possibly Poland and Estonia, who have all in their response voiced criticism of this,
and then there's a like-minded group of other countries – Belgium, Bulgaria, and so forth
– that…
Okay.
…want the proposal in its current form.
If you're wondering what does Denmark think about all this, well, Denmark has the most
absurd position.
Denmark wants end-to-end encrypted services to be included in the proposal, but they do
not want – Denmark does not want to weaken encryption in any way, and it's a bit hard
to sort of monitor and get access to encrypted communication without weakening encryption
in some way, because the whole point of encryption is…
Okay.
…to prevent this minor swing.
So the big question now going forward is, will the majority among the member states
be able to pressure the minority to give up its opposition so that council reaches a compromise?
That is often how it plays out, because sort of the way council works is seeking compromises.
But this really remains to be seen.
And now I want to…
Okay.
I'll hand over to Karen, because we also have the good guys in the European Parliament.
Well, sort of the good guys we have in the European Parliament, we have a lot of different
committees.
The main committee is our Fundamental Rights Committee, which is called LIBE.
They are the ones sort of writing the main opinion from the parliament regarding the
proposal.
Then we have a bunch of other committees, including the FAM Committee, which is for
equality, and also the Cult on the Budget.
So, the most important part of the committee is the public opinion.
So, the most important part of the committee is the public opinion, because if you want
to have a public opinion, we write opinions, and let the LIBE Committee know what we…what
we think that they should include.
But they can usually just disregard what we're saying and just continue on with what they're
thinking.
We've had a draft report from the LIBE rapporteurs in April, where they do have protection of
message content for end-to-end encryption, but I mean this is a little bit like, I don't
know if you recall the copyright directive debate.
You know, the, the…
where they said well we're not going to have upload filters but we're going to
ask you as a service provider as a platform to do something that you can
only do without with an upload filter we're not asking you to have it but
we're asking you to provide us with an end result that requires you to have an
upload filter and this is a little bit what the problem is with the debate in
this crypto war 4.0 which is going to be the next debate as well here in the
PON hack is that they're not actually saying precisely what it is that they
want the service providers to be doing because they know that's gonna be
unpopular so they just sort of fudge it and say we are gonna have we're gonna
ask you to provide us with this end result but we're not going to tell you
where it is and we've had also in the Draft Report from the lead committee
voluntary detection orders which is sort of trying to improve the position and
the drift so I would argue it's one. Feel free to speak to the floor if you have any other comments or comments?
the proposal that we came from the commission.
So instead of having it mandatory, then it's just voluntary.
And also we are going to have supporting age verification.
We're hoping that it's going to have not last 10, 15 years before we have something,
but we have sort of e-wallet where you'll be able to have age verification
without sharing your identity.
And also different mitigation measures so that you don't need to have detection orders.
In the FAM committee where I was what's called the shadow rapporteur from the Renew Group,
we actually had a lot of proposals on how to improve the proposal, so amendments.
But unfortunately, they said that this was too technical for the Equality Committee to look at.
So they said that they were out of scope for the FAM opinion.
So this is...
was also we have a Swedish rapporteur in the committee.
And the commissioner that has put the proposal forward is also a Swedish commissioner.
And this is like her piece de resistance, her like big thing that she wants to achieve
in this mandate of her being a commissioner.
So there's a lot of personal pride and ego in this.
So the Swedish rapporteur in the FAM committee managed to get all
of our amendments taken off the table.
So they weren't included.
So they weren't included in the FAM opinion.
Jesper already mentioned the council's legal service.
And that they had an opinion saying basically you can't do this
and respect our charter of fundamental rights.
So basically you're going against the sort of fundamental laws of the European Union
if you want to go forward with this proposal.
We in the parliament asked our lawyers, the parliament legal service, to look at the proposal.
And they came up with the same conclusion.
That this proposal is garbage and you shouldn't adopt it.
And it should actually be taken away and looked at again.
Unfortunately, the people who've invested a lot of private pride
and commitment to this are actually still going ahead.
So we have, this is the complimentary impact assessments.
We're also saying, okay, it's not, you cannot technically have detection orders.
So we're also saying, okay, it's not, you cannot technically have detection orders.
You can only do that for known CSAM.
And even then, if you're doing it with hash, you can circumvent that and it doesn't actually work.
The problem with the proposal from the commission, in my opinion,
is that you're trying to use technology to protect kids that is not actually going
to protect them because it can be circumvented.
Whether we're talking about hashing for known CSAM, but also if you're looking
at age verification, age verification.
For example, in app stores, then you can find the apps somewhere outside
of the app store and then upload it to your device.
We have amendments from LIBE that are actually looking quite good with protection
of end-to-end encryption and also that the targeted detection orders are actually going
against persons that are suspected in involvement of child sexual abuse.
Where we're saying, okay, you can actually detect stuff, but only if you have, of course,
a court order looking at it if there is an investigation going on.
Because I usually say you can't, you shouldn't, if you want to find a needle in a haystack,
you shouldn't make the haystack bigger, but you should actually find a magnet.
And if you are going to have detection orders and scanning of all of our communication,
you're going to be making the haystack bigger.
And then also, I mean, we are a parliament that's quite split on this,
so there are also some bad amendments on.
For example, voluntary detection.
And the situation in the parliament is that we are very split on this proposal.
And unfortunately, a lot of the people that are the rapporteurs
of the shadows are quite pro the proposal, a little bit the situation that I was talking
about in the family committee where the person writing the opinion liked the proposal
and is not listening to the criticism.
So therefore, it's really important.
Not only.
to influence the people that are the rapporteurs
or the shadows of the proposal, but also their wider group.
So the next steps are going to be that there are compromise amendments
for the LIBE report, and that works as the rapporteur
that we looked at here from Spain, Javier and the conservative groups.
My Spanish is not good enough to pronounce that.
But he will negotiate with the other political groups
about the amendments that have been put forward
and trying to find out if they can reach a compromise on the amendments.
And once they have those, they are going to be put to a vote
in the LIBE committee, and then after that,
they're going to be put to a vote in the plenary.
We're all 705 of us, or a little bit less,
and people don't care to show up.
They're going to vote on the proposal as a whole.
LIBE has been postponed until October,
and then after that, there will be a vote in the plenary.
And it is, so if that's going to be in October, possibly later,
it will probably be in the spring, just before the election
of the next European Parliament.
That means that there is a lot of personal interest
of the different parliamentarians,
in the result coming out, because they need to go out
and defend it only weeks later in the general public.
And I think that is a real big opportunity for us
to actually influence the people in parliament,
to say, are you able to go out and meet your voters
and defend what you voted through?
But that means that we need to actually try and influence
not just the people in the specific committee,
but more.
I think that is a huge opportunity.
And I think that is something that we need to do more widely.
In Renew, for example, we have a lot,
we have a couple of members from the FTP in Germany.
And Germany, even the government is against the proposal,
as Jesper was saying.
And the debates that we've been having internally
in the group has actually shifted the position
of our rapporteur, who is a Belgium lady,
called Hilde Bartmans, who is very pro the proposal.
And there has been a lot of,
a lot of lobbying from companies that can provide technology
for doing client science scanning and scanning in general.
And also Ashton Kutcher will be appearing later
in the slides as well.
And the S&D is also split.
They have a large German fraction in the political group.
And they are trying to then also shift the position
of the S&D group.
And they have a lot of work to do there.
But there they have the problem that the commissioner,
she is a Swedish social democrat.
And then how do you then balance supporting your political family
commissioner and having good legislation?
So I will very quickly, sort of, outline who is trying
to influence the legislative process,
what is sometimes called lobbying.
We have sort of three groups of,
of efforts on the S&D group.
Free advocacy groups, civil society organizations like IDRI,
Victorian Frontier Foundation, CGT, and others.
It's not an exhaustive list.
They tend to sort of oppose the main elements of the child sexual abuse regulation,
detection orders, and age identification that I've talked about.
And at IDRI, we have also called for the entire proposal to be rejected
because children deserve better.
So if you take detection orders out of her proposal,
that is basically all about mass surveillance.
There's very little death doing something for children online.
So opposing us are mainly the child protection organization,
or I should say some of them are critical,
but a majority of child protection organizations throughout Europe support the proposal,
and they are sort of the most staunch supporters,
are really an organization called THORN, led by Ashton Kuster,
who pushes for technological solutions and goes to the European Parliament
and gives movie-style explanations of how technology works.
For instance, that Ashton Kuster's scanning technology cannot be used for anything else
than child sexual abuse material, so there's absolutely no risk of mission creep.
We're talking about matching hash values,
and these hash values are very important.
Hash values can be anything, but that is sort of forgotten.
Big tech, service providers, Google, Meta, Apple, and so forth, are also involved.
They tend to oppose mandatory measures,
but they like voluntary measures when nobody tells them what to do.
And sort of the most principal opposition that has come out
is an opposition to weakening encryption
just because it's not a good thing.
It's because a law in the United Kingdom or in the European Union requires it,
because this will have global effects.
So WhatsApp, Signal, and Apple, I forgot to add that to the slide,
have said that in principle they will refuse to comply with such demands.
Then maybe one day Signal will be blocked in the European Union,
just like Signal is blocked in Iran, and we'll have to use it for proxies.
Who knows?
That could be what we're looking at.
This is just a dude.
This is Moritz Koerner, one of Karen's colleagues in the Renew group,
making jokes about who is advising the commission.
It's actually more tragic than it's funny.
And this is just to give you an example of sort of how this lobbying activity works,
sending briefing papers to parliamentarians,
or rather to their assistants,
because they don't have time to read them themselves.
So there was a fact check of top nine claims, blah, blah, blah,
from around the child protection,
from around the child protection organizations,
which was immediately followed by a fact checking of the fact checking
done by Idri, actually by myself, because Ella Jakubowski was on holiday.
Yeah, I will, in view of time, I'll skip our Idri advocacy efforts
and just mention that the commission really has no response to the criticism
from the tech community and criticism of technical issues
in general.
There was an open letter from the scientific community,
signed by more than 500 at present scientists,
saying that detection technologies are deeply flawed and vulnerable to attack,
and that undermining inter- and encrypted services,
back-drawering them will have severe technical implications.
Well, what was the response from the commission?
Well, she gave a speech a week later where she sort of compared that
letter to a report from a victim of child sexual abuse,
typically not happening online, but that's beside the point.
So on one hand, we have this report from that individual.
On the other, we have an article that is the scientific letter that only speaks
about technical hypotheticals, and she's sort of basically calling it
conspiracy theories, which is totally insane because it's a well-founded critique
of the proposal.
And now, Karen will tell you how you can stop this, or help stopping this.
I think the last slide is quite evocative of the problem.
They're proposing a technical solution where the technology that they're pointing
to simply isn't going to be working.
At the same time, you have sort of front organizations saying that they're working
to protect children against sexual abuse online, saying that they're not going to be able to
protect children against sexual abuse online.
And so, we have to get some of the other organizations on board to say,
okay, this is going to help, and it's the only way of helping children against sexual abuse.
And therefore, we need to say, okay, we want to actually help children against sexual abuse.
We need to get some of the other children's rights organizations on board on this,
and get them to speak out about the problems that this proposal is going to have on protecting kids.
Because I think if we just look at the very real technical criticism,
then we're going to lose a lot of people, because they don't actually care about the technology
and the solutions that could be proposed or not.
Because it's like, oh, it's, there's a debate on one side and the other side,
and then we'll just ignore both of them.
There is the EDRI campaign teams, both at a European level.
There is a working group, a campaign working group that, on a slide that Jesper skipped.
And then there are the national organizations.
Okay.
So, I think one of the most important things you should do if you're a Dane sitting here,
is go and actually become a member of IIT Politisk Feijoneg.
It costs you 100 haks a year, and will help to sort of reinforce the organization.
And then also join the communication campaign on this.
At the national level, the current government and members of the parliament in a lot of countries need
to approve the communication campaign.
The President has recently been called on to do that.
And so, I think, we actually need to do that.
Decision made by the government when they go into the council. So in Denmark EU will value
Will open value will have to approve the mandate for negotiations and the final vote of the
Of the Danish government when they go to the vote on the 28th of September
So therefore it's really important that you target for example the EU
Spokesperson in the different political parties and also the person dealing with technology and in Denmark
we even have a digitalization minister now and try and
Explain to them in easy tangible ways of how
this
Proposal is not going to be working in the European Parliament. You could go in and then contact the individual MEPs
both in Liba
ahead of the vote in
You can go in on the committee website and see who the members are
Emails are
already available you can contact us and
Try and provide us with
Arguments that we can then also bring forward in our groups
Individual emails are of course better than
Then the
sort of mass
Emailing systems where we just put up a filter
And put that in a folder or delete it because I mean we we're not that technically smart, but we can
Work around outlook which is so what we're using
Technical input is of course very important let us know what doesn't work and
Then also I mean, I think it's really important to try and use
personal tangible and national arguments we were discussing a little bit about whether we should actually use
mention the Rasmus Paludan and the
And the sort of debate that we have in Denmark and Sweden about the Quran burnings
But I mean try and use the political debates that are in each member state and try and get the journalists and the politicians involved
Communicate about this there's a lot of people communicating about why they think it's a good proposal
You need to help communicate the problems that are there with the proposal. I think it's
taking what yes was writing for example
mighty police screening and repeating it on your own websites or wherever is it's going to be useful and
Use the platforms that are there that you know how to use to get people's attention
We know that this is not
Working. I mean Google has had an automated tool to detect abusive
images of children, but the system is getting it wrong and
We need to make sure that people actually understand
how amazing
The internet is what it can be used for good things and also that it allows young
Persons and children to actually engage with communities that they are a part of but might not be present where they're living
Geographically and also that we need to make sure that the technology that we use
Encourage children to actually think for themselves
We can use technology in a good way
but the the proposal
From the Commission is not the way to use technology. We're trying to hide away things
We're trying to filter things we are breaking encryption where and instead of using technology to actually empower kids to
be able to identify danger and seek help when they need it and also and
To have the privacy that they also deserve so we need to actually use technology to empower children and to help them rather than
To take away their freedom and their rights
We have a couple of minutes left
One or two for questions, and I don't think we have like a thank you slide. We're not very polite. We're Danish
So I think there is a roaming mic if you have a question or two and otherwise
We'll go out of the tent and we'll be happy to take questions
You
started out by saying that that your
Way into this was going out to tell these people that we're also trying to protect the children
but
You didn't really come up with
very much in terms of alternatives
What are the alternatives
The alternatives are actually spending money on having police enforcement
looking at investigations and looking at the criminal networks
that are distributing and creating
child sexual abuse material it is also having
more responsible
social media platforms for example
And also having like use of for example pop-up functions if they detect
You're being asked to share your address or meet with somebody that you have somebody online
That you have like a pop-up that saying well, I usually you know this person
Is this somebody that you trust that you want to meet with?
Do you really want to share your address with the person?
Do you want to share your phone number with them?
Help kids also to, if they want to share nude images,
to think about it before they do so they make conscious choices.
And also to make sure that we don't spend a lot of money on technology
that's not going to be working,
but actually spend it on supporting kids and the children's rights organizations
rather than just spending it on technology.
But it's not been written up as a formal proposal or amendment?
I have written it up as formal amendments
that were then taken out of the Equality Committee.
The problem as well is that we have, for example,
Edry that's saying we should take the proposal completely off the table
and say it's so bad.
That we shouldn't even be discussing it
and therefore don't want to engage with the proposal
and trying to see how we can improve it.
And then we have the people that just love it.
And I've been trying to strike a middle ground saying
if this is going to go through, we need to improve it a lot
so that it's acceptable what's being put into law at the end.
But it's easier to say let's keep out of it
and ask the Commission to take it off the table completely.
And that's why there's not a lot of us trying to engage with the proposal
in terms of trying to improve it
rather than just getting it off the table or saying that it's wonderful.
I think it's also the case that the Commission spent typically years
preparing a proposal, doing multiple rounds of consultation,
writing hundreds of pages of impact assessments,
considering policy options.
And for a civil society organization like Edry to sort of do that,
well, we've thought about it,
but which I know...
We can't do that in a credible way.
So the right thing to do is call for the proposal to be rejected
so that the Commission, the next Commission,
without Ylva Johansson,
can come up with a better proposal to protect tourism online.
Maybe we should move it outside for...
Yes.
Yes, by all means.
Further questions is outside.
Thank you for being here, Karen and Jesper.
Let's give them a round of applause.
Thank you.