Tanya Cushman Reviewer Reviewer's Name
Hello, everybody, and welcome to BornHack 2023.
The first organizers arrived here about a week ago,
and it is insane to look around and see how much has changed,
and all the volunteers who have helped have done so much work
and deserve all our gratitude.
We'll get back to that later,
but it is fantastic to see everybody putting up camps
and moving into the field and unpacking
and starting to build our temporary home for the next week.
Well, technically, BornHack is a two-week event, right?
Only the volunteers know that secret,
so you get to be here much longer
if you help out with build-up and tear-down.
No.
We are very excited.
This has been a year of many challenges,
and, well, it always is,
but maybe some particularly big ones this year.
In particular, some sad news.
We lost one of our organizers, Jesper, this year,
or last year, in October,
very suddenly and way too soon,
and it hit all of us hard.
We dedicated the tagline for this year to Jesper,
Make Legacy,
because we feel that, well, everybody wants to leave a legacy,
and Jesper absolutely did leave a legacy.
He had a tremendous impact on BornHack as an organization
and on all of us personally.
And...
he left a giant void.
Thank you to the people in info
and the people in wellness
who have stepped up to fill the void after him.
Thank you in particular
to the new radio team
and to Maunus,
who have sponsored the new radios
and the new repeater and everything,
so we can continue the work that Jesper did
in every sense of the word.
There's nothing really we can do to properly mark this,
but I wanted to do a minute of silence,
but instead, I think that doesn't feel right,
because Jesper wasn't the silent type.
Instead, we'll do 30 seconds of silence
and then 30 seconds of applause to celebrate his life.
Starting now.
.
Thank you all, it means a lot, give me 30 seconds.
It's not a fun first slide, but let's pick it up from here.
The code of conduct is pretty basic to BornHack, and it's actually one of the things that Jesper
also helped out a lot with, I forgot to mention that Morten from the NOC team stepped up and
took Jesper's place in the code of conduct team, so thank you also, Morten, for that.
The code of conduct, you probably have all seen it by now, because it's taped to the
inside of the toilet doors, so it's pretty hard to miss.
We take this seriously.
We expect you to do the same.
It is about being nice to each other and respecting each other's personal space.
It's a photo policy and much more.
Make sure you read it, make sure you follow it.
If you have questions, we are available, there's a conduct team that you can speak to, and
we usually don't have to resort to any major code of conduct things.
People are generally very, very nice to each other here.
We really appreciate it.
We appreciate that, and we think and hope that that will continue, of course, but the
code of conduct is there to be a guideline in case some people have questions about that.
Reach out to the conduct team, please.
Okay.
Like I said, everybody who some people even showed up on the first day or second day,
so have been here almost a week, along with the first officer.
I'm not sure if you can see the difference.
I'm not sure.
It is such a big job putting up all this stuff, and the rain has not, the weather
has not helped one bit.
It has been not only raining, but very unstable, so occasionally raining and occasionally very
hot, so you have to change in and out of outfits every 10 seconds.
There's been a lot of work, and to the people who take extra days off of work and stuff
to come and help make this happen, and also in the other end who stay for the teardown
and extra space.
Rachel, a big thank you.
Can you please all stand up, people who helped with the build-up, so we can see how many people
there actually is?
Thank you.
Born Hackers, like the bar, always a work in progress.
Even though we have had a bit more of a less stressful build-up because we had a few more
days and some stuff got delivered and put up earlier than usual, so it's been a nice example
of a build-up the way it should be and not too stressful and not too many long nights
and stuff, but it would be crazy to think that we have remembered everything and gotten
everything done, so there's still small things to do, and there'll be stuff that keeps popping
up over the week.
We'll put jobs on the whiteboard by the info desk, so if you come by and see something and
think, I can do that, and I have some time and I want to help out, then by all means,
please talk to the info desk or somebody if you need to, or just do the job if it's easy
to do.
If you see something wrong and you can't fix it, then please let us know.
We will find somebody who can fix it.
I have a venue map.
At some point, and the venue continually evolving over the week is exemplified by, I made these
slides two hours ago and the map is already outdated, so bear with me on that.
I'll try to explain what happened when we get to it, but we're rolling with the punches
and we'll make everything work, of course.
Oh, here it is.
It's not terribly big, but...
Yeah, okay.
It's not terribly big.
Okay.
So...
Well, I'll just use the colors.
Okay.
So we are in the white square in the middle of the light blue triangle, the general camping,
and this is the speaker stand.
Across the road, straight ahead is the bar.
It is hard to miss.
It is a big, colorful, loud place with all the beers.
We have northeast of this general camping.
In the pointy end, we have the caravans.
This year, they moved to the other side of the road, and across the road from them, we
have some more general camping for our tents.
On the other, between the bar and general camping is the orga area with the info desk
and all that.
It is also the organizer's personal village and where we go to chill out and get away
from people, like everybody needs to occasionally.
So, please, unless you have something urgent, try to reach somebody in the info desk or
somewhere else, and please stay out of the orga village as much as possible.
Not that we don't love you all, but we also have our stock of booze and everything in
there.
We want to just keep it free of people.
That is for us to drink.
No.
Yeah.
So, following the central main road south, there's an entrance into the food area, and
past the food area, there's the noisy camping area.
Sorry, party camping area.
You don't have to be noisy down there.
On the other side of the road from that is the cozy camping area, which we introduced
last year when we moved the speaker's tent down here.
It has turned out to be quite a nice little camping area.
It's very popular this year.
It's nice to see.
Going further up the road, there's a big shower and toilet building.
All the showers are down in the south end of the venue.
There's a separate building that has two showers and four toilets, and inside the main building,
there's two more showers and two more toilets.
Also, there's two toilets down here by the bar.
That's the venue.
If you have questions...
Oh, and the silent area, the neon light bulb.
No.
The light blue area in the top is the silent camping, and the eastern part of that, or
maybe the western part, it's not fully clear yet, will be converted to an extra caravan
area, because we're kind of running out of space.
There's ample space down there, so we'll kind of remodel the venue a little bit last minute,
forced by...
Well, we kind of estimated wrong, I think, how much room caravans take or something.
Okay.
The info desk is across the road from...
Yeah, and a bit down the road from where we are now.
Many of you have probably been there to get your wristband.
You can come back to get more hacks, get some mate if the bar isn't open, ask questions,
pick up merchandise, pick up the badges when we get to that.
They will be ready soon, I think, tomorrow or the day after or something.
The team needs people to help cover the shifts.
It's not difficult work.
They sit down and just help people, and they have a thorough introduction, so most people
should be able to do it.
They really need some help, so please go to the info desk and ask them if you're interested
in helping out.
They would love to be able to cover the shifts without having to work all of them all the
time.
For those of you who haven't been here before, we have something called Hacks.
You might have heard about it already.
It is our internal...
It is our internal local currency.
We packed it to the Danish Krona, so it is worth the same as Danish Krona.
If something costs 150 hacks, it is the same as 150 Danish Krona.
They can be bought at the info desk or at the bar when the bar is open, or you can buy
them online and just buy them on the web shop and use the ticket in the bar or the info
desk.
You can also use them at the food...
Apart from the info desk and the bar, the food vendor accepts them.
They can basically be used like real money, except the only way to buy alcohol is with
hacks.
You cannot buy it with real money, which is the main reason we have them.
You will need...
If you want to go to the bar and buy anything with any kind of alcohol in it, you will need
to go get some hacks in the info desk to do that.
They are these little...
We haven't even gotten any yet.
Little colored coins.
You will see them everywhere.
Thank you.
Thank you very much.
Okay.
If you order village tents or tables and chairs and stuff, the tents you probably found,
tables and chairs, if you still need to get that, you can go to the info desk.
Please coordinate with the info desk.
Don't just take stuff, because then we have no chance to keep track of it.
It is not logged in.
We know you can just walk up and take it, and we know you have paid for it and stuff,
but please coordinate with us.
It is really tricky to keep track of stuff when people just take it.
Don't just take it and tell us in the bar at 1 a.m.
I took two chairs and four tables.
So please go do it properly in the info desk when they are open.
We may have a few extra tables and chairs and benches.
Go by info tomorrow and check if we have any surplus.
If you forgot to order, you will need some extras.
We have electricity all over the venue.
Thanks to the hard-working power team.
They have rolled out more than a kilometre of the very heavy cables.
And the power points are more or less all over the venue.
Please keep them covered from the rain so we don't have any outages because something got wet.
And if you see one without cover, please fix it yourself or notify somebody who can fix it.
Please don't just ignore it and leave it and think somebody else will do it.
Let everybody help out.
And things will get fixed much quicker and stop from breaking.
There's an example here.
It is not the biggest picture.
But a happy-looking power point.
It has a bag over it.
And the bag is secured with some pegs in the back.
Or what are they called?
Yeah.
Some secured in the back.
It is cloth pegs.
Yeah.
Cloth pegs.
Okay.
Connect your cables if you need an adaptor because we don't have...
We have the weird Danish standard here.
Maybe we have some...
Do we have some in the info desk or not?
I don't know actually.
Ask somebody who knows.
We don't.
Well...
Yeah.
We'll figure it out.
Come ask us if you can't get power because things don't fit.
We'll make it fit somehow.
Along the same lines, the network team have been working hard to get the network up and running.
You can get gigabit Ethernet to your table.
You can get Wi-Fi.
You can even get a fiber blink if you arrange it especially with the network team.
So if you have special needs other than Wi-Fi, you can absolutely get that sorted.
We have three SSIDs.
The bornhack NAT is the one that acts mostly like a home Internet connection.
The bornhack 802.1X is with 802.1X authentication, funnily enough.
And the IPv6 one is with the modern IP family without the legacy IPv4 one.
We get constant requests to use more bandwidth and I guess that applies this year as well.
Does it?
Knock team?
Yes.
Great.
So please use more bandwidth.
The bar, as you can see, is progressing nicely.
It is always fascinating even to, I think, even to the people building it, how it's going to look.
But to everybody watching it during buildup and in the first days, so much happens and it becomes increasingly more awesome as the days go by.
Please use the bar.
It is an important part of the money that we use to make this event work, especially this year.
We've had a few sponsors fall off, fall away, and it's been difficult to make ends meet.
So we've had to cut a few things.
The hot tub, for example, is not here this year.
Very sad to say, but we had to make some difficult cuts here and there, and that was one of the things that we had to take away.
We hope it will be better.
We hope it will be back next year.
But please use the bar.
We absolutely depend on the profits from the bar to make this whole thing work.
We have a very nice selection of craft beer and booze and can make cocktails, and there's all the mate in the world.
We might have slightly overdone it on the mate this year, so please.
There's many, many kinds and many, many bottles of each kind, so that's great.
The bar has closing hours.
We have a permit to sell booze from the authorities, and that ends at 2 a.m. every night.
So there's last rounds at 1.50.
Get your purchases in there.
Get in line.
Get in line, because we have to stop selling alcohol.
And the bar doesn't necessarily have to shut down entirely, but we cannot sell any more alcohol.
So buy your bottles and stuff before 2, and then stick around.
When does it reopen?
Well, I mean...
That is thinking like a hacker.
No, we better not play games with them, but, yeah, it opens when the first bar staff wakes up the next day.
Usually around noon-ish, I would say.
So, yeah.
Okay.
When we are a lot of people gathered, we generate a lot of trash that is inevitable,
from food and drinks and everything.
And it is a lot of work handling trash from just a few hundred people like we are,
generates so much trash and so much deposit, like empty bottles and cans and stuff,
that we need to handle it properly from the beginning to not generate massive amounts of work.
And also, if it's not handled properly, we get wasps and a thousand nasty things as a result of not handling trash properly.
So, we have some trash cans around, and there are signs on them.
Please look at the signs before you put stuff in, so you use the correct trash cans.
We have five different ones.
Two of them are for deposits.
They have this circular logo thing.
It's on the trash cans as well.
And if the bottles have that, you know the system from wherever you live.
And the deposit cans and plastic bottles go in one container.
And the deposit glass bottles go in another container.
Apart from that, there's a glass container for just booze glass bottles or whatever glass that doesn't have deposit.
And one for cardboard.
And finally, one that doesn't fit for all the trash that doesn't fit in any of the others.
Is that pretty clear?
Two different kinds of deposit.
One for cans and plastic bottles.
One for glass.
And then there's glass, cardboard, and the rest.
Okay?
Fantastic.
The people sorting it at the end.
It will send you happy thoughts forever if you don't generate too much sorting.
As you can imagine, sorting 300-400 people's deposit after a week or two is not fun work.
So the less stuff that has been put in wrong, the less we have to sort, the better.
So please spend the extra ten seconds.
Check the signs.
Put it in properly.
And please and thank you from the sanitation team.
Thank you.
Yes?
What about plastic?
Plastic what?
Just general plastic.
Yeah.
In this municipality, they haven't joined the rest of us in the 21st century.
So it's not going to fix this issue?
No, absolutely not.
No, no.
We would sort in ten kinds if we could.
But they are just going to mix it all together when they pick it up anyway.
So there's no reason.
Sadly.
We hope next year we come back and see ten trash cans outside.
But we've been hoping that for four years now.
Let's see when it happens.
Thank you.
Sure.
Good question, though.
OK.
Like I mentioned, we've had a rough time of it with sponsors this year.
But we have managed to find some new sponsors.
And we are, of course, always tremendously grateful for all the support we are getting.
Some sponsors pay cash and help just with the general finances of the event.
Some lenders stuff that we would otherwise have to spend money on getting, which is
just as good as getting money.
And it all helps out.
And even small sponsors that may not be big companies and can't put in that much, it all
helps.
Because I'd much rather have five small sponsors than one big one if the amount is the same,
because it's just nicer.
So to all the sponsors, big and small, thank you to all the people who jumped in when the
shit hit the fan.
And we really needed to find new sponsors on pretty short notice.
Thank you all for jumping in to assist me and the others on the sponsors team and coming
with new leads.
If any of you have an idea for an organization that might want to help, please send them
my way or towards the sponsors' email.
And we can reach out to them.
Thank you.
The absolute most successful way to do it is if you know somebody who can make the decision
about giving some money or not and prepare them and then put us in contact with them.
That method has close to 100% success rate.
And just getting a contact, call this dude and this company, has a close to 0% success
rate.
It is a massive difference.
So if you know somebody, can go poke your boss and say, hey, we should pay 10,000 to
this event next year.
Because they are really cool and they help the community a lot and such and such.
It helps us a lot.
And it's barely any money in a company's budget for the whole year.
Almost no matter how small a company, except ours.
So thank you to all of you who helped find sponsors.
I'll go through them now.
And there will be their logos on the website and everything.
We have a small paper with the badges this year that also have the sponsors' logo on
them.
Please send them your thanks and thoughts and use their services if you at all can.
The big ones this year are DKNOCK, which is another event.
And they're full of lovely networking people.
And they stepped in when they heard we were struggling and helped out a fellow event.
Samdata is a big labor union in Denmark that, among other things, has...
HK is a big labor union.
Samdata is the IT department for IT people.
And Zebra Group is my employer that has lots of companies, among others the one where I'm
employed called MindFuture.
Silver sponsors.
Epson has, for the fourth year in a row, I think, sponsored this very nice video setup
with a high intensity brightness projector that works even when the sun is shining and
the weather is sweet.
So thank you for that.
And that's a good example of something we would otherwise have to go out and rent.
And they are very expensive.
Jobindex and CIMA4 are both new sponsors.
And thank you to those as well.
Among the sponsors are also Bornholm Spirits, who continue to supply.
We started out at Bornholm, but they continue to supply SaberBlurter and other nice things
for us at a very nice price.
Feebaboo is providing the internet connection, not the fiber, but the actual uplink to the
internet.
Magenta, PCBWay, are sponsoring the...
The PCBs for the badges.
And Raymion are sponsoring speakers.
And Roskilde Auto and Skade Center is sponsoring the shuttle car.
And the rest are financial...
No, TukTek is hosting, sponsor for the Bornhack stuff.
And the rest are financial sponsors.
And thank you so much to them.
There's a full year now until the next Bornhack.
And a lot of this sponsor stuff takes some months to settle.
And it's really tricky to do two weeks before Bornhack.
So if you have an idea, get started in the start of next year, not in June or July.
Because it might be too late for decision-makers have gone on holiday and everything.
So spring is a good time to be thinking about sponsors for Bornhack.
Oh, that's quite the segue.
So we are in an area that sometimes has...
Well, all the time has ticks.
And sometimes they latch onto people and sit down by the angles or in humid places on the body.
They are nasty.
They can sometimes rarely but occasionally have a disease.
And it can infect people and can get really nasty.
So if you discover a tick, get it removed as soon as possible.
We have tick removers in the info desk.
And SIRT can help remove them.
It can be difficult to check.
Like it's the back of the knees and weird places.
Have a friend help you in the tent.
It might be fun.
And make sure you check when you're in the shower.
And if you feel that might be a problem,
they are very, very small.
They can look like just a little piece of dirt.
Some of them are incredibly tiny.
So, yeah, make sure you keep an eye out for those little fuckers.
Okay.
Bicycles.
The info desk is the place to go if you need to ride a bike somewhere.
Maybe go shopping or maybe just go for a nice ride around in nature or whatever you need.
We have helmets and locks and lights and stuff for them.
Different sizes.
There's a few children's bikes too.
And there's a trailer or two as well.
They are free still.
This is one of the things we considered introducing a payment for when we were,
because we are struggling a bit financially.
Instead, we suggest a small donation to cover the cost.
But there's no, they are free.
But please consider donating something if you take a bike.
The parking lot.
Most of you arrived by car.
So you will have noticed the parking lot.
I just wanted to mention, please park sensibly.
And, like, don't, it goes without saying, don't double park and don't park so other people can't get out.
There's plenty of room down there for all the tickets we sold if people park sensibly.
So last year we had a, no, two years ago, an annoying incident where we had to run around and find somebody who was parked so other people couldn't get out.
So please consider everybody when you get out.
Everybody when you put your car down.
If there's any issues in the parking lot, please notify the info desk.
We don't necessarily know because we're not, not all of us are driving around.
We arrive here and then we leave two weeks later.
So we might not notice.
So please notify us if there's something with the driving plates or someone is parked badly or something.
If you ordered T-shirts, hoodies, and merchandise, it will be produced during the week.
And when it's ready, we'll announce it and you can pick it up in the info desk.
It is being produced by, yeah, and a few other volunteers.
We're doing a lot of work for it.
And it's always such nice merchandise we get.
So thank you for all the work you're doing.
Oh.
Badges.
This year's badge is NFC focused.
It can, it consists of two badges actually.
There's a reader which is the active part that has the computer and a tag which is a passive thing that can be read with the active part.
It's a very cool setup and it enables a lot of fun NFC hacking.
And we hope to see some cool things, cool applications of it.
As mentioned quite a few times by now, we are kind of broke.
And other events have charged for badges for a while.
And we've never done that because we, yeah, we kind of feel that we would love for this to just be a part of the ticket.
We haven't announced this earlier because we've been trying to secure sponsors to make it fully free.
That has not been possible.
A badge is 100 hacks.
If you have a full week ticket, then you have a QR code.
QR code in the same PDF as your ticket.
And you can use that to get a hacks, sorry, a badge for 100 hacks.
If you want additional badges or you are here on a one day ticket or you want one to take home to a friend or something, it's 150 hacks.
Hopefully next year we can go back to the full week tickets including a badge in the prize.
Sadly this was the best we could do this year.
The badges will be presented tomorrow.
Thank you.
The badges will be presented tomorrow at 1300 by Floma from the badge team who will talk about the design and what it can do.
And I'm sure there will be a lot of fun things about it.
They look, I wanted to include a picture but I didn't have time.
They look fantastically cool.
So I'm looking forward to seeing them all around the venue.
Thank you.
So we still have a few teams that need members.
The info team is continuously onboarding new people.
They always need people to set up there.
Sometimes they have to sit two or three people to manage the load.
And it just takes a lot of volunteers to keep the info desk open.
The video team manages this stuff right here.
Make sure stuff is recorded and streamed.
And we can watch the recordings later.
Or at least sit in the tents and watch the streams live.
Not everything is recorded.
Please make sure you note in the program if there's a little recording icon or not.
And if not, you have to be present here if you want to see it.
The stuff that's being recorded, if you're prevented from seeing it, you can catch it later on the stream.
If you want to join the video meeting, the video team, there's an onboarding meeting tomorrow Thursday at noon here in the speaker's tent.
They have a very thorough onboarding.
And it looks a bit intimidating, all the equipment.
But it is easy to do.
And you get a first-row seat for the talks.
And we would appreciate help with that.
The sanitation team, colloquially Team Shit, handles...
They do not clean toilets.
Might occasionally unclog one.
But cleaning is handled by an external cleaning company.
But they handle stuff like making sure there's handpaper.
Handpaper towels and soap and stuff in the toilets.
And the trash being emptied and put in the container.
And the deposit bags being emptied and stuff like that.
So it's handling all the waste but not actually cleaning toilets.
We have people for that.
They're also onboarding continuously.
And you can go to the info desk and speak to Anke, I guess, if you're interested in joining.
On the website, there's a list of teams.
And you can see there which ones still need members.
We've also, as a new initiative, started a daily volunteer meeting every day at 14.00.
It is in the start tent across from the info desk.
And it is an attempt to keep some of the awesome communication going we've had during build-up.
We have meetings after each meal.
And we have breakfast, lunch, and dinner prepared by Jonathan, which is always fantastic.
And after that, we have a conference.
And we talk about what needs to be done.
And people put up their hands and go do stuff.
And that kind of stops when the event starts because we lose contact to all the volunteers.
We don't have these regular meetings anymore.
And we want to remedy that by doing this daily volunteer meetup at 14.00.
Everybody, you don't have to be on a team.
If you don't have anything to do, if you want to help out, show up at the start tent across from info desk.
One of the recurring themes will be,
since we are a bit broke this year, we could not afford as much cleaning as we normally can.
So the food area will not be clean for us.
We have to do that ourselves.
And one of the things we will do every day at 2.00 is to take a bunch of volunteers,
go down there, do the tornado, make it look really nice.
And hopefully we can keep it going.
You are also, of course, all required to clean up after yourself when you use the food area,
when you cook, when you do dishes.
If you spill something, please fix it yourself.
It's not necessary.
It's not necessary to say.
But we know that when many people use the kitchen, no matter how careful everybody is,
there's going to be spills and stuff that needs cleaning.
And since there are no cleaners doing it, we have to do it ourselves.
If you see something, clean it up.
Absolutely.
That would be fantastic.
But we are planning to take a team of people once a day and give it the once over.
So it stays nice and inviting to use.
So if you feel like helping out with that and other stuff that pops up,
it will be every day at 14.00 in the volunteer tent.
We hope to see many people.
And we are excited to introduce this new...
We think it's going to be a great addition to an already great event.
SIRT are here to take care of us in case something happens.
It is our medic team.
We take care of small and big things like ticks or small cuts or worse.
We haven't had much of the worst, but we have people to handle it in case it happens.
We have a hard starter.
We have first aid kits.
We have educated people who have been in situations where they have to take care of people before.
And we are in good hands.
They are wearing orange vests.
They can be called on the radio.
You can call the born hack phone.
There will also be...
If you have a deck phone, then there's a...
You can call 112 on the deck phone.
And there's a lot of ways to get in touch with them.
And they will also be visible on the site.
There's always 24 hours a SIRT person on duty.
They need more people, if I recall correctly.
Yes.
And they have a team meeting Thursday.
That's tomorrow at 11 in the cabin.
I can't see if you're nodding.
Yes.
Thank you.
In the cabin.
And they need team members.
And they need members, yes.
You don't have to be like a trained anything.
But it, of course, helps if you are.
Photo team will wear white vests.
It is...
They are recognizable for a good reason.
We have a code of conduct, like I mentioned.
And one of the important...
One of the parts of it, they're all important, is that you're not allowed to take pictures
at Bonn Heck unless everybody or all people in the photo agree to the photo being taken.
This means I cannot take a crowd photo here.
It would take forever to ask everybody.
Well, I have a microphone.
But still, generally, you can take crowd pictures.
It's tricky.
And it's sad.
But we have to protect people's privacy.
And prioritize that over people's desire to take cool pictures of crowds.
We do, however, want to see cool pictures.
And that is quite the dilemma.
So we have a photo team.
They all know...
Well, you all know the code of conduct because you've used the toilets.
But they know...
A lot of people here personally know who they can take pictures of and who has already said no.
And if they see new people, they might come and ask, is it okay I take a picture here?
You are free to say no and stay where you are.
You are free to say no and step out.
And the photographer can take the picture, make it work somehow.
But they are visible in white vests and, of course, a piece of huge optics around their neck.
And...
And they will ask permissions for pictures.
And if you feel like a picture has been taken where you weren't asked or maybe you were in it or you are not sure,
you are very welcome to go ask the photographer to see the pictures and browse through.
And if you feel like you are on one of them or you are...
Then it can be deleted.
But it shouldn't happen.
They are careful and they know what they are doing.
I'm not sure.
Does the photo team need more people?
Yes, everybody is welcome.
Okay, so if you like taking pictures and this sounds like something you could and would do,
then talk to Tobias Fonsmark and he can introduce you to the whole thing.
There is a meeting tomorrow at noon.
Is it also in the cabin?
Yes, exactly.
Also in the cabin.
Great.
The game team has prepared a token game again this year.
The tokens are little text strings.
They are hidden around the venue offline and online on physical signs or it could be on servers or networks.
There are all kinds of things.
There are hints in your profile on the website.
And I think they will keep adding tokens throughout the week.
And the hunt is usually great.
The hunt is usually competitive and fun and it's kind of like a treasure hunt for nerds all around the venue.
It is a great tradition and I hope many of you will play.
I know the game team has put a lot of work into it.
The last slide is just a thank you to the volunteers.
This event would not be possible without the volunteers.
That goes without saying.
We are, what, 11 people in the Orga group and it would absolutely not be possible to do all this without them.
Without 30 or 40 people helping out with carrying stuff around and helping us with our crazy ideas.
And, hey, we want to build a weird thing here.
Can you?
And people just run over and start building.
It's just fantastic to be around people with this kind of drive and this kind of passion.
And it's so nice that you throw that drive and that passion towards helping us make this event even more fantastic.
So, again, thank you all.
And a big thanks to the rest of our colleagues as well.
Thank you.
Please consider showing up for the meetings at the 1400.
We've been a bit jiggy and added it to the schedule, so it will show up in your giggity and in your feedreaders and calendars and stuff.
So give it a try, show up if you have nothing else to do.
I added this slide in case I thought of something to say.
I wanted to say one thing.
talking, but I haven't.
So I don't think I have anything else, but if any team leads may have comments or stuff
I forgot to include that would be relevant to include now, then we can do that.
We are getting a microphone, just a second.
Is there a regular Bonhag network?
Is there?
Yes.
Oh, I didn't see.
Oh, sorry.
There's four SSIDs and one of them is just called Bonhag and it's a plain old public
V4 and V6.
You get a real IP address.
Make sure your firewall is properly configured because that's like going on the old school
internet back in the 90s.
It's supposed to be.
It's not.
Oh, damn.
Okay.
I'll repeat because the audio was a bit low.
If you ordered village gear and you ordered the black upholstered chairs, sorry, you ordered
the white garden chairs and accidentally instead took the black upholstered chairs, please
bring them back because we need them.
The people who actually ordered them need them.
And come back and get some V4s.
Thanks.
white garden chairs instead.
Basically, the garden chairs, the white ones, are
good for the grass, and the other ones are good for when
you have a floor in your
tent. It's
kind of late to change now, because we can't
change the order, but
if you did get the
upholstered chairs, and you have those on your receipt,
and you know, you know what
I'm saying. If you took the wrong chairs,
please bring them back. Thank you.
Any
other questions?
Just ask without the microphone.
How do you submit a category
to Hacker Jeopardy? Oh, that's a very
good question.
The Hacker Jeopardy will be on tomorrow,
and then again Saturday,
and again Monday for the finals.
Sign-ups is
to info at bornhack.dk
by mail. We already got the first sign-up
a few days before the event,
and
we always, the game team, always
needs more categories.
If you've played Hacker Jeopardy before,
or been a
spectator,
you know what this is about.
It is
find a fun category, find some questions that are
not too difficult.
The one trap people always fall in
is like, okay, I'm an expert on this,
I'll make a category so difficult that I'm
the only person in the room who can answer it.
And that's just
not a lot of fun to other people than the person
who knows all the answers.
What we want is categories
that go from the most difficult one,
maybe
maybe 25% knows it,
and the easiest one, almost everybody knows it,
and it's a chase for the buttons.
It has to be, it's much more fun that way.
Trust us, we've tried both ways,
and take our words for it.
So please send categories to,
is there a game-team at bornhack.dk
and send your categories, or send questions.
If you don't know quite how to formulate it,
they will be happy to get you started.
If you're playing and you submitted a category,
please let us know the day you're on,
so we don't accidentally schedule your own questions
when you're playing.
Yeah, yes?
I missed POC in this point.
It would be fun to say that DECT is working now.
For the first time in a few years,
we have a working DECT network.
Thank you to the POC team for getting that up and running.
Thank you.
This means you can go to the website,
register a phone number in the phone book there
with your account, and then you get an activation code,
you dial that on your DECT phone, and you are rolling.
It's easy, and it's fucking awesome,
and I'm looking forward to getting my own phones hooked up
as soon as I don't have a million other things to do.
So, oh, any more questions?
I can't really see.
You forgot to give a hand to the Orca team.
Thank you.
We love you, too.
We forgot to say, you can spot the organisers from these very snazzy latest fashion black
vests that we're wearing this year.
So black vests for Orca, white vests for photo team, orange for SIRT, and the yellow vest
is other volunteers.
So that's the colour scheme for this year, or hopefully going forward.
OK, fantastic.
We got through it.
Under an hour.
That's the new record, and I almost didn't cry, and we're pretty good.
So...
See you at the bar!
Yes, exactly.
We'll see you all at the bar.
Thank you for everything.