It has become possible, at least for all my webcam and screen share videos, so I'm going
to share that with you today, how that is helping me, and hopefully you can get some
inspiration from that, either to improve your own setup or to see, hey, okay, that's maybe
not so difficult. Maybe I can start putting some videos out there as well. So that's it.
Why am I doing this? Well, that's because 11 years ago, I quit my daytime job to become
a writing instructor. A year later, I figured out that being a self-employed writing instructor
with a small kid and a family you want to see sometimes, that's not super easy, so I
decided I would try to take some of that.
My teaching online, back then, 10 years ago, we were like two people in Denmark who did
online courses on horse training, so people were a bit like, oh, that's weird, but also
pretty interested because it brought some knowledge to them that they had a hard time
obtaining in other ways without driving a long while to get there or something like
that.
So this is me 10 years ago, almost to the date.
It was all bit women's 01s, but the thing was, I think that the technical心 tribal
issues imagining did a great job because I used to go out in Denmark as well with a couple
of women exchange lines and somethings and things, but not much you can do together.
It was, I don't want to complain, but you know, just being a kind-quality person, I
passed the four year, but I didn't seem to be able to get anywhere other than to train
my children.
Thank you.
Thank you, Kai.
not so super, also the internet connection back then was like
terrible, but I managed.
It
improved a wee bit pretty fast by
switching webinar provider.
I've always been
sort of both compassionate but also a bit
picky about how my teaching content shall be because I know
it makes a difference for people. I've used to be a teacher and
I know it makes a difference to people if you're just
providing them talking slides
or if you actually are there on webcam. Even if it's
a grainy old webcam with a fussy
image, it makes a difference that people can actually see you and can feel a
connection to you
when you're teaching online. So
I upgraded my system to something where I actually felt that
they could see me better
and that worked.
Then I started doing
also not just live webinars but also recording videos and this here, this is
some of the videos that took a long time to produce compared to
the video time because I had to record the slides
presentation first or have the images for that and put into my video editor.
Then I had to sit there and talk about the slides,
record that, put them together, put the logo on,
put the text on and
that took usually longer than actually doing the video.
Then the video had to process afterwards before I could upload it.
It was boring.
That is like 2015.
Then in 18, as I said, I met OBS at my first born hack.
I had been looking at it previously because I heard someone talk about it at some
marketing webinar I had attended but it was like, ah, it's a bit, it's difficult and I
don't really know what to do about it.
But then when I had my hands in it at
born hack, I was like, yeah, okay, oh, so there's something about scenes and there's
something about sources, ah, I get that now.
I can go back and use this.
Still took me six months because as far as I could tell when I was digging through my
archives yesterday, I only started using OBS in January 2019.
So that's like almost four and a half years ago now.
This is one of the first attempts.
The video series where I put myself in in the corner and I had some background images
that I could switch like slides and that worked really well and it was still like a one-take
video.
Of course, doing one-take videos means that you need to actually know what you're going
to talk about and not make that many mistakes and stuff, but today I much rather do, if
I'm doing like a 10-minute video.
10 minutes.
I try not to make them longer, but if I'm doing like a 10-minute video or 5-minute video,
if something goes wrong, I just restart.
It's a lot faster than actually having to go back and edit out a cough attack or whatever.
So it really, really helps my flow in content creation.
This is then in May 2019 where I started doing.
I started doing screen share videos.
My business had then moved on from doing, as you can see, this has not much to do with
horses.
I'm now primarily teaching other people how to use the online course and email marketing
system called Simplero.
I've been doing that since 2015, 16, where it slowly took over.
So, today, my main video production is Simplero.
So today, my main video production is Simplero.
I started doing all this videos where I'm on screen share and I show something from
inside Simplero and tell people how to set up a course or create an email series or do
fancy automation stuff.
So, I started doing these courses also back sometime in 2019 and this is what it looked
like back then.
So, today, I'm going to be inspiring my customers to use my inland work.
And this is then what it looks like today.
I've gone to green screen.
So now I can just put myself in without sitting in a square
with some sort of background.
That's really nice, and that's also built in in OBS.
Also, I use this to stream.
This is actually from, I have like a membership club
for people who are using Simplero.
And we do monthly themes, and they are like live streamed.
We have a Facebook group.
So I live stream it to the Facebook group using OBS.
So I get a high quality local recording of the stream,
because then it's not the stream.
Then it's just what's happening on my desktop.
Then I also stream it to Facebook.
And then afterwards, I take the recorded video
from my desktop computer and upload it
to Simplero.
So the course material in Simplero.
So I have both this option.
I don't know.
You're probably not that much of a Facebook crowd.
But in Facebook, if you do live, you
can either do screen share or do webcam.
You can't combine them.
When I use OBS to stream, I can combine totally like I want.
So I have full control.
And I get the local recording in high quality.
And I could also use this to stream to YouTube or any other
service where you can stream with a stream key.
So that's really, really nice.
And that makes my work so much easier also.
I've also been doing like if you want
to teach something about like a creative process or thought
process, then it's not always the best.
Like people get so much, especially
during corona, people had so much of everything being online
and people just doing talking slide presentations.
And it kind of gets boring.
If you need to keep people's attention,
then you should mix things up.
So what I have on my desk is I have a second webcam mounted
on an arm.
So I can take that and point it down on my desk.
And then I can have a writing pad.
And I can.
I can sketch up things, either if I want to design flows
or I want to sketch out a thought process
or whatever it is I want to do.
I can actually do that and put that on webcam as well.
And then I still have myself down in the corner.
So I can also look up, put down the pen, and sit there
and talk to people.
And this is, I know from my students,
that they are like.
I'm really happy about this way of doing things.
I could also be standing by a whiteboard or whatever
I wanted to do that was like something else.
I had been looking into, oh, maybe I
should get one of those fancy drawing pads for my computer.
And because I wanted to do some live drawing stuff,
and then I was like, hmm, I have an extra webcam.
I have pen.
I have paper.
How does that work?
And that actually works excellent.
So that's it.
Thank you.
So that's a way of mixing things up.
And that's totally easy to set up several camera sources
in OBS.
And I can switch between the scenes so that I can do this.
And then I can switch to another scene where I have screen share.
Or I can switch to another scene where it's just me on webcam.
And I can sort of spice my teaching up a bit
without having to do all that editing that, for me, I know
some people are probably editing faster than me.
But for me, at least, it takes a lot of time.
And it isn't really worth it.
I could maybe get like 2%, 3%, 4%, 5% fancier videos
if I decided to do after editing.
But that's really, really not worth it.
So this is how things look today.
This is how it looks from inside OBS.
And in a second, I'm going to show you how it looks from inside OBS.
I'm going to switch over so you can see.
I'm going to open OBS here on my machine.
And then we can take a look at how does this actually work.
How do we set it up?
What do you need to be aware of?
And then there will be some room for questions.
Yeah?
So.
Oh, yeah.
Just a second.
I wanted to show you my setup as well.
So this is my desktop at home being unusually tidy.
So I have like two screens.
Because if you're working with OBS,
you can do that in a one-screen setup.
But it's really, really, really nice to have like two screens.
So you can have whatever you are, if you're doing a screen share,
then you have whatever you're working with on the front screen.
And then you have OBS.
Or if you have some chat you need, you can do that.
But if you have something you need to pay attention to,
you have that on the other screen.
That's a really, really big help.
And I also highly recommend that, even if you don't use OBS,
if you're doing any other sort of webinars or anything
where you need to be able to both screen share something
or have your slides and also keep an eye on a chat
or some other tech that is running, it's really, really, really, a lot easier.
If you have at least two screens.
I teach a lot of my clients are like not very techie.
And when I come and say, yeah, you should probably
get an extra screen.
And they're like, but I only have my MacBook.
And then we'll have to figure out how to attach an extra screen
because it's just so much easier.
I have a microphone and I have an external webcam.
And that's basically it.
What you maybe can see in the corners of the desk
is I have a couple of, that's like 20 vat halogen, not halogen,
LED working lights that are pointing away from me
because they create a pretty good ambient light.
So that's a lot easier than buying some very fancy studio lights.
If you have some.
Why?
Oh, wait, is walls that you control the light up on
and then it comes back that that really makes a big difference.
I tried buying one of them.
Famous ring lights.
Because like there, so fancy, right?
But I have glasses.
And if you have glasses and you're sitting in front of a ring light,
you have ring light in your glasses.
And that doesn't really look that good on videos.
Actually you can see it in the, it's also
reflected in the eyes of people that have ring light.
So you can you can see it.
inside there, the irises.
So I still have the ring light, but now it's mounted under the ceiling and it's also pointing
away from me, so it's creating ambient light instead of shining directly in my eyes.
So that's the setup.
I also bought a low-noise mouse and keyboard, because I found out at some point that when
I was sitting doing things and setting things up and I needed to type, all that typing,
especially with the microphone so close to the keyboard, that was sort of annoying.
But basically, I would say get a decent webcam, get a second monitor so you have at least
two.
Okay.
And you can see here, this is my green screen setup, so this is, this image is looking the
other way.
My office is not very big, and I have my back up to a, what do you call that, a cabinet
with a lot of glassware.
It's brown.
It's not very pretty.
It showed on some of my first webinar videos.
Then I got a white roller blind that I couldn't put up, that I mounted in the ceiling, so
I could roll that down when I was doing videos, and I could pull it up again when I needed
to go to the cupboard behind me.
And now I've upgraded that, so now I have mounted just basically a piece of vibrant
green sheet on the roller blind, fastened it with magnets so it's easy to remove.
And that's my green screen.
And that's working really, really well.
So that's like a super cheap setup to get a green screen, so you can remove your background,
put yourself in any background you want.
Even when I'm doing, I do a lot of Zoom meetings, and Zoom also has all these virtual backgrounds
thing, but you can really, really see if people, I'm sure you have had meetings with people
that are using virtual background and are not sitting on like a uniform.
Then if they have a headset on, sometimes the headset disappears, sometimes their ears
disappear, sometimes their arms disappear.
If you're using a green screen and you tell Zoom that you actually have a green screen,
it is working much, much better.
So you won't be as fussy as the usual virtual background function.
So I really like that.
It has upped my game a lot.
Cheers.
Yeah.
I think that was the last slide.
Yes, it was.
Good.
So OBS.
Open Broadcaster Software.
It's open source, so it's free.
It's running on Windows, Mac, Linux.
I'm on a Linux machine.
And it runs real.
really well. It also had a built-in virtual webcam function, so like if you're using some
program where you need to put in your webcam that, for instance, the software I use for,
I use this really, it's a nice software to do webinars in called Webinar Jam, but the
customer support is like really, really crappy, so I can't really recommend them, but I signed
up so long ago that I'm like grandfathered into the big plan forever, so hey, it works,
and I like to use it, but I don't really recommend it, but they don't have a streaming function.
I can't put in, I can't get a stream key for them and then say I just want to stream my
OBS feed into Webinar Jam. I have to use my webcam, and can of course do slides and webcam
and stuff, but they don't have.
Now they have sort of a virtual background function for the webcam, but it's not very
good, so I'm like I would much rather just take my OBS feed, put that into Webinar Jam
or whatever else service I'm using, and now there's a virtual webcam function in OBS,
so I can just tell Webinar Jam to use my virtual webcam. That's not super, there's sometimes
a bit of a delay, so it's not necessarily super good for Zoom.
But I think that I can do it.
If you're using a virtual meeting, you can do it, but those real time meetings is maybe
not always the good solution, but it can be done. But it works super well for webinars,
and that makes it a lot easier. Then I don't have to use all the controls in the webinar
program to switch between slides and webcam, and I just do everything in OBS as I used
to do.
And I can even make the local recording in OBS as well to get the high-quality recording
that I want.
So I love OBS.
It's like one of my absolutely favorite tools.
So what does it look like?
I do run a slightly old version on my laptop for some reason, so it might look slightly
different if you go and install a new version now.
I just only realized a few days ago, and then I didn't want to rock the boat by running
a big upgrade.
But the principles are the same.
What we have here is you can put it in down here I have studio mode.
This is what we have here where we have like a preview screen and a program screen.
Actually, those of you that can see the setup up here, where we're using the
black magic box, it has the same principle.
You have program, that is what we are streaming live or showing or recording, and preview
is what we will, if we click the transit button, get instead of what we are recording or streaming
now.
So that's like the main setup that we have these two scenes that we're looking at.
And a scene in OBS is like a combination of
sources.
So you can have a number of scenes that you're switching between.
This scene I have right here.
And this is if it's in studio mode.
I can also just say I'm only doing like one scene.
I don't want the studio mode thing.
But I really like that I can have usually what I'm doing is I have one scene that is
just me and webcam, maybe with a background image of like I have
the
a starting slide or something like that, or title slide.
So I have that as the background.
And then I switch to me with screen share and the webcam.
And of course, at home, I have the green screen.
So what we have here is we put in the scene.
So we have a scene.
And we can rename that to something.
That makes sense.
So we could call this one.
That didn't really work.
Yes, it did work.
So we call this webcam and screen.
So that's one scene.
And I can have here I have now I have adjusted some resolution.
So I have to like if I can
do this.
I'm moving that one.
This is a lot easier with a real mouse, you know.
There we go.
And now I move the video capture device somewhere else.
I need to see if I can grab that and drag it back in.
There it goes.
There.
So I can put myself in the corner here.
Here it goes.
Yes.
So that is like we have a screen with screen share and the webcam.
That would be a quite usual setup for me.
I could also put in my logo and some text at the bottom if I wanted to do that.
Then if I say, hey, I want to have another screen that is just me on the webcam maybe,
then I go and say here I can add a scene.
There's a little plus down here.
So add a scene and then we call that just webcam.
And it's a really good idea.
Tiny piece of advice.
Label your scenes in a sane way.
Because like three years later, when you're running still on the same setup,
and you have like 20 different scenes and they are all labeled something weird,
it makes it a bit hard to go in and see what is actually the two scenes I need to use today.
That will, of course, never happen.
But I'm going to do that.
I'm going to do that.
Okay.
I don't know what happened to you, but that happened to me.
So label it.
Then we have to go here and see now it says here we don't have any sources.
Yeah, I know.
So I go and add a source.
And I say I want, since this one was supposed to be webcam only,
I go and add a video capture device.
And since I already have...
An input device for my built-in webcam, I just go and say I want to add this one.
So I click add existing, and then I can take this one.
And I can say okay.
So now I have the webcam.
Then we can say...
And it's...
Then we can see, oh, but it's four by three.
It's not 69.
So I can go and right-click this one.
And we can say settings, properties.
I'm going to show you how to do the green screen as well in a moment.
So I have here...
I can see what is this...
What's the device?
It's input one.
What's the video format?
Resolution.
Then I can say, hey, can this actually do...
It can do 1280 by 720.
So that's at least 69.
That was what I wanted.
I can change the frame rate.
So it can only...
It can only do a frame rate of 10 if I set the resolution to 720.
So that's maybe not so impressive.
And there's also something about color range.
This is also where you can experiment with if your color settings are not correct, if you need it to zoom in or something like that.
You set that here under setting for the camera.
You have all these settings here, like set the power line frequency to 50 and stuff like that.
So you have all the controls for your webcam inside.
OPS are small.
Then...
And see now we changed the resolution.
So now it got like way too big.
Oops.
That was not what I tried to do.
So we just need it to exactly fit here.
Bridge.
So that goes, fits.
So if this was at home and I was using my green screen, then I would also add the filter.
Because green screen, that lives in filters.
So I go down here to the bottom and I pick filters.
And then I can say I want to...
Add an effect filter.
If I could get to the bottom of this.
Oh, my screen is too small.
How do I do that?
Now that's a good question.
There goes.
So here I have the effect filters and I want to add that.
And I have what's called a chroma key.
And that is the...
So chroma, that's something with color.
So we need to fill out and call this one green screen.
So I can remember what it is.
And then I can choose what type of screen am I sitting with.
Do I have a green, blue, magenta, or custom color?
Sometimes you need to say custom.
And then give it a slightly...
If your green screen is a different shade of gray, or not gray, green.
You might have to tell it exactly what color green your green screen is.
But otherwise, just go with green.
And then you can experiment with these.
So now there's like nothing green behind me.
So it isn't working.
But what you need to do is you need to experiment a bit with similarity, smoothness, and spill reduction.
To make it fit your setup with your webcam, your lightning, the exact color of your green screen.
So that it actually removes the background.
But it doesn't remove all of you.
Or you don't get green hair unless you have that already.
If you have green hair already, green screen is a really bad idea.
Also, don't wear...
Green clothes.
Don't wear a multicolored scarf with green stuff.
Actually, I've had issues when I've been wearing this old Bornhack or Bornhack t-shirts with the green logo on them.
Then you can see it's a minor detail.
But then you'll suddenly see...
Then you become transparent where the logo is.
You can see the back...
Whatever is behind you in the layers here on the screen.
That they will appear through whatever green clothing you have on.
I still haven't...
I need to get like a long-sleeved green roller neck sweater to play around with.
I haven't gotten to that.
But I think that would be fun.
So you could be a talking head?
Exactly.
Then I can become totally a talking head.
In the middle of the screen.
And also need some green gloves.
I had an issue once where I did a webinar where I needed to talk about...
That was on horse training where I needed to talk about like comfort zone or zone of development or zone of danger.
So like where you are, are you comfortable or are you...
It's a bit exciting or a bit too interesting but it's still okay.
Or is it feeling like really dangerous?
And I had three pieces of paper.
A green, a yellow and a red.
And whenever I hold up the green piece of paper, it just disappeared and showed the background.
I was like, oh, I need to do something else about this.
I had to figure out a way to actually...
I think I found a very different shade of green paper.
And then it kind of worked.
But you have to think about what you're doing when you're using green screen like this.
Because it actually filters out anything green.
So...
But that will give some interesting effects sometimes.
But it is pretty easy to just put this in.
Also, if I wanted to have maybe that...
Okay, now I wanted to use the 16.9.
And not the 4.3 output of my webcam.
But I want to just cut a wee bit off.
And the sides.
I could put in another filter as well.
I think...
Yeah, that's like a crop.
So I could say...
Like...
We just call that crop.
And then I can say, okay, so on the left, I want to crop 100 pixels.
And on the right, I want to crop 100 pixels.
There it goes.
If I for some reason wanted to do that.
So now my input is smaller.
And then maybe I want to turn it to the side.
Maybe I want to put it in the middle.
Whatever.
But I have put like a bit of cropping on the sides without altering the input format.
So that can also be helpful.
That can also be helpful if like you have your webcam put in a position where it...
Of course, if you need the entire width of the webcam, that's not a good solution.
But like if you have a corner that will always be shown on your webcam where your green screen isn't covering or something like that,
you can just crop that out without actually having to alter the resolution.
So now if I say I have this, I want to now do my live presentation or something like that.
Then I'll have to set up some streaming.
And I do that by going here to Tools, I think.
No.
Settings.
Here.
Under File, we have Settings.
And then I have like...
There's like a ton of settings.
And it's...
You basically start with the default settings.
And then see where that takes you.
One of the things I really, really also like about using OBS, that is because it's open source,
it has so many users and there's like a ton of videos on YouTube about using OBS.
So if you find a function and you're a bit like, hmm, how should I do that?
Go Google.
Find a video on YouTube.
See what people say.
Check out a different couple of videos to see who...
Is saying something sensible.
Because it's usually very easy to find information on whatever it is you need.
That also means if you have some sort of issue, there's someone, probably someone who already had that.
If you have an issue with a specific webcam that isn't working or something like that,
there's a good chance that someone else has already had that problem and have solved it.
So I really like that.
And also because it is a program that is widely used, there's a lot of development going on.
So there's continuously coming new versions.
But what we wanted to look at is, we might look at the output first.
Because if I want to do a recording, I want to make sure that I'm actually recording in the format that I would like.
So I say, yes, we want the encoder to be 264.
That makes sense.
Something about the audio bitrate, that's probably okay.
We can turn on some advanced encoder settings, but usually that's not necessary.
And we can say, what is the recording quality?
Same as stream, that's usually recommended.
Because if the computer needs to...
both create a stream in one resolution and a video output in another resolution, it has to work harder.
If you have a big computer with a lot of resources, that's not a problem.
If you're working on a laptop, then maybe you need to do that.
Actually it says here, recordings cannot be paused if the recording quality is set to same as stream.
Yeah, that kind of makes sense.
There's now, that wasn't when I started, but now there is a pause function.
So if you're doing something and then you hit a snag and you need to investigate something,
that happens a lot when I do videos.
It's like when you sit with a live piece of software and you demo that,
there might be something weird going on sometimes.
So sometimes, if I'm like five minutes into a video,
and I've been demoing some new feature or something like that,
and then something unexpected happens,
what I do instead of having to start over is I say,
I'll just, just a second, I'll investigate this,
and then I hit the pause button, that's if I'm not live,
then I hit the pause button,
and then I can go investigate and figure out,
have I misunderstood this feature?
Do we have a bug?
Is this doing what it's actually supposed to do?
Did I just click something wrong?
What happened?
And then I can go back to OBS and my screen share,
and I can pick up where I left, and I can say,
okay, so what we need to do is this, this, this,
again, instead of having to restart the recording
and start from the beginning.
Recording format, it defaults to Matroska,
which usually works really, really well.
There's also audio settings, video settings.
So we have, like, the canvas resolution,
and then we have the output resolution.
So the canvas resolution, that's what we are working on
in the program or preview,
and then we have the output scale resolution,
and we need to have the, you can see here,
like, the aspect ratio on the canvas,
is 1600 to 899.
That's, like, as close to 16.9 as you'll get, right?
I'm not really sure what happened to the last pixel here
since it's not 1600 by 900, but hey.
Yeah, we have a question there.
Can you hand him to me?
Then I'll just grab a bit of water.
And I need to hurry up.
What's the point of having a canvas bigger
than what we are going to actually output to,
because scaling might get lost?
Yeah, yeah.
You are absolutely right.
Usually I would also, I'm not quite sure
why it has default to the 1600.
I would usually make those the same because it's annoying.
And I would usually set this to 1080 for output
because then I get, like, the maximum quality on my videos.
One of the things you need to be aware of
if you're screen sharing is that if you're using, like, 1080
and people are maybe watching it on their phones
or on a smaller screen size, then things will become, like,
rather tiny where they are looking, like, nice and sharp
on your big screen than you can in your browser
when you're visiting any page.
Now I have, like, a really crappy resolution here.
But if you just, if you're on a page that you want to screen share
and you are working in a high resolution
and you want your audience to have a chance
to actually pick up on what you're doing,
you can use control and plus.
And I usually run on 125% zoom.
Because that actually makes it a lot easier
for my audience to see what's going on
if they're sitting on a smaller screen than me.
And I can keep the high resolution quality
on the videos, on the webcam, on everything.
I kind of like that.
Yeah, we have another question there.
So this is also regarding the base canvas resolution
and the output scaled resolution.
So, for example, I'm doing a broadcast
or recording on my computer,
but my computer has a 4K screen.
Here is where I can choose, hey, what people see is just 1080p?
Yeah.
And it does the downscaling?
Okay.
And I saw there's also a recording option.
Then the recording is also the downscaled version.
Yeah.
Okay.
Thank you.
And that's a good point.
So, and also, if you're using, like,
if you're using background images,
it's a really good idea that whatever background image
you're using is actually
your canvas size.
So if I have a 1600 by 900 canvas size,
I should make my background images that size
because then I don't have to scale them.
Then I'll get a better quality.
So that's good to keep in mind.
The last thing I wanted to show you
before we have time for a few questions more,
that's, like, the stream.
You just go to the stream here,
and then you choose whatever services
they have some predefined sources you can use.
I found out that choosing Facebook Live
actually doesn't work.
I usually need to say custom,
not Twitch, custom.
There it goes.
And then I, from my Facebook,
it tells me the server,
and it tells me the stream key.
And in Facebook, I can set up so that I have
for the same Facebook,
I have a recurring stream key,
so I don't have to go into OBS every time
and change the stream key.
That is, of course, less secure.
If someone should obtain my stream key,
they can now stream to my Facebook groups.
But the risk of that happening is not, like, enormous.
And if it happens, I can go and reset my stream key.
But you, of course, need to be aware
that that's the risk of reusing stream keys.
But it's a lot easier.
You don't have to go into OBS every time
and paste in the new stream key when you're going live.
There's also, you can program hotkeys,
and there's other settings.
But basically, this is OBS.
This is my Swiss Army knife for video production.
I love working in it.
It saves me, I have no idea,
over the last, now, four and a half years,
how many hours of editing work this has saved me.
I just love that I can get an idea to a video,
I can create the setup.
Usually, it's only like editing a small piece of text
or something like that in the scenes I already have.
I sit down, I click record,
I show whatever it is I want to show.
This could also be something to a client
if I need to tell them how to set up something specific
in their Simplero account.
I go into their Simplero account.
I do a short recording with OBS.
I upload it to their account.
I send them an email and say,
hey, here's the video.
And I don't need to do any,
after processing, the Matruska video is just ready to use
as soon as I hit stop recording on OBS.
I love it.
It's fantastic.
Yeah?
Any questions?
Hello again.
So the question I have is I use,
I personally use a fork of OBS,
but I'm considering using OBS itself
because it's well maintained.
The software I use is also an older version
and I only have a single screen.
And you early showed you have a studio mode
and a single mode screen thingy.
Yeah.
So studio mode is just switching between
showing like two,
both the preview and the program
or only having...
Yeah.
So mine looks like this.
And when you were doing your talk in studio mode,
I saw when you were building scenes,
you can just play around in the scene,
adding sources.
And on the right side for us,
that is what is live.
And then the left side is...
The left side is always preview.
And the right side is always live.
How do you push the preview to the live?
Yeah.
Then I just hit transition
and then I switch to the new scene.
Yeah.
Because for example,
when I do a broadcast or at work,
I need to present something.
Sometimes they ask something,
I need to pull in a terminal.
Yeah.
Or maybe I need a scene with a terminal in it.
But I was just wondering with this mode,
I can check for myself something first
and then push it to live?
And then press it to program.
Push it to program.
Yeah.
Thank you.
And you said there were virtual webcams.
Yeah.
Is that you can designate pretty much any...
The video output of any app,
of any window that is running on your machine,
you can designate that to be a virtual webcam?
Yeah.
Because then whatever is running in program
will then be shown on the virtual webcam.
Ah, I see.
It's a pretty cool feature.
For a long while,
it was like a special plugin on Windows
where they had it on Linux,
where they had it on Windows and I also think Mac.
But now it's built in from the beginning.
Hi.
I've heard that the Linux version of OBS
is more limited than the Windows version.
Is that still the case or...
I think so, yes.
It's still...
One of the specific example was the virtual webcam
where you needed a special plugin
that someone else had created for the Linux version.
That is now built in.
And there are some other limitations,
but it's...
I've been running this on Linux for four and a half years
and I'm happy, happy.
You can't remember any other limitations?
No, no.
I haven't met anything where I've been limited
and then what usually happens is
if I find something and I start Googling
and then they say,
hey, there's this function you blah, blah.
And then I see, oh, okay,
so that's like a Windows function
and then I Google a bit more
and then I find out, okay,
so that's not available on Linux yet.
But it's...
So far, the only thing I've seen
was the webcam, the virtual webcam function.
Okay, thank you.
Hello again.
So as I said, I do presentations at work,
you know, Monday meetings,
but I'm considering live streaming.
Yeah.
I'm not sure what I'm going to do yet.
Earlier in the settings,
you were scrolling through like the video and audio
and I saw shortcuts.
When you're recording for yourself
or doing a presentation,
do you use any shortcuts?
For like scene changing?
I do that.
If I use more than two or three scenes,
I can put shortcuts on specific scenes
so that I know that if I hit F2
or something like that,
it will, in the preview,
switch to a specific scene
so I don't have to scroll and look for it.
I can just hit a button.
That was also what we had
on the video box set up here
way back when, when we used OBS.
And that works really nicely
because that's a big help.
If you have any questions,
we have many scenes you're switching between.
Okay.
And I'll assume that all the shortcuts
are defaulted in the application
and you don't need to add yourself
because when I was researching a week ago
when I looked on YouTube
to some reviews about OBS,
they all, most of them suggested
to get one of these devices
with like multiple buttons and so on.
Yeah.
But they're very pricey.
So I was wondering if everything is just doable
on just a regular keyboard
with your computer or on the laptop.
I actually can't remember.
Yeah, see, you have here like start streaming,
stop streaming.
You have keys for that
that you can put in.
I'm guessing then you just put in
the key combination you want.
But there's also a way to put
key shortcuts on your specific scenes.
I just can't remember how.
Okay, so let's try this.
I have to put in this.
I can't remember how you do that,
but there's a way to do it.
You can bind a shortcut to a specific scene?
Yeah, there's a way to do that
but I just can't remember right now how you do that.
Thank you.
It's there.
The green screen function, does it have to be green or can you designate pretty much
any color to be the back?
You can use other colors and you can tell OBS exactly what color you have.
Some colors work better than others and you also have to consider, but like if your brand
colors are green and you're wearing a lot of green, you need to figure out another color
because otherwise everything will be very weird.
So you can do other colors.
Blue is another traditional color for, then it's blue screen instead of green screen.
That also works really well.
So it works better if it's a primary color?
Yeah.
So you just need to, and you can, in the chroma key settings, you can specify the color of
your green screen.
Yeah.
Any more questions?
No?
Okay.
So if you get any questions, then you're welcome to stop me on the street here and
say hi or send me an email or anything.
I'll be happy to answer your questions.
Please give a big round of applause to Arete.
Thank you.