Hey, so the next speaker we have is Musica, that will talk about R on OpenBSD.
Let's give him a hand.
Thank you.
R is a programming language that I use for writing electronic music, and OpenBSD is the
operating system that I run on most of my computers, including this here laptop.
If you were here last year, maybe you were at my music set, you got to see some of my
music that I wrote in R. You can use R for many other things, but yeah, that's what I
use R for.
OpenBSD is an operating system.
So first, if we're going to use R on OpenBSD...
Maybe we should talk about why you would want to use R on OpenBSD.
But for me, it's just, like, I like to use R to write electronic music.
Maybe there are people here who use R for statistics, anyway.
But the problem with R is that in many ways it can be harder to administer, to keep it
up to date, to keep packages working.
And OpenBSD can help with that.
But the problem is it's only weirdos like me who use R on OpenBSD.
There may be ten people who use R on OpenBSD.
So it's very common that a package has not been tested on OpenBSD.
Agenda for today is to discuss some differences between R or OpenBSD and some alternatives.
This will help explain why there can be a problem when you try to install something.
Then we'll discuss how to install R and related software on OpenBSD.
And then how you can, once you've succeeded at installing these softwares, then you can
take advantage of special features that exist in OpenBSD.
So some reasons you might use R. You might like these strange language features that
it has.
One thing I like about R is it has a large, stable base.
Like...
Like how...
Kind of like a standard library.
And then there are other packages, and those often don't work, but the base works.
And CRAN, which is the repository of contributed packages, has an interesting approach to testing.
This is something I kind of like.
You don't say that this package works with these versions of dependencies, but you say
these are dependencies.
And if you ever break one of your reverse dependencies, or your package fails its tests,
you are required to fix it within a week.
Or your package gets removed from R. So from the public repository.
So you...
You can't trust that any particular version combination will work, except that the current
version generally works.
So those are some interesting features of R. Some interesting features of OpenBSD.
Or...
Sorry.
Differences.
Some things that make it difficult to install R and OpenBSD is most people who use R probably
use maybe GNU Linux or Mac OS.
I'm not really sure.
Maybe Windows.
So you...
With different GNU Linux distributions, if you're on the same architecture, you can simply
copy a static binary from one to the other, and it usually should work.
But OpenBSD uses a different binary format.
So that doesn't work.
You have to compile special...
So you have to deal with different versions of compilers and different supported C functions
and stuff.
Some other differences are the cultural differences.
It's kind of...
OpenBSD we often say is a more cathedral development pattern, where there's a large base system.
For example, in many GNU Linux distributions, even the package Ed, or the function Ed could
be part of a package.
And it would be possible to...
Uninstall the true editor Ed.
But in OpenBSD, it's part of the base system.
You can't uninstall it.
Also OpenBSD puts a lot of attention on documentation, on keeping things simple, and doesn't really
care to follow fashions.
So we don't have...
I don't know what...
I live under a rock.
I don't know what are the new fashions in GNU Linux.
Yes.
So anyway.
What happens?
What happens is because of these differences I just talked about, you will have...
Usually you have a problem with compilation.
There could be other problems too.
And so you have to patch your R packages.
So I'll explain how to do that.
And as a last resort, if you can't patch the packages, you can run R in a virtual machine
running Alpine Linux, and then you can use R serve for communication between your OpenBSD
system, which you really want to use, and the R system for these strange functions that
don't work on OpenBSD.
And then once you've done this, I will show you some of the benefits that come with using
OpenBSD system.
So the installation of the base system is pretty easy.
You use the package add from OpenBSD.
And that's just to install the base R. For RStudio, which is a very common but bodily
named software, you can use package RStudio.
It's bodily named because if it's RStudio, you're going to think it's for making music.
Of course, R is a language for making music.
That's how I think about it.
But RStudio doesn't make music.
It's just an integrated development environment.
And if you want to make music, you have to follow my directions for making music.
So many people use RStudio.
I don't use RStudio, but I make music.
Those RStudio users, they're opposers, I think.
And anyway, so you've installed R. You've installed maybe RStudio.
But for the other packages...
You use the internal R function, installed packages.
Maybe most of you here already know R, because it's kind of a specific thing that came.
Did anyone already know about installed packages, for example?
Yeah.
Okay.
So maybe I didn't have to talk about all this.
The problems you have usually is compilation, like I said.
So yeah, we'll get to that later.
And then when you find the...
So maybe...
For example, maybe you're using something that's built on...
For Linux.
So it's using some C function that is considered insecure and deprecated by OpenVSD, and it
won't be allowed.
Or you're using a compiler with a different name.
So yes.
So these are some of the problems that happen when you try to compile something that was
never tested on OpenVSD.
To fix it, you read the error message.
This is very important.
Often, the error message says exactly what is going on, but people just think, oh, I'm
scared.
This is an error message.
Bad.
Yes.
So then you can find what is the bug, and you can try to fix it.
The person responsible for most of the porting of R to OpenVSD is Ingo Fehnerer.
So you probably wind up talking to him if you try to report the bug.
Or you can, of course, fix it yourself.
But here we have a problem sometimes.
Because...
I talked about...
It's a bit of a cultural difference.
In R, we have a bit more nuance also.
We have the base system, which is kind of managed by one set of people.
And then we have this thing called the tidyverse, which is kind of managed by a company.
And the first part really follows the GNU ethical criteria, but the second group, the
tidyverse people, often...
I don't know.
Are willing to throw away their freedoms.
In this group, we often use proprietary...
Not I, but they often use proprietary disservices as software substitutes, for example GitHub
and Slack.
So for example, one time...
Sorry.
Where as the base...
In fact R is part of the GNU project.
So R follows the GNU ethical criteria.
repository criteria to contribute a patch to base R you can send an email or
use bugzilla these are both free possibilities but to contribute to some
of those other packages I once had an issue where I had a package that worked
in our studio in the text editor but it would not work outside the text editor
so I fixed it but then I tried to contribute my patch and they required
that I create a poll request on github and this is absolutely not okay because
by doing this I would be giving up my rights to use free software I would be
succumbing to the proprietary github and I chose to I chose the path of freedom
rather than slavery and as a consequence my patch has not made it into this
library so in order to continue using that library well in fact there are a
few options first option which is the one that I
usually choose and which is what I chose in this case is just I don't use
the package because I really don't like most of this tidyverse stuff but if you
really need to and you can't get it patched because they will not respect
your ethical views you can install GNU Linux and R inside of the GNU Linux and
you can use R serve for communication between the two so here is how you would
install the
Linux
in the virtual machine you can use the virtual machine device that's available
in openVSD and then you install Alpine Linux on the virtual machine then you
can install R and Alpine Linux and then we'll get to the installation part of R
serve and then you can set it to run as a daemon so this is how you create the
the virtual machine
and then this is the configure it the openVSD configuration file for running it
at boot here's the R code and the the top is what you run on the GNU Linux
system and that would expose a service that you can connect to with the bottom
part from the openVSD system and then you can you can write a function as if
it is running on the openVSD system but it's actually running on the
GNU Linux system and it's serialized with the communication yes so now we've
succeeded at installing somehow whatever packages we shall use now we can take
advantage of the special openVSD features I already mentioned the virtual
machines I have some notes about the the middle group the documentation the
daemons and the firewall I listed some other cool features that maybe we could
talk about but since is awfully specific group specific topic R and openVSD I
suspect maybe you have specific topics that would be interesting to you you
could say them now or later and we could try to discuss them any anyone at the
moment have a particular topic about R and openVSD that you're curious about
no okay oh yes
the question is our virtual machines related to BSD jails and the answer is
pretty much no I'll just take this right now so there is such a thing as a
Chirrut jail and that is common in all postx systems Solaris and
FreeBSD have things that are sort of more powerful versions of jails in
FreeBSD they're called jails in Solaris they're called sorry
Solaris, it was, no, it's not Solaris, it's the new one, the new one that was based on,
what was it, Brian Cantrell and, no, it was Solaris and then it's probably still available
in some other, anyway, the zones in Solaris and jails in FreeBSD, but these, virtual machines
here are in fact virtual machines, not jails, so jails are, you're still running as a user
on the host system, but the virtual machine, you're running a, really you're running a
new, a separate kernel in the virtual machine.
So yes, and that's why it's possible, for example, that's, no, yeah, so that's, we'll
stop at that for the virtual machines.
So I will discuss some differences in document, some of the advantages of the documentation
and the daemons and the firewall.
First is just.
This is, there are a few entry points to the documentation, but I suppose the FAQ says
this is the, really the first entry point, it explains how to install the base system
and then that would refer you to all the other documentation that's available.
And perhaps the main source of documentation is the manual pages, which you access with
the man command.
Similar to on other Unix-like systems, but the OpenBSD and the BSDs in general have very
good manual pages.
Now another thing is it's very easy to create background daemons in OpenBSD.
Kids these days like to use systemd on GNU Linux.
There are some others available, for example, actually I don't remember any of the names
because I don't use GNU Linux, but yes, in case you don't like systemd, there are options
on GNU Linux, but also the BSDs don't use systemd.
This is how you could create a daemon for the RStudio server.
You would write a file like this one.
Oh, I see what I did.
It's missing, at the top it has to have a shebang bin corn shell.
All the daemons work like that.
So this file has six lines.
We're going to break it down into a few parts.
The bottom three lines are really...
You should think of them as boilerplates.
This is an ordinary corn shell function, a corn shell script, but this is the standard
way of writing a service, is to copy these lines and configure the rest.
In fact the rc reload is...
This is wrong.
The rc reload is not part of the boilerplate.
This disables the reload command.
I'm sorry.
Sorry.
So this, though, is the main configuration.
We say the daemon is this program, the rserver program.
We run it with these flags, run it as this user.
And when we stop the program, the rc system will look for the process with the name...
Userlocal bin, RStudio bin, rserver.
And with the flags, www ports, and it would heal that process.
That's how we can automate.
automatically create the stop subcommand.
In fact, I think this should be really part of the RStudio port, so I have been meaning
to submit this to OpenBSD ports, but also it is so easy to make it, so maybe we do not
need to do that.
So that was the RC.d.
Now we will talk about some firewall stuff.
I trust the R base code, I trust the OpenBSD base code, I do not trust the code on CRAN,
I certainly do not trust the code that I write, so for me it is very important to have a firewall.
I will show an example of how I might configure my R firewall.
For the user that is running R, I want to forbid most network access, but I want to
allow access to CRAN.
I want to allow access to a Postgres database, and if it is running RStudio server, I will
allow RStudio server to listen.
So here are the rules.
The firewall is called PF.
PF has two sorts of things that are like variables.
The first type is tables, the second is macros.
I will not explain the difference.
We want a table for the CRAN mirror that we are going to use, we have a table for the
database that we are going to use, the user that will be using R, so we are going to create
a firewall just for this user, and here are the ports.
We start with block, return, and pass.
This says that by default we will allow everything.
So first we allow everything for all users, the network is allowed for all users, but
now we will say...
We will block everything for just the R user.
So we are blocking TCP and UDP in, and we are also blocking TCP and UDP out for just
the user with the macro use R.
So first we start with allow everything, now we block everything for our user, now we will
allow limited access for our user.
So we will allow that...
The user...
The first one, we will allow DNS lookups.
Next we will allow downloading of packages from CRAN.
Next we will allow access to our database.
And last we will allow incoming connections on the RStudio server ports.
So this gives you a flavour of some of the advantages of using R and OpenBSD for the
good documentation.
These various cool features I showed you.
The disadvantage, of course, is some things don't work, but I have shown you how to deal
with those problems.
One last warning.
OpenBSD works very well.
Very rarely does it crash.
And the software is very simple, so it is very easy to understand.
And the upgrades work very well.
If there is a problem with the upgrade, it is probably documented in the changelog.
So it is very easy to upgrade.
So I recommend against using this at a job, because it works too well.
If you use it at work, your colleagues will think you are not doing anything.
And that is because you aren't.
Because there is nothing to do.
It just works.
It is important at a job that you use very unreliable, unstable software, unsecure software,
maybe even proprietary software, because that is even more insecure and unstable.
That way, you always have things working.
And you will always be stressed and challenged, and people will think you are a good worker.
And that's all.
Thank you.
Any questions?
So thank you for being here.
Let's give them a hand.
Subtitles by the Amara.org community