So, my name is Auker van Sloten. I'm a web developer. I've been doing this stuff since
about 1996. And the last few years I've been building a software system that is a middleware
between all kinds of different APIs, and it's a mess. So, the idea is that I'm trying to
get to a point where connecting to an API and getting some information from it is not
as much a chore as it is right now. So, as a colleague of mine mentioned, if I wanted
to
make people enthusiastic about something, I should not focus on the features. I should
tell you how the system will change your life for the better. If you buy my product, your
life will be better. And also important, this presentation is meant to be interactive. So,
if you have a question, put up your hand and ask away.
So
the good news is, you don't have to hand code a client for a specific API. You don't even
have to parse an open API spec and run some magic code to generate some kind of client
library for you. There's just a single client code that is working for every API out there.
It's of course JavaScript, the one true language out there. No boos? Okay. There is no real
separate query language to learn, there's no SQL, there's no GraphQL, there's no object
relational mapping, no injection attacks, of course. Everything is just JavaScript.
The API's endpoints are not something that you have to search for in some kind of documentation.
The endpoints follow normally from the data that is in there. There are no filter or paging
arguments to send in a weird syntax. And all the data runs on the server in memory, where
your query will also run, so everything is fast by default. And most importantly, the
API is future proof, so your client code doesn't need to be updated whenever the API changes.
You can just use the old version, or you can automate updating it to whatever new thing
is invented later. There are no flying cars, but we do have time travel. Does this sound
any way better than a current crop of API's? Good. Then the rhetorical question is, I said
all API's are the same. I said all API's are the same. I said all API's are the same.
I said all API's are the same. I said all API's are the same. I said all API's are the
same. I said all API's are the same. I said all API's are the same. I said all API's are
the same. I said all API's are the same. I said all API's are the same. I said all API's
are the same. I said all API's are the same. I said all API's are the same. I said all
API's are the same. I said all API's are the same. I said all API's suck. I'm really interested
in what you think. Do API's currently suck, and I mean online API's? No, nobody thinks
they suck?
itters feedback.
They do a lot of great work.
ATkind0 All right.
I make my life easier.
ATkind0 So you like programming, to, say, a REST API?
Tansy userist 1No, I use them. I don't program them.
ATkind0 Oh, right.
Okay.
Then the thing is, if I want to make a good API, we have to somehow define what a good
API is.
So I gave you a glimpse earlier on, but most people these days say, well, a REST API, that's
how stuff is supposed to work.
So who knows what a REST API is?
Can you tell me?
Is there a way for a microphone to... or do I have to repeat the question?
That's also possible.
It is a network-based API that uses HTTP to request a resource, typically through a URL,
and then a response will be delivered from the server, typically in the form of text,
JSON, or some other data format.
Sometimes even empty content.
All right.
So that's the common answer, and that is what today we mean with a REST API, but the original
meaning of REST is a bit wider than that.
The most important thing, REST stands for Representational State Transfer, and it was
not invented.
It was reverse engineered from the biggest software system that we as humanity have ever
made, the World Wide Web.
And a researcher was thinking, well, why is this thing, the World Wide Web, so successful,
so large, where any other system that we've designed fails to scale even to a small fraction
of the web?
And he wrote some rules and named that rule set REST.
So the World Wide Web is the one true REST API out there.
All other REST APIs that I have found are not.
I'm not going to talk about them.
All of them are
going to start getting a bitolan Vegan, and probably from the very beginning.
All of that data is going toinvoke a neoliberal
vaping.
I hope I said a lot, because I've gotten enough.
information in that data to automatically be able to infer what to do with that. That's
not actually there usually. Another thing that you would like to have is information
on what can I do with this data in the form of links, for example, or form actions or
stuff like that. That's also usually not there. So instead of REST, what we really have is
JSON over HTTP. And that's the state of the art. JSON has a slight problem here because
JSON is never just JSON. To understand a JSON data format, you need to know what service
you're talking to. You would need to read the documentation, see how they encoded certain
things that are difficult to encode in JSON. So there's a lot of thinking, reading, custom
programming.
So there's a lot of thinking, reading, custom programming.
To really make use of that stuff. GraphQL is a recent improvement on REST in that they
said it is important that you keep the round trips between your client and the server to
as limited amount as possible because each round trip adds lag, adds more time between
responses. So GraphQL allows you to...
In your query, state up front, I'd like to have this and this and this and this information.
Please give it to me in one go so I don't have to go and fetch more. So that's an improvement.
But GraphQL is, again, limited. The implementation of GraphQL differ widely. And you'll need
to read up again on how is this GraphQL server implementing GraphQL exactly and which enhancements
does it have and how can I use that?
Then there is OpenAPI. How many people here have heard about OpenAPI? It used to
be called Swagger. One, two, all right, three. A few.
OpenAPI is an attempt to write down how your API is actually designed in such a way that
I can automatically generate a client for it so that I don't have to do the hand coding
of a client.
That's a nice idea. Years ago, there used to be something called SOAP. And SOAP had
a similar idea and they used XML language called WSDL for web service description language
to try and do almost exactly the same thing. And, of course, everybody uses SOAP these
days because it was a runaway success.
Slight sarcasm there.
So, I think OpenAPI is just travelling right in the same direction and it is going for
the same heading, for the same problems. You have a generated client and then the specification
change. So, you need to regenerate your client, but the client has changed because the specification
has changed. So, now, you need to refactor your code to use the new client and we are
back to square one.
So, I'm back to square one. And we had approximately 15 minutes of discussion. And we had to also
I haven't actually even talked about the meaning of the data.
This is just how do I call your API to get some data.
There's no description of meaning in there at any point.
So a typical REST stack these days is, this is just a simple one.
There are many much more complex ones out there.
But you have typically a few things.
There's the client side.
I'm using a browser-based app for an example here.
Then there's the server, and then there's your database.
Usually that's a relational database, so that is SQL.
Your server is some kind of framework that connects to your database.
That needs to translate the relational data into more object-oriented data.
Many people use object-relational mapping for that, and that is one of the most complex
pieces of software you can introduce in your own system.
Please don't, but people still do.
Then you need to define the endpoints, which URLs are you going to listen to, and what
kind of information am I going to push on those endpoints.
Then you need to translate your data from your internal object structure.
Object structure to JSON, which is not trivial.
You need to be aware of all kinds of problems in there.
And then you need to have an API on the client side that calls your service, maybe generated
through an open API specification.
That translates the JSON again to your internal data structures, and then you can use it in
your application in the browser.
There's a lot of...
I'm sorry.
There's a lot of moving parts in this system.
And more importantly, there's a lot of translation from one data format to another data format
to another data format.
So a lot of stuff can go wrong here, and it usually does.
Right.
I already mentioned some of those issues.
There are many more, but first one, all the different formats.
There is a...
There's an impotence mismatch that you cannot accurately translate everything from one language
into another.
So you'll have to define your own custom formatting for that.
There is no idea what kind of data you're actually accessing when you're requesting
a URL.
You don't know which URLs are there unless you read the open API spec.
And if I ask for information from...
If I ask for information from a URL, what kind of information am I going to get back?
This is all undefined behavior, and everybody implements their own system for that.
People have tried to make this easier by writing standardized frameworks, and then you just
use this framework, connect to a relational database, and it will automatically create
endpoints for you.
You can do this with what's called CRUD, create, read, update, delete semantics.
But what you're actually doing is almost exporting your relational database to the web.
And you have almost direct access to tables and columns and rows and stuff like that,
which is not the way we usually think about application data.
And it's also...
In a way, it's...
Inherently not transactional.
So if I have to update each element of a table, each row, separately from a remote system,
and the network breaks halfway through, the data is suddenly in an inconsistent state.
So these CRUD semantics are really the kind of the worst kind of way to actually use an
API.
And then we are on the web, but we haven't had any real links.
JSON has no link type.
I can use a string with a URL in it, but I have to know that it is a URL, and I have
to really make sure that when I parse something that I know the semantics of what that URL
is trying to tell me.
And one I found out fairly late is that there's a lot of confusion about the...
I'm sorry.
In a database, you have a row.
Each row has an ID.
And that ID you can use to link stuff to.
In a REST API, usually each object also has an ID.
Whatever that ID may be, we don't know.
It's up to the person implementing the API.
Lately, UUIDs, the universally unique IDs, have become popular.
And they solve quite a few of these issues, but they don't really tell you much besides it is an ID.
So what happens is that services use URLs as an ID and then add the UUID inside there somewhere.
And you have, for example, a database with cars and then the REST API is example.com slash cars slash some ID.
And then, you know, all right, so this ID is probably a car, but it doesn't have to be because things change in the world.
In fact, it mixes type information with provenance, where does this come from, with identity.
And once you mix stuff, things become problematic later on.
When the world.
Changes.
As an example of things that can go wrong, I thought I'd show a few minor things and bigger systems.
Azure from Microsoft is a famous system.
Everybody here is aware of that it exists.
But one of the things that is less clear if you start out first is it's not one API.
It is a mix of many different systems.
And there's probably a single group of people in Microsoft that try to hide all that stuff behind a single API endpoint.
But differences in implementations do leak through.
And one of those differences is how do I write a identity URL for anything inside Azure?
And there is about six different ways to do this.
All of them sort of almost like each other, but not quite.
Some services return identities in one form, other services in another.
Some require a specific form if you enter any data.
So now you have to read data, transform the identity to a different format, and send that to the same API.
Otherwise, things won't work.
And these are just a few of the things that I have found.
So let's look at the basic syntax of the API, which is very well documented inside Azure.
Notice the extra quotes here.
Those are not optional.
But they are optional in the groups syntax.
So, you know, simple things.
Then there's Google.
Google has a very large API service.
And it's very well documented as long as you look at the basic URL syntax.
So which endpoints do you want to look at?
Which endpoints do you want to look at?
Which endpoints require which parameters?
And what kind of data will it return?
It's very well-documented.
But then I like to use my native client, and they make a library for that, and say I use PHP.
I can install the default Google RPC client in PHP and I get about 27,000 lines of PHP.
And there is a single README describing that API.
single document of a few hundred lines. And if you need to know more, they happily point
you to a generated class documentation of the thing. So that's not very helpful, especially
since they changed the semantics of the REST API to be more PHP-like. So now I don't actually
know what I need to send, because what's documented in the REST API is not the format that the
client library is using. And the client library, of course, is not documented. And this is
Google. So if Microsoft and Google can't create a perfect API based on REST, maybe it's best
if we just throw REST out and try to...
...redesign something that is more well-defined and less open for interpretation and for different
interpretations as well. So it's maybe not very readable. What it says
here is, let's innovate. What do we really need in 2023? Because the world has changed
a bit since...
We designed most of the stuff that we're using these days. Databases are designs in
the 60s, I think, relational databases. Maybe the 70s. And in that time, the CPUs were not
as powerful as today. Memory was very expensive. So you couldn't use... You had to use a lot
of indexes and read as few things as possible from the hard disk. These days, memory is
still slower than...
They're CPU. And SSDs are still slower than memory. So relatively, that still holds up.
But the data set that I can now store in main memory is so much bigger than we could even
dream of, like, 30 years ago. Do the same things still hold for designing a system today
compared to 30 years ago?
Yeah.
So I've posited that it really doesn't for most use cases. Case in point, I researched
how much does it cost to have a server online with, say, two terabytes of main memory? So
not two terabytes of disk, but two terabytes of main memory. And I found some systems available
for about 1,400 euros per month. And that is a lot of money for you and I personally,
but for a company that's like me, it's a lot of money. And I think it's a lot of money.
But it's also a lot of cost.
You're right.
It's a lot of money for you and I personally.
And most data sets fit very comfortably within that amount of memory. So I don't really have
to think about storing stuff on disk most of the time. If you have data sets that are
larger than that, then, yeah, you're going to need to use the existing difficult use
stuff.
Because I've been thinking about writing something new. And I think it was probably
the most complicated.
Okay.
So.
something. I want to keep it as simple as possible. And I've said, well, I'm only going
to focus on stuff that will fit in memory. That's one of the things that I'm doing. This
is the context that I'm trying to keep to make a research thing, something that we can
tinker with and see, well, does this actually work? Is this an improvement over the old
thing without having to write, like, thousands and thousands and thousands of lines of code?
So, I've limited scope to keep things simple. There's an ‑‑ I used to call this the
80% use case. I want to create a solution for about 80% of the problem space, and focus
on that. And the other 20% of the problem space usually takes up another 80% of your
time.
code. So, this keeps things small. The other thing is I've focused on APIs that are read
optimized so the reads highly outweigh the writes. And, again, all data should be available
in memory. I have no problem whatsoever with HTTP. I really like it, so I'm not going to
innovate on that. JSON, though, is not as great as I would like. Is anybody here aware
of things like linked data or the semantic web? All right. For those who don't know this,
Sir Tim Berners-Lee has been trying to get us into the next generation of the web by
adding meaning to the data.
Okay.
And the way they did this, I think it started around 2010. I'm not quite sure. In that time,
you use XML, of course. And the idea was that each thing you want to say about something
is encoded in such a way that you know the exact meaning of what you're encoding, not
just the data. And being Sir Tim Berners-Lee, he did it by using URLs for everything. But
another thing, which I think is very important, is that you have to be able to use a lot of
things.
And I think the other thing, which is more surprising, is he used something called predicate
logic, most famously known from, I think, Prolog. And this is a knowledge-based thing
designed in the 70s. So it was used for artificial intelligence before we used neural networks
for that stuff.
And it means that you store data as a set of triples where you have some subject, some
kind of relation.
And an object. So everything you can say about anything, you divide in these triples where
the middle part is the predicate, the relation. And the left and the right are entities that
you relate to each other in a certain way.
I've been using linked data for a few years now on the SOLID project, which is also a
new thing from Tim Berners-Lee.
SELAAM.
where they add an API to the whole link data format, link data platform it's called, and
it is actually almost what I described earlier in can we build something like this.
Imagine a world where everybody was using solid and link data and most of those lines
that I wrote on that highlight there would be finished, it would be done.
One problem, though, it's really difficult to use link data in an application.
You need to really rethink how you use data, you basically need to use Prolog to reason
about the data, which obviously doesn't work.
So I want to go to link data.
Because it...
Solves a lot of these problems.
But it makes application programming massively much more complicated.
So I think we need to have something between JSON and link data, something that is easy
to program with, but it does have meaning, and I can change it to something larger.
I don't like the document centric rest APIs because they hide whatever is inside them.
And one other thing that rest is not very good at is asynchronous updates.
And asynchronicity is very important for large scale APIs.
So I want to embrace that.
How do we go about writing something that potentially is completely new system?
We have to be aware of the different requirements for different elements of the trip, but I think
that certain programs that are generally serving different use cases we have transfer files
from the exact places that they come from.
And if the same thing strikes your mind, you can use b5 except for action, that gives you
a completely wrong memory.
And I think that the only benefit ability for most, which is betterntby making these layout
changes is using commands.
of any system. And the bottom element is infrastructure. There is supposed to be an extra line under
there, but infrastructure needs to be very simple. It needs to be fixed. And it needs
to be durable. That's the missing line we know there. You don't want infrastructure
changing too often. You don't want to have custom codes to read specific parts of the
infrastructure. And JSON is doing very well for all those things. It's simple. It's fixed.
It's durable. And I think that's one of the reasons that JSON is so well-known and well-used.
The problem is that on the platform side, we need a bit more than that. And JSON is
not powerful enough to support something that is slightly more flexible.
And that's the reason why we have a lot of stuff out there like open API, because JSON
itself cannot really represent all the information that you have. But if you go above the platform
to the application level, that's where we really want something that is flexible, that
is powerful, that can handle complex situations. But it means that it is less durable, and
it's less all-encompassing. So can we build something that works on the infrastructure
and on the platform level, and then the application level, I leave for another time? I've been
trying to do stuff like that. On the infrastructure level, HTML is the example to strive for. This
is something that has blown away everything else that was out there. If you do something
document-centric or even application building, you're using HTML. JSON, it has the same level
of being everywhere, but it is much less powerful. The first HTML had about 25 elements, but
it also had attributes where you could add custom information to this fixed set of HTML
elements.
JSON has five types.
JSON is a set of elements that are not included in the HTML, but it has a set of elements
that are still not included. And there is no way to extend it. There is no way to add
extra attributes or stuff like that. So metadata needs to be encoded in the JSON itself. And
there you can have collisions between the normal data and the metadata. And then people
are going to do fancy things like adding an ampersand or an at sign in front of a property,
and now it's a special property, and stuff like that is making our lives miserable.
So I've gone and updated JSON and added a bit of HTML into it. So I've added tags. It
is still backwards compatible. You can still read, parse normal JSON. It will work fine.
But I've added about 25 data types to the JSON system.
And, important, a link type. So it can actually represent link data inside JSON tag. And
each tag can have any kind of attribute that you want.
I'll probably be best showing you what I mean. Let's see. Come on. There's my cursor.
Is this readable?
Yeah.
All right. So this is a JSON tag format. And you can see it's just JSON with some weird
ass tags strewn in between them. What this allows is I can now accurately represent not
just that it is an object, but I can say, well, this is actually a person.
And I can store the data and read it in back. And I don't have to have separate knowledge
about which classes are associated with which arrays or properties. It's basically right
in there.
I've also added a date type. So now that I know that this is a date, I can automatically
create the correct user interface for changing this stuff.
All right.
So there is a lot more besides that. Let me see. Yeah. So here's a list of types that
I've defined right now. So what I've done is I've taken a look at what types JavaScript
natively supports, which are useful to have, what types databases usually support. And
I've taken a look at Postgres for that.
Of course, the basic JSON types need to be in there because it needs to be fully backwards
compatible. And I've taken a look at something called Rebol or Red Language, which famously
has a lot of semantic types in the programming language itself. I'm not sure this is the
final set of data types. I really like feedback from people if this is something that they
want to use.
I don't want to miss things. But I also like to keep it as small as possible.
So that's the infrastructure part.
Let's kind of get this back. Yeah. All right.
Where did it go?
There's a bug.
Okay.
Then a platform. The platform I've called simply store because we've been doing a lot
of components that are meant to be very simple, and they're all prefixed with simply. The
whole presentation is called simply present and is actually running on a solid data port.
So it's already a bit in the future there. And the things that I've
decided to do differently than the normal REST systems is embracing asynchronicity.
So I've gone for the CQRS design pattern, and that's called command query responsibility
segregation. And there are a few reasons for that. The query part is a separate endpoint,
and it will only do queries. So you cannot change data on the query endpoint. You can't
change it.
There's no way to do any kind of injection attack in queries. The query actually runs
on an immutable data set, so even if you could break the query engine to do updates, the
data set itself just won't allow it. This solves a lot of security concerns that many
REST APIs have.
Okay.
thing is that the commands are always asynchronous. So there's a separate endpoint where I can
send a command. A command can do anything. It can change the data. But it will not reply
right away if I've changed this. The command is actually your transaction. It can do any
kind of thing. And most specifically, it doesn't do CRUD. I have not implemented a create,
update, delete semantics for changing the data. Because if you do that, you no longer
have any idea what the meaning of the change is. If I say I want to add a car, then I know,
okay, so I have a car. And a car must have a manufacturer. And it may have a year for
entry. And it can be data that is stored in lots of different places. But the command
says I have an email.
And I have a new car. So now I know that all these little pieces of data are related
to introducing a new car in the system.
That's the benefit of CQRS. Then the endpoints are not actually random. You have a data space.
That's all the data that that server has to offer you. And each route entry of the data
space is also a route entry.
Okay.
So you have a route entry, an endpoint for your system automatically. And I do that by
using a JSON pointer to point inside the data space. And you get custom results.
Then queries. There's no GraphQL. There's no custom language. It's just JavaScript.
This is one of the more out there solutions. You're sending JavaScript to the server. The server
will run that JavaScript for you and send you the result back. The advantage is if I
have a terabyte of data and my query is 20 lines of JavaScript, it's a lot faster to
send the 20 lines of JavaScript to the server than to send a terabyte of data to the client.
It also solves one of the main problems. I want to have paging. Well, it is JavaScript.
You just add a slice to your query, and you have paging.
The next thing is the SimpliStore is designed as a baseline, and you need to customize it
because each data set has its own requirements. So, for example, the commands, it doesn't
come with any commands. You will have to write your own. So it's not a separate server. It's
a library that you can use to build your own stuff on top of it.
Okay.
Then the command endpoint is using a command log where each new command creates
a new data set that is tied to that entity, and it automatically creates a log which you
can use as an audit log or you can use it to go back into time and replay all the commands
to generate a new set if somehow you made a bug in your command earlier. Now you can
go back, fix the bug, rerun all the commands, and you have an up-to-date, correct data set.
And finally, well, there's a bit more below this, but the screen doesn't show it. I use
UUIDs for everything, and the IDs are not stored in the data. They are stored in the
metadata, so it's an attribute in the JSON tag.
Okay.
So the server is in charge of generating IDs, and this is needed because if I send a command
to the server to add something and there's a communication problem, so I don't get an
acknowledge back, I can send it again and be sure that even though I've sent the same
command twice, I won't end up with two entities in the data set because the ID is the same
so the server will know, all right, I've seen this thing already. That's for the at least
once semantics of the communication.
Finally, everything is in memory, but we are missing one key feature that databases
have brought us, and that's ACID compliance. So that means atomicity, consistency, isolation,
and durability. We need to make sure that our system also fulfills all those promises
as well.
So the thing is already available.
Okay.
So that's an example to tinker with. The state is that it's currently just a read-only data
set. I haven't implemented any commands yet. But you can already use it. And I'll try to
show a demo here.
I have to move that.
Is this readable enough?
Yeah.
All right.
So this is a query.
This is a query.
And I can create an interface. And I can change the function.
So this is a Siri interface. And this is the interface I made for a data set. To the right is the list of data that is in this system. It automatically lists that. And I can change the URL and say, what's it called? I think it was called People. And then it will show a list of the people that are in here. So I can use the URL just to browse through the data set and see.
get kind of a summary of all the data back.
Let's go back to the root.
On the left, I can create a query in JavaScript syntax, and it will run on the server and
send the result back.
What it can also do is use a slightly more GraphQL-like syntax, and say I want a name
of everybody in there.
There you go.
These are all the people in the database, and even though this doesn't really look like
JavaScript.
This is an extra library I made to create a more user-friendly query language in JavaScript,
and it's just array manipulation.
It does array filter and array map.
I can do a filter as well.
Let's see.
Okay.
So that is a regular expression.
It says any name that starts with a capital L. And then I've got a subselection of my
data.
I can also add a slice here to show me just a limited number of results.
So basically, you can do any kind of normal JavaScript programming.
What you can't do here is network access, nor disk access or any special API.
It is running in Node, but it is sandboxed, so it's in a special virtual machine.
It has no access to anything except your data and a few other bits and pieces that are useful.
All right.
So that's it.
Thank you.
Yeah.
The next things that I want to implement is the commands and the multi-threading and see
how far I can get this system to grow.
I'm really curious what you people think of this approach and if there is any flaw in
the design of this thing that you can see coming.
Okay.
Thank you.
Thank you very much.
And if you would be interested in taking it for a spin and see what you like or don't
like.
I'll be coming with the microphone.
What about data limits, like rate limits for the clients?
Well, that's a good question.
Okay.
So the whole idea is right now that I just put it open so anybody can just blast away
at it, but you can fairly easily do a denial of service attack, and that's not nice.
So what I want to do is add a proxy in front of it, an API gateway, and let it handle things
like rate limiting, do something like an API key, so you need to have an API key to actually
talk to the system, and then you can do a rate limiting by API key.
There are many systems that already implement this kind of stuff, so I thought I'll ignore
it and just do something like, what's it called, traffic.
Traffic is an API gateway.
That's nice.
Or any other system in front of it, yeah.
Okay.
Very interesting concept.
I do wonder, how would you actually do joins?
Yeah.
Like in classical SQL join with the system.
Well, that's an interesting thing, because joins are needed when you have normalized
your data into separate columns.
So what I actually end up doing is this data set, for example, was in separate files, separate
JSON files for each type of people and starships and movies and stuff like that, and then they
link to each other by using a number and maybe even a type.
And what I've done is I've joined that in memory.
So if you ask Luke Skywalker and you go to which starship does it have, it's just right
there.
You don't need to join because it is already joined.
This does presuppose that you know how you're going to relate data to each other.
So that is an important thing, similar to many of the NoSQL databases that do the exact
same thing.
Okay.
Thank you.
Any more questions?
No?
Let's give a big hand.
Thank you.