We have the last presentation today in the speaker's tent is Peter Stuecke, who is going
to talk about simplex chat, simple messaging with unusually good privacy.
Let's give a round of applause for Peter.
Thank you very much.
So yes, simplex chat.
It's a messenger.
I want to talk a little bit about why it is better than many others, maybe most, maybe
all.
I'm going to go into a bit of propaganda about good technology and bad technology.
I feel very strongly about that.
Talk about some good messengers and then compare with this, which I find is an unusually good
messenger.
I'll talk about what client software there is.
I'll talk about the feature set that works already, and then I'll talk about what's on
the roadmap for this project.
Maybe we'll look into the protocol.
It's a little bit complicated with this other computer because of the graphics.
And then thank you and questions.
So good technology and bad technology, right?
I don't know if you've thought about this before, but why another messenger?
You may be thinking, and I say, well, most of the messengers out there are really bad
technology.
So please make an effort to get friends and loved ones away from this bad technology that
a lot of people are using.
Most of new technology is actually really, really bad.
And it's not made for us, it's made to make money off of us in some way or other, right?
And I argue that this is why the Internet has come to feel so bad lately, right?
With many, perhaps, were around in the beginnings of the Internet.
And that was awful.
fun and exciting, but now it's really, really not so much fun anymore. So the thing is,
you are valuable, right? Everybody who's dealing with technology, who's using technology is
really valuable. And by choosing what you use and what you do not use, which is very
important, I find that we talk way too rarely about not using technology, choosing to reject
stuff that is actually bad, right? By choosing what you use and what you don't use, you're
determining the value of technology, because technology is worth nothing if nobody uses
it. So there's this reverse network effect. Maybe you heard of the network effect. The
more people use something, the better.
The more powerful it becomes and the more difficult it is to switch to something else.
Well, if we start to move away from technology and choose not to use technology, then we're
also helping get rid of that technology, which is really what we should do, because it's
not in our interest. So whenever we use bad technology, we also help increase its value.
We are sort of actively supporting this bad technology.
So don't...
Don't do that. If you can at all avoid it, right? It's important to reject bad technology.
Enough propaganda. So some bad messengers, like WhatsApp is a bad messenger. It's a centralized
system. It's U.S. jurisdiction. It's even forced centralized, right? There's no way
to integrate with this system, really. It's closed. It also uses strong identifiers, so
it's not so privacy optimized.
Privacy friendly. It's the full name and it's closed source. So it's also really, really
hard work to find out what is it actually doing. Signal is surprisingly similar to WhatsApp.
Like, the main difference is that it's open source. Meh. It's especially the way that
Signal uses phone numbers as identifiers, I find is an absolute disaster and completely
rules out using...
Signal for anything. And Signal is also a centralized closed system because they refuse
to federate with anybody else, right?
Then we have, for example, Telegram is another bad technology. Nobody knows what that is,
where that's based, but it's still centralized and it's closed. Like, you can build bots
and stuff, but you can't really run your own server as far as I know. And the security properties
are...
Meh.
Non-existent to unclear is what I wrote. Like, if you have a group in Telegram, anybody
can just connect and download all of everything that has been said there. And for the direct
chats, I'm not so sure what is really going on there. And it's also closed source, right?
And it's the identities and a bad situation, all of these. And there are more bad examples,
right?
But the slide is full.
So let's talk about Simplex. And I find that... I call it an unusually good messenger because
it does a lot of things really, really right. I'm not involved in the project in any way.
I found it a couple of months ago and I looked through it. Not the code, but the protocol
and the design. I was really happily surprised. It was refreshing. So there are no global
user identities.
There's...
Yeah. There's just... There's no way to recognize the same user. Means there's also no discovery
or search. So there's no way to find people inside the system, which I argue is a really
good thing. That means we have to create connections explicitly when we meet or over some other
channel. And why I think this is a good thing is that we have no spam. It's impossible to
get spam in. Or...
I mean, if you do get spam, it's from somebody you know because you connected with them.
Right?
So invitations is what is used to create a connection. And it can be a QR code or it
can be just a link that you share over some other medium. And once you've connected, you
can also verify if you'll meet later. If you're not connecting in person, you can... When
you'll meet at some later time, you can verify.
That your connection is really not manned in the middle by anybody.
Invitations are... There are two kinds. That's kind of fun. I haven't seen that anywhere
before. They can either be single use. That's sort of the normal case for adding one contact,
adding a new contact. There's only one chance to use it, and then it gets locked in. Or
it can be multi-use. That's like a public invitation to join a group or maybe to contact
me if I want to. I could do that. And these are both revocable. So at any time, I can
also stop the invitation, and anybody who tries to use it after that will not be able
to connect. And that's really nice. Nice properties.
Then there's this incognito option, which is a lot of fun. So because there are no user
identities, right? How do we...
How do we...
What can we do with that? So we can have the situation where my client uses a different
identity in every context. So it has a different identity for every person I'm communicating
with, and it has a different identity in every single group that I'm a member of. This means
that somebody that I'm communicating directly with, they cannot know whether I am a member
of some chat groups. And that may be really, really useful for me.
Normally, clients, or I don't know about normally, but clients do have the possibility
to probe group members. So if you join a group, you can send a probe to everybody to sort
of check if they are known to you already. Switching on this incognito option makes that
not work, right? Then it just... You will have duplicate contacts perhaps with the same
name and, yeah, and be none the wiser.
Okay.
Thank you very much.
Thank you.
The server architecture is delightfully simple. It's a very simple server. It doesn't do much
of anything. It's a message queue, just receiving messages and sending them out. There's crypto
and so on, of course. But the server doesn't know very much or really anything about the
contents. And the servers are decentralized. There's not one single server. You can have
your own server.
So what we've already seen is similar toちゃん to all the servers. And there are many servers
already in operation and it doesn't really matter which server you use. You can also
move servers, like change servers at will. That's also fun. A nice new concept that I
haven't seen in really anywhere before. The protocol is layered. That helps with this
. . . So I wrote like TCP-IP . . . . that helps with the separation that the server Jawand
the protocol is layered that helps with this separate.
We also have thelived based. We can actually run... In this nail- librarization I created.
Yeah.
Oh wow.
Really good.
Good.
Make sure that you have media harm.
Cool.
Just really neat.
St toujours de realizar de realizar estea en medio.
server doesn't really know it only takes care of transport messages going going
through it doesn't know the contents only the clients know what's what's
inside the messages of course the server can see IP addresses but we can use Tor
and maybe other methods as well in order to to not show our real IP address if we
want to and the the way the protocol works and the way this this sort of lose
server architecture or well flexible server architecture works allows the
servers to not really have a lot of persistence they don't need to store
much information which I also find is is great of course a malicious server could
still store everything but the the common case
that
the happy path is that the server doesn't need to store really anything at
all almost almost but very very little which is also a really good really good
thing and this is very different from matrix for example where the server has
to store everything about everybody since forever
don't use matrix so what about the client software what is available right
now there's the command line software it's the original implementation of
the
of the the simplex chat protocol is written in Haskell runs on at least
Linux Mac OS and and Windows I don't know that anybody has tried it on BSD so
please do that then there are mobile apps for Android and iOS the it's young
ish the first version was released in in March last year 2022 and by now the
Android version is up to version 5.2 so there's there's quite a lot of
development going on and
I've been using it for two months just about and I've had two updates so far so
about one update a month with the few new features in the first one and one
new feature red acknowledgment like us the second check mark in the in the last
update go download you can from F droids it's the it's already available there
you can get the APK file directly from from upstream but use asteroid
it's better, you get the updates and it's also signed and so on. It's even available
in the Play Store. Get F-Droid instead. And the Android app I feel works really well.
I'm happy with it, using it for a couple of months. It's written in Kotlin. iOS, I haven't
played with that, but I have a couple of friends who are hostage in iOS and they are able to
communicate with me and I'm with them and it's fine. Everything's fine.
Feature set, so it does text messaging, of course. That's the really basic stuff, right?
You can also send links. They are a separate message type. Links can contain a preview.
The preview is created on the sender side, but there's an option to disable this. So
you just send the link text and nothing else, like the link address. But if you have it
on the option on, there's pretty graphics of the web page that the link points to. You
can send also attachments, images and any other kind of file, but images are then displayed
in the conversation. Supports replies, so you can quote a previous message. Supports
forwarding and if enabled, it allows to delete messages also in conversations.
Secret chat groups. The chat groups are quite fun because they
are not...
Not stored anywhere except on the clients. So the server doesn't know that there is a
group. It only sees lots of connections between people or like between clients, right? And
they are no different from one-to-one connections. So a group looks for the server exactly the
same as many person-to-person connections. That's nice. It works fine to create groups
and manage groups.
It also supports audio and video calls. That works as well. Uses WebRTC, so the privacy
benefits of the simplex message queue protocol are lost. But well, it works for calling.
And if you enable Tor inside the app, I don't know what happens with the WebRTC. We should
investigate that. That's on my to-do list. But anyway, the calling works fine also. So,
these are some to-dos on the roadmap at the project. They want to do this, as I mentioned,
right? We can change servers. Change which server is being used for an established contact.
That can be done manually at the moment. But they want to make that automatic, I guess,
every now and then. Change server and or just replace the queue that is being used. When
contacting somebody using an invitation, they want to add sort of an introduction
message of some kind, some encryption for local files stored, navigation and search
inside the conversation.
Larger groups. So I don't know where the cutoff is, but it seems that there is some kind of
scalability limit, right? Because there is this everybody-to-everybody connection or
situation in the groups.
I can imagine that if doing really thousands or hundred thousands of people in a group
that doesn't scale so well. So I'm interested to see what they come up with there.
Ephemeral like disappearing conversations, sure. Sharing location, sure. I don't know
about this web widget stuff. Not so much for me. But okay, I guess. Programmable automations.
Like maybe vacation replies is the classic one. And then there is I think a big one that
really it doesn't matter so much to me personally, but multi-device support I think is really
valuable for a lot of people. And I look forward to that working as well. And then for those
who want to, they want to help create easier discovery, something based on DNS. And then
this message delivery relay for senders is something I think like what Tor does as well
with you add extra systems in front to just not show the exact IP address you're using
and still get messages delivered. That's also fine. But yeah, I like the general sort of
ideas that they have in the roadmap. I think this is fun. And especially the multi-device
support I think will make a big difference for people being excited about this. So I'm
really excited about this.
So now I was considering just walking through the protocol descriptions because they are
actually really simple. And I encourage you to read them. But on this computer, I'm not
so sure if that will work out.
Yeah. Okay. Let's say no. So okay. Let's try here.
Okay.
What to do.
Yeah.
Okay.
They want help translating. Why not.
Yeah.
Yeah, so they talk about privacy here and why it matters there was some discussion some debate about that, right?
Why why do we need privacy or or how much?
This this story is amazing somebody who made a phone call to a relative in Afghanistan and then was put in Guantanamo for 15 years
It's not a not a good situation so
Simplex they talk about what they what they do
I mentioned some of this ownership of the data, right? Everything is client-side. I think that's a really good good feature
and
We can run our own servers
I talked about signal being centralized with all the metadata
How is it different from matrix etc
Well, there is no identity at all
It's really every connection is a new connection
Quick install platform design
So not the chat protocol also not the server implementation
Here this is what I want
So
I'm going to show you a little bit of a demo of what we can do with the Tcp. It's not really long for a protocol description markdown
Independent of any transmission system, so it works over TCP on the internet, right?
But it can also use anything else
But it doesn't really doesn't really care as long as the the message format is is the same
We could also use bridges build bridges between lots of different transports
It's
right
The the data model or the communication model has three participants the recipient
The server and the sender this order will make sense in a in a second
The server has these queues message queues and
A queue is created by the recipient. So if I want to
if I want to invite a
Contact to to reach me. I prepare a queue for this and I then
Provide some information in the QR code or in a link to the person I want to
Want to be reachable for right and they then connect to the other side of the server and
Then we have a one-way channel
They do the same and then over there
this one-way channel, they send me how I will be able to reach them, and then we have a
two-way channel, and this is all transparent. It happens just that the app does it. But
these two paths, they don't need to go over the same server. They usually don't, and they
don't identify us also in any way. That's also nice. So out-of-band messages, we need
to do this initial contact, out-of-band. simplex queue, as I said. It sends messages in one
direction. can be communicated in a link. It has this syntax. and Bob, they want to
communicate. Alice wants to receive messages from Bob.
She creates the new queue, creates a random key, creates another random key.
The first one is for Bob to encrypt the contents of messages, and the second one is for Alice
to communicate with the server.
Then another key pair for one extra encryption layer that the server uses between itself
and Alice, so that anything that goes into a server, the same data never comes out.
This is also a nice feature that I don't know that I've seen anywhere else.
This makes correlation really difficult for anybody watching the server.
Then Alice creates the queue with this new command.
The server responds and says, here are the IDs that you and Bob need to use.
Alice gives Bob this information, gives him first the public key for the messages, and
then where the server is, and then his sender ID for this queue.
Bob creates then his...
His key for communicating with the server, and prepares confirmation message to Alice,
so he then sends through the server to Alice, okay, I'm here.
Alice then receives this message from Bob and locks the queue to only work with Bob.
Up until that point, anybody else who also guessed the information.
That's fine.
Thank you.
So the message that Alice sent to Bob out of band could also have tried to connect, but
only one.
So the winner, the first one wins, and Bob would get an error message, and if Alice and
Bob are communicating as they need to be out of band, then they will recognize that somebody
is trying to mess with them, and that's it.
Now this one-way communication from Bob to Alice has been established, and after that
Bob does exactly the same thing.
You create a channel for Alice to reach Bob.
Here's a nice diagram showing exactly this.
And here's how the queue works once it has been established.
So the recipient subscribes.
And it's verified.
Then you can see that the queue has been established.
So the recipient subscribes.
Then the sender subscribes and is verified, sends a message.
The recipient fetches messages from the queue.
That's it.
It's really simple.
And there's end-to-end encryption going on inside or of the message contents as well.
But the server doesn't know and doesn't care.
That's pretty much it, right?
Multiple servers do not communicate with each other.
They don't need to share any state.
They don't need to know anything about each other.
The clients decide everything.
Servers need to store messages only until they are downloaded by the recipient.
No history or logs need to be stored.
Again, very unlike matrix.
And so what was this last point?
Yeah, simplex queues one way.
Crypto, it's using a lot of, it's using salt, the salt crypto box.
It's using EDD, ED24519, ED448.
Servers must not store and send stuff to other servers.
Sure, there are message delivery notifications.
So for, and that's also a really nice, I think a nice, they've solved that nicely.
So for mobile operating systems, there are proprietary services for push notifications,
right?
And we don't want to send the message contents and we also don't want to send the metadata
there.
Here, there is a sort of extra subscription possible for a notification help.
Yeah.
That will receive information that there is something to fetch in the queue, but not what
it is and not from who and nothing else.
And can send this through the proprietary push notification infrastructure.
That's fun also.
And it works really well.
Even on the, so I heard the command line client actually also does this kind of notification
on macOS.
Which is fun for us.
Yeah.
For macOS users.
Here are the details of the block structure.
It's quite simple, refreshing.
So when I read through this detailed and slow, I had the feeling I'm actually able to implement
this.
It's going to take maybe a week, but it's really, it's really straightforward, right?
That's very nice.
I haven't seen such a simple protocol in a while.
Yeah.
What are some interesting commands that we can take a look at?
I haven't tried acknowledgeMessageDelivery.SuspendQueue.
I haven't tried that.
Yeah.
SendMessage.
ReceiveMessage.
Okay.
So some, has some, some, some depth, right, to the message structure but it's, it's all
right.
It's not so bad.
ErrorResponses.
We have transport protocol, TCP, whatever port, TLS 1.3 with this particular algorithm,
ChaCha20, Poly1305, SHA256, 24519, ED, and X, key exchange and signatures.
Strict, so a couple of really strict requirements on how the server behaves.
The client has a possibility to reject the server if the server starts behaving strangely.
Fixed size communication blocks, so 16 kilobyte communication blocks.
That's good to not reveal how large messages are that are being sent.
And 16 kilobyte is not so much overhead.
I think that's okay.
Yeah, and that's it.
That's the end of the protocol specification.
So, let's see.
Page 9.
That's all the protocol fun I want to go into.
But I encourage you to look at the documentation.
The documentation is really good.
There's a user guide.
And there's also a description of what the message protocol is for the contents of the messages.
I didn't talk at all about that.
It's a very simple JSON format.
Yeah, quite straightforward.
So, if you want to, you can connect to the BornHack23 Simplex group.
There's already like 15 people maybe in it once you've installed.
And thank you to organizers and volunteers for making this event.
And I'll take questions if you have any.
We have a question here.
Yeah, thanks for the talk.
Actually, very interesting.
As a Matrix user, I know that Matrix is really optimized for large rooms with large groups.
And you said for the servers with Simplex, they don't know if it's like a one-to-one connection or a connection to a group chat.
And I wonder how well does Simplex scale for larger groups?
And is it even a design goal to scale that much?
Right.
Excellent question.
So, at the moment, groups are the same.
It's the same as one-to-one.
So, if I'm in a group, I have a connection to everybody else in the group.
And everybody else also has a connection to everybody else in the group.
That doesn't scale so great.
I don't know where the limit is, but it will be somewhere.
And on the roadmap, they have this large group point.
I don't know what the status is.
But clearly, somebody is thinking about it.
And they want to also have a good solution for that.
Thank you.
Someone in the middle of your talk, you mentioned that the server re-encrypts incoming messages into another key, sending it out.
And that was good for stopping correlation effects.
And then, at the end, you mentioned a 16-kilobyte padding.
Are those connected?
Because without the padding, I can see that the correlation could be done anyway.
These 16 kilobytes, is that the message size?
Or what is that?
So, the 16 kilobyte is a block size.
So, it's the smallest amount of data that will go out.
Anything coming in or out of the server will be a multiple of 16 kilobytes.
Does that answer the question?
Yeah.
Okay.
And, yes, correlation.
There is the extra encryption on sending to the recipient, on the server sending to the recipient of a message.
To make sure that what comes in is never what goes out.
Yeah.
So, thanks for the talk.
I think I also read the protocol, and I thought it was a kind of nice take to do something really new.
However, I also thought that this is very much a privacy-focused, mostly privacy-focused application.
And for using broad-scale communications with other people.
It has some big flaws, I would say.
Kind of hard to have this as the one app to use.
So, and especially, for instance, if I were to have people contact me somehow.
Well, should you have email as a fallback as the first point of contact?
Or how would you go about doing it?
And what happens if you lose your device?
Because if I understood correctly, you can't really save your link to...
To the persons you have, because then if you would use that shared link again, then it will be an error.
So, think like, if you lose your device, and you have, like, how would you go about doing it?
And basically, can you see any problems, as I will see, having this as the only app in big quotation marks?
Thanks.
So, let me confirm, I understood two questions.
One question was how to use this...
For inviting anybody to contact me, anybody I don't know to contact me.
And the second one was about how to handle the situation where I lose my device.
Was, is that, did I understand correctly?
Okay, so let's start with the first one.
I mentioned, it was quick, sorry about that.
There are two kinds of invitations.
There's a single-use invitation, but there's also a multi-use invitation.
And this is, this is a multi-use invitation.
So, it's possible to publish a multi-use invitation on a web page, on a slide, and any number of people can use this to connect to, in this case, the group.
I could also put my own, like, one for me personally there, and I can revoke these at some later time.
I will, after the event, I will revoke this.
So, make sure to join me.
Join now.
But I think the multi-use invitation is the solution for the first.
And the second part, what do I do if I lose my device?
Well, you restore the backup that you had made on a new device.
Other questions?
Personally, so, once the multi-device feature is available, I'm really excited about this.
I think this can work really for everyone.
And all use cases, right?
Okay, so there's this broadcast and super large group.
That's also an important feature, but I'm really enthusiastic about how this is going, and it's been around for not very long.
Thank you for the talk.
Do you know if there's any...
Is there any progress on making a desktop client that's not the CLI one they have, or if anybody's working independently on implementations in other languages besides the Haskell?
So, I've seen that they have a to-do for a desktop client.
I don't know what the status is because I personally don't care, but a lot of people want that as well.
That's true.
And other implementations, well, my fingers are itching to implement this myself.
So, maybe there will be one.
Maybe there will be one at some point, but I'm not going to promise when.
And other than that, I don't know.
You people should also create an implementation.
Why not?
It's pretty straightforward.
And I think that's a good, also, call for action to, well, either at a minimum, like, integrate with what is there, but also look at creating more implementations.
Was there one more over there?
Okay.
Any other questions?
There was one.
Yeah.
Is this related to the very similar-looking protocols on the surface level from Noster and Session?
I don't know.
I haven't looked at them.
Any other questions?
Let's give a round of applause for Peter, then.
Thank you.