The next speakers we have is the game team that will give us the state of the game.
Let's give them a hand.
Thank you.
We were supposed to be three people presenting today.
One is currently treating a wound, so I will be the first one.
And then we will have Asbjorn announcing the winner of the game game in the last half.
So yes, the token game has now ended.
You can still attempt to find some tokens if you want, but you can't win anymore.
So we had a lot of different activities.
So the two official ones we have.
They are the Hacker Jeopardy and the Token Hunter.
But we also have a lot of game related things created by participants.
So we have some board games.
We have a game jam, which is announced in a bit.
A Pendleton, garden games, a Mario Kart tournament.
It sounds like they really had fun in that Mario Kart tournament.
I could hear it all the time.
We have music quiz, treasure hunt, and a 080 tournament.
So it's very nice to see people enjoying themselves.
And we also have the Pixel Flood, of course.
So the Hacker Jeopardy.
We had a lot of positive constructive feedback.
So we had this year done a bit of prep work.
I'm not personally the one who does the Hacker Jeopardy, but the team who did it did some
really nice work.
And it seemed to have paid off, the preparation.
They were really going a few months in a while.
So it was really nice to see all the emails we got.
Yes, and we got nine categories during the camp.
So that's it.
Thank you.
Any other questions?
So any минутes.
No, thank you.
We have some questions about...
One roundup for it is, we need more hacker, network, and cyber security-related topics.
We could see that some participants could need a bit of more network knowledge, but
it will also be nice to have some cyber security things.
We have previously been focused a lot on software-related stuff.
I hope that's a good point.
of, but it is a growing field and we have a lot of participants working in these fields
and interest in them. So if you have some ideas you can write it to the email listed
here. We would very much like so. You can just write it in this moment or wait a few
months, but we would very much like the categories because they are really hard to make up.
Well then we have the token game. So in 23 we had 60 participants. This is really nice.
It is actually a few more than in 2021 and 2022.
We had 27 participants.
The unique tokens, it is 10 more than the last time. We did a little more preparation.
So I think it is an okay, nice amount. I would personally like to prepare some more tokens
ahead of BornHack, but it is really hard to come up with tokens also. So if participants
want to make some, you are most definitely welcome and write us an email.
Thank you.
If you want. So the average tokens found per participant were four. Well, it is less
than 2021. You were really playing that year. But it is really nice that people who started
playing kept playing a bit more than last year. That is really nice to see. We have
eight participants who found more than 10 tokens.
That is the...
We do not really categorize them, but I would say that is like the players who keep playing
and attempting to find as many as they can.
And then we have two participants who found all 27 tokens. So you can battle it out with
whoever gets the prize. But you have to figure that out.
So what lessons did we learn this time?
We did not have enough tokens that did not need a computer. So a lot of the tokens require
to have some computing knowledge and also a computer in your hand. It would be nice
to have some more tokens that are based on puzzles and color recognition and similar
things.
Okay.
It has been heavily dependent on the token as a string, as a text string, so it's just
naturally that's the way we went, that somehow you could get a token out of a piece of string
somewhere.
But it would be very nice to have some things where you could use pattern recognition also.
Yes, I have already said it, but we would benefit if we prepare more.
We are very low maintenance when we're in off events.
Most of the content happens actually at the event and not even during build up.
It's just when the event starts, this is when token hunt creation starts.
Yeah.
We did some small things and it really helped out.
We had the space invader, for example, which already included token before it was set up.
So yeah, we have received a lot of nice input and yeah, we would like to also make tokens
more accessible for players.
So this is a thing that we need to work on.
It's again the thing with the computers.
Not everybody...
Not everybody is that good with computers necessarily or may not be studying a computer
science degree at a university and doing math all the time.
So again, it's like we keep enjoying this, but magic just happens when other teams and
other participants just say, hey, I would like to make a token.
I would like to make this token.
Can I make this token?
And then we say yes, most definitely.
So it's really nice when the batch team or this year, the phone operations center really
like just said, yeah, I would like to make this thing.
Can I make this thing?
Yeah.
And that came some really nice things out of it.
So I can show some more details on it.
We have the batch token.
Yeah.
So I'm not the one who created this.
I'm a bit unsure about the details on them, but let's get to it.
So on the batch, there is, well some letters you can read.
Well, they hit this whole grid, refers to a token.
So it is based encoded.
And you can if you decode it, you can get Frank Millard, 1806...
Maybe south!
If he's from Africa.
And it's just to know some more info.
Maybe south?
Sorry.
Something like this.
Yeah, well, and the year.
So you can, let's see how many we have here, yes, a lot of things.
So that's a lot of references to this one-time pad of the paper from Frank Miller and I guess
you had to go in and read it, or similar, to start finding the tokens.
But yes, that was most definitely tokens on the batch again this year.
Maybe we will have it again.
So the batch had NFC, right, yeah, I didn't make these slides, unfortunately, so I'm not
sure what all these numbers mean, but someone says hack the planet.
And you're right.
You're right.
Maybe you could convert it to the token at the end.
I'm sorry, I don't know what the end result gives.
Maybe a participant could explain.
Yeah, and then we have this one.
It's also a bit of evil that this batch gives you access to the data needed to gain SSL
access to a VM that contains some data that contains more tokens.
Yeah, again, I have no idea what this means.
It's unfortunately Dennis who knows what all these numbers mean, and yeah, you can find
him.
And you could find him in this talk if you want, and get some explanation, but sorry,
I cannot.
So we also had some dex phone numbers.
You can call the number that corresponds to token game, and it will read out some nice
letters to you in phonetic alphabet.
You probably have to record it or call it at least three times or four times to get
the whole thing.
a token there. You can also call the number token and you will get a conversation from
the movie Hackers where I crash overwrite the main character, request a number from
a person, and if you call that number, then you activate an ohm light where you can then
read the numbers. So, yeah, that's also Get Lisa's Numbers, and that's also one of the
numbers mentioned in the movie, one of the phone numbers, so you can get a little hint.
Thank you to the Phone Operations Centre, because that little piece of evil
was there.
That was actually very nice. I really loved calling in and testing different things.
Oh, yes, of course, that's conversion. I guess that says token, and that says Lisa,
and that says token hunt, or similar. Apparently, there was no audio. Sorry about that.
So, we also, well, I also made some artwork together with Bart, and this, well, it didn't
start as a token, but we made some artwork, and I thought, yeah, why not include a token?
This would be fun. So, that's a small thing that says Space Invader 1978, and if you mix
those letters around, you will get a token.
Very easy, but you just have to spot it. Also, credit to the nice person who took this
picture, because I'm not that good at taking images. We also have a token in the sticker
exchange. Maybe you can see the QR code. So, there were two boxes of stickers in the sticker
exchange at the info desk.
You scan both of them. The hint is ROT in the sticker exchange, so that was the hint.
And the QR code, one of the QR codes have some letters, and then it said plus four or
minus four, and the other one did the same. So, you could do a rotation, plus four, rotation
minus four, and put them together.
So, I accidentally made one of them a little too long, so it had 33 characters, but, yeah.
Small correction was that you just removed the last letter of the token.
So, this was the token hunt. Do we have any questions about some tokens? Maybe I can answer
some. Yes.
This was definitely not all tokens. It was just a few selects.
So, I saw that one of the tokens is the sequence of lights down the main path. Is that right?
Yeah, I think so, yes.
I couldn't figure out any combination of lights that would make up 30 and make sense. Also,
one of them is white.
Maybe the participant over here can answer the question.
So, I guess the question is how are you supposed to do that one?
So, the white one is actually blue. And you can see the paper and the film, if you look.
And there's two towards the cabin. Those count.
The first one is blue.
Yeah.
I think it's green. Yeah.
one here towards the bar doesn't count and the two towards the food area doesn't count
either. All right.
How can people sign up or help out with the game team? You didn't really specify.
Yeah. Well, you can sign up on the Bonehack website for the game team and then drop us an email and say,
hey, I would very much like to be part of the token hunt. Right now it's me and Dennis who are making the token hunt,
but having an extra person or two extra people being the, what is the English word for this,
but being the caretakers of the tokens.
Would be very nice. It would allow us to have more minds on it.
So, yes, go to the Bonehack website and sign up.
If I can ask, there was a hex in the game.
There was a hex in the slides between the presentations.
It looked like it was a valid token, but was it?
Which one, sorry?
There was a hex value in the slides between the presentations.
Yes.
So it was valid.
That was a hex encoded token in the info beamer, yes.
Yeah. I couldn't figure out how to, I mean, I decoded it, but I couldn't get to a valid token, but yeah.
So there's a very nice website called CyberChef.
Yes.
If you search on that.
I used it.
Okay.
If you type it in correctly, hopefully you should get the token.
There was not that much else in that token than finding it and typing it and then converting it over.
Yeah, I've done that.
But yeah, maybe you can show me later.
Yes.
But I also make mistakes sometimes.
So,
it could be I also made some mistake, but try again and then ask me if it didn't work.
So.
All right.
And then I will hop further to the next thing.
Well, we have the winner.
Oh, apparently it's, oh, sorry.
Beyond the end of the talk.
Sorry about that.
I had to change that in the last second since I didn't look at the, yeah, sorry.
We have the Pixel Flute.
Well, this is a graph.
It's also showed up in the NOC, sorry, State of the Network talk.
This is a monstrosity made by Aspion.
So, it has an 80 gigabits, which I can explain a bit more about it.
But we had some participants pulling their own fibers.
We had Aspion.
We had Aspion himself making a pixel accelerator.
Takes a 10 megabit nick, like an old Bonhack batch, and then do loop magic.
And apparently turns it up to 10 gigabits.
I don't know, like something with 15 kilometers of fiber.
Yeah.
It took a few days to get this up and running, but it seems like people were enjoying themselves.
So, I hope this can keep showing up and more people would like to participate.
We have a little graph here.
Well, you can see it started, okay, the graph at least started Sunday.
I can hop over to this and say, well,
the peak at the 95 percentile was at 31 gigabits per second.
The switch is limited to 80 gigabits.
So, we'll get to near that.
Well, I guess we will get a larger switch or something.
But we averaged it.
Averaged it.
I cannot say that word.
Our average was 21 gigabits per second.
And the peak is like a weird thing to count.
But at 43.
We had some new protocols.
I misspelled that, apparently.
New protocols implemented.
You can find it on the link.
It's the same link that hopefully all players saw.
Again, this year, we had multiple 10 gigabit clients.
Yes, the pixel accelerator thing was great.
Great.
We streamed some movies on it.
Well, not me, but Max streamed some movies on it.
Labifier Village pulls their own fiber and put in some QSFP plus optics.
They were, however, limited to 10 gigabits per machine.
So, it's not like bring the largest machine you can and the largest neck.
Because I could just find a 100 gigabit neck and put it in if the switch could take it.
So, all clients are limited to 10 gigabits.
And we were as well.
But we just could sit in our comfy tents instead of going all the way out and installing a machine.
Legacy IP addresses were again punished this year.
You had to use IPv6.
Or else you would get some transparency on your pixels.
You can see the little pony, perhaps.
That was because I didn't update my client and could not find the IPv6 version I made somewhere.
So, yes, it was transparent.
I just sent enough pixels that it's not immediately visible.
So, there was also a participant who attempted to create a distributed Pixel Flu client.
The goal was to play Doom on it.
Like with one controller and then multiple machines, like multiple small machines and stuff.
The distributed version or distribution thing worked but not playing Doom.
Maybe that will work next time.
So, yes, I guess we can go to the Gamjam.
And I will attempt to remember to announce the winners of the token hunt.
Tuki!
Jan Poonamute, Li Pali, Ilu Musi.
Oh, wait.
I have to do this.
I'm just talking English.
Right.
Then you understand.
Okay.
We did the first ever Born Hack Gamjam.
And it was a great success.
Thank you for everybody who played.
If you have your laptop out right now, you can go to pyjam.as.
And see all the submissions.
We had eight very beautiful games made by, I think, something like 15 nice hackers.
All of the games had to fit the theme Switch, which was announced last Friday at 1800.
And then we had three days.
To complete the game.
The deadline was yesterday at 1800.
So, since there's eight games, I just want to show you all of them.
Because I couldn't help myself.
This one, Kill Switch by Vell, is really cool.
It was made by a child.
I think the first time they ever made a game.
It's a Switch.
There's also, like, some Nintendo Switches.
And there's some networking Switches.
And there's a light Switch.
And you have to press one of three buttons and try and kill the prisoner instead of the
cops.
But, yeah.
So, yeah.
But, it's very cool.
It plays on the web browser.
And it has a leaderboard.
Moral switch is gamifying the trolley problem.
When the game was given a moral dilemma.
And you have to choose who you want to kill.
The text was generated, I think, using a large language model.
And also, images that were being made on the fly.
So, it would make at run-time new scenarios.
That's quite cool.
Somebody made a game called Pass Parentheses 2, I think they uploaded it under the same
name twice, but this was Astro One, Mass, Nilsson, Philip.
This is a game which had several different backend implementations, so every time you
die you switch to a different backend which had its own complete different state and different
rules for the game.
I think there was backend written in like Haskell and Go and Rust, right?
So that's kind of crazy.
So there's several different games, there's one which is like a pixel art drawing game
and this is a snake game.
This one turns out to be a lot of fun because there's an HTML injection in the username
field.
So you can just change the game on the fly, yeah, this website was looking really crazy
last night because of the HTML injection, that was cool.
Dao also made a game called Save the Network.
Which is about...
It's about defending a network switch, you have all of these different ports, some of
them they turn red while they're being hacked, so you have to be quick and click it, so it's
kind of like a whack-a-mole game.
This is super difficult, but it has nice audio and stuff also.
Another cool game, Designuda, Nicholas, made a game called Shield Switch, in which it's
sort of like an Asteroids type game, where there's different types of asteroids, it's
difficult to see right now, but these are like the red ones.
And then you switch between being in the red state or the blue state, so you can pass
the phase through different kinds of asteroids, depending on what color it is.
That's quite cool.
Nicholas, who made this game, also composed an original soundtrack for this game, and
just because he had more time and wanted to, he also made an original soundtrack for this
game, so that's super cool.
This sliding snake is a terminal-based game, in which you control a snake and you try and
avoid these lines of trees.
And then you switch between being in the red state or the blue state, so you can pass the
phase through different kinds of asteroids.
I think this was originally made to run on a receipt printer.
That's great.
This was my game.
It's like a physics-based game, where you're the snake inside of your network switch, because
you know the snake inside the network switch, right?
You pick up packets and you try and drop them in the right place, and you try not to switch
the packets wrong.
Samuel made a game called Switch Off the Music, this is a mobile phone game, which is GPS-based.
So the plot is that it's late and all the hackers are making a lot of noise, and you
have to go and find the parties and then tell them to turn off the music.
This game will get your heart rate up, like you're sprinting around the field and trying
to turn off the music before you lose your patience.
That's a lot of fun.
All right, so those were the games.
We had a rating system, so it works like this.
Anybody who submitted a game could rate the other games.
We had a little bit less than 24 hours to play and rate all of them.
These are the categories.
There's an overall score that determines the winner of the game jam totally, and then these
other aspects of creativity and aesthetics, how well it fit the theme of Switch, and how
fun the gameplay was.
So let's do the winner's announcement for each of these categories.
The aesthetic winner is...
Mortal Switch!
The creativity winner is, and I'm sure you're not surprised about this, Switch Off the Music!
The gameplay winner is...
Shield Switch!
And the theme winner is...
Moral Switch!
Again!
Thank you.
All right, can I have a drum roll for the total winner?
The winner of the Born to Hack Game Jam 2023 is...
Shield Switch!
But really, so much thanks to everybody who played.
It's been a lot of fun making games with you, and we're definitely going to do this again
next year.
So there's a theme for the game jam, which was Switch this year.
I'd really like to hear suggestions.
I'd like to hear suggestions for a theme for next year.
The game jam Luludare does this thing of submitting a bunch of different themes, and then we vote
about it.
I think we should do that next year.
So send an email to the game team, or send a message to me, or just come find me if you
have a good idea for a theme.
Also I want to make it so that I don't know the theme in advance, because that would be
more fun for me.
Yeah, but that's it for game jam.
Thanks for playing.
And as you can see, he's a big fan of the game.
He's a big fan of the game.
And as you can see, he's a bit more energetic than I am.
So yes, now the Tokenhund winner is, well, yeah, you have to play Rock, Paper, and Scissor,
but it's Emilie and Sebastian.
You can decide amongst yourself, or do you want to play Rock, Paper, and Scissor?
Last Token, first.
Okay.
I guess we can fight for a year about that one.
So, yes, thank you so much for visiting this talk.
See you next year.
Are there any questions?
Thank you for the great presentation.
Thank you for the great state of the game.
Let's give him a round of applause.